<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mol Ther Nucleic Acids</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Mol Ther Nucleic Acids</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Molecular Therapy. Nucleic Acids</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2162-2531</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Society of Gene &#x00026; Cell Therapy</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31927306</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6953775</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S2162-2531(19)30396-8</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.omtn.2019.12.002</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>MEL Ameliorates Post-SAH Cerebral Vasospasm by Affecting the Expression of eNOS and HIF1&#x003b1; via H19/miR-138/eNOS/NO and H19/miR-675/HIF1&#x003b1;</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>Guoqiang</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Hongjin</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3"><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>Yuhua</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4"><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>Yaohua</given-names></name><email>neucrosis@yeah.net</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#x02217;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au5"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Xiaohua</given-names></name><email>daoguac30363696@163.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="cor2" ref-type="corresp">&#x02217;&#x02217;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au6"><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>Feng</given-names></name><email>projiafeng@163.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="cor3" ref-type="corresp">&#x02217;&#x02217;&#x02217;</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Neurosurgery, Ren Ji Hospital, School of Medicine, Shanghai Jiao Tong University, Shanghai 200127, People&#x02019;s Republic of China</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x02217;</label>Corresponding author: Yaohua Pan, Department of Neurosurgery, Ren Ji Hospital, School of Medicine, Shanghai Jiao Tong University, No.1630 Dongfang Road, Pudong, Shanghai 200127, People&#x02019;s Republic of China. <email>neucrosis@yeah.net</email></corresp><corresp id="cor2"><label>&#x02217;&#x02217;</label>Corresponding author: Xiaohua Zhang, Department of Neurosurgery, Ren Ji Hospital, School of Medicine, Shanghai Jiao Tong University, No.1630 Dongfang Road, Pudong, Shanghai 200127, People&#x02019;s Republic of China. <email>daoguac30363696@163.com</email></corresp><corresp id="cor3"><label>&#x02217;&#x02217;&#x02217;</label>Corresponding author: Feng Jia, Department of Neurosurgery, Ren Ji Hospital, School of Medicine, Shanghai Jiao Tong University, No.1630 Dongfang Road, Pudong, Shanghai 200127, People&#x02019;s Republic of China. <email>projiafeng@163.com</email></corresp><fn id="fn1"><label>2</label><p id="ntpara0010">These authors contributed equally to this work.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>14</day><month>12</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="collection"><day>06</day><month>3</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>12</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>19</volume><fpage>523</fpage><lpage>532</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>26</day><month>8</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>2</day><month>12</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2019 The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><license license-type="CC BY-NC-ND" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="abs0010"><p>Melatonin (MEL) has been demonstrated to exert a protective effect against subarachnoid hemorrhage (SAH), and nitric oxide (NO) has been shown to play an important role in the pathogenesis of vasospasm. This study aims to explore the underlying molecular mechanisms of MEL in the control of vasospasm following SAH. MEL administration attenuates SAH-induced vasospasm and neurobehavioral deficits. Expressions of H19, eNOS, and miR-675 are low in the SAH group, while expressions of miR-138 and HIF1&#x003b1; are high in&#x000a0;the SAH group. Also, MEL treatment upon SAH rats completely restores the dysregulation of H19, eNOS, miR-675, miR-138, and HIF1&#x003b1; to their normal levels. Moreover, MEL dose dependently increases the luciferase activity of H19 promoter and hence the expression of H19. Additionally, H19 directly targets miR-675 and miR-138 to increase miR-675 expression and inhibit miR-138 expression. As virtual target genes of miR-675 and miR-138, respectively, HIF1&#x003b1; and eNOS are also regulated by the treatment with MEL. In particular, MEL treatment increases the expression of miR-675 and eNOS level while decreasing the expression of miR-138 and HIF1&#x003b1; in a dose dependent manner. Our study found that MEL ameliorates post-SAH vasospasm by regulating the expression of eNOS and HIF1&#x003b1; via the H19/miR-138/eNOS/NO and H19/miR-675/HIF1&#x003b1; signaling pathways.</p></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>melatonin</kwd><kwd>eNOS</kwd><kwd>HIF1&#x003b1;</kwd><kwd>post-SAH vasospasm</kwd><kwd>H19</kwd><kwd>miR-138</kwd><kwd>miR-675</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0010">Although only accounting for less than 10% of all cases of stroke, subarachnoid hemorrhage (SAH) can lead to devastating consequences.<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> In fact, the annual incidence of SAH in the US is about 1 in 10,000, while the combined mortality and morbidity of SAH is higher than 50%.<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> As a type of SAH, aneurysmal SAH (aSAH) is particularly dangerous because it can induce vasospasm. Statistical data showed that about 30,000 patients develop aSAH in the US every year.<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref> On the other hand, melatonin (MEL, also termed N-acetyl-5-methoxytryptamine) has been demonstrated to exert a protective effect against SAH in experimental animals.<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref> For example, Ayer et&#x000a0;al.<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> showed that MEL decreased the mortality of severe SAH, while the administration of MEL was shown to reduce SAH-induced pulmonary edema, cerebral vasospasm, neurological symptoms, and oxidative stress.<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref></p><p id="p0015">Although the mechanisms underlying vasospasm-induced injuries remain unclear, nitric oxide (NO) has been shown to play an important role in the pathogenesis of vasospasm.<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> As a potent inflammation inhibitor and vasodilator, NO regulates platelet aggregation and the proliferation of smooth muscle cells.<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr"><sup>7</sup></xref> In addition, the polymorphisms in the gene of endothelial NO synthase (eNOS) have been linked to an increased risk of vasospasm and injuries to the cerebral aneurysm.<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr"><sup>8</sup></xref> Furthermore, under hypoxic conditions, the accumulation of hypoxia-inducible factor-1&#x003b1; (HIF1&#x003b1;) in tissues causes erythropoiesis, glycolysis, and angiogenesis.<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref> In particular, vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF), a target of HIF1&#x003b1;, acts as a strong promoter of angiogenesis and participates in the development of cerebral vasospasm.<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref></p><p id="p0020">As an extensively studied type of non-coding RNA (ncRNA), microRNAs (miRNAs) have been shown to play critical roles in many cellular and physiological processes, such as apoptosis, growth, proliferation, and differentiation of cells.<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref> During its action, mature miRNA binds to RNA&#x02010;induced silencing complex (RISC) and subsequently interacts with the 3&#x02032;&#x02010;untranslated region (3&#x02032;&#x02010;UTR) of its target mRNAs to regulate their expression at transcriptional and post&#x02010;transcriptional levels.<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref> Recently, it has been shown that long ncRNAs (lncRNAs) also play important functions in many cellular processes.<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref> Unlike miRNAs, lncRNAs usually contain more than 200 nucleotides and hence have more complex structures.<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref> In general, lncRNAs can be divided into the following five types based on their positions relative to adjacent protein&#x02010;coding genes: intergenic lncRNA, intronic lncRNA, bidirectional lncRNA, antisense lncRNA, and sense lncRNA.<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref> In terms of SAH, it was demonstrated that the expression of NGF, miR-675, and H19 is significantly increased in SAH rats, while the treatment of SAH rats by MEL reduced the expression of NGF, miR-675, and H19, indicating that MEL can prevent SAH-induced early brain injury (EBI) by regulating the activity of the H19-let-7a-NGF-apoptosis and H19-miR-675-P53-apoptosis pathways.<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref></p><p id="p0025">In our previous study, MEL treatment has been reported to regulate the expression of H19.<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref> Furthermore, H19 acts as a host gene of miR-675 and the increase in H19 expression has been associated with increased miR-675 expression.<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> Meanwhile, as a competing endogenous RNA of miR-138, H19 can sponge the function of miR-138.<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref> Furthermore, we found that, as a target of miR-675, HIF1&#x003b1; is functionally associated with post-SAH vasospasm.<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref> In this study, we established an animal model of SAH and vasospasm. By treating SAH rats with MEL, we investigated the effect of MEL on the signaling pathways of H19/miR-138/eNOS/NO and H19/miR-675/HIF1&#x003b1;.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec2.1"><title>MEL Administration Attenuates Neurobehavioral Deficits</title><p id="p0030">The diameter of the middle cerebral artery (MCA) in sham rats showed no obvious difference upon MEL treatment, while the rats in the SAH group showed a reduced MCA diameter, which was then significantly increased by the administration of MEL (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;1</xref>A). In addition, vehicle-treated SAH rats displayed significant neurobehavioral deficits, while the treatment with MEL reduced the level of neurobehavioral deficits (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;1</xref>B), thus validating that MEL administration could attenuate neurobehavioral deficits.<fig id="fig1"><label>Figure&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>MEL Administration Attenuated Neurobehavioral Deficits</p><p>(A) Rats in the SAH group showed a reduced MCA diameter, but the administration of MEL in SAH rats significantly increased MCA diameter. (B) SAH rats exhibited obvious neurobehavioral deficits, while the administration of MEL in SAH rats obviously reduced the severity of neurobehavioral deficits.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><title>Differential Expressions of H19, miR-675, and miR-138 among Various Groups</title><p id="p0035">Real-time PCR was carried out to compare the expression of H19, miR-675, and miR-138 among the SHAM, SHAM+MEL, SAH+VEH, and SAH+MEL groups. As shown in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;2</xref>, H19 (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;2</xref>A) and miR-675 (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;2</xref>B) expression in the SHAM group were comparable with that in the SHAM+MEL group. However, the expression of H19 and miR-675 was much lower in the SAH+VEH group, but the treatment with MEL obviously increased the expression of H19 and miR-675. In contrast, the rats in the SAH+VEH group showed a much higher level of miR-138 (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;2</xref>C) than the rats in the SHAM group, but the treatment with MEL obviously decreased the expression of miR-138. Therefore, H19, miR-675, and miR-138 were all differentially expressed upon the onset of SAH and further treatment of MEL among SAH rats.<fig id="fig2"><label>Figure&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>H19, miR-675, and miR-138 Were Differentially Expressed among Various Groups</p><p>(A) H19 expressions in SHAM and SHAM+MEL rats were similar. H19 expression in SAH rats was much lower, while the administration of MEL in SAH rats obviously increased H19 expression (*p&#x000a0;&#x0003c; 0.05, versus SHAM group; #p&#x000a0;&#x0003c; 0.05, versus SAH+VEH group). (B) miR-675 expressions in SHAM and SHAM+MEL rats were similar. miR-675 expression in SAH rats was much lower, while the administration of MEL in SAH rats obviously increased miR-675 expression (*p&#x000a0;&#x0003c; 0.05, versus SHAM group; #p&#x000a0;&#x0003c; 0.05, versus SAH+VEH group). (C) miR-138 expressions in SHAM and SHAM+MEL rats were similar. miR-138 expression in SAH rats was much higher, while the administration of MEL in SAH rats obviously decreased miR-138 expression (*p&#x000a0;&#x0003c; 0.05, versus SHAM group; #p&#x000a0;&#x0003c; 0.05, versus SAH+VEH group).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><title>Levels of HIF1&#x003b1; and eNOS among Various Groups</title><p id="p0040">Real-time PCR and western blot analysis were performed to examine the expression of HIF1&#x003b1; and eNOS among the SHAM, SHAM+MEL, SAH+VEH, and SAH+MEL groups. As shown in <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;3</xref>, the rats in the SAH+VEH group showed evidently increased expression of HIF1&#x003b1; mRNA (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;3</xref>A) and protein (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figures 3</xref>C and 3D), while the mRNA and protein levels of HIF1&#x003b1; in the SAH+MEL group were similar to those in the SHAM and SHAM+MEL groups. On the other hand, the rats in the SAH+VEH group showed evidently decreased expression of eNOS mRNA (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;3</xref>B) and protein (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figures 3</xref>C and 3E), while the mRNA and protein levels of eNOS in the SAH+MEL group were similar to those in the SHAM and SHAM+MEL groups. Furthermore, an immunohistochemistry (IHC) assay was used to compare the protein levels of HIF1&#x003b1; and eNOS among the four groups. As shown in <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;4</xref>, the protein level of HIF1&#x003b1; in the SHAM group was similar to that in the SHAM+MEL group, but the protein level of HIF1&#x003b1; in the SAH+VEH group was much higher than that in the SHAM group. However, the treatment of SAH rats by MEL significantly reduced the protein level of HIF1&#x003b1;. Meanwhile, the level of eNOS protein (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;5</xref>) in the SHAM group was comparable with that in the SHAM+MEL group, while the level of eNOS protein in the SAH+VEH group was significantly lower. In addition, the treatment of SAH rats by MEL significantly increased the protein level of eNOS. Therefore, the mRNA and protein expressions of HIF1&#x003b1; and eNOS were all differentially expressed upon the onset of SAH and further treatment of MEL among SAH rats.<fig id="fig3"><label>Figure&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Expression of HIF1&#x003b1; and eNOS Was Compared among Various Groups Using Real-Time PCR and Western Blot Analysis</p><p>(A) Expressions of HIF1&#x003b1; mRNA in the SHAM and SHAM+MEL groups were similar, while the expression of HIF1&#x003b1; mRNA in SAH rats was much higher, and the administration of MEL in SAH rats obviously decreased the expression of HIFIA mRNA (*p&#x000a0;&#x0003c; 0.05, versus SHAM group; #p&#x000a0;&#x0003c; 0.05, versus SAH+VEH group). (B) Expressions of eNOS mRNA in the SHAM and SHAM+MEL groups were similar, while the expression of eNOS mRNA in SAH rats was much lower, and the administration of MEL in SAH rats obviously increased the expression of eNOS mRNA (*p&#x000a0;&#x0003c; 0.05, versus SHAM group; #p&#x000a0;&#x0003c; 0.05, versus SAH+VEH group). (C) Expression of HIF1&#x003b1; protein was increased in SAH rats, while expression of eNOS protein was decreased in SAH rats compared with the SHAM and SHAM+MEL groups, and administration of MEL in SAH rats decreased the expression of HIF1&#x003b1; protein and increased the expression of eNOS protein. (D) Expressions of HIF1&#x003b1; protein in the SHAM and SHAM+MEL group were similar, while the administration of MEL in SAH rats decreased the upregulated expression of HIF1&#x003b1; protein in SAH rats (*p&#x000a0;&#x0003c; 0.05, versus SHAM group; #p&#x000a0;&#x0003c; 0.05, versus SAH+VEH group). (E) Expressions of eNOS protein in the SHAM and SHAM+MEL group were similar, while the administration of MEL in SAH rats increased the downregulated expression of eNOS protein in SAH rats (*p&#x000a0;&#x0003c; 0.05, versus SHAM group; #p&#x000a0;&#x0003c; 0.05, versus SAH+VEH group).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr3"/></fig><fig id="fig4"><label>Figure&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>Expressions of HIF1&#x003b1; Was Determined among Various Groups Using IHC</p><p>Expression of HIF1&#x003b1; was determined among various groups using IHC, and it was found that evident increase in HIF1&#x003b1; protein expression was observed in SAH group, while it was decreased by MEL treatment (magnification, 200&#x000d7;).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr4"/></fig><fig id="fig5"><label>Figure&#x000a0;5</label><caption><p>Expressions of eNOS Was Compared among Various Groups Using IHC</p><p>Expression of eNOS was compared among various groups using IHC, and the results showed that the protein expression of eNOS was evidently decreased in the SAH group, while the administration of MEL in SAH rats obviously increased the protein expression of eNOS (magnification, 200&#x000d7;).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr5"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec2.4"><title>Effect of MEL on the Expression of H19, miR-675, miR-138, HIF1&#x003b1;, and eNOS</title><p id="p0045">Effects of MEL on the expression of H19, miR-675, miR-138, HIF1&#x003b1;, and eNOS were investigated in SH-SY5Y (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;6</xref>) and U251 (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;7</xref>) cells using luciferase assay, real-time PCR, and western blot analysis. As shown in <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figures 6</xref>A and <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>A, the co-transfection of SH-SY5Y and U251 cells with H19 and miR-138 suppressed the luciferase activity of H19, validating H19 to sponge miR-138 in a cellular model. In addition, the transfection of SH-SY5Y (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;6</xref>B) and U251 (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;7</xref>B) cells with wild-type 3&#x02032; UTR of eNOS significantly reduced the luciferase activity of miR-138, indicating eNOS as a potential target of miR-138. Meanwhile, SH-SY5Y (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;6</xref>C) and U251 (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;7</xref>C) cells co-transfected with wild-type 3&#x02032; UTR of HIF1&#x003b1; and miR-675 mimic showed a reduced luciferase activity, leading to the conclusion that miR-675 could target HIF1&#x003b1;. Furthermore, the luciferase activity of H19 showed a concentration-dependent increase over an increasing concentration of MEL (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figures 6</xref>D and <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>D), and MEL also upregulated the expression of H19 (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figures 6</xref>E and <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>E) and miR-675 (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figures 6</xref>F and <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>F) while downregulating the expression of miR-138 (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figures 6</xref>G and <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>G) in SH-SY5Y and U251 cells in a concentration-dependent manner. Moreover, the administration of MEL dose dependently decreased the mRNA (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figures 6</xref>H and <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>H) and protein (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figures 6</xref>J and <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>J) expression of HIF1&#x003b1; while increasing the mRNA (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figures 6</xref>I and <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>I) and protein expression of eNOS in SH-SY5Y and U251 cells. All these results suggested that MEL increased H19 expression, which in turn increased the expression of miR-675 and decreased the expression of miR-138, thus affecting the expression of targets of miR-675 or miR-138, HIF1&#x003b1;, and eNOS.<fig id="fig6"><label>Figure&#x000a0;6</label><caption><p>Effect of MEL on the Expression of H19, miR-675, miR-138, HIF1&#x003b1;, and eNOS in SH-SY5Y Cells</p><p>(A) Co-transfection of the cells with H19 and miR-138 mimics reduced the luciferase activity of the cells (*p&#x000a0;&#x0003c; 0.05, versus control group). (B) Transfection of the cells with wild-type 3&#x02032; UTR of eNOS significantly decreased the luciferase activity of miR-138 (*p&#x000a0;&#x0003c; 0.05, versus control group). (C) Transfection of the cells with miR-675 mimics significantly decreased the luciferase activity of wild-type 3&#x02032; UTR of HIF1&#x003b1; (*p&#x000a0;&#x0003c; 0.05, versus control group). (D) MEL dose dependently increased the luciferase activity of the H19 promoter (*p&#x000a0;&#x0003c; 0.05, versus untreated cells). (E) MEL dose dependently increased the expression of H19 (*p&#x000a0;&#x0003c; 0.05, versus untreated cells). (F) MEL dose dependently increased the expression of miR-675 (*p&#x000a0;&#x0003c; 0.05, versus untreated cells). (G) MEL dose dependently decreased the expression of miR-138 (*p&#x000a0;&#x0003c; 0.05, versus untreated cells). (H) MEL dose dependently downregulated the expression of HIF1&#x003b1; mRNA (*p&#x000a0;&#x0003c; 0.05, versus untreated cells). (I) MEL dose dependently upregulated the expression of eNOS mRNA (*p&#x000a0;&#x0003c; 0.05, versus untreated cells). (J) MEL dose dependently downregulated the expression of HIF1&#x00391; protein while upregulating the expression of eNOS protein.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr6"/></fig><fig id="fig7"><label>Figure&#x000a0;7</label><caption><p>Effect of MEL on the Expression of H19, miR-675, miR-138, HIF1&#x00391;, and eNOS in U251 Cells</p><p>(A) Co-transfection of the cells with H19 and miR-138 mimics reduced the luciferase activity of the cells (*p&#x000a0;&#x0003c; 0.05, versus control group). (B) Transfection of the cells with wild-type 3&#x02032; UTR of eNOS significantly decreased the luciferase activity of miR-138 (*p&#x000a0;&#x0003c; 0.05, versus control group). (C) Transfection of the cells with miR-675 mimics significantly decreased the luciferase activity of wild-type 3&#x02032; UTR of HIF1&#x003b1; (*p&#x000a0;&#x0003c; 0.05, versus control group). (D) MEL dose dependently increased the luciferase activity of H19 promoter (*p&#x000a0;&#x0003c; 0.05, versus untreated cells). (E) MEL dose dependently increased the expression of H19 (*p&#x000a0;&#x0003c; 0.05, versus untreated cells). (F) MEL dose dependently increased the expression of miR-675 (*p&#x000a0;&#x0003c; 0.05, versus untreated cells). (G) MEL dose dependently decreased the expression of miR-138 (*p&#x000a0;&#x0003c; 0.05, versus untreated cells). (H) MEL dose dependently downregulated the expression of HIF1&#x003b1; mRNA (*p&#x000a0;&#x0003c; 0.05, versus untreated cells). (I) MEL dose dependently upregulated the expression of eNOS mRNA (*p&#x000a0;&#x0003c; 0.05, versus untreated cells). (J) MEL dose dependently downregulated the expression of HIF1&#x003b1; protein while upregulating the expression of eNOS protein.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr7"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0050">In mammalians, MEL acts as an essential constituent and a free radical scavenger in the defense against oxidants and hence can effectively protect cells against oxidative damage.<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref> MEL may play its anti-oxidative role via several routes, i.e., by increasing the activity of endogenous antioxidant enzymes such as superoxide dismutase (SOD), by protecting the functions of endogenous antioxidant enzymes such as catalase, and by reducing the level of free radicals in the body.<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20</sup></xref> In fact, both MEL and its metabolites, including N1-acetyl-5-methoxykynuramine and N1-acetyl-N2-formyl-5-methoxykynuramine, are potent scavengers of free radicals.<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref> Furthermore, MEL can cross cell membranes easily and will not be reduced by redox cycling.<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr"><sup>22</sup></xref> Several previous studies have shown that MEL alleviates the severity of SAH by reducing the severity of focal cerebellum injury by decreasing the magnitude of vasospasm and endothelial cell apoptosis in blood vessels, by reducing the rate of mortality, and by reducing the symptoms of EBI and neurological disorders.<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> MEL has also been reported to affect the expression of H19 lncRNA, a host of miR-675 and a negative regulator of p53 expression.<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref> In this study, we found that the administration of MEL attenuated SAH-induced vasospasm and neurobehavioral deficits. In addition, H19 and miR-675 were lowly expressed in the SAH rats, along with highly expressed miR-138, while the treatment with MEL restored the expression of H19, miR-675, and miR-138 in SAH rats.</p><p id="p0055">It has been shown that, by regulating the expression of let-7a and miR-675, H19 is implicated in post-SAH brain injury by mediating nerve growth factor (NGF)- and P53-induced apoptosis.<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref> In fact, H19 plays its role by harboring a hairpin that serves as the precursor of miR-675-3p and miR-675-5p4.<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr"><sup>26</sup></xref> In addition, individuals suffering from post-SAH EBI usually show significantly increased levels of cerebral vasospasm, apoptosis, oxidative stress, and inflammatory responses.<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr"><sup>27</sup></xref> Recently, a pre-clinical study on glioma also demonstrated the presence of a loop between miR-675-5p and HIF1&#x003b1;.<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr"><sup>28</sup></xref> In addition, it was shown that cerebral vasospasm can be caused by the impairment to the blood-brain barrier via dysregulated VEGF expression and excessive apoptosis of endothelial cells.<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr"><sup>29</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr"><sup>30</sup></xref> Furthermore, in a rat model of SAH, the expression and activity of HIF1&#x003b1; are elevated in the cortex and hippocampus, suggesting the presence of a direct correlation between apoptosis and the expression of HIF1&#x003b1;.<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr"><sup>31</sup></xref> In this study, we found that the expression of HIF1&#x003b1; in the SAH+MEL group was much higher than that in the control group, along with a much lower level of eNOS expression.</p><p id="p0060">By directly interacting with the 3&#x02032; UTR of Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding protein S100A1 and downregulating its expression, miR-138 can reduce eNOS activity in the body.<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr"><sup>32</sup></xref> Subsequently, the reduced level of eNOS limits the amount of NO available in the regulation of vascular tone by decreasing the amount of L-arginine metabolized into citrulline and NO. As a result, upon the development of SAH, the immunoreactivity of eNOS in cerebrovascular endothelia is decreased.<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr"><sup>33</sup></xref> On the other hand, the treatment of SAH by simvastatin, a compound that can increase the expression of eNOS in cerebrovascular tissues, delayed the occurrence of cerebral vasospasm.<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr"><sup>28</sup></xref> Using a canine model of SAH, Khurana et&#x000a0;al.<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr"><sup>34</sup></xref> showed that vasospasm can be alleviated with intrathecal delivery of eNOS mRNA, while other results indicated that the increase in eNOS expression may reduce the severity of cerebral vasospasm. A large amount of evidence also suggested that various factors can induce the onset of post-SAH cerebral vasospasm.<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr"><sup>35</sup></xref> For example, several <italic>in&#x000a0;vitro</italic> and <italic>in&#x000a0;vivo</italic> studies showed that oxyhemoglobin and its metabolites can trigger the synthesis of free radicals, which subsequently generate oxidative stress and induce vasospasm.<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr"><sup>36</sup></xref> In summary, critical vasodilators, such as NO and peroxynitrite, which is generated by a rapid reaction between NO and superoxide radical (O2<sup>&#x02212;</sup>), may lead to the imbalance between cerebral vasoconstrictors and vasodilators, eventually causing cerebral vasospasm.<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr"><sup>37</sup></xref><sup>,</sup><xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr"><sup>38</sup></xref> In this study, we found that MEL dose dependently increased H19 expression, which in turn increased the expression of miR-675 and decreased the expression of miR-138, thus affecting the expression of target genes of miR-675 or miR-138.</p><p id="p0065">In this study, our results suggested that MEL could ameliorate post-SAH vasospasm by regulating the expression of eNOS and HIF1&#x003b1; via H19/miR-138/eNOS/NO and H19/miR-675/HIF1&#x003b1; signaling pathways.</p></sec><sec id="sec4"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="sec4.1"><title>Animal Grouping and Treatment</title><p id="p0070">In this study, a total of 32 male SD rats with an average body weight of 400&#x000a0;g were randomly allocated into four weight-matched groups, i.e., a sham group (SHAM group, surgery without the induction of SAH, N&#x000a0;= 8), a sham+MEL group (SHAM+MEL group, sham-operated rats treated with MEL, N&#x000a0;= 8), a SAH+vehicle group (SAH+VEH group, SAH rats treated with saline, N&#x000a0;= 8), and a SAH+MEL group (SAH+MEL group, SAH rats treated with MEL, N&#x000a0;= 8). First, the rats in SAH+VEH and SAH+MEL groups underwent a previously described surgical operation to induce the onset of SAH.<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref> In brief, after an incision of 4&#x000a0;cm in length was made over the anterior midline on the neck, the internal carotid artery (ICA) and right external carotid artery were separated. Subsequently, a sharpened wire was inserted into the stump of the right external carotid artery and advanced to the intracranial ICA. Upon the proper placement of the wire, a laser doppler flowmetry (AD Instruments, Colorado Springs, CO, USA) should show that the signal of ipsilateral core binding factor (CBF) was reduced. In the next step, the wire was pushed inward 3&#x000a0;mm to puncture the cerebral ICA at the bifurcation. Among the three experimental groups set up in this study, the rats in the SHAM group underwent all surgical procedures except the step of suture perforation, while the rats in the other two groups underwent the entire surgical procedure. After the surgical operation, all animals were housed in single cages and had free access to food and water until dissection. All animal experiments were performed in line with internationally recognized guidelines for the care and use of laboratory animals, and the institutional animal ethics committee approved this study.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.2"><title>Assessment of Vasospasm</title><p id="p0075">The assessment of vasospasm in rats was performed on day 3 after the surgery using cerebrovascular casting.<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> In brief, the rats were anesthetized using isoflurane and then perfused transcardially using PBS containing 4% of formalin and 3% of gelatin-India ink. Subsequently, the rats were dissected to collect the brain tissue, and the severity of SAH was graded by inspecting the morphology of blood vessels under a microscope in conjunction with a high-definition medical image analysis system (HMIAP-2000, Tongji Medical University, Wuhan, China).<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref> In addition, the smallest diameter within the MCA outside the lateral sulcus was measured to evaluate the degree of vasospasm.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.3"><title>RNA Isolation and Real-Time PCR</title><p id="p0080">The total RNA from tissue and cell samples was extracted using a Trizol kit (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA), followed by the determination of the concentration and purity of extracted RNA using a DU-640 spectrophotometer (Beckman, San Jose, CA, USA). A ratio of A<sub>260</sub>/A<sub>280</sub> between 1.8 and 2.0 was considered as acceptable purity for extracted RNA to be used in subsequent experiments. In the next step, the total extracted RNA was reversely transcribed into cDNA in accordance with the instruction of a PrimeScript RT reagent kit (Takara, Tokyo, Japan) using the following reaction conditions: reverse transcription at 37&#x000b0;C for 15&#x000a0;min and reverse transcriptase inactivation at 85&#x000b0;C for 5 s. Subsequently, real-time PCR was performed on an ABI7500 instrument (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA, USA) using a SYBR premix EX Taq kit (Takara, Tokyo, Japan) and the following reaction conditions: pre-denaturation at 95&#x000b0;C for 10&#x000a0;min and 40 cycles of denaturation at 95&#x000b0;C for 15&#x000a0;s and annealing at 60&#x000b0;C for 1&#x000a0;min. The real-time PCR reaction system contained 9.0&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L of SYBR mix, 0.5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L of forward primer, 0.5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L of reverse primer, 2.0&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L of cDNA template, and 8.0&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L of RNase-free dH<sub>2</sub>O, with a total volume of 20&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L. The relative expression of H19 (forward, 5&#x02032;-TGCTGCACTTTA CAACCACTG-3&#x02032;; reverse, 5&#x02032;-ATGGTGTCTTTGATGTTGGGC-3&#x02032;), miR-675 (forward, 5&#x02032;-TGGTGCGGAGAGGGCCCACAGTG-3&#x02032;; reverse, 5&#x02032;-GCGAGCACAGAATTAATACGAC-3&#x02032;), miR-138 (forward, 5&#x02032;-GGTGTCGTGGAGTCGGCAA-3&#x02032;; reverse, 5&#x02032;-AACTTCACAACACCAGCTTA-3&#x02032;), HIF1&#x003b1; mRNA (forward, 5&#x02032;-CGGGATCCTCTCTAGTCTCACGAGGGGTTTCC-3&#x02032;; reverse, 5&#x02032;-GCTCTAGAGATGCTACTGCAATGCAATGGTT-3&#x02032;), and eNOS mRNA (forward, 5&#x02032;-GCCAATGCAGTGAAGATC-3&#x02032;; reverse, 5&#x02032;-GCACAGAAGTGCGGGTAT-3&#x02032;) was calculated using the 2<sup>&#x02212;&#x00394;&#x00394;Ct</sup> method, while the expression of U6 (forward, 5&#x02032;-CGCTTCGGCAGCACATATACTA-3&#x02032;; reverse, 5&#x02032;-TGCTGTAGCCAAATTCGTTG-3&#x02032;), and GAPDH (forward, 5&#x02032;-TCAGTGGTGGACCTGACCTG-3&#x02032;; reverse, 5&#x02032;-TGCTGTAGCCAAATTCGTTG-3&#x02032;) were used as the internal reference.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.4"><title>Cell Culture and Transfection</title><p id="p0085">SH-SY5Y and U251 cells were cultured at 37&#x000b0;C and 5% CO<sub>2</sub> in a&#x000a0;95% humidity incubator. For transfection experiments, the cells&#x000a0;were maintained in a DMEM culture medium supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum (Gibco, Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA). When the cells reached a density of 85%, they were trypsinized using 0.25% trypsin and passaged. Subsequently, the cells in the logarithmic phase of growth were seeded into 96-well plates at a density of 2&#x000a0;&#x000d7; 10<sup>4</sup> cells/well and cultured overnight. On the next day, the cells were transfected using Lipofectamine 2000 (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA) following the instruction of the manufacturer. After transfection, the cells were cultured at 37&#x000b0;C for 48&#x000a0;h before they were collected for subsequent analyses. In addition, for experiments of MEL treatment, the cells were treated with different concentrations of MEL for 24&#x000a0;h prior to the measurement of expression of various target genes.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.5"><title>Vector Construction, Mutagenesis, and Luciferase Assay</title><p id="p0090">To investigate the regulatory relationship of H19/miR-138, miR-138/eNOS, and miR-675/HIF1&#x003b1;, as well as to investigate the effects of MEL treatment on the activity of H19 promoter, full-length sequences of H19, miR-138, and miR-675, as well as the 3&#x02032; UTR sequences of HIF1&#x003b1; and eNOS containing the binding sites for miR-675 and miR-138, respectively, were cloned into pcDNA luciferase vectors (Promega, Madison, WI, USA). At the same time, site-directed mutagenesis was carried out in the site of interaction of H19/miR-138, miR-138/eNOS, and miR-675/HIF1&#x003b1; to create mutant vectors of H19, miR-138, miR-675, HIF1&#x003b1;, and eNOS. Subsequently, SH-SY5Y and U251 cells were co-transfected with wild-type and mutant vectors of genes of interest, and the luciferase activity of transfected cells was measured using a dual-luciferase reporter gene assay kit (Promega, Madison, WI, USA) at 48&#x000a0;h after transfection on a luminescence plate reader (Promega, Madison, WI, USA).</p></sec><sec id="sec4.6"><title>Western Blot Analysis</title><p id="p0095">Cell and tissue samples were harvested and lysed in an SDS lysis buffer to extract sample&#x000a0;proteins, which were then heated to 100&#x000b0;C for 5&#x000a0;min and loaded (20&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L per sample) onto a 10% polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (PAGE) gel. Subsequently, the resolved proteins were transferred onto a polyvinylidene fluoride (PVDF) membrane at a voltage of 48 V, and the membrane was incubated with 5%&#x000a0;bovine serum albumin for 2&#x000a0;h at room temperature to block&#x000a0;endogenous antibodies. In the next step, after being rinsed&#x000a0;in tris-buffered saline and Tween 20 (TBST), the membrane was incubated overnight at 4&#x000b0;C with anti-HIF1&#x003b1; (cat. no. #3716S, 1:500 dilution, Cell Signaling Technologies, Beverly, MA, USA) and anti-eNOS primary antibodies (cat. no. #9572S, 1:500 dilution, Cell Signaling Technologies, Beverly, MA, USA). After the incubation with primary antibodies, the membrane was washed with 1&#x000d7;&#x000a0;TBST and then incubated with horseradish peroxidase (HRP)-labeled secondary antibodies (cat. no. sc2357, 1:2,000 dilution, Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Santa Cruz, CA, USA). After the incubation, the membrane was washed with TBST again and then developed in enhanced chemiluminescence reagents (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA). The relative protein expression of HIF1&#x003b1; and eNOS was then calculated using GAPDH as the internal control.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.7"><title>Immunohistochemistry</title><p id="p0100">Tissue samples were fixed in 10% formaldehyde, dehydrated in gradient alcohol, embedded in paraffin, and sliced into 4-&#x003bc;m sections. The sections were then dewaxed and dehydrated by gradient alcohol (95%, 80%, and 75%; 1&#x000a0;min each step). After being washed by running water for 1&#x000a0;min, the sections were incubated with 3%&#x000a0;H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> at 37&#x000b0;C for 30&#x000a0;min, followed by a PBS rinse. In the next step, the sections were boiled in 0.01&#x000a0;M citrate buffer at 95&#x000b0;C for 20&#x000a0;min. After being cooled down to room temperature, the sections were washed again by PBS. Subsequently, the sections were blocked with normal goat serum at 37&#x000b0;C for 10&#x000a0;min and incubated with anti-HIF1&#x003b1; and anti-eNOS monoclonal antibodies (1:100 dilution, Abcam, Cambridge, MA, USA) overnight at 4&#x000b0;C.&#x000a0;Following the incubation, the sections were washed with PBS for 2&#x000a0;min and incubated with HRP-conjugated secondary antibodies (1:1,000 dilution, Abcam, Cambridge, MA, USA) at room temperature for 30&#x000a0;min. Afterward, the sections were developed with diaminobenzidine (DAB), counterstained with hematoxylin, and mounted. In the next step, 10 view fields were randomly selected on each section and observed under a microscope to determine the percentage of cells positive for the expression of target genes.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.8"><title>H&#x00026;E Staining</title><p id="p0105">The collected tissue samples were dissected and fixed overnight at 4&#x000b0;C with 4% paraformaldehyde. These samples were then embedded in paraffin and sectioned for H&#x00026;E staining, which was carried out according to the instruction of an H&#x00026;E staining kit (Beyotime Biotechnology, Shanghai, China).</p></sec><sec id="sec4.9"><title>TUNEL Assay</title><p id="p0110">Collected tissues were stained according to the instructions of a TUNEL kit (Beyotime Biotechnology, Shanghai, China) to observe the status of cell apoptosis in different samples. In brief, the tissue samples were made into paraffin sections, dewaxed by a conventional xylene treatment, rehydrated by gradient alcohol, blocked with 3% H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> solution at room temperature for 10&#x000a0;min, and incubated with the reagents in the kit following the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. Finally, the sections were observed and photographed under a fluorescence microscope (BX53, Olympus, Tokyo, Japan) to analyze the apoptotic profile of the samples.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.10"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p id="p0115">All results were analyzed by SPSS statistical software version 21.0. Each experiment was repeated in triplicate. All measurement data were expressed as mean&#x000a0;&#x000b1; SD. The t test was used for comparing two groups, while a one-way ANOVA was used for comparing multiple groups, with a Scheff&#x000e9; test being used as a post hoc test. A p value of &#x0003c;0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p></sec><sec id="sec4.11"><title>Ethics Approval and Consent to Participate</title><p id="p0120">All animal experiments were performed in line with internationally recognized guidelines for the care and use of laboratory animals.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="sec4.12"><title>Availability of Data and Material</title><p id="p0125">The data that support the findings of this study are available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec5"><title>Author Contributions</title><p id="p0130">G.H. and H.C. planned the study; G.H., H.C., Y.Y., Y.P., and F.J. collected and analyzed the data; G.H. and Y.P. composed the manuscript, and all the other co-authors approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="sec6"><title>Conflicts of Interest</title><p id="p0135">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Gijn</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerr</surname><given-names>R.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rinkel</surname><given-names>G.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Subarachnoid haemorrhage</article-title><source>Lancet</source><volume>369</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>306</fpage><lpage>318</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17258671</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>J.T.</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name></person-group><article-title>Epidemiology of aneurysmal subarachnoid hemorrhage</article-title><source>Neuroimaging Clin. N. Am.</source><volume>7</volume><year>1997</year><fpage>659</fpage><lpage>668</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9336491</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ingall</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Asplund</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000e4;h&#x000f6;nen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonita</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A multinational comparison of subarachnoid hemorrhage epidemiology in the WHO MONICA stroke study</article-title><source>Stroke</source><volume>31</volume><year>2000</year><fpage>1054</fpage><lpage>1061</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10797165</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ersahin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Toklu</surname><given-names>H.Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cetinel</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Y&#x000fc;ksel</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye&#x0011f;en</surname><given-names>B.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sener</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Melatonin reduces experimental subarachnoid hemorrhage-induced oxidative brain damage and neurological symptoms</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Pineal Res.</source><volume>46</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>324</fpage><lpage>332</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19215574</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ayer</surname><given-names>R.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugawara</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Melatonin decreases mortality following severe subarachnoid hemorrhage</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Pineal Res.</source><volume>44</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>197</fpage><lpage>204</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18289172</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>A.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sehba</surname><given-names>F.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bederson</surname><given-names>J.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Decreased nitric oxide availability contributes to acute cerebral ischemia after subarachnoid hemorrhage</article-title><source>Neurosurgery</source><volume>47</volume><year>2000</year><fpage>208</fpage><lpage>214</lpage><comment>discussion 214&#x02013;215</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10917364</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moncada</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Higgs</surname><given-names>E.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nitric oxide: physiology, pathophysiology, and pharmacology</article-title><source>Pharmacol. Rev.</source><volume>43</volume><year>1991</year><fpage>109</fpage><lpage>142</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1852778</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khurana</surname><given-names>V.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sohni</surname><given-names>Y.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mangrum</surname><given-names>W.I.</given-names></name><name><surname>McClelland</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Kane</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>F.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meissner</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Endothelial nitric oxide synthase gene polymorphisms predict susceptibility to aneurysmal subarachnoid hemorrhage and cerebral vasospasm</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Cereb. Blood Flow Metab.</source><volume>24</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>291</fpage><lpage>297</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15091109</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Semenza</surname><given-names>G.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Agani</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Feldser</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Iyer</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kotch</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Laughner</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hypoxia, HIF-1, and the pathophysiology of common human diseases</article-title><source>Adv. Exp. Med. Biol.</source><volume>475</volume><year>2000</year><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>130</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10849654</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhardwaj</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SAH-induced cerebral vasospasm: unraveling molecular mechanisms of a complex disease</article-title><source>Stroke</source><volume>34</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>427</fpage><lpage>433</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shivdasani</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MicroRNAs: regulators of gene expression and cell differentiation</article-title><source>Blood</source><volume>108</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>3646</fpage><lpage>3653</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16882713</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bartel</surname><given-names>D.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MicroRNAs: genomics, biogenesis, mechanism, and function</article-title><source>Cell</source><volume>116</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>281</fpage><lpage>297</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14744438</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hung</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>H.Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long noncoding RNA in genome regulation: prospects and mechanisms</article-title><source>RNA Biol.</source><volume>7</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>582</fpage><lpage>585</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20930520</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miao</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bu</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Large-scale prediction of long non-coding RNA functions in a coding-non-coding gene co-expression network</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><volume>39</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>3864</fpage><lpage>3878</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21247874</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long non-coding RNA and microRNA-675/let-7a mediates the protective effect of melatonin against early brain injury after subarachnoid hemorrhage via targeting TP53 and neural growth factor</article-title><source>Cell Death Dis.</source><volume>9</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>99</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29367587</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>H19-derived miR-675 contributes to bladder cancer cell proliferation by regulating p53 activation</article-title><source>Tumour Biol.</source><volume>37</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>263</fpage><lpage>270</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26198047</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>W.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>W.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>C.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>G.X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>L.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>D.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Waye</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The lncRNA H19 promotes epithelial to mesenchymal transition by functioning as miRNA sponges in colorectal cancer</article-title><source>Oncotarget</source><volume>6</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>22513</fpage><lpage>22525</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26068968</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lei</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>2-methoxyestradiol reduces cerebral vasospasm after 48 hours of experimental subarachnoid hemorrhage in rats</article-title><source>Exp. Neurol.</source><volume>202</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>348</fpage><lpage>356</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16904108</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref19"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reiter</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pineal melatonin: cell biology of its synthesis and of its physiological interactions</article-title><source>Endocr. Rev.</source><volume>12</volume><year>1991</year><fpage>151</fpage><lpage>180</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1649044</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olayaki</surname><given-names>L.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alagbonsi</surname><given-names>I.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdulrahim</surname><given-names>A.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Adeyemi</surname><given-names>W.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bakare</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Omeiza</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Melatonin prevents and ameliorates lead-induced gonadotoxicity through antioxidative and hormonal mechanisms</article-title><source>Toxicol. Ind. Health</source><volume>34</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>596</fpage><lpage>608</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29759042</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Onuki</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Almeida</surname><given-names>E.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Medeiros</surname><given-names>M.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Mascio</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibition of 5-aminolevulinic acid-induced DNA damage by melatonin, N1-acetyl-N2-formyl-5-methoxykynuramine, quercetin or resveratrol</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Pineal Res.</source><volume>38</volume><year>2005</year><fpage>107</fpage><lpage>115</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15683465</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref22"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luchetti</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Canonico</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Betti</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arcangeletti</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pilolli</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Piroddi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Canesi</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Papa</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Galli</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Melatonin signaling and cell protection function</article-title><source>FASEB J.</source><volume>24</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>3603</fpage><lpage>3624</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20534884</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref23"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aydin</surname><given-names>M.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Caner</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sen</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ozen</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Atalay</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cekinmez</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Altinors</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of melatonin on cerebral vasospasm following experimental subarachnoid hemorrhage</article-title><source>Neurol. Res.</source><volume>27</volume><year>2005</year><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15829164</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref24"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martinez-Cruz</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Espinar</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pozo</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Osuna</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guerrero</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Melatonin prevents focal rat cerebellum injury as assessed by induction of heat shock protein (HO-1) following subarachnoid injections of lysed blood</article-title><source>Neurosci. Lett.</source><volume>331</volume><year>2002</year><fpage>208</fpage><lpage>210</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12383932</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref25"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nanda</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ras protein contributes to cerebral vasospasm in a canine double-hemorrhage model</article-title><source>Stroke</source><volume>35</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>1750</fpage><lpage>1755</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15143294</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref26"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cullen</surname><given-names>B.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The imprinted H19 noncoding RNA is a primary microRNA precursor</article-title><source>RNA</source><volume>13</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>313</fpage><lpage>316</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17237358</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref27"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sehba</surname><given-names>F.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pluta</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The importance of&#x000a0;early brain injury after subarachnoid hemorrhage</article-title><source>Prog. Neurobiol.</source><volume>97</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>14</fpage><lpage>37</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22414893</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref28"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McGirt</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parra</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheng</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pearlstein</surname><given-names>R.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Laskowitz</surname><given-names>D.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pelligrino</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Warner</surname><given-names>D.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Simvastatin increases endothelial nitric oxide synthase and ameliorates cerebral vasospasm resulting from subarachnoid hemorrhage</article-title><source>Stroke</source><volume>33</volume><year>2002</year><fpage>2950</fpage><lpage>2956</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12468796</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref29"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kusaka</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schonholz</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nanda</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Caspase inhibitors prevent endothelial apoptosis and cerebral vasospasm in dog model of experimental subarachnoid hemorrhage</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Cereb. Blood Flow Metab.</source><volume>24</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>419</fpage><lpage>431</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15087711</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref30"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kusaka</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishikawa</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nanda</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Granger</surname><given-names>D.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Signaling pathways for early brain injury after subarachnoid hemorrhage</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Cereb. Blood Flow Metab.</source><volume>24</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>916</fpage><lpage>925</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15362722</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref31"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Calvert</surname><given-names>J.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Colohan</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multiple effects of hyperbaric oxygen on the expression of HIF-1 alpha and apoptotic genes in a global ischemia-hypotension rat model</article-title><source>Exp. Neurol.</source><volume>191</volume><year>2005</year><fpage>198</fpage><lpage>210</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15589527</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref32"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Most</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lerchenm&#x000fc;ller</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rengo</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahlmann</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ritterhoff</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rohde</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Busch</surname><given-names>C.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Laube</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heissenberg</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>S100A1 deficiency impairs postischemic angiogenesis via compromised proangiogenic endothelial cell function and nitric oxide synthase regulation</article-title><source>Circ. Res.</source><volume>112</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>66</fpage><lpage>78</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23048072</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref33"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pluta</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>B.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dawson</surname><given-names>T.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>S.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boock</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oldfield</surname><given-names>E.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Loss of nitric oxide synthase immunoreactivity in cerebral vasospasm</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Neurosurg.</source><volume>84</volume><year>1996</year><fpage>648</fpage><lpage>654</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8613858</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref34"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khurana</surname><given-names>V.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>L.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eguchi</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Brien</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Katusic</surname><given-names>Z.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Protective vasomotor effects of in&#x000a0;vivo recombinant endothelial nitric oxide synthase gene expression in a canine model of cerebral vasospasm</article-title><source>Stroke</source><volume>33</volume><year>2002</year><fpage>782</fpage><lpage>789</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11872904</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref35"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grasso</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An overview of new pharmacological treatments for cerebrovascular dysfunction after experimental subarachnoid hemorrhage</article-title><source>Brain Res. Brain Res. Rev.</source><volume>44</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>63</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14739002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref36"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aladag</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Turkoz</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sahna</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parlakpinar</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gul</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The attenuation of vasospasm by using a sod mimetic after experimental subarachnoidal haemorrhage in rats</article-title><source>Acta Neurochir. (Wien)</source><volume>145</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>673</fpage><lpage>677</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14520547</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref37"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Toda</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ayajiki</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Okamura</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Preganglionic and postganglionic neurons responsible for cerebral vasodilation mediated by nitric oxide in anesthetized dogs</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Cereb. Blood Flow Metab.</source><volume>20</volume><year>2000</year><fpage>700</fpage><lpage>708</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10779014</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref38"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagata</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Town</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsui</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Asano</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intracisternal increase of superoxide anion production in a canine subarachnoid hemorrhage model</article-title><source>Stroke</source><volume>32</volume><year>2001</year><fpage>636</fpage><lpage>642</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11239179</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>