<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Heliyon</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Heliyon</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Heliyon</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2405-8440</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31938746</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6953709</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S2405-8440(19)36803-3</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2019.e03144</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e03144</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Teachers&#x02019; burnout: A SEM analysis in an Asian context</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name><surname>Prasojo</surname><given-names>Lantip Diat</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name><surname>Habibi</surname><given-names>Akhmad</given-names></name><email>Akhmad.habibi@unja.ac.id</email><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#x02217;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3"><name><surname>Mohd Yaakob</surname><given-names>Mohd Faiz</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4"><name><surname>Pratama</surname><given-names>Robin</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au5"><name><surname>Yusof</surname><given-names>Mat Rahimi</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au6"><name><surname>Mukminin</surname><given-names>Amirul</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au7"><name><surname>Suyanto</surname></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au8"><name><surname>Hanum</surname><given-names>Farida</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Universitas Negeri Yogyakarta, Indonesia</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Universitas Jambi, Indonesia</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Universiti Utara Malaysia, Malaysia</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x02217;</label>Corresponding author. <email>Akhmad.habibi@unja.ac.id</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>09</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>1</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>09</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>e03144</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>8</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>13</day><month>11</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>30</day><month>12</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2019 The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><license license-type="CC BY" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="abs0010"><p>Researchers in educational psychology have researched Teacher Self-Concept (TSC) and Teacher Efficacy (TE) as two main predictors predicting burnout. Guided by a model developed by Zhu, Liu, Fu, Yang, Zhang &#x00026; Shi (2018), the researchers aimed at building a model involving TSC, TE, and three components of burnout; Emotional Exhaustion (EE), Depersonalization (DP), and Reduced Personal Accomplishment (RPA) through Structural Equation Modeling (SEM). The researchers investigated predicting factors of burnout by reporting TSC and TE that might directly affect the components and examine the probability of TE to become a mediator of the correlation between TSC and burnout. This research also examined whether the difference emerges constantly among demographic information (gender and teaching experience) regarding all involved variables. A sample of 876 teachers across three Indonesian provinces completed a printed form of questionnaires. Some statistical procedures namely Content Validity Index (CVI), Exploratory Factor Analysis (EFA), Confirmatory Factor Analysis (CFA), Covariance-Based Structural Equation Modeling (CB-SEM), and t-test were conducted. Findings informed that the model is valid and reliable. TSC could directly affect EE, DE, and RPA, as well as indirectly influence them mediated by TE. Besides, TE is also reported to have significant relationships with EE, DE, and RPA. No significant differences in terms of age and teaching experiences emerge, except for EE.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="teaser" id="abs0015"><p>Teachers, TSC, TE, Burnout, Gender, Teaching experience, Education; Educational psychology; Health education; Pedagogy; Teaching research, Psychology.</p></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Teachers</kwd><kwd>TSC</kwd><kwd>TE</kwd><kwd>Burnout</kwd><kwd>Gender</kwd><kwd>Teaching experience</kwd><kwd>Education</kwd><kwd>Educational psychology</kwd><kwd>Health education</kwd><kwd>Pedagogy</kwd><kwd>Teaching research</kwd><kwd>Psychology</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0010">The teaching profession has been considered as a highly stressful job with multiple stressors resulting in a high risk of burnout (<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Friedman, 2003</xref>). Work-related pressures like catching up with submission deadlines, adapting to unhealthy working conditions, and dealing with problematic students were among the challenges faced by the teachers. The constant exposures of the teachers on these situations, if not properly handled, may turn them into possibilities of experiencing a malfunctioned reaction called &#x0201c;burnout&#x0201d;.</p><p id="p0015">Theoretically, there are three components of burnout that have been introduced and conceptualized called &#x0201c;Maslach Burnout Inventory&#x0201d; (MBI) (<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Maslach et&#x000a0;al., 1996</xref>). The parts of burnout have gained international acceptance and were validated in many studies (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Chan, 2007</xref>) while investigating the specific predictors on burnout components is an exciting research topic. Teacher's self-perceptions have been now significantly and increasingly investigated as essential factors affecting burnout. Guided by the model established by <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Zhu et&#x000a0;al. (2018)</xref> in China and the model of TE by <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Tschannen-Moran et&#x000a0;al. (1998)</xref>, this research aimed at investigating whether and how TSC and TE can affect the components of burnout speculating that TSC would affect burnout through TE. Besides, the researchers also examined the significant differences in term of gender and teaching experiences for all constructs.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><label>2</label><title>Literature review</title><sec id="sec2.1"><label>2.1</label><title>Teacher burnout</title><p id="p0020"><xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Maslach (1999)</xref> defined &#x0201c;burnout&#x0201d; for a malfunctioned reaction to severe psychological and relational stressors, especially at the workplace. Moreover, it happens even in the interpersonal-purposed occupation, including teaching professions. Workers who have severe burnout syndrome influence their overload to their peers as well as their own experience. They might perform a syndrome of EE, DE, RPA (<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Maslach, 1999</xref>). In a specific way, EE shows depletion of emotional sources. DE is a detached behavior towards the receivers. RPA refers to a feeling of being incompetent doing a job. These three components have been agreed by many educational academics to be separately investigated constructs as they are influenced by various kinds of cycles (<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Skaalvik and Skaalvik, 2010</xref>) which are also applied in this research context. The burnout model found by <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Maslach and Leiter (1997)</xref> was implemented to elaborate the predictors of teachers&#x02019; burnout for Asian context, especially in Indonesia.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><label>2.2</label><title>Teacher efficacy</title><p id="p0025">Many researchers have explored TE (e.g. <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Bandura, 1977</xref>; <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Love et&#x000a0;al., 2019</xref>; <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Rotter, 1966</xref>). In the beginning, <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Rotter (1966)</xref> explored TE from the perspective of teaching activities informing that reinforcement is considered to be not of teachers' control when they perceived that the effects of the environment are more significant than teachers' control or it outreaches their abilities or locus of control. Afterwards, <xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Bandura (1977)</xref> stated that efficacy is a belief to achieve goals from one's capabilities namely self-efficacy as future-oriented thought; she/he can decide what activities to choose and how much effort to do as well as how long to deal with emerged challenges. This research adapted Bandura's proposal where TE is a definition of a judgment of one's capabilities to include desired outcomes of student engagement.</p><p id="p0030">The correlational studies between TE and burnout have been investigated by many researchers (e.g. <xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Dicke et&#x000a0;al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Friedman, 2003</xref>; <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Leiter, 1992</xref>; <xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Tang et&#x000a0;al., 2001</xref>; <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Wang et&#x000a0;al., 2015</xref>). For example, <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Leiter (1992)</xref> reported TE as an efficacy crisis or <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Friedman (2003)</xref> as a breakdown of efficacy. On the other hand, TE was reported to be positive as a factor protecting someone from burnout or a personal resource to decrease the level of burnout (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Dicke et&#x000a0;al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Schwarzer et&#x000a0;al., 2000</xref>). Quantitatively, <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Brown (2012)</xref> reported that there was a strong relationship between TE to EE and RPA and the relationship between TE and DE. In addition, multivariate analysis for 16 works of literature presented a weak correlation between classroom management efficacy and burnout. Meanwhile, the strongest correlation emerged between personal accomplishment and classroom management efficacy.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><label>2.3</label><title>Teacher Self-Concept</title><p id="p0035">TSC was defined as teachers&#x02019; perception of the evaluation of the effectiveness of instructional activities (<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Yeung et&#x000a0;al., 2014</xref>). Teachers with negative TSC can have an emotional problem or stress (<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Villa and Calvete, 2001</xref>), which might cause burnout. Some empirical researchers have investigated the correlation between TSC and burnout (e.g. <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Friedman and Farber, 1992</xref>; <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Rad and Nasir, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Villa and Calvete, 2001</xref>). <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">Friedman and Farber (1992)</xref> through a sample of primary school teachers responding to a TSC scale for items like personal competence and burnout revealed that teachers with negative satisfaction of professionalism had a higher chance of suffering burnout. Meanwhile, <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Rad and Nasir (2010)</xref> reported a negative link between TSC and burnout through a sample of 150 senior teachers. Similarly, <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Villa and Calvete (2001)</xref> reported a poor relationship between TSC and burnout.</p><p id="p0040">In this research, TSC is defined as teaching competence beliefs that is different from SE in several terms used in previous studies (<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Bong and Skaalvik, 2003</xref>). Specifically, TSC is a general perspective that uses more general measures. It has significant effects on evaluation which strongly depends on social comparison gaining reflection to perceived competence. On the other hand, SE in this study is examined by a context-based evaluation that focuses on whether capability reaches objective goals or standards.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.4"><label>2.4</label><title>Mediation effects</title><p id="p0045"><xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Tschannen-Moran et&#x000a0;al. (1998)</xref>, who submitted a model for the natural cycles of TE emphasized the significant role of the cognitive process. Teachers are suggested to assess the resources of efficacy in establishing their TE by analyzing their daily teaching skills and ability as well as instructional tasks. Therefore, the efficacy formation is preceded by the assessment of teaching competence. <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Poulou (2007)</xref> encouraged the theory by investigating the predictors that affect TE. The results informed that self-perception of instructional competence and personal signs as well as positively affected TE. <xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Poulou (2007)</xref> opined on the broader construct consisting of general aspects of competence which might have a substantial contribution to TE. Based on these backgrounds, the investigation was carried out to confirm whether TSC has a contribution to burnout through TE.</p><p id="p0050">The researchers further investigated if the mediation emerges continually among demographic information of gender and teaching experience. Gender has been reported to have a significant difference in predicting TSC, TE and burnout. Some studies (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Grayson and Alvarez, 2008</xref>; <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Purvanova and Muros, 2010</xref>) informed that females showed more EE, while men suffered more DE and RPA. Meanwhile, for teaching experience, young teachers had a more burnout than that of senior ones (<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">Gavish and Friedman, 2010</xref>) and more experienced teachers had higher self-efficacy that new teachers did (<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Tschannen-Moran and Hoy, 2007</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec2.5"><label>2.5</label><title>Hypotheses</title><p id="p0055">Six hypotheses were included to help guide the readers of this study. <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;1</xref> exhibits the proposed path model of the study with six hypotheses.<statement id="enun_H1"><label>H1</label><p id="p0060">There will be a significant relationship between TSC and TE</p></statement><statement id="enun_H2"><label>H2</label><p id="p0065">There will be a significant relationship between TSC and EE</p></statement><statement id="enun_H3"><label>H3</label><p id="p0070">There will be a significant relationship between TE and EE</p></statement><statement id="enun_H4"><label>H4</label><p id="p0075">There will be a significant relationship between TSC and DE</p></statement><statement id="enun_H5"><label>H5</label><p id="p0080">There will be a significant relationship between TE and DE</p></statement><statement id="enun_H6"><label>H6</label><p id="p0085">There will be a significant relationship between TSC and RPA</p></statement><statement id="enun_H7"><label>H7</label><p id="p0090">There will be a significant relationship between TE and RPA</p></statement><fig id="fig1"><label>Figure&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Model of the research.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0010">Figure&#x000a0;1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><label>3</label><title>Method</title><p id="p0095">Some procedures were conducted to achieve the purpose of this research, namely; Content Validity Index (CVI), EFA, CFA, CB-SEM, and t-test. Universitas Negeri Yogyakarta that funds this research did not require any ethical approval for the study. Informed consent was obtained from all individual participants involved in the study. The researchers ensured the anonymity of the participants.</p><sec id="sec3.1"><label>3.1</label><title>Scale development</title><p id="p0100">Five items of TSC were constructed from the TSC Evaluation Scale by <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Villa and Calvete (2001)</xref> measuring teachers&#x02019; general self-evaluation of competence. A survey instrument by <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Yu et&#x000a0;al. (1995)</xref> was adapted for TE with five items. High scores indicated higher TSC and TE. MBI items (<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Maslach et&#x000a0;al., 1996</xref>) were adapted for teacher burnout, comprising three sub-scales: EE (5 items), DE (3 items), and RPA (7 items). The items were measured on a 5-point Likert scale ranging from 1 = never to 5 = always. The adaptation of the instrument involved a discussion with five educational experts through content validity. Therefore, the final decision of eliminating few original items and changing the scales from a 7-point to a 5-point Likert was taken based on the careful consideration and discussion with the experts for context specific instrument (<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Hair et&#x000a0;al., 2010</xref>). The researchers also perform CVI, EFA, and CFA to further purify the instrument to fit the context. High scores on the scales specified the high possibility of being burnout. Through back-translation strategies, the translation of the instruments was done from English to Indonesian and Indonesian to English involving two professional translators (<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Colina et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec3.2"><label>3.2</label><title>Content Validity Index (CVI)</title><p id="p0105">A CVI procedure (<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Lynn, 1986</xref>; <xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Habibi et&#x000a0;al., 2020</xref>; <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Halek et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>) involving 10 Indonesian educational experts was conducted to establish the validity of the instruments to fit Indonesian educational context. The items were rated on a 4-point scale in the CVI process (1 = not relevant/not clear to 4 = very relevant/very clear) (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Halek et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>). The CVI was evaluated for the item level (I-CVI) and scale level (S-CVI). The I-CVI was evaluated by informing a score of 3 or 4 to the experts divided by the experts&#x02019; total number (<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Lynn, 1986</xref>). With ten experts, the I-CVI should not be less than the value of .780 (<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Habibi et&#x000a0;al., 2020</xref>; <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Halek et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>). The S-CVI was the average portion of the items on one scale rated 3 or 4 (average agreement by experts = S-CVI/AVE); the acceptable value for the S-CVI is .800 (<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Halek et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>). Only one item was deleted which scored lower than the I-CVI and S-CVI threshold.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.3"><label>3.3</label><title>Pilot study</title><p id="p0110">After the CVI process, a pilot study was done with 50 Indonesian teachers from one province. The researchers permitted the teachers to write comments about how they comprehended each item and confusing items were revised. In addition, a reliability test was conducted at this stage by assessing Cronbach's alpha values. No values were found to be less than .700 (<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">Pallant, 2016</xref>) as the cut off point for the Cronbach alpha evaluation.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.4"><label>3.4</label><title>Data collection</title><p id="p0115">As the reliability assessment of the pilot study was done, we distributed the instruments to the participants. Through, simple random sampling, the researchers distributed printed instrument to 1000 Indonesian high school teachers from 3 cities, Jambi, Bandung, and Yogyakarta. Eight hundred and seventy-six data were fully completed and measurable after the data screening process (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;1</xref>). There were 618 (70.54%) female respondents and 258 (29.35%) were males. Their teaching experience varied, 291 (33.22%) teachers whose teaching experience was less than five years and 585 (66.78) whose teaching experience was more than five years. The researchers referred to the theory of <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Ghaith and Shaaban (1999)</xref> who categorized teachers with less than five years teaching experience as novice teachers and with more than five years as experienced teachers.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1"><label>Table&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Summary statistics of demographic variables.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0020">Table&#x000a0;1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Variables</th><th>N</th><th>%</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="3">Gender</td></tr><tr><td>Male</td><td>618</td><td>70.5</td></tr><tr><td>Female</td><td>258</td><td>29.35</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Teaching experience</td></tr><tr><td>Less than five years</td><td>291</td><td>33.22</td></tr><tr><td>Five years and more</td><td>585</td><td>66.78</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec></sec><sec id="sec4"><label>4</label><title>Results</title><p id="p0120">Before the main procedures of data analysis (EFA, CFA, and CB-SEM) were conducted, the normality assessment was done by measuring the Skewness, Kurtosis, and Histogram. Hair at al. (2010) recommended the threshold value from -1 to +1 for the Skewness and -2 to +2 for the Kurtosis. Multicollinearity issue happens if the correlation matrix with correlations was more than 0.90 (<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Hair et&#x000a0;al., 2010</xref>).</p><sec id="sec4.1"><label>4.1</label><title>Preliminary analysis</title><p id="p0125">The findings of the Skewness and Kurtosis values of each construct were reported to be satisfactory (<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Hair et&#x000a0;al., 2010</xref>). The Skewness values were from -.675 to .004 and the Kurtosis values ranged from -.1.518 to .121. Using histogram that is a graph performing the real form the data distribution shape, the data were found to be normally distributed because they performed a higher distribution in the middle than the edge sides. In terms of multicollinearity, inter-correlations amongst the constructs ranged from .322 to .656. Therefore, the discriminant validities of the variables were reached because the correlation matrix with correlations was less than 0.90 (<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Hair et&#x000a0;al., 2010</xref>). The average mean value of TSC is (M = 3.75; SD = .492); TE (M = 4.05; SD = .580), EE (M = 3.82; SD = .662), DE (M = 3.78; SD = .556), RPA (M = 3.90; SD = 626). Overall, the summary statistics of each item is informed in <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;2</xref>.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl2"><label>Table&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Summary statistics of study constructs.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0025">Table&#x000a0;2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Scale items</th><th>M (SD)</th><th>SD</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="3">MBI</td></tr><tr><td>EE-Item 1</td><td>3.81</td><td>.758</td></tr><tr><td>EE-Item 2</td><td>3.72</td><td>.847</td></tr><tr><td>EE-Item 3</td><td>3.89</td><td>.833</td></tr><tr><td>EE-Item 4</td><td>3.67</td><td>.789</td></tr><tr><td>EE-Item 5</td><td>4.01</td><td>.810</td></tr><tr><td>DE-Item 1</td><td>3.96</td><td>.672</td></tr><tr><td>DE-Item 2</td><td>3.54</td><td>.672</td></tr><tr><td>DE-Item 3</td><td>3.83</td><td>.694</td></tr><tr><td>RPA-Item 1</td><td>3.94</td><td>.835</td></tr><tr><td>RPA-Item 2</td><td>3.96</td><td>.842</td></tr><tr><td>RPA-Item 3</td><td>3.89</td><td>.745</td></tr><tr><td>RPA-Item 4</td><td>3.84</td><td>.782</td></tr><tr><td>RPA-Item 5</td><td>3.84</td><td>.794</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">TSC</td></tr><tr><td>TSC-Item 1</td><td>4.08</td><td>.706</td></tr><tr><td>TSC-Item 2</td><td>4.03</td><td>.699</td></tr><tr><td>TSC-Item 3</td><td>4.12</td><td>.707</td></tr><tr><td>TSC-Item 4</td><td>4.11</td><td>.687</td></tr><tr><td>TSC-Item 5</td><td>3.90</td><td>.750</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">TE</td></tr><tr><td>TE-Item 1</td><td>3.69</td><td>.698</td></tr><tr><td>TE-Item 2</td><td>3.80</td><td>.611</td></tr><tr><td>TE-Item 3</td><td>3.74</td><td>.626</td></tr><tr><td>TE-Item 4</td><td>3.67</td><td>.674</td></tr><tr><td>TE-Item 5</td><td>3.81</td><td>.654</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec4.2"><label>4.2</label><title>Reliability and EFA results</title><p id="p0130">The main examination of the data was conducted through Cronbach's alpha to see the reliability, EFA, CFA for the factor analysis assessment, and CB-SEM for deciding the fit model (<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Hair et&#x000a0;al., 2010</xref>). Since the adapted instrument was translated form English into Indonesian, EFA was conducted to obtain new constructs from the study sample characteristics (<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Hair et&#x000a0;al., 2010</xref>). For the EFA procedure, component principal analysis (PCA) approach was used to formulate uncorrelated linear combination against observable variables. For the EFA, Kaiser Meyer Olkin (KMO), Bartlett's Test of Sphericity, eigenvalue, communality, and factor extraction were computed. The KMO value, greater than .500, is regarded as appropriate while the value of &#x0003e;.800 is considered to be highly satisfactory, and Bartlett's Test of Sphericity is significant at p &#x0003c; .050. Factors, with an eigenvalue &#x0003c;1.0, should be deleted from the factor list while communality value should not drop for less than .300 (<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Hair et&#x000a0;al., 2010</xref>). The value of factor loading for each item (&#x0003e;.400) is significant to confirm the questionnaire (<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Hair et&#x000a0;al., 2010</xref>).</p><p id="p0135">The complete explanation of reliability and EFA procedures can be seen in <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;3</xref>. The KMO value of the data was highly satisfactory (.925) and Bartlett's Test of Sphericity was 10084.447 (significant at <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; .001). Using Varimax rotation, five factors were achieved with eigenvalues from 1.014 to 8.975. No issue emerged for the Communality. One item (EE5) was eliminated due to highly detected cross-loading. The Cronbach's alpha (&#x003b1;) values ranged from .754 to 875.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl3"><label>Table&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>EFA results and Inter-item reliability test.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0030">Table&#x000a0;3</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Factor</th><th/><th>1</th><th>2</th><th>3</th><th>4</th><th>5</th><th>Communality</th><th>Eigenvalue</th><th>&#x003b1;</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="5">TSC</td><td>TSC3</td><td>.793</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td>.639</td><td>8.975</td><td>.875</td></tr><tr><td>TSC1</td><td>.780</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td>.565</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>TSC4</td><td>.771</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td>.570</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>TSC2</td><td>.732</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td>.531</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>TSC5</td><td>.533</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td>.597</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td rowspan="5">RPA</td><td>RPA2</td><td/><td>.766</td><td/><td/><td/><td>.707</td><td>1.722</td><td>.842</td></tr><tr><td>RPA3</td><td/><td>.758</td><td/><td/><td/><td>.643</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>RPA1</td><td/><td>.712</td><td/><td/><td/><td>.744</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>RPA4</td><td/><td>.709</td><td/><td/><td/><td>.769</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>TRA5</td><td/><td>.561</td><td/><td/><td/><td>.515</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td rowspan="5">TE</td><td>TE1</td><td/><td/><td>.712</td><td/><td/><td>.624</td><td>1.449</td><td>.810</td></tr><tr><td>TE3</td><td/><td/><td>.668</td><td/><td/><td>.760</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>TE5</td><td/><td/><td>.660</td><td/><td/><td>.675</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>TE4</td><td/><td/><td>.653</td><td/><td/><td>.717</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>TE2</td><td/><td/><td>.592</td><td/><td/><td>.667</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td rowspan="4">EE</td><td>EE2</td><td/><td/><td/><td>.774</td><td/><td>.745</td><td>1.213</td><td>.859</td></tr><tr><td>EE4</td><td/><td/><td/><td>.741</td><td/><td>.633</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>EE3</td><td/><td/><td/><td>.635</td><td/><td>.713</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>EE1</td><td/><td/><td/><td>.610</td><td/><td>.768</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">DE</td><td>DE2</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td>.827</td><td>.683</td><td>1.014</td><td>.754</td></tr><tr><td>DE1</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td>.742</td><td>.620</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>DE3</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td>.709</td><td>.490</td><td/><td/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec4.3"><label>4.3</label><title>Testing measurement model</title><p id="p0140">Following the EFA procedure, CFA was examined using three indices to confirm the EFA: the Chi-Square Test (&#x003c7;2), the Root Mean Square Error of Approximation (RMSEA), and the Standardized Root Mean Square of Residual (SRMR) were all measurements of this procedure. The relative goodness-of-fit indices recommended for this study are; Comperative Fit Index (CFI) and Tucker-Lewis Index (TLI). To achieve a fit model, the cut-off points were implemented for each measurement; RMSEA = &#x02264; .080 (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Kelley and Lai, 2011</xref>), SRMR = &#x02264; .08 (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Hu and Bentler, 1999</xref>), TLI = &#x02265; .900, and CFI = &#x02265; .900 (<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Hair et&#x000a0;al., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Kline, 2005</xref>).</p><p id="p0145">Using different samples, CFA was conducted in order to verify the EFA result or test measurement model. CFA can facilitate further evaluation regarding the fitness of the model in line with the structure of the factors (<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Hair et&#x000a0;al., 2010</xref>). The initial measurement model did not achieve the fit model; RMSEA = .069, SRMR = .026, TLI = &#x02265; .876, and the CFI = .918. In this initial measurement TLI did not meet the cut-off point. Besides, two items (RPA5 &#x00026; TE4) gained low loading values (<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Hair et&#x000a0;al., 2010</xref>). Therefore the two items were eliminated. All loading factors after the elimination of the two items were appropriate that ranged from .621 to .896 (<xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;4</xref>). The final results show good fit indices for the CFA; &#x003c7;2 = 830.366, &#x003c7;2/df = 5.190, RMSEA = .069, SRMR = .025, TLI = &#x02265; .914, and the CFI = .928. Cronbach's alpha (&#x003b1;) coefficients, composite reliability (CR) and average variance extracted (AVE) were calculated to determine the reliability of the instrument. <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Hair et&#x000a0;al. (2010)</xref> and <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">Pallant (2016)</xref> indicated that alpha values of 0.60&#x02013;0.70 are satisfactory. CR should be more than 0.60, whereas AVE should be above 0.50. <xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;4</xref> performs that all values of &#x003b1;, CR, and AVE exceed the requirements.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl4"><label>Table&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>CFA results of Final measurement model (all construct).</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0035">Table&#x000a0;4</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Construct</th><th>Item</th><th>Standardized loadings</th><th>(CR)</th><th>(AVE)</th><th>&#x003b1;</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="4">Emotional Exhaustion</td><td>EE1</td><td>.742</td><td>.778</td><td>.860</td><td>.859</td></tr><tr><td>EE2</td><td>.793</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>EE3</td><td>.797</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>EE4</td><td>.780</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Depersonalization</td><td>DE1</td><td>.682</td><td>.709</td><td>.753</td><td>.754</td></tr><tr><td>DE2</td><td>.682</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>DE3</td><td>.763</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td rowspan="4">Reduced Personal Achievement</td><td>RPA4</td><td>.621</td><td>.772</td><td>.859</td><td>.842</td></tr><tr><td>RPA3</td><td>.706</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>RPA2</td><td>.896</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>RPA1</td><td>.865</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td rowspan="4">Teacher self-concept</td><td>TSC1</td><td>.707</td><td>.698</td><td>.792</td><td>.828</td></tr><tr><td>TSC2</td><td>.717</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>TSC3</td><td>.663</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>TSC5</td><td>.706</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td rowspan="4">Teacher efficacy</td><td>TE1</td><td>.753</td><td>.745</td><td>.834</td><td>.792</td></tr><tr><td>TE2</td><td>.758</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>TE3</td><td>.810</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>TE5</td><td>.662</td><td/><td/><td/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>CR: composite reliability; AVE: Average Variance Extracted; &#x003b1;: Crobach's alpha.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec4.4"><label>4.4</label><title>Relationship between TSC, TE and burnout</title><p id="p0150">To support the path analysis of CB-SEM, the correlational analysis was conducted through Pearson correlation coefficient. This study implemented general <italic>r</italic> value guideline (<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Evans, 1996</xref>); 00-.19 as &#x0201c;very weak&#x0201d;; .20-.39 as &#x0201c;weak&#x0201d;; .40-.59 as &#x0201c;moderate&#x0201d;; .60-.79 as &#x0201c;strong&#x0201d;, and .80&#x02013;1.0 &#x0201c;very strong&#x0201d;. The findings of the study (<xref rid="tbl5" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;5</xref>) indicated that the correlation between TE and TSC is significant and moderate (<italic>r</italic> = .564, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; .01), TE and EE is significant and strong (<italic>r</italic> = .657, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; .01), TE and DE is significant and moderate (<italic>r</italic> = .452, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; .01), TE and RPA is significant and moderate (<italic>r</italic> = .550, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; .01), TSC and EE is significant and strong (<italic>r</italic> = .650, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; .01), TSC and DE is significant and moderate (<italic>r</italic> = .440, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; .01), TSC and RPA is significant and moderate (<italic>r</italic> = .578, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; .01), EE and DE is significant and weak (<italic>r</italic> = .380, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; .01), EE and RPA is significant and moderate (<italic>r</italic> = .656, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; .01), DE and RPA is significant and weak (<italic>r</italic> = .332, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; .01).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl5"><label>Table&#x000a0;5</label><caption><p>Pearson correlation results among the constructs (** <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; .01).</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0040">Table&#x000a0;5</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th>TSC</th><th>EE</th><th>DE</th><th>RPA</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>TE</td><td>.564**</td><td>.657**</td><td>.452**</td><td>.550**</td></tr><tr><td>TSC</td><td>1</td><td>.650**</td><td>.440**</td><td>.578**</td></tr><tr><td>EE</td><td/><td>1</td><td>.380**</td><td>.656**</td></tr><tr><td>DE</td><td/><td/><td>1</td><td>.322**</td></tr><tr><td>RPA</td><td/><td/><td/><td>1</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="p0155">Similar to the testing measurement model, some threshold points were also implemented for each measurement to assess the final model; RMSEA = &#x02264; .080, SRMR = &#x02264; .08, TLI = &#x02265; .900, and the CFI = &#x02265; .900. The findings of the SEM report the structural model of &#x003c7;2 = 881.682, &#x003c7;2/df = 5.4090, RMSEA = 0.071, TLI = .910 and CFI = .923. All loading values were in the range from .62 to .90, exceeding the desirable standard of .50 (<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Hair et&#x000a0;al., 2010</xref>). The hypothetical structural information for the CFA became the finalized model indicating correlation among TSC, TE, EE, DE, and TRA for the context of Indonesia or other developing countries. The final model from this research can be used as an option to support or argue the previous research on factors affecting burnout among teachers. In conclusion, the evaluations of the modeling were fit for the Indonesian context.</p><p id="p0160">TSC was included as an independent variable that predicted EE, DE, and RPA as burnout components, and TE was included as variable mediating TSC for burnout in the modeling process for this research. TSC had the stronger effect to EE (&#x003b2; = .69; <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; .001) than DE (&#x003b2; = .61; <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; .001) and RPA (&#x003b2; = .29 <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; .001). TE was correlated to all three burnout components. The TE effect of mediation could be essential. Through the mediation of TE, TSC had a greater indirect effect on DE (&#x003b2; = .29; <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; .001) and RPA (&#x003b2; = .29; <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; .001) than that of EE (&#x003b2; = .26; <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; .001) indicating a partial mediation effect. Additionally, the final result of the SEM process is depicted in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;2</xref> and <xref rid="tbl6" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;6</xref>.<fig id="fig2"><label>Figure&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Final study.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0015">Figure&#x000a0;2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl6"><label>Table&#x000a0;6</label><caption><p>SEM results for the structural model.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0045">Table&#x000a0;6</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Hypothesis</th><th>Path</th><th>&#x003b2;</th><th>S.E.</th><th>C.R.</th><th>p</th><th>Label</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><xref rid="enun_H1" ref-type="statement">H1</xref></td><td>TSC&#x02192;TE</td><td>.69</td><td>.053</td><td>15.496</td><td>&#x0003c;.001</td><td>Yes</td></tr><tr><td><xref rid="enun_H2" ref-type="statement">H2</xref></td><td>TSC&#x02192;EE</td><td>.26</td><td>.063</td><td>11.168</td><td>&#x0003c;.001</td><td>Yes</td></tr><tr><td><xref rid="enun_H3" ref-type="statement">H3</xref></td><td>TSC&#x02192;DE</td><td>.29</td><td>.057</td><td>5.860</td><td>&#x0003c;.001</td><td>Yes</td></tr><tr><td><xref rid="enun_H4" ref-type="statement">H4</xref></td><td>TSC&#x02192;RPA</td><td>.29</td><td>.077</td><td>9.128</td><td>&#x0003c;.001</td><td>Yes</td></tr><tr><td><xref rid="enun_H5" ref-type="statement">H5</xref></td><td>TE&#x02192;EE</td><td>.61</td><td>.044</td><td>5.795</td><td>&#x0003c;.001</td><td>Yes</td></tr><tr><td><xref rid="enun_H6" ref-type="statement">H6</xref></td><td>TE&#x02192;DE</td><td>.36</td><td>.046</td><td>5.002</td><td>&#x0003c;.001</td><td>Yes</td></tr><tr><td><xref rid="enun_H7" ref-type="statement">H7</xref></td><td>TE&#x02192;RPA</td><td>.47</td><td>.060</td><td>6.209</td><td>&#x0003c;.001</td><td>Yes</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec4.5"><label>4.5</label><title>Significance differences</title><p id="p0165">The study also investigated whether the demographic information (gender and teaching experience) differs regarding all constructs (TSC, TE, EE, DE, RPA). The t-test results reported that there is no statistical difference between male and female teachers concerning all constructs. Similarly, no significant differences emerge for teaching experience but one construct, DE (<italic>t</italic> = -3.417; <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; .005) Complete information and comparison of the values across the demographic can be seen in <xref rid="tbl7" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;7</xref>.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl7"><label>Table&#x000a0;7</label><caption><p>Differences regarding gender and teaching experience.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0050">Table&#x000a0;7</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td>Construct</td><td>Demographic information</td><td>n.</td><td>Mean</td><td>SD</td><td>t</td><td>df</td><td>p</td></tr><tr><td colspan="8"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">TSC</td><td>Female</td><td>618</td><td>4.08</td><td>.619</td><td>-.781</td><td>874</td><td>.435</td></tr><tr><td>Male</td><td>258</td><td>4.11</td><td>.540</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">TE</td><td>Female</td><td>618</td><td>3.74</td><td>.517</td><td>-1.039</td><td>874</td><td>.299</td></tr><tr><td>Male</td><td>258</td><td>3.79</td><td>.485</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">EE</td><td>Female</td><td>618</td><td>3.76</td><td>.674</td><td>-.432</td><td>874</td><td>.666</td></tr><tr><td>Male</td><td>258</td><td>3.79</td><td>.682</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">DE</td><td>Female</td><td>618</td><td>3.77</td><td>.569</td><td>-1.027</td><td>874</td><td>.305</td></tr><tr><td>Male</td><td>258</td><td>3.81</td><td>.522</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">RPA</td><td>Female</td><td>618</td><td>3.91</td><td>.664</td><td>-.064</td><td>874</td><td>.949</td></tr><tr><td>Male</td><td>258</td><td>3.91</td><td>.687</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>TSC</td><td>Beginner</td><td>291</td><td>4.04</td><td>.578</td><td>-1.301</td><td>874</td><td>.194</td></tr><tr><td/><td>Experienced</td><td>585</td><td>4.10</td><td>.605</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">TE</td><td>Beginner</td><td>291</td><td>3.73</td><td>.468</td><td>-1.233</td><td>874</td><td>.218</td></tr><tr><td>Experienced</td><td>585</td><td>3.77</td><td>.526</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">EE</td><td>Beginner</td><td>291</td><td>3.72</td><td>.661</td><td>-1.323</td><td>874</td><td>.186</td></tr><tr><td>Experienced</td><td>585</td><td>3.79</td><td>.684</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">DE</td><td>Beginner</td><td>291</td><td>3.68</td><td>.543</td><td>-3.417</td><td>874</td><td>&#x0003c;.005</td></tr><tr><td>Experienced</td><td>585</td><td>3.82</td><td>.557</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">RPA</td><td>Beginner</td><td>291</td><td>3.87</td><td>.603</td><td>-.892</td><td>874</td><td>.373</td></tr><tr><td>Experienced</td><td>291</td><td>4.04</td><td>.578</td><td/><td/><td/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec></sec><sec id="sec5"><label>5</label><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0170">Through CVI, reliability assessment after the pilot study, and factor analysis (EFA and CFA), the model that involves TSC, TE, and burnout components (DD, DE, and TRA) is informed to be valid and reliable for (<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Hair et&#x000a0;al., 2010</xref>). Through some modifications and deletions of few items, the model is decided to fit the relationship between predictors and teachers&#x02019; burnout in the context of Asia, especially Indonesia with all values measuring the model fulfill the common threshold values used by SEM researchers (<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">Pallant, 2016</xref>).</p><p id="p0175">The researchers examined TSC and TE as the exploring factors to predict teachers' burnout. The study includes a large sample of Asian culture and tested whether teachers&#x02019; burnout varies based on their demographic information. The findings are hoped to facilitate a current understanding of the systematic function of TSC and TE in predicting EE, DE, and TRA as the burnout components in a different context and circumstance. Based on CB-SEM analysis, the findings informed that TSC directly affects burnout, as well as indirectly influences burnout via TE. The findings of the research facilitate our hypotheses that have been assumed based on the study reported by <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Tschannen-Moran et&#x000a0;al. (1998)</xref> and <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Zhu et&#x000a0;al. (2018)</xref>. Generally, TSC provided a basis offer for teachers to perform judgment on efficacy. TSC and TE could work together as affecting protective factor to variables of burnout. The direct affecting findings of this are not accordance with previous research (e.g. <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Rad and Nasir, 2010</xref>; <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Villa and Calvete, 2001</xref>) that informed the negative correlation between TSC and all burnout variables. However, <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Zhu et&#x000a0;al. (2018)</xref> disclosed that TSC was confirmed to positively influence TRA. Compared to TSC, TE had better influences on burnout components, EE, DE, RPA.</p><p id="p0180">TSC has been described as a general belief of competence in instruction. This general belief can directly affect all components of burnout, TE, DE, and RPA and indirectly impact the other two syndromes of burnout through TE. Compared to TSC, TE had less impact on burnout. A possible elaboration for this might be that TE reflects a more specific perception of competence; thus, low TE could cause the increasing of burnout. Even though this study was carried out with teachers from a non-western psychosocial circumstance, teachers' professional appreciation has also been conducted based on individual achievement, similar to teaching appreciation in many western countries. Therefore, a social comparison should always be conducted in research about teachers&#x02019; burnout in the future with different cultures of the samples (<xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Zhu et&#x000a0;al., 2018</xref>).</p><p id="p0185">The findings of the also informed that most demographic information (gender and teaching experience) do not significantly differ regarding all constructs (TSC, TE, EE, DE, RPA). Only one construct in the burnout component (DE) is found to be different regarding teaching experience. The results of current study argue what <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Grayson and Alvarez (2008)</xref> and <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Purvanova and Muros (2010)</xref> found in the previous studies that informed that female respondents showed more EE, while men had more DE and RPA. On the other hand, for teaching experience, teachers with few experiences had more burnout than teachers with many experiences (<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">Gavish and Friedman, 2010</xref>) and more experienced teachers had higher TE than new teachers did (<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Tschannen-Moran and Hoy, 2007</xref>). Even though, the differences are reported to be insignificant in terms of teaching experience; it is suggested to maximally help teachers decrease their feeling of burnout by providing them with more teaching training to improve their skills and experience.</p></sec><sec id="sec6"><label>6</label><title>Conclusion and recommendation</title><p id="p0190">All predictors (TSC and TE) have been reported to be significant in predicting teachers' burnout. The findings of the research advocate the proposed model. The model can be a guidance for future Asian researchers to predict teachers&#x02019; burnout. On the other hand, the study informed that gender and teaching experience are not significantly different for all variables; one construct is reported to be different regarding teaching experience for DE. Based on the results of this study, the needs of building TSC and TE to prevent burnout is recommended for the Asian context. Educational stakeholders should ensure that schools can be institutions that teachers will be successful in promoting learning activities. As a result, TSC and TE are fostered and burnout can be eliminated. The simplest and most practical way for school is to facilitate teachers multiple opportunities experiencing beneficial teaching such an open course with some motivated students. Through this way, they can be motivated to keep developing their own style and influence other teachers for learning to teach. Working with peers would also be useful while making lesson plans. With this kind of self-learning and peer learning, they can accumulate experience and verbal encouragement and appreciation from expert teachers that will improve TSC and TE (<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Tschannen-Moran et&#x000a0;al., 1998</xref>).</p><p id="p0195">Some advantages of the concept and measure of this study can be detected. TSE was a concept of a general belief of teaching competence. The sample represented an appropriate size. The shifting condition in Indonesia from achievement attainment to process-based instruction in the 21<sup>st</sup>-century education make research about teachers' burnout, to be a priority since students&#x02019; academic performance is now less valued causing the students to have more problems with behaviors or discipline problems. Therefore, this research considered future research motivating students to both attain achievement and decrease student discipline problems. A limitation that should be considered is that the adopted TE items focused on promoting students attain good achievements, not their discipline problems. Since there have been many reports with students in the context of Indonesia, a more measurement to deal with students discipline problems must be considered. Another lack of this research is the method of this study; in-depth and enriched information through qualitative inquiry is recommended for future researchers, especially in developing countries.</p></sec><sec id="sec7"><title>Declarations</title><sec id="sec7.1"><title>Author contribution statement</title><p id="p0200">Lantip Diat Prasojo: Conceived and designed the experiments; Performed the experiments; Wrote the paper.</p><p id="p0205">Akhmad Habibi: Conceived and designed the experiments; Analyzed and interpreted the data; Contributed reagents, materials, analysis tools or data; Wrote the paper.</p><p id="p0210">Mohd Faiz Mohd Yaakob, Mat Rahimi Yusof, Amirul Mukminin, Suyanto: Contributed reagents, materials, analysis tools or data; Wrote the paper.</p><p id="p0215">Robin Pratama: Performed the experiments; Analyzed and interpreted the data; Contributed reagents, materials, analysis tools or data.</p><p id="p0220">Farida Hanum: Analyzed and interpreted the data; Wrote the paper.</p></sec><sec id="sec7.2"><title>Funding statement</title><p id="p0225">This research was fully funded by <funding-source id="gs1">Universitas Negeri Yogyakarta</funding-source> No. 4868AA/UN34/SPK/2019 done from January to June 2019.</p></sec><sec id="sec7.3"><title>Competing interest statement</title><p id="p0230">The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec id="sec7.4"><title>Additional information</title><p id="p0235">No additional information is available for this paper.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bandura</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Self-efficacy: toward a unifying theory of behavioral change</article-title><source>Psychol. Rev.</source><volume>84</volume><year>1977</year><fpage>191</fpage><lpage>215</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">847061</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bong</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Skaalvik</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Academic self-concept and self-efficacy: how different are they really?</article-title><source>Educ. Psychol. Rev.</source><volume>15</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>40</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>C.G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A&#x000a0;systematic review of the relationship between self-efficacy and burnout in teachers</article-title><source>Educ. Child Psychol.</source><volume>29</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>47</fpage><lpage>63</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>D.W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Burnout, self-efficacy, and successful intelligence among Chinese prospective and in-service school teachers in Hong Kong</article-title><source>Educ. Psychol.</source><volume>27</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2007</year><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>49</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Colina</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marrone</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ingram</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>S&#x000e1;nchez</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Translation quality assessment in health research: a functionalist alternative to back-translation</article-title><source>Eval. Health Prof.</source><volume>40</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>267</fpage><lpage>293</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27207929</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dicke</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>P.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marsh</surname><given-names>H.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kunter</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmeck</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leutner</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Self-efficacy in classroom management, classroom disturbances, and emotional exhaustion: a moderated mediation analysis of teacher candidates</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Educ. Psychol.</source><volume>106</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>569</fpage><lpage>583</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="optTXtSuLvxAV"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Straightforward Statistics for the Behavioral Sciences</source><year>1996</year><publisher-name>Brooks/Cole Publishing</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Pacific Grove</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>I.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Self-efficacy and burnout in teaching: the importance of interpersonal relations efficacy</article-title><source>Soc. Psychol. Educ.</source><volume>6</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2003</year><fpage>191</fpage><lpage>215</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>I.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Farber</surname><given-names>B.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Professional self-concept as a predictor of teacher burnout</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Educ. Res.</source><volume>86</volume><issue>1</issue><year>1992</year><fpage>28</fpage><lpage>35</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gavish</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>I.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Novice teachers&#x02019; experience of teaching: a dynamic aspect of burnout</article-title><source>Soc. Psychol. Educ.</source><volume>13</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>167</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ghaith</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaaban</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The relationship between perceptions of teaching concerns, teacher efficacy, and selected teacher characteristics</article-title><source>Teach. Teach. Educ.</source><volume>15</volume><year>1999</year><fpage>487</fpage><lpage>496</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grayson</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>H.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>School climate factors relating to teacher burnout: a mediator model</article-title><source>Teach. Teach. Educ.</source><volume>24</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2008</year><fpage>1349</fpage><lpage>1363</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hair</surname><given-names>J.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Black</surname><given-names>W.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Babin</surname><given-names>B.J.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Multivariate Data Analysis</chapter-title><year>2010</year><publisher-name>Pearson Prentice Hall</publisher-name><publisher-loc>New Jersey</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Habibi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yusop</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Razak</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The dataset for validation of factors affecting pre-service teachers&#x02019; use of ICT during teaching practices: Indonesian context</article-title><source>Data in Brief</source><volume>28</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>7</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Halek</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Holle</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartholomeyczik</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development and evaluation of the content validity, practicability and feasibility of the Innovative dementia-oriented Assessment system for challenging behaviour in residents with dementia</article-title><source>BMC Health Serv. Res.</source><volume>17</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>554</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28806934</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>L.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bentler</surname><given-names>P.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cutoff criteria for fit indexes in covariance structure analysis: conventional criteria versus new alternatives</article-title><source>Struct. Equ. Model.</source><volume>6</volume><issue>1</issue><year>1999</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>55</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Accuracy in parameter estimation for the root mean square error of approximation: sample size planning for narrow confidence intervals</article-title><source>Multivar. Behav. Res.</source><volume>46</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>32</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref17"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kline</surname><given-names>R.B.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Principles and Practice of Structural Equation Modeling</chapter-title><edition>second ed. ed.</edition><year>2005</year><publisher-name>The Guilford Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref19"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leiter</surname><given-names>M.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Burn-out as a crisis in self-efficacy: conceptual and practical implications</article-title><source>Work Stress</source><volume>6</volume><issue>2</issue><year>1992</year><fpage>107</fpage><lpage>115</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Love</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Toland</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Usher</surname><given-names>E.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Spriggs</surname><given-names>A.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Can I teach students with Autism Spectrum Disorder?: investigating teacher self-efficacy with an emerging population of students</article-title><source>Res. Dev. Disabil.</source><volume>89</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30913505</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lynn</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Determination and quantification of content validity</article-title><source>Nurs. Res.</source><volume>35</volume><year>1986</year><fpage>382</fpage><lpage>385</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3640358</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref22"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maslach</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Progress in understanding teacher burnout</chapter-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Vandenburghe</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huberman</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Understanding and Preventing Teacher Burnout: A Sourcebook of International Research and Practice</source><year>1999</year><publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc><fpage>211</fpage><lpage>222</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref23"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maslach</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leiter</surname><given-names>M.P.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>The Truth about Burnout</chapter-title><year>1997</year><publisher-name>Jossey Bass</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref24"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maslach</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>S.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leiter</surname><given-names>M.P.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title><italic>Maslach Burnout Inventory Manual</italic>. Mountain View</chapter-title><year>1996</year><publisher-name>CPP, Inc</publisher-name><publisher-loc>California</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref25"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pallant</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>SPSS Survival Manual: A Step by Step Guide to Data Analysis Using IBM SPSS</chapter-title><edition>sixth ed.</edition><year>2016</year><publisher-name>Allen &#x00026;Unwin</publisher-name><publisher-loc><italic>Crows Nest</italic>. NSW</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref26"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Poulou</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Personal teaching efficacy and its sources: student teachers&#x02019; perceptions</article-title><source>Educ. Psychol.</source><volume>27</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2007</year><fpage>191</fpage><lpage>218</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref27"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Purvanova</surname><given-names>R.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Muros</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gender differences in burnout: a meta-analysis</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Vocat. Behav.</source><volume>77</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>168</fpage><lpage>185</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref28"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rad</surname><given-names>A.Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nasir</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Burnout and career self concept among teachers in Mashhad, Iran</article-title><source>Procedia Soc. Behav. Sci.</source><volume>7</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>464</fpage><lpage>469</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref29"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rotter</surname><given-names>J.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Generalized expectancies for internal versus external control of reinforcement</article-title><source>Psychol. Monogr.</source><volume>80</volume><year>1966</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>28</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref30"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwarzer</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmitz</surname><given-names>G.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Teacher burnout in Hong Kong and Germany: a cross-cultural validation of the Maslach burnout inventory</article-title><source>Anxiety Stress Coping</source><volume>13</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2000</year><fpage>309</fpage><lpage>326</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref31"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Skaalvik</surname><given-names>E.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Skaalvik</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Teacher self-efficacy and teacher burnout: a study of relations</article-title><source>Teach. Teach. Educ.</source><volume>26</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>1059</fpage><lpage>1069</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref32"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>C.S.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Au</surname><given-names>W.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwarzer</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmitz</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mental health outcomes of jobstress among Chinese teachers: role of stress resource factors and burnout</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Organ. Behav.</source><volume>22</volume><issue>8</issue><year>2001</year><fpage>887</fpage><lpage>901</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref33"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tschannen-Moran</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoy</surname><given-names>A.W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The differential antecedents of self-efficacy beliefs of novice and experienced teachers</article-title><source>Teach. Teach. Educ.</source><volume>23</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2007</year><fpage>944</fpage><lpage>956</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref34"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tschannen-Moran</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoy</surname><given-names>A.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoy</surname><given-names>W.K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Teacher efficacy: its meaning andmeasure</article-title><source>R<italic>ev. Educ. Res.</italic></source><volume>68</volume><issue>2</issue><year>1998</year><fpage>202</fpage><lpage>248</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref35"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Villa</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Calvete</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development of the teacher self-concept evaluation scale and its relation to burnout</article-title><source>Stud. Educ. Eval.</source><volume>27</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2001</year><fpage>239</fpage><lpage>255</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref36"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>N.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahimi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Self-efficacy and causal attributions in teachers:Effects on burnout, job satisfaction, illness, and quitting intentions</article-title><source>Teach. Teach. Educ.</source><volume>47</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>120</fpage><lpage>130</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref37"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yeung</surname><given-names>A.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Craven</surname><given-names>R.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaur</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Teachers&#x02019; self-concept and valuing of learning:Relations with teaching approaches and beliefs about students</article-title><source>Asia Pac. J. Teach. Educ.</source><volume>42</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>305</fpage><lpage>320</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref38"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xin</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Teacher&#x02019;s sense of teaching efficacy: its structure and influencing factors</article-title><source>Acta Psychol. Sin.</source><volume>27</volume><issue>2</issue><year>1995</year><fpage>159</fpage><lpage>166</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref39"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The relationship between teacher self-concept, teacher efficacy and burnout</article-title><source>Teach. Teach.</source><volume>24</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>788</fpage><lpage>801</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list><ack id="ack0010"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank all respondents of this study for their time and willingness to complete the questionnaire.</p></ack></back></article>