<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="book-review"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Aust Prescr</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Aust Prescr</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">AP</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Australian Prescriber</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0312-8008</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1839-3942</issn><publisher><publisher-name>NPS MedicineWise</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6954875</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">austprescr-42-206</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18773/austprescr.2019.064</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Book Review</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Therapeutic Guidelines: Ulcers and wound management. Version 2</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vemuri</surname><given-names>Kanthi</given-names></name><role>Infectious diseases advanced trainee</role></contrib><aff id="aff1">Sunshine Coast University Hospital, Queensland</aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>02</day><month>12</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>12</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>42</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>206</fpage><lpage>206</lpage><product product-type="book"><source><bold>Melbourne: Therapeutic Guidelines Limited; 2019. 155 pages</bold></source><comment>&#x02028;Also available at </comment><x>&#x000a0;</x><x>&#x000a0;</x><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.tg.org.au/">http://www.tg.org.au/</ext-link><x>&#x000a0;</x></product><permissions><copyright-statement>(c) NPS MedicineWise 2019</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><copyright-holder>NPS MedicineWise </copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/" specific-use="CC BY-NC-ND 4.0"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial No Derivatives (CC BY-NC-ND) 4.0 License.</license-p></license></permissions></article-meta></front><body><p>This latest edition is a brilliant, informative guide to managing ulcers and wounds. It provides a succinct summary and a practical, easy-to-follow framework for managing these challenging conditions. The tables, boxes, figures and illustrative photos help to easily navigate through the important facts, in a timely fashion.</p><p>I think the best aspect of this book is that it highlights the importance of early establishment of an aetiology of the ulcer in tailoring the management. This edition has a chapter on skin tears which are so common in older people. It provides information on prevention, assessment and how to avoid complications such as infection and conversion into a chronic ulcer. The chapter on wounds in the high-risk foot describes the importance of prevention and the need to focus on revascularisation and pressure-redistribution strategies during the early assessment.</p><p>The emphasis on non-pharmacological measures for ulcer healing such as foot care, foot wear, compression stockings and appropriate dressings highlights the vast experience the expert group has in this field. The well-designed tables provide an excellent guide to choose the appropriate dressings depending on wound characteristics. There is also a new section about a palliative approach to ulcers that are not expected to heal, including pain management and dressing choice.</p><p>I highly recommend this latest edition, which incorporates all the known successful strategies, to every clinician involved in ulcer and wound management, both in the hospital and community.</p></body></article>