<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Heliyon</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Heliyon</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Heliyon</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2405-8440</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31938741</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6953643</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S2405-8440(19)36670-8</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2019.e03011</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e03011</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Development of 5-day hikikomori intervention program for family members: A single-arm pilot trial</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name><surname>Kubo</surname><given-names>Hiroaki</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name><surname>Urata</surname><given-names>Hiromi</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3"><name><surname>Sakai</surname><given-names>Motohiro</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4"><name><surname>Nonaka</surname><given-names>Shunsuke</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au5"><name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>Kazuhiko</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">d</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au6"><name><surname>Tateno</surname><given-names>Masaru</given-names></name><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">e</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au7"><name><surname>Kobara</surname><given-names>Keiji</given-names></name><xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff">f</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au8"><name><surname>Hashimoto</surname><given-names>Naoki</given-names></name><xref rid="aff7" ref-type="aff">g</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au9"><name><surname>Fujisawa</surname><given-names>Daisuke</given-names></name><xref rid="aff8" ref-type="aff">h</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au10"><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>Yuriko</given-names></name><xref rid="aff9" ref-type="aff">i</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au11"><name><surname>Otsuka</surname><given-names>Kotaro</given-names></name><xref rid="aff10" ref-type="aff">j</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au12"><name><surname>Kamimae</surname><given-names>Hiroho</given-names></name><xref rid="aff11" ref-type="aff">k</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au13"><name><surname>Muto</surname><given-names>Yuya</given-names></name><xref rid="aff11" ref-type="aff">k</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au14"><name><surname>Usami</surname><given-names>Takashi</given-names></name><xref rid="aff11" ref-type="aff">k</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au15"><name><surname>Honda</surname><given-names>Yoko</given-names></name><xref rid="aff11" ref-type="aff">k</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au16"><name><surname>Kishimoto</surname><given-names>Junji</given-names></name><xref rid="aff12" ref-type="aff">l</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au17"><name><surname>Kuroki</surname><given-names>Toshihide</given-names></name><xref rid="aff13" ref-type="aff">m</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au18"><name><surname>Kanba</surname><given-names>Shigenobu</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au19"><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>Takahiro A.</given-names></name><email>takahiro@npsych.med.kyushu-u.ac.jp</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#x02217;</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Department of Neuropsychiatry, Graduate School of Medical Sciences, Kyushu University, Maidashi 3-1-1, Higashi-ku, Fukuoka, 812-8582, Japan</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Faculty of Education, University of Miyazaki, 1-1 Gakuen Kibanadai-nishi, Miyazaki, Miyazaki, 889-2192, Japan</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>School of Child Psychology, Tokyo Future University, 34-12 Senju Akebono-cho, Adachi-ku, Tokyo, 120-0023, Japan</aff><aff id="aff4"><label>d</label>Aiiku Counseling Office, Aiiku Research Institute, Imperial Gift Foundation Boshi-Aiiku-Kai, 5-6-8 Minami-azabu, Minato-ku, Tokyo, 106-8580, Japan</aff><aff id="aff5"><label>e</label>Department of Neuropsychiatry, Sapporo Medical University, S1 W17, Chuo-ku, Sapporo, 060-8556, Japan</aff><aff id="aff6"><label>f</label>Shimane Prefectural Counseling Center for Physical and Mental Health, 1741-3 Higashi-Tsuda-Cho, Matsue, Shimane, 690-0011, Japan</aff><aff id="aff7"><label>g</label>Department of Psychiatry, Hokkaido University Graduate School of Medicine, Kita 15, Nishi 7, Kita-ku, Sapporo, 060-8638, Japan</aff><aff id="aff8"><label>h</label>Department of Neuropsychiatry, Keio University School of Medicine, 35 Shinanomachi, Shinjuku-ku, Tokyo, 160-8582, Japan</aff><aff id="aff9"><label>i</label>Department of Mental Health Policy, National Institute of Mental Health, National Center of Neurology and Psychiatry, 4-1-1 Ogawa-Higashi, Kodaira, Tokyo, 187-8553, Japan</aff><aff id="aff10"><label>j</label>Department of Neuropsychiatry, School of Medicine, Iwate Medical University, 19-1 Uchimaru, Morioka, Iwate, 020-8505, Japan</aff><aff id="aff11"><label>k</label>Fukuoka City Mental Health and Welfare Center, Maizuru 2-5-1, Chuo-ku, Fukuoka, 810-0073, Japan</aff><aff id="aff12"><label>l</label>Center for Clinical and Translational Research, Kyushu University, Maidashi 3-1-1, Higashi-ku, Fukuoka, 812-8582, Japan</aff><aff id="aff13"><label>m</label>Department of Clinical Psychology Practice, Graduate School of Human-Environment Studies, Kyushu University, 744 Motooka, Nishi-ku, Fukuoka, 819-0395, Japan</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x02217;</label>Corresponding author. <email>takahiro@npsych.med.kyushu-u.ac.jp</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>09</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>1</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>09</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>e03011</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>12</day><month>9</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>13</day><month>11</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>6</day><month>12</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2019 The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><license license-type="CC BY-NC-ND" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="abs0010"><sec><title>Backgrounds</title><p>Hikikomori, a severe form of social withdrawal, is increasingly a serious mental health issue worldwide. Hikikomori is comorbid with various psychiatric conditions including depression, social anxiety and suicidal behaviors. Family support is encouraged as a vital first step, however evidence-based programs have yet to be established. Mental Health First Aid (MHFA) is one of the most well-validated educational programs encouraging lay people such as family members, to support close persons suffering from various psychiatric conditions such as depression, anxiety and suicidal behaviors.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>We newly developed an educational program for family members of hikikomori sufferers mainly based on MHFA and &#x02018;Community Reinforcement and Family Training (CRAFT)&#x02019; with role-play and homework. As a single-arm trial, 21 parents (7 fathers and 14 mothers) living with hikikomori sufferers participated in our program with five once-a-week sessions (2 h per session) and six monthly follow-ups, and its effectiveness was evaluated using various self-rated questionnaires.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Perceived skills toward a depressed hikikomori case vignette, stigma held by participants, and subscales of two problematic and one adaptive behaviors of hikikomori sufferers were improved throughout the sessions and follow-ups. In addition, positive behavioral changes of hikikomori sufferers such as improved social participation were reported by participants.</p></sec><sec><title>Limitations</title><p>Single-arm design and evaluation using self-rated questionnaires are the main limitations of the present study.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Our newly developed program has positive effects on family members in their contact and support of hikikomori sufferers. Future trials with control groups are required to validate the effectiveness of this program.</p></sec></abstract><abstract abstract-type="teaser" id="abs0015"><p>Clinical psychology; Depression; Mental health; Psychiatry; Suicide; Pathological social withdrawal (hikikomori); Depression; Social anxiety; Mental health first aid (MHFA); Community reinforcement and family training (CRAFT); Family support</p></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Clinical psychology</kwd><kwd>Depression</kwd><kwd>Mental health</kwd><kwd>Psychiatry</kwd><kwd>Suicide</kwd><kwd>Pathological social withdrawal (hikikomori)</kwd><kwd>Social anxiety</kwd><kwd>Mental health first aid (MHFA)</kwd><kwd>Community reinforcement and family training (CRAFT)</kwd><kwd>Family support</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0010">Hikikomori, a severe form of social withdrawal, has been highlighted in Japan since the late 1990s (<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Saito, 1998</xref>; <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Kato et&#x000a0;al., 2011</xref>, <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). A survey by Japan's Cabinet Office in 2016 estimated that hikikomori sufferers aged between 15 and 39 number 540,000 in Japan (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Cabinet Office, 2016</xref>). Moreover, the same office has recently estimated the number of hikikomori between 40 and 65 to be 610,000 in Japan (<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Cabinet Office, 2019</xref>). Sufferers with hikikomori have been reported not only in Japan but also in many other countries and it is increasingly considered to be serious worldwide condition (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Kato et&#x000a0;al., 2011</xref>, <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>, <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">2016b</xref>, <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>, <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>; <xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">Teo et&#x000a0;al., 2015a</xref>, <xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">2015b</xref>; <xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">Wu et&#x000a0;al., 2019</xref>).</p><p id="p0015">Hikikomori is characterized as 1) staying at home for most of the day, 2) avoidance of social participation (e.g. working and schooling), and 3) these conditions continue at least six months (<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Saito, 2010a</xref>). Hikikomori cases are often comorbid with a variety of psychiatric disorders such as mood disorders (especially major depressive disorder), schizophrenia, social anxiety disorders, and personality disorders (<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Kondo et&#x000a0;al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">Teo et&#x000a0;al., 2015b</xref>). Furthermore, a recent epidemiological survey has shown that hikikomori sufferers have a higher risk of suicide (<xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">Yong and Nomura, 2019</xref>).</p><p id="p0020">A recent survey has revealed that the average age of people with hikikomori was 34.4 years old and the average duration of the hikikomori condition was 9.6 years (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">KHJ, 2018</xref>). Prolonged and aging hikikomori is becoming a novel social issue, called the 80&#x02013;50 problem (hikikomori sufferers in their 50s living with parents in their 80s). Support for people with hikikomori condition is prone to delay. Only 6.6 % of hikikomori sufferers initiate the search for help by themselves, and in 72.2 % of cases it is a parent or relative who is first to consult support institutions (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Ito, 2003</xref>). In addition, it takes 4.4 years on average for people with hikikomori to utilize support. In 13.0 % of hikikomori cases, it takes more than 10 years to initial support (<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Saito, 2010b</xref>).</p><p id="p0025">Therefore, more effective intervention approaches for hikikomori are warranted. In 2010, Japan's Ministry of Health, Labor, and Welfare published &#x0201c;Guidelines for assessment and support of hikikomori,&#x0201d; and proposed a four grade step-by-step approach. Family support/approach is encouraged as the first step (<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Saito, 2010a</xref>). However, an evidence-based family intervention approach to deal with mental health problems has not been developed. Family members (mainly parents) have difficulty in approaching hikikomori sufferers mainly due to a lack of knowledge (about mental health problems and hikikomori condition in particular) and stigma towards such problems (<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Kato et&#x000a0;al., 2017a</xref>). In many cases, family members tend not to provide appropriate support, and may &#x0201c;turn a blind eye&#x0201d; for many years (<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">Kato et&#x000a0;al., 2017a</xref>). We suppose that delay of direct support for hikikomori sufferers is partly caused by such parental behaviors. Thus, it is important for family members, especially parents, to acquire appropriate knowledge and skills for dealing with hikikomori sufferers directly.</p><p id="p0030">Mental Health First Aid (MHFA) is a mental health educational/training program for non-professionals of mental health such as school teachers, firefighters and lay people, originally developed in Australia in 2000 (<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Kitchener and Jorm, 2002</xref>; <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Langlands et&#x000a0;al., 2008</xref>). The MHFA program helps participants not only to increase mental health literacy, but also to obtain practical skills to provide help to persons with mental health problems by learning the five-step MHFA principles (<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Kitchener and Jorm, 2002</xref>). The five-step MHFA principles (3rd version) are as follows: Step 1) Approach the person, assess and assist with any crisis; Step 2) Listen non-judgmentally; Step 3) Give support and information; Step 4) Encourage the person to get appropriate professional help; and Step 5) Encourage other support (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Kitchener et&#x000a0;al., 2013</xref>). The 12-h standard MHFA program utilizes the same five-step principles targeted to four psychiatric conditions (depression, anxiety, psychosis, substance abuse) (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Kitchener et&#x000a0;al., 2013</xref>). Hikikomori sufferers often have a variety of psychiatric conditions, thus we hypothesize that the MHFA five-step approach is applicable to most hikikomori cases.</p><p id="p0035">In addition, the cognitive behavioral approach, especially Community Reinforcement and Family Training (CRAFT), is considered a candidate approach for family members of hikikomori sufferers (<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Saito, 2010a</xref>). CRAFT was originally developed for substance use disorders as a family intervention method (<xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Smith and Meyers, 2004</xref>). Sakai and his colleagues modified the original CRAFT program for parents with hikikomori sufferers to encourage help-seeking behaviors (<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Nonaka et&#x000a0;al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Sakai and Nonaka, 2013</xref>). The CRAFT program targeting family members of hikikomori sufferers is conducted as both individual (<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Sakai et&#x000a0;al., 2015</xref>) and group sessions (<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Nonaka et&#x000a0;al., 2013</xref>). In this program, functional analysis, an assessment method based on behavioral therapy, is applied to alter malfunctional family interactions (<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Sakai and Nonaka, 2013</xref>). Functional analysis of behavior therapy (FABT) helps to clarify the chronological relationship among targeting behaviors (e.g. aggressive behaviors by hikikomori sufferers), prior events to the targeting behaviors (e.g. parental criticism) and following results (e.g. parents avoid hikikomori sufferers due to aggressive behaviors). FABT emphasizes that changing prior events (e.g. exchange criticism for calm words) can alter the targeting behaviors and following results for more appropriate interactions among family members (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Hanley et&#x000a0;al., 2003</xref>). In addition, positive communication skills are introduced by the CRAFT program for hikikomori so that parents can alter malfunctional prior events such as criticizing, scolding, or vague words (<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Sakai and Nonaka, 2013</xref>).</p><p id="p0040">We herein hypothesize that the combination of MHFA and CRAFT (mainly FABT) provides a helpful option in supporting family members with hikikomori sufferers. The purpose of the present study is to develop a 5-day family intervention program combining MHFA and CRAFT, and to evaluate the effectiveness of the program as a single-arm open trial.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><label>2</label><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="sec2.1"><label>2.1</label><title>Ethics</title><p id="p0045">This study was approved by the ethics committee of Kyushu University, and was registered at the UMIN Clinical Trials Registry (UMIN000029643; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://upload.umin.ac.jp/cgi-open-bin/ctr/ctr_view.cgi?recptno=R000033862" id="interref0010">https://upload.umin.ac.jp/cgi-open-bin/ctr/ctr_view.cgi?recptno=R000033862</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><label>2.2</label><title>Program development</title><p id="p0050">The original MHFA is 12-hour program (<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Kitchener and Jorm, 2002</xref>). Previously we have developed short-time MHFA-based intervention programs so that participants can learn the essence and basic skills of MHFA efficiently for specific settings such as a medical setting for clinical patients and an ordinary company setting for office workers (<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Kato et&#x000a0;al., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Suzuki et&#x000a0;al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Kubo et&#x000a0;al., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">Nakagami et&#x000a0;al., 2018</xref>).</p><p id="p0055">We herein developed a family intervention program consisting of five once-a-week sessions (2 h per session) including lectures, group-work (i.e. role-playing) and homework based on the MHFA (the five-step MHFA principles of depression and suicide intervention), and CRAFT programs (FABT) to encourage participants to practice communication with hikikomori sufferers in daily life (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;1</xref>). We introduced basic knowledge about mental health literacy including the biopsychosocial background and therapeutic approach for hikikomori (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Kato et&#x000a0;al., 2011</xref>, <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>, <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">2016a</xref>, <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">2017b</xref>, <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>; <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Hayakawa et&#x000a0;al., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">Teo et&#x000a0;al., 2018</xref>). Next, we introduced the basics of MHFA, especially focusing on MHFA skills for depression and suicidal behavior in the supporting hikikomori sufferers. In addition, we introduced the positive methods of communication practiced in CRAFT program (<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Sakai and Nonaka, 2013</xref>). Detailed contents of each session are shown in <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;1</xref>.<fig id="fig1"><label>Figure&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Group work of communication based on CRAFT using FABT.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0015">Figure&#x000a0;1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Contents of the 5-day hikikomori intervention program for family members.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0025">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Session 1</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>A psychiatrist (TAK) introduced 1) knowledge about mental health literacy including the biopsychosocial background and therapeutic approach for hikikomori, 2) the MHFA 5-step principles, and 3) information about supporting resources for people with hikikomori.</td></tr><tr><td>For homework, we required participants to record the daily behaviors of their children (greetings, conversation, asking for help, calling for dinner, etc.).</td></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Session 2</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>To organize more appropriate interactions between the parent and their children, we introduced the MHFA approach for hikikomori and FABT.</td></tr><tr><td>For homework, we required participants to classify the behavior of their children into desirable (greetings, reply to parent's proposal, going out, etc.) and undesirable (ignoring family members, abusive words to family members, shut-in, etc.) behaviors.</td></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Session 3</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>At first, to obtain listening skills, role-playing of active listening (i.e. Step 2 of MHFA; listen non-judgmentally) was introduced. A pair of participants played listener and speaker roles alternately. Next, FABT-based practice to enhance desirable behaviors was conducted to alter interactions between the parent and their children (see <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). Positive communication based on CRAFT includes plain, short, and positive way of speaking rather than using vague, confusing, or negative words.</td></tr><tr><td>For homework, we required participants to think of positive words suitable with CRAFT communication to enhance desirable behaviors of their children.</td></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Session 4</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>To acquire practical skills in encouraging their children to utilize professional support, a pair of participants alternately played the case scenario of a parent and a hikikomori sufferer based on MHFA.</td></tr><tr><td>For homework, we required participants to list up supporting resources such as psychiatric clinics and hikikomori support centers.</td></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Session 5</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>We reviewed the whole of the program and demonstrated breathing technique as a MHFA self-help strategy. Next, Q &#x00026; A time was introduced to discuss the difficulty in approaching their children with hikikomori condition. Finally, we informed the participants of individual and group follow-up sessions.</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><label>3</label><title>Measurements</title><sec id="sec3.1"><label>3.1</label><title>Demographic data</title><p id="p0060">Demographic data of participants themselves and hikikomori sufferers were collected. The data included the age, gender and relationship of participants and hikikomori sufferers, and the duration of the hikikomori condition. The present condition of hikikomori sufferers (e.g. how often they went out or how frequently they utilized support) and their life history were also collected indirectly from participants.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.2"><label>3.2</label><title>Perceived skill</title><p id="p0065">To evaluate perceived skills based on MHFA for early intervention of hikikomori cases, an original questionnaire using a case vignette of hikikomori was developed as shown below:</p><p id="p0070"><italic>&#x0201c;Mr. A is 30 years old. After graduating university, he was employed at a company. However, he quit his job six months after employment. Then, he got part-time job, however, he was unable to continue to work. He changed his part-time job several times. Afterwards, he didn't work or seek a job for a year. Now, he seldom goes out of his room. When you occasionally see him in the hallway, he returns to his room. He seems to avoid family members, and his face is vacant and gloomy. You (respondent), a parent of Mr. A, are worrying about him.&#x0201d;</italic></p><p id="p0075">Respondents are asked to imagine themselves as a parent of Mr. A, and to answer nine questions rating the possibility of performing behaviors in accordance with MHFA: (1) leave Mr. A alone for a while (This is an inappropriate behavior based on MHFA; assessed as a reversal score), (2) tell Mr. A that you are concerned about him at an early stage, (3) consult a support center about Mr. A, (4) greet Mr. A when you see him, (5) ask about Mr. A's physical condition such as appetite or sleep, (6) ask about Mr. A's feelings of depression, (7) directly convey the possibility of depression when Mr. A's depressed mood proved to be serious, (8) directly ask about suicidal thoughts when you think Mr. A probably suffers from depression, (9) recommend Mr. A visit a psychiatric or psychosomatic department.</p><p id="p0080">The possibility of each behavior was rated using five-point scale indicating 0 (absolutely no), 1 (probably not), 2 (don't know), 3 (probably yes), and 4 (absolutely yes).</p></sec><sec id="sec3.3"><label>3.3</label><title>Confidence</title><p id="p0085">The confidence level in management of people with hikikomori expressing depressive symptoms was evaluated by six original questions based on the MHFA: (1) approach a person with hikikomori, (2) listen non-judgmentally, (3) tell the possibility of clinical depression, (4) give support and information, (5) ask about &#x0201c;suicidal thoughts,&#x0201d; (6) encourage the person to obtain appropriate professional help. Respondents were asked to answer these questions on a five-point scale, ranging from 0 (not confident at all) to 4 (very confident).</p></sec><sec id="sec3.4"><label>3.4</label><title>Stigma</title><p id="p0090">The Japanese version of 12-item Link's Devaluation-Discrimination Scale was conducted to measure respondents' stigma toward mental health problems (<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Shimotsu et&#x000a0;al., 2006</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec3.5"><label>3.5</label><title>Problematic behaviors of hikikomori</title><p id="p0095">Hikikomori Behavior Checklist (HBCL) was conducted to measure problematic behaviors by the family members (children) of participants (<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Sakai et&#x000a0;al., 2004</xref>). This scale is consisted of 45 items and has 10 factors as sub-scales: (1) Aggressive behavior, (2) Social anxiety, (3) Obsessive-compulsive behavior, (4) Avoidance from family members, (5) Depression, (6) Absence of activities of daily living, (7) Incomprehensible maladapted behavior, (8) Absence of social participation, (9) Decreased activity, and (10) Irregular life pattern. Respondents were asked regarding behavior within the last three months with a four-point scale.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.6"><label>3.6</label><title>Adaptive behavior of hikikomori</title><p id="p0100">Adaptive Behaviors Scale for Hikikomori (ABS-H) was conducted to assess the adaptive behavior of the hikikomori sufferer (<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Nonaka et&#x000a0;al., 2018</xref>). This scale is consisted of 26 items and has four factors as sub-scales: (1) Interaction, (2) Family, (3) Value, and (4) Social participation. Respondents were asked to answer regarding the behaviors of their family members (children) within the last three months.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.7"><label>3.7</label><title>Depressive symptoms of participants</title><p id="p0105">The Japanese version of the Patient Health Questionnaire (PHQ-9) was conducted to assess the severity of depressive symptoms within the last two weeks (<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Kroenke et&#x000a0;al., 2001</xref>; <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Muramatsu et&#x000a0;al., 2007</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec3.8"><label>3.8</label><title>Stress responses of participants</title><p id="p0110">Stress Response Scale-18 (SRS-18) was conducted to measure psychological stress responses of respondents (<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Suzuki et&#x000a0;al., 1997</xref>). This scale is consisted of 18 items and has three factors as sub-scales: (1) Depression-Anxiety, (2) Irritability-Anger, and (3) Helplessness.</p></sec><sec id="sec3.9"><label>3.9</label><title>Hikikomori condition</title><p id="p0115">We evaluated a retrospective assessment on hikikomori condition at the final follow-up session (Jun 2018). Participants responded to a self-rated question whether their family member (child) was suffering from hikikomori during the period of pre-participation (Oct 2017) and during the period of the final follow-up session (Jun 2018), respectively.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec4"><label>4</label><title>Participants</title><p id="p0120">Participants were recruited through advertisements issued by the municipal government. Regarding eligibility criteria, duration of the hikikomori period had to exceed six months. Participants were informed of the aims and methods of the present study and that their participation was completely voluntary. 21 parents (7 fathers and 14 mothers) living with a child with hikikomori participated in the present study. Participants who agreed to participate in the study then registered as study participants with written informed consent. All the participants (N = 21) agreed to join the present study.</p></sec><sec id="sec5"><label>5</label><title>Procedure</title><p id="p0125">From November to December 2017, we implemented the newly developed family intervention program at Kyushu University hospital. The five-session program was held weekly as group learning. An experienced psychiatrist who is a MHFA-Japan trainer (TAK) conducted the session, and two clinical psychologists (HKu and HU) facilitated the session and conducted the group work.</p><p id="p0130">During October 2017 (one month before the program), a 1-h individual interview was conducted to collect demographic data. In addition, we conducted six monthly follow-ups. The first follow-up, implemented in January 2018, was a 1-h individual interview. In the follow-up interview, we asked participants about problems in approaching their child. For the second to sixth follow-ups, along with the review of the program, we conducted group-work discussing the difficulties in approaching hikikomori sufferers in daily life, and coping with stress among participants.</p><p id="p0135">Self-rated questionnaires were conducted just before Session 1 (#1), immediately after Session 5 (#5), and each follow-up sessions (from FU1 to FU6). SRS-18 was conducted at each time point (five sessions and six follow-ups). An illustration of the procedure is shown in <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;2</xref>.<fig id="fig2"><label>Figure&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Procedure of the present study.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0020">Figure&#x000a0;2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec6"><label>6</label><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="p0140">Data obtained from 21 participants was longitudinal for each self-rated questionnaire. Scores of SRS-18 were obtained at 11 time points (conducted every session from #1 to FU6); other scores were obtained at 8 time points (#1, #5 and FU1-FU6). Linear mixed-effects models were used to evaluate the longitudinal changes in each measurement. We included time (each time point) as a fixed effect; and we included participants, including drop-out patterns and missing scores, as a random effect. In addition, we reported marginal R<sup>2</sup> (variance explained by fixed factors) as effect size (<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Nakagawa and Schielzeth, 2013</xref>).</p><p id="p0145">In this study, 4 pairs of couples (both father and mother) jointly participated (total 8 participants). Thus, we conducted group comparison analysis between joint participation group (both parents have participated) and single participation group (either father or mother has participated). For group comparison, liner mixed-effects models were conducted as well as longitudinal changes of measurement mentioned above. Time (each time point) and parental participation type (joint or single participation) were included as fixed effects. In order to evaluate the effects of the present program on parents, we included perceived skills, confidence, stigma, depressive symptoms, and stress response among participants as group comparison analysis.</p><p id="p0150">All analysis was performed using R version 3.5.1 (<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">R Core Team, 2018</xref>). We used the lme4 package for fitting liner mixed-effect models and MuMIn package for calculating R<sup>2</sup>.</p></sec><sec id="sec7"><label>7</label><title>Results</title><sec id="sec7.1"><label>7.1</label><title>Demographic data of participants and hikikomori sufferers</title><p id="p0155">21 parents (7 fathers and 14 mothers) participated in the present study. Among the 21 participants, 4 couples (husband and wife) participated. The average age of the participants was 61.62 &#x000b1; 6.42 (ranging 49&#x02013;76). Their children with hikikomori condition were 13 males and 4 females, and the average age of the child was 27.59 &#x000b1; 6.24 (ranging 19&#x02013;39). Average duration of hikikomori condition was 100.94 &#x000b1; 59.37 months (ranging 12&#x02013;228 months). Participants' demographic data was shown in <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;2</xref>, and hikikomori sufferers&#x02019; demographics were shown in <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;3</xref>.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl2"><label>Table&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Demographic data of participants (parents).</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0030">Table&#x000a0;2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th>N</th><th>%</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Total</td><td>21</td><td/></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Sex</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Male</td><td>7</td><td>33.3</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Female</td><td>14</td><td>66.7</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Age</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;40&#x02013;49</td><td>1</td><td>4.8</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;50&#x02013;59</td><td>8</td><td>38.1</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;60&#x02013;69</td><td>10</td><td>47.6</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;70&#x02013;79</td><td>2</td><td>9.5</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Mean</td><td>61.62 (SD = 6.42)</td><td/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Note: Among the 21 participants, 4 pairs of couples (husband and wife) participated.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl3"><label>Table&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Demographic data of hikikomori sufferers.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0035">Table&#x000a0;3</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th>N</th><th>%</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Total</td><td>17</td><td/></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Sex</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Male</td><td>13</td><td>76.5</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Female</td><td>4</td><td>23.5</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Age</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;10&#x02013;19</td><td>1</td><td>5.9</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;20&#x02013;29</td><td>10</td><td>58.8</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;30&#x02013;39</td><td>6</td><td>35.3</td></tr><tr><td>Mean</td><td>27.59 (SD = 6.24)</td><td/></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Duration of hikikomori (months)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;12&#x02013;59</td><td>6</td><td>35.3</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;60&#x02013;119</td><td>5</td><td>29.4</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;120-</td><td>6</td><td>35.3</td></tr><tr><td>Mean</td><td>100.94 (SD = 59.37)</td><td/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec7.2"><label>7.2</label><title>Rate of attendance in the program</title><p id="p0160">20 of 21 participants attended all five sessions. One participant did not attend Session 2 (#2). The average rate of attendance of the five-session program was 99.05 %. As for the six follow-ups, 16 participants attended all the follow-ups; one participant did not attend the follow-ups at all, one attended one follow-up, two participants (a couple) attended three follow-ups, and one attended five follow-ups. The average rate of attendance of six follow-ups was 85.71 %.</p></sec><sec id="sec7.3"><label>7.3</label><title>Effectiveness of the program</title><p id="p0165">The average scores of each time point of the self-rated questionnaires were shown in <xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;4</xref>. Mixed-effects modeling of the present program was shown in <xref rid="tbl5" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;5</xref>. Although effect sizes are low, some scores of self-rated questionnaires proved to show significant changes throughout program sessions and follow-ups as shown below.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl4"><label>Table&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>Average scores of each time point of the self-rated questionnaires.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0040">Table&#x000a0;4</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th/><th>#1</th><th>#5</th><th>FU1</th><th>FU2</th><th>FU3</th><th>FU4</th><th>FU5</th><th>FU6</th><th/><th/><th/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="13">Perceived skills</td></tr><tr><td/><td>N</td><td>21</td><td>21</td><td>20</td><td>18</td><td>19</td><td>19</td><td>19</td><td>17</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Total</td><td>Mean</td><td>22.71</td><td>26.10</td><td>25.65</td><td>24.83</td><td>23.74</td><td>24.95</td><td>25.58</td><td>26.47</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td><italic>SD</italic></td><td><italic>5.09</italic></td><td><italic>4.86</italic></td><td><italic>4.63</italic></td><td><italic>4.57</italic></td><td><italic>6.50</italic></td><td><italic>5.51</italic></td><td><italic>4.68</italic></td><td><italic>4.86</italic></td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td colspan="13">Confidence</td></tr><tr><td/><td>N</td><td>21</td><td>21</td><td>20</td><td>19</td><td>19</td><td>19</td><td>19</td><td>16</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Total</td><td>Mean</td><td>10.52</td><td>11.76</td><td>11.35</td><td>11.21</td><td>11.68</td><td>11.05</td><td>12.74</td><td>11.75</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td><italic>SD</italic></td><td><italic>4.03</italic></td><td><italic>3.38</italic></td><td><italic>3.54</italic></td><td><italic>3.53</italic></td><td><italic>5.14</italic></td><td><italic>4.29</italic></td><td><italic>6.26</italic></td><td><italic>3.77</italic></td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td colspan="13">Stigma</td></tr><tr><td/><td>N</td><td>20</td><td>21</td><td>20</td><td>19</td><td>18</td><td>18</td><td>19</td><td>17</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Total</td><td>Mean</td><td>31.70</td><td>30.14</td><td>29.25</td><td>28.84</td><td>29.78</td><td>29.39</td><td>29.63</td><td>28.47</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td><italic>SD</italic></td><td><italic>6.03</italic></td><td><italic>5.41</italic></td><td><italic>6.10</italic></td><td><italic>6.10</italic></td><td><italic>5.69</italic></td><td><italic>6.66</italic></td><td><italic>6.19</italic></td><td><italic>6.45</italic></td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td colspan="13">HBCL</td></tr><tr><td/><td>N</td><td>20</td><td>20</td><td>20</td><td>19</td><td>16</td><td>17</td><td>18</td><td>16</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Aggressive behavior</td><td>Mean</td><td>7.00</td><td>6.90</td><td>6.80</td><td>6.16</td><td>7.19</td><td>7.06</td><td>7.22</td><td>6.75</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td><italic>SD</italic></td><td><italic>5.10</italic></td><td><italic>5.37</italic></td><td><italic>5.37</italic></td><td><italic>5.07</italic></td><td><italic>5.91</italic></td><td><italic>4.95</italic></td><td><italic>5.14</italic></td><td><italic>4.97</italic></td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Social anxiety</td><td>Mean</td><td>6.25</td><td>6.05</td><td>5.89</td><td>6.44</td><td>6.65</td><td>6.44</td><td>6.31</td><td>6.10</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td><italic>SD</italic></td><td><italic>2.66</italic></td><td><italic>3.14</italic></td><td><italic>2.63</italic></td><td><italic>2.76</italic></td><td><italic>2.72</italic></td><td><italic>2.19</italic></td><td><italic>2.05</italic></td><td><italic>2.70</italic></td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Obsessive-compulsive behavior</td><td>Mean</td><td>4.20</td><td>4.20</td><td>3.89</td><td>3.63</td><td>3.76</td><td>3.44</td><td>3.69</td><td>4.25</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td><italic>SD</italic></td><td><italic>2.62</italic></td><td><italic>2.29</italic></td><td><italic>2.51</italic></td><td><italic>2.20</italic></td><td><italic>1.83</italic></td><td><italic>2.06</italic></td><td><italic>2.34</italic></td><td><italic>2.64</italic></td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Avoidance from family members</td><td>Mean</td><td>5.45</td><td>5.95</td><td>5.58</td><td>5.94</td><td>5.76</td><td>5.56</td><td>5.56</td><td>5.50</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td><italic>SD</italic></td><td><italic>3.51</italic></td><td><italic>3.46</italic></td><td><italic>3.56</italic></td><td><italic>3.40</italic></td><td><italic>2.98</italic></td><td><italic>3.00</italic></td><td><italic>2.87</italic></td><td><italic>3.58</italic></td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Depression</td><td>Mean</td><td>3.10</td><td>3.65</td><td>2.32</td><td>4.50</td><td>2.82</td><td>2.83</td><td>2.63</td><td>3.40</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td><italic>SD</italic></td><td><italic>3.21</italic></td><td><italic>3.09</italic></td><td><italic>2.96</italic></td><td><italic>3.43</italic></td><td><italic>2.59</italic></td><td><italic>2.79</italic></td><td><italic>2.60</italic></td><td><italic>2.91</italic></td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Absence of activities of daily living</td><td>Mean</td><td>6.95</td><td>7.65</td><td>7.21</td><td>7.94</td><td>7.29</td><td>7.39</td><td>7.25</td><td>6.95</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td><italic>SD</italic></td><td><italic>4.02</italic></td><td><italic>3.89</italic></td><td><italic>3.61</italic></td><td><italic>3.93</italic></td><td><italic>3.46</italic></td><td><italic>3.11</italic></td><td><italic>3.91</italic></td><td><italic>3.90</italic></td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Incomprehensible maladapted behavior</td><td>Mean</td><td>2.70</td><td>2.85</td><td>2.74</td><td>3.38</td><td>3.29</td><td>2.78</td><td>2.50</td><td>2.55</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td><italic>SD</italic></td><td><italic>1.49</italic></td><td><italic>2.08</italic></td><td><italic>1.62</italic></td><td><italic>2.12</italic></td><td><italic>1.77</italic></td><td><italic>1.72</italic></td><td><italic>1.46</italic></td><td><italic>1.60</italic></td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Absence of social participation</td><td>Mean</td><td>7.75</td><td>7.75</td><td>7.58</td><td>8.06</td><td>7.65</td><td>7.50</td><td>7.38</td><td>7.55</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td><italic>SD</italic></td><td><italic>1.26</italic></td><td><italic>1.51</italic></td><td><italic>1.46</italic></td><td><italic>1.30</italic></td><td><italic>1.53</italic></td><td><italic>1.38</italic></td><td><italic>1.49</italic></td><td><italic>1.47</italic></td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Decreased activity</td><td>Mean</td><td>5.70</td><td>5.75</td><td>5.63</td><td>5.81</td><td>5.47</td><td>5.50</td><td>5.44</td><td>5.90</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td><italic>SD</italic></td><td><italic>1.55</italic></td><td><italic>1.61</italic></td><td><italic>1.90</italic></td><td><italic>1.33</italic></td><td><italic>1.42</italic></td><td><italic>1.50</italic></td><td><italic>1.97</italic></td><td><italic>1.70</italic></td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Irregular life pattern</td><td>Mean</td><td>5.50</td><td>6.10</td><td>5.11</td><td>6.44</td><td>6.47</td><td>6.06</td><td>5.63</td><td>6.10</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td><italic>SD</italic></td><td><italic>2.42</italic></td><td><italic>2.47</italic></td><td><italic>2.36</italic></td><td><italic>2.18</italic></td><td><italic>1.85</italic></td><td><italic>1.90</italic></td><td><italic>2.45</italic></td><td><italic>2.43</italic></td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Total</td><td>Mean</td><td>54.50</td><td>56.75</td><td>52.11</td><td>59.31</td><td>56.24</td><td>54.72</td><td>53.13</td><td>55.30</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td><italic>SD</italic></td><td><italic>17.12</italic></td><td><italic>17.96</italic></td><td><italic>17.37</italic></td><td><italic>17.03</italic></td><td><italic>13.19</italic></td><td><italic>12.85</italic></td><td><italic>14.25</italic></td><td><italic>15.57</italic></td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td colspan="13">ABS-H</td></tr><tr><td/><td>N</td><td>18</td><td>19</td><td>20</td><td>19</td><td>17</td><td>18</td><td>16</td><td>16</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Interaction</td><td>Mean</td><td>10.17</td><td>9.26</td><td>10.20</td><td>9.58</td><td>9.88</td><td>10.22</td><td>8.56</td><td>10.81</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td><italic>SD</italic></td><td><italic>5.80</italic></td><td><italic>5.46</italic></td><td><italic>6.73</italic></td><td><italic>5.73</italic></td><td><italic>6.59</italic></td><td><italic>5.96</italic></td><td><italic>5.71</italic></td><td><italic>7.25</italic></td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Family</td><td>Mean</td><td>6.94</td><td>7.32</td><td>6.85</td><td>7.53</td><td>7.29</td><td>7.67</td><td>6.75</td><td>7.63</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td><italic>SD</italic></td><td><italic>2.91</italic></td><td><italic>2.96</italic></td><td><italic>2.57</italic></td><td><italic>2.74</italic></td><td><italic>2.67</italic></td><td><italic>2.85</italic></td><td><italic>2.54</italic></td><td><italic>2.50</italic></td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Value</td><td>Mean</td><td>3.78</td><td>3.95</td><td>4.50</td><td>4.37</td><td>4.35</td><td>4.50</td><td>3.75</td><td>4.69</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td><italic>SD</italic></td><td><italic>2.17</italic></td><td><italic>2.06</italic></td><td><italic>2.60</italic></td><td><italic>3.34</italic></td><td><italic>3.03</italic></td><td><italic>3.04</italic></td><td><italic>2.05</italic></td><td><italic>2.73</italic></td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Social participation</td><td>Mean</td><td>2.17</td><td>1.16</td><td>1.90</td><td>2.79</td><td>2.24</td><td>1.72</td><td>1.69</td><td>1.75</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td><italic>SD</italic></td><td><italic>1.89</italic></td><td><italic>1.18</italic></td><td><italic>2.26</italic></td><td><italic>2.12</italic></td><td><italic>2.26</italic></td><td><italic>2.21</italic></td><td><italic>1.99</italic></td><td><italic>2.17</italic></td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Total</td><td>Mean</td><td>23.06</td><td>21.68</td><td>23.45</td><td>24.26</td><td>23.76</td><td>24.11</td><td>20.75</td><td>24.88</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td><italic>SD</italic></td><td><italic>9.78</italic></td><td><italic>8.66</italic></td><td><italic>10.84</italic></td><td><italic>10.14</italic></td><td><italic>10.22</italic></td><td><italic>10.73</italic></td><td><italic>8.73</italic></td><td><italic>12.52</italic></td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td colspan="13">PHQ-9</td></tr><tr><td/><td>N</td><td>21</td><td>21</td><td>20</td><td>18</td><td>18</td><td>19</td><td>19</td><td>17</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>Total</td><td>Mean</td><td>4.43</td><td>4.43</td><td>4.55</td><td>2.72</td><td>4.22</td><td>3.95</td><td>4.00</td><td>3.12</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td/><td>SD</td><td><italic>5.40</italic></td><td><italic>4.47</italic></td><td><italic>5.14</italic></td><td><italic>2.94</italic></td><td><italic>4.54</italic></td><td><italic>4.39</italic></td><td><italic>4.29</italic></td><td><italic>5.20</italic></td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>SRS-18</td><td/><td>#1</td><td>#2</td><td>#3</td><td>#4</td><td>#5</td><td>FU1</td><td>FU2</td><td>FU3</td><td>FU4</td><td>FU5</td><td>FU6</td></tr><tr><td/><td>N</td><td>20</td><td>20</td><td>20</td><td>21</td><td>20</td><td>20</td><td>19</td><td>19</td><td>19</td><td>19</td><td>16</td></tr><tr><td>Depression-Anxiety</td><td>Mean</td><td>4.60</td><td>3.75</td><td>3.00</td><td>2.62</td><td>2.95</td><td>4.15</td><td>3.74</td><td>4.26</td><td>4.32</td><td>3.42</td><td>3.56</td></tr><tr><td/><td><italic>SD</italic></td><td><italic>4.20</italic></td><td><italic>3.90</italic></td><td><italic>2.93</italic></td><td><italic>2.77</italic></td><td><italic>2.94</italic></td><td><italic>3.85</italic></td><td><italic>3.35</italic></td><td><italic>4.64</italic></td><td><italic>4.27</italic></td><td><italic>3.90</italic></td><td><italic>4.33</italic></td></tr><tr><td>Irritation-Anger</td><td>Mean</td><td>2.30</td><td>2.25</td><td>1.45</td><td>1.33</td><td>1.95</td><td>2.20</td><td>1.32</td><td>2.84</td><td>2.37</td><td>2.00</td><td>1.75</td></tr><tr><td/><td><italic>SD</italic></td><td><italic>2.69</italic></td><td><italic>2.61</italic></td><td><italic>1.66</italic></td><td><italic>1.70</italic></td><td><italic>2.33</italic></td><td><italic>2.64</italic></td><td><italic>2.00</italic></td><td><italic>4.17</italic></td><td><italic>3.01</italic></td><td><italic>3.09</italic></td><td><italic>2.61</italic></td></tr><tr><td>Helplessness</td><td>Mean</td><td>3.30</td><td>3.90</td><td>3.10</td><td>2.95</td><td>2.85</td><td>2.70</td><td>2.37</td><td>3.37</td><td>3.68</td><td>3.26</td><td>3.50</td></tr><tr><td/><td><italic>SD</italic></td><td><italic>3.58</italic></td><td><italic>3.55</italic></td><td><italic>2.74</italic></td><td><italic>2.80</italic></td><td><italic>2.87</italic></td><td><italic>3.24</italic></td><td><italic>2.52</italic></td><td><italic>3.51</italic></td><td><italic>4.14</italic></td><td><italic>3.96</italic></td><td><italic>4.14</italic></td></tr><tr><td>Total</td><td>Mean</td><td>10.20</td><td>9.90</td><td>7.55</td><td>6.90</td><td>7.75</td><td>9.05</td><td>7.42</td><td>10.47</td><td>10.37</td><td>8.68</td><td>8.81</td></tr><tr><td/><td><italic>SD</italic></td><td><italic>9.44</italic></td><td><italic>8.76</italic></td><td><italic>6.67</italic></td><td><italic>6.25</italic></td><td><italic>7.29</italic></td><td><italic>9.13</italic></td><td><italic>7.08</italic></td><td><italic>11.69</italic></td><td><italic>10.42</italic></td><td><italic>10.32</italic></td><td><italic>10.44</italic></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="tbl5"><label>Table&#x000a0;5</label><caption><p>Estimated treatment effect from the linear mixed-model analysis.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0045">Table&#x000a0;5</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td>Outcome</td><td>Slope</td><td>Standard error</td><td><italic>p</italic> value</td><td>95% CI</td><td>R<sup>2</sup></td></tr><tr><td colspan="6">Perceived skills</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Total</td><td>0.25</td><td>0.10</td><td>*0.02</td><td>(0.05, 0.45)</td><td>0.02</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6">Confidence</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Total</td><td>0.07</td><td>0.08</td><td>0.38</td><td>(-0.08, 0.22)</td><td>0.00</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6">Stigma</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Total</td><td>-0.29</td><td>0.07</td><td>***0.00</td><td>(-0.42, -0.15)</td><td>0.02</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6">HBCL</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Aggressive behavior</td><td>-0.03</td><td>0.05</td><td>0.50</td><td>(-0.13, 0.06)</td><td>0.00</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Social anxiety</td><td>0.02</td><td>0.04</td><td>0.59</td><td>(-0.05, 0.09)</td><td>0.00</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Obsessive-compulsive behavior</td><td>-0.09</td><td>0.03</td><td>**0.01</td><td>(-0.15, -0.03)</td><td>0.01</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Avoidance from family members</td><td>-0.02</td><td>0.04</td><td>0.50</td><td>(-0.10, 0.05)</td><td>0.00</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Depression</td><td>-0.05</td><td>0.04</td><td>0.25</td><td>(-0.13, 0.03)</td><td>0.00</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Absence of activities of daily living</td><td>-0.02</td><td>0.05</td><td>0.65</td><td>(-0.11, 0.07)</td><td>0.00</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Incomprehensible maladapted behavior</td><td>0.03</td><td>0.03</td><td>0.36</td><td>(-0.04, 0.10)</td><td>0.00</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Absence of social participation</td><td>-0.01</td><td>0.02</td><td>0.61</td><td>(-0.05, 0.03)</td><td>0.00</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Decreased activity</td><td>-0.06</td><td>0.03</td><td>*0.04</td><td>(-0.12, -0.00)</td><td>0.01</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Irregular life pattern</td><td>-0.03</td><td>0.03</td><td>0.29</td><td>(-0.09, 0.03)</td><td>0.00</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Total</td><td>-0.27</td><td>0.22</td><td>0.24</td><td>(-0.70, 0.17)</td><td>0.00</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6">ABS-H</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Social interaction</td><td>0.08</td><td>0.08</td><td>0.32</td><td>(-0.08, 0.25)</td><td>0.00</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Family</td><td>0.06</td><td>0.03</td><td>0.05</td><td>(0.00, 0.12)</td><td>0.00</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Value</td><td>0.12</td><td>0.05</td><td>*0.01</td><td>(0.03, 0.21)</td><td>0.02</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Participation in society</td><td>-0.02</td><td>0.04</td><td>0.62</td><td>(-0.11, 0.06)</td><td>0.00</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Total</td><td>0.24</td><td>0.14</td><td>0.08</td><td>(-0.03, 0.51)</td><td>0.00</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6">PHQ-9</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Total</td><td>0.01</td><td>0.06</td><td>0.85</td><td>(-0.10, 0.12)</td><td>0.00</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6">SRS-18</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Depression-Anxiety</td><td>0.06</td><td>0.04</td><td>0.15</td><td>(-0.02, 0.14)</td><td>0.00</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Irritation-Anger</td><td>0.02</td><td>0.04</td><td>0.54</td><td>(-0.05, 0.10)</td><td>0.00</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Helplessness</td><td>0.03</td><td>0.04</td><td>0.50</td><td>(-0.05, 0.10)</td><td>0.00</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Total</td><td>0.11</td><td>0.09</td><td>0.24</td><td>(-0.07, 0.30)</td><td>0.00</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tspara0040"><p>CI: confidence interval.</p></fn><fn id="tspara0t040"><p>* p &#x0003c; .05, ** p &#x0003c; .01, *** p &#x0003c; .001.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="p0170">The score of perceived skills in early intervention for depressive symptoms of a hikikomori case based on MHFA was significantly improved throughout the sessions and follow-ups (Slope = 0.25, 95% CI = [0.05, 0.45], <italic>p</italic> = 0.02). Average scores of each sub-item and their mixed-effects modeling were shown in Supplement 1. Some scores of the sub-items were significantly improved. Throughout the sessions and follow-ups, participants tended not to leave hikikomori sufferers alone and showed significant improvement on perceived skills in approaching and asking depressive feelings and suicidal thoughts (these skills are recommended alongside with MHFA).</p><p id="p0175">In addition, stigma toward mental health problems was significantly reduced throughout the sessions and follow-ups (Slope = -0.29, 95% CI = [-0.42, -0.15], <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001) (<xref rid="tbl5" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;5</xref>).</p><p id="p0180">Furthermore, some hikikomori sufferers&#x02019; behaviors reported by participants were significantly improved (<xref rid="tbl5" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;5</xref>). Specifically, adaptive behavior of &#x0201c;value&#x0201d; score assessed with ABS-H were significantly improved (Slope = 0.12, 95% CI = [0.03, 0.21], <italic>p</italic> = 0.01). Value score of ABS-H represents &#x0201c;acting/trying to approach the ideal/goal (<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Nonaka et&#x000a0;al., 2018</xref>).&#x0201d; Two problematic hikikomori behaviors based on HBCL, &#x0201c;obsessive-compulsive behavior&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;decreased activity&#x0201d;, were significantly reduced throughout the sessions and follow-ups (Slope = -0.09, 95% CI = [-0.15, -0.03], <italic>p</italic> = 0.01; Slope = -0.06, 95% CI = [-0.12, 0.00], <italic>p</italic> = 0.04, respectively).</p><p id="p0185">Hikikomori condition (reported indirectly by parents) were shown in <xref rid="tbl6" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;6</xref>. Two out of 18 respondents reported that their child's hikikomori condition improved at last follow-up compared with pre-participation in the present study.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl6"><label>Table&#x000a0;6</label><caption><p>Hikikomori condition (indirectly reported by parents).</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0050">Table&#x000a0;6</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td/><td>Pre-participation</td><td>Last follow-up</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Hikikomori condition</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3">Do you think your child is in hikikomori condition?</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Yes</td><td>17</td><td>15</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;No</td><td>1</td><td>3</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec7.4"><label>7.4</label><title>Group comparison between joint participation group and single participation group</title><p id="p0190">Among 21 participants, 4 couples (8 participants) have jointly participated in the present study. We have compared the effects of the present program on parents between joint participation group and single participation group. As for perceived skills, confidence and stigma, no significant differences were observed between two groups. Total score of PHQ-9, two stress response sub-scales (Depression-Anxiety and Helplessness) and total score of SRS-18 were significantly lower among joint participation group compared to single participation group from before participation (#1) to the end of the follow-ups (FU6) (shown in Supplement 2).</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec8"><label>8</label><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0195">In the present study, we newly developed a five-day intervention program, combining MHFA and CRAFT, for family members (mainly parents) who live with a child suffering from hikikomori. The trial program was conducted for five weekly sessions and six monthly follow-up sessions, for 21 parents who live with a child suffering with hikikomori, and the present program has at least some positive effects on family members living with hikikomori sufferers.</p><p id="p0200">The present program has improved participants&#x02019; perceived skills for the management of a hikikomori sufferer with depressive symptoms (based on the case vignette), and reduced stigma toward mental health problems. MHFA is known to be effective in improving knowledge of mental health problems including psychiatric disorders, reducing stigmatizing attitudes, and increasing supportive behaviors (<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Hadlaczky et&#x000a0;al., 2014</xref>). Hikikomori cases are often comorbid with psychiatric disorders (<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Kondo et&#x000a0;al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">Teo et&#x000a0;al., 2015b</xref>). Thus, this program in encouraging the acquisition of MHFA-based knowledge and skills in dealing with mental health problems is suggested to be useful especially in hikikomori cases comorbid with psychiatric conditions. As for each sub-item score of perceived skills, asking &#x0201c;feelings of depression&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;suicidal thoughts&#x0201d; were improved (see Supplement 1). These results are consistent with previous studies that evaluated the effectiveness of short version of MHFA-based intervention programs for specific settings such as a medical setting for clinical patients and an ordinary company setting for office workers (<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Kato et&#x000a0;al., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">Suzuki et&#x000a0;al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">Kubo et&#x000a0;al., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">Nakagami et&#x000a0;al., 2018</xref>). It is suggested that participants of the present study can obtain practical MHFA-oriented skills for management in hikikomori sufferers. In addition, Nakamura et&#x000a0;al. reported that reduction in stigma toward mental health problems among family members enhances help-seeking behavior (<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Nakamura et&#x000a0;al., 2006</xref>). The present program is expected to improve such aspects, and further validation is needed. These changes seen in self-rated questionnaires seemed to occur just after taking the program (between #1 and #5), and such changes were kept throughout follow-ups. We have conducted monthly follow-up sessions. It is possible that regular follow-ups would also have a positive effect on participants.</p><p id="p0205">Perceived skills in approaching a child with hikikomori based on MHFA improved throughout the sessions and follow-ups, however participants&#x02019; confidence in management of hikikomori cases was unchanged. We provided a large variety of content every week in the program, which may have been excessive. It is possible that participants felt difficulty in attaining sufficient success or competency in approaching their child due to the complexity of the program content. Thus, longer intervals between sessions (e.g. every other week) would give participants enough time to try newly obtained skills in their home with hikikomori sufferers. Furthermore, revising the program design and especially cutting down superfluous content would also be helpful.</p><p id="p0210">The present program, consisted of five 2-h weekly sessions, showed improvement in obsessive-compulsive behavior and decreased activity. Previously, Sakai and Sakano developed a 12-session, 2-h group intervention program for family members of hikikomori sufferers, and evaluated the effectiveness of the program by assessing the changes in problematic behaviors (<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Sakai and Sakano, 2010</xref>). From 9th to 11th session of their intervention program, functional analysis of problematic behaviors based on behavior therapy and behavioral psychoeducation were conducted, and outcomes between intervention group and control group were compared using self-rated questionnaires including HBCL among their participants. According to HBCL, decreased activity was improved in the intervention group while obsessive-compulsive behaviors worsened (<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Sakai and Sakano, 2010</xref>). On the other hand, Nonaka et&#x000a0;al. implemented a monthly CRAFT program consisted of six 2-h sessions as a single-arm trial for parents of hikikomori cases, and they revealed that aggressive behaviors, avoidance of family members, incomprehensible maladapted behaviors and obsessive-compulsive behaviors were improved (<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Nonaka et&#x000a0;al., 2013</xref>). The present study validated the improvement of obsessive-compulsive behaviors by CRAFT-oriented interventions.</p><p id="p0215">A World Health Organization epidemiological survey in Japan between 2002 and 2006 targeting individuals aged between 15 and 49 years reported that 1.2% of the population has experienced hikikomori for a period greater than 6 months (<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Koyama et&#x000a0;al., 2010</xref>). According to this survey, the lifetime prevalence of hikikomori is higher in males (1.8%) than in females (0.4%) (<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Koyama et&#x000a0;al., 2010</xref>). In the present study, the number of male sufferers was approximately three times higher than females (13 males and 4 females). Thus, this construction would represent hikikomori's general characteristics. On the other hand, a series of surveys by Japan's Cabinet Office reported that hikikomori sufferers aged between 40 and 65 were estimated to exceed those of aged between 15 and 39 (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Cabinet Office, 2016</xref>, <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2019</xref>). As represented by the 80&#x02013;50 problem, aging hikikomori is an urgent social issue in Japan. However, no participant living with a hikikomori sufferer more than 40 years of age participated in the present study. Further study targeting family members living with middle aged hikikomori is warranted to evaluate the effectiveness of the present program.</p><p id="p0220">In the present study, aversive effects were not reported except for a decrease in time spent with children (worsening rate was 5.6 %). It is presumed that the present program is safe and of low invasiveness in supporting family members and their children with hikikomori. Furthermore, the attendance rate of the program was high (99.05% of five sessions; 85.71% of six follow-ups). This implies that our newly developed program is suitable for parental needs.</p><p id="p0225">The MHFA program is reported to have positive effects on participants&#x02019; mental health (<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Kitchener and Jorm, 2002</xref>). However, in the present trial, the mental health conditions of participants themselves including depressive symptoms and stress responses were not significantly changed throughout the sessions and follow-ups. The average total score of PHQ-9 (depressive symptoms) at each time point (#1, #5 and FU1-FU6) was ranged 2.72&#x02013;4.55; SRS-18 (stress response) at each time point (#1-FU6) was ranged 6.90&#x02013;10.47 (<xref rid="tbl4" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;4</xref>). These scores indicate that participants in this study have not expressed a clinical level of depressive symptoms or stress response (<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">Suzuki et&#x000a0;al., 1997</xref>; <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Kroenke et&#x000a0;al., 2001</xref>; <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Muramatsu et&#x000a0;al., 2007</xref>). Future studies targeting hikikomori family members with high depressive symptoms and/or psychological stress are warranted.</p><p id="p0230">In the present study, joint participation group showed lower depressive symptoms and stress response than single participation group at baseline (#1). This result implies that parents who participated in this study as a couple may have a more positive marital relationship in their daily life. During the course of this program, we have directly observed positive behaviors by jointly participating fathers and mothers such as; 1) some participants talked together on their paternal/maternal roles in concerning with their hikikomori sufferer, and 2) some participants reviewed their previous marital relationships and tried to reform their roles vis-a-vis each other. Based on the above-preliminary observations, joint participation may have merits especially in rebuilding family relationships and enhancing appropriate paternal/maternal roles. Larger studies with additional scales should be conducted to confirm our hypothesis.</p><p id="p0235">The present study has some limitations. First, all assessments were conducted based on self-rated questionnaires among participants (parents), thus actual behavioral changes in participants and their children with hikikomori were not directly evaluated. In addition, behavioral changes of their children were assessed as a retrospective evaluation at final follow-up. Hence, recall bias would have affected participants&#x02019; reports. Moreover, follow-up period was 6 months; behavioral changes of hikikomori sufferers would occur at larger time frame (e.g. not a monthly basis but a year basis). Longitudinal and longer evaluation of behavioral changes is preferable in future trials. Finally, the present study was a single-arm design with no control groups. In addition, effect size of the observed effectiveness was low (effect sizes of self-rated questionnaires were 0.01&#x02013;0.02 at R<sup>2</sup>). Alongside with revision of the program, future randomized controlled trials are required to validate the effectiveness of the program. Hikikomori is becoming a serious issue not only in Japan but also worldwide (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">Kato et&#x000a0;al., 2011</xref>, <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>, <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">2016b</xref>, <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>; <xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">Teo et&#x000a0;al., 2015a</xref>, <xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">2015b</xref>), thus it is vital to develop effective family intervention programs internationally.</p></sec><sec id="sec9"><title>Declarations</title><sec id="sec9.1"><title>Author contribution statement</title><p id="p0240">H. Kubo: Conceived and designed the experiments; Performed the experiments; Analyzed and interpreted the data; Contributed reagents, materials, analysis tools or data; Wrote the paper.</p><p id="p0245">H. Urata: Performed the experiments; Analyzed and interpreted the data.</p><p id="p0250">M. Sakai, S. Nonaka, K. Saito, M. Tateno, K. Kobara, N. Hashimoto, D. Fujisawa, Y. Suzuki and K. Otsuka: Contributed reagents, materials, analysis tools or data.</p><p id="p0255">H. Kamimae, Y. Muto, T. Usami and Y. Honda: Performed the experiments.</p><p id="p0260">J. Kishimoto: Analyzed and interpreted the data.</p><p id="p0265">T. Kuroki and S. Kanba: Conceived and designed the experiments.</p><p id="p0270">T. Kato: Conceived and designed the experiments; Performed the experiments; Analyzed and interpreted the data; Contributed reagents, materials, analysis tools or data; Wrote the paper.</p></sec><sec id="sec9.2"><title>Funding statement</title><p id="p0275">T. Kato was partially supported by the Grant-in-Aid for Scientific Research on (1) The <funding-source id="gs1">Japan Agency for Medical Research and Development</funding-source> (AMED) (JP19dk0307073 &#x00026; JP18dk0307075), and (2) Innovative Areas &#x0201c;Will-Dynamics&#x0201d; of The <funding-source id="gs2">Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science, and Technology</funding-source>, Japan (JP16H06403).</p></sec><sec id="sec9.3"><title>Competing interest statement</title><p id="p0280">The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec id="sec9.4"><title>Additional information</title><p id="p0285">The clinical trial described in this paper was registered at UMIN Clinical Trials Registry under the registration number UMIN000029643.</p><p id="p0290">Supplementary content related to this article has been published online at <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.heliyon.2019.e03011" id="intref0015">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.heliyon.2019.e03011</ext-link>.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Cabinet Office</collab></person-group><chapter-title>Wakamono No Seikatsu Ni Kansuru Chousa-Houkokusho [Investigation on Life of Youth]</chapter-title><year>2016</year><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www8.cao.go.jp/youth/kenkyu/hikikomori/h27/pdf-index.html" id="intref0025">https://www8.cao.go.jp/youth/kenkyu/hikikomori/h27/pdf-index.html</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Cabinet Office</collab></person-group><chapter-title>Seikatsu Joukyou ni Kansuru Chousa [Investigation on living conditions]</chapter-title><year>2019</year><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www8.cao.go.jp/youth/kenkyu/life/h30/pdf-index.html" id="intref0030">https://www8.cao.go.jp/youth/kenkyu/life/h30/pdf-index.html</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hadlaczky</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hokby</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mkrtchian</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carli</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wasserman</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mental Health First Aid is an effective public health intervention for improving knowledge, attitudes, and behaviour: a meta-analysis</article-title><source>Int. Rev. Psychiatry</source><volume>26</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>467</fpage><lpage>475</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25137113</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hanley</surname><given-names>G.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwata</surname><given-names>B.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>McCord</surname><given-names>B.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional analysis of problem behavior: a review</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Appl. Behav. Anal.</source><volume>36</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>147</fpage><lpage>185</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12858983</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hayakawa</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Watabe</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Teo</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Horikawa</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuwano</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimokawa</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato-Kasai</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kubo</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohgidani</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sagata</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Toda</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tateno</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinfuku</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kishimoto</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanba</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Blood biomarkers of Hikikomori, a severe social withdrawal syndrome</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><volume>8</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>2884</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29440704</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Hikikomori No Taiou Gaido-Rain [Guideline for Response to Hikikomori]</chapter-title><year>2003</year><publisher-name>Ministry of Health, Labour and Welfare</publisher-name><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.mhlw.go.jp/topics/2003/07/tp0728-1.html" id="intref0035">https://www.mhlw.go.jp/topics/2003/07/tp0728-1.html</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hashimoto</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayakawa</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kubo</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Watabe</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Teo</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanba</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multidimensional anatomy of 'modern type depression' in Japan: a proposal for a different diagnostic approach to depression beyond the DSM-5</article-title><source>Psychiatry Clin. Neurosci.</source><volume>70</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>7</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26350304</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanba</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Teo</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A&#x000a0;39-year-old "adultolescent": understanding social withdrawal in Japan</article-title><source>Am. J. Psychiatry</source><volume>173</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>112</fpage><lpage>114</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26844793</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanba</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Teo</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hikikomori: experience in Japan and international relevance</article-title><source>World Psychiatry</source><volume>17</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>105</fpage><lpage>106</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29352535</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanba</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Teo</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hikikomori: multidimensional understanding, assessment and future international perspectives</article-title><source>Psychiatry Clin. Neurosci.</source><volume>73</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>427</fpage><lpage>440</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31148350</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinfuku</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sartorius</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanba</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Are Japan's hikikomori and depression in young people spreading abroad?</article-title><source>Lancet</source><volume>378</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>1070</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21924990</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinfuku</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sartorius</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanba</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Loneliness and single-person households: issues of kodokushi and hikikomori in Japan</chapter-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Okkels</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kristiansen</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Munk-J&#x000f8;rgensen</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Mental Health and Illness in the City. Mental Health and Illness Worldwide</source><year>2017</year><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Singapore</publisher-loc><fpage>205</fpage><lpage>219</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujisawa</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Uehara</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hashimoto</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sawayama</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanba</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Otsuka</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development of 2-hour suicide intervention program among medical residents: first pilot trial</article-title><source>Psychiatry Clin. Neurosci.</source><volume>64</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>531</fpage><lpage>540</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20727109</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tateno</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shinfuku</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujisawa</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Teo</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sartorius</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Akiyama</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishida</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>T.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Balhara</surname><given-names>Y.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Umene-Nakano</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujimura</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wand</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>R.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shadloo</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>H.U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lerthattasilp</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanba</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Does the 'hikikomori' syndrome of social withdrawal exist outside Japan? A preliminary international investigation</article-title><source>Soc. Psychiatry Psychiatr. Epidemiol.</source><volume>47</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>1061</fpage><lpage>1075</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21706238</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Teo</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tateno</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Watabe</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kubo</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanba</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Can Pokemon GO rescue shut-ins (hikikomori) from their isolated world?</article-title><source>Psychiatry Clin. Neurosci.</source><volume>71</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>75</fpage><lpage>76</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27862668</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>KHJ</collab></person-group><chapter-title>Hikikomori No Jittai Ni Kansuru Anke-To Chousa Houkokusho [Research Report on Actual Conditions of Hikikomori]</chapter-title><year>2018</year><publisher-name>KHJ National federation of families with hikikomori persons in Japan</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Tokyo</publisher-loc><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.khj-h.com/wp/wp-content/uploads/2018/05/Sakai_binder_2017.pdf" id="intref0040">https://www.khj-h.com/wp/wp-content/uploads/2018/05/Sakai_binder_2017.pdf</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kitchener</surname><given-names>B.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jorm</surname><given-names>A.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mental health first aid training for the public: evaluation of effects on knowledge, attitudes and helping behavior</article-title><source>BMC Psychiatry</source><volume>2</volume><year>2002</year><fpage>10</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12359045</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref18"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kitchener</surname><given-names>B.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jorm</surname><given-names>A.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>C.M.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Mental Health First Aid Manual</chapter-title><edition>third ed.</edition><year>2013</year><publisher-name>Mental Health First Aid Australia</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Melbourne</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref19"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kondo</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakai</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuroda</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiyota</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitabata</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurosawa</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>General condition of hikikomori (prolonged social withdrawal) in Japan: psychiatric diagnosis and outcome in mental health welfare centres</article-title><source>Int. J. Soc. Psychiatry</source><volume>59</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>79</fpage><lpage>86</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22094722</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koyama</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyake</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawakami</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsuchiya</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tachimori</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeshima</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><collab>World Mental Health Japan Survey Group, 2002-2006.</collab></person-group><article-title>Lifetime prevalence, psychiatric comorbidity and demographic correlates of &#x0201c;hikikomori&#x0201d; in a community population in Japan</article-title><source>Psychiatry Res.</source><volume>176</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>74</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20074814</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kroenke</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Spitzer</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>J.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The PHQ-9: validity of a brief depression severity measure</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Gen. Intern. Med.</source><volume>16</volume><year>2001</year><fpage>606</fpage><lpage>613</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11556941</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref22"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kubo</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Urata</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Katsuki</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirashima</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueno</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujisawa</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hashimoto</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobara</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitsui</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanba</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Otsuka</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development of MHFA-based 2-h educational program for early intervention in depression among office workers: a single-arm pilot trial</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><volume>13</volume><year>2018</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e0208114</object-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref23"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Langlands</surname><given-names>R.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jorm</surname><given-names>A.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>C.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitchener</surname><given-names>B.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>First aid for depression: a Delphi consensus study with consumers, carers and clinicians</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Affect. Disord.</source><volume>105</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>157</fpage><lpage>165</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17574684</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref24"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muramatsu</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyaoka</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamijima</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Muramatsu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Otsubo</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gejyo</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The patient health questionnaire, Japanese version: validity according to the mini-international neuropsychiatric interview-plus</article-title><source>Psychol. Rep.</source><volume>101</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>952</fpage><lpage>960</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18232454</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref25"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakagami</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kubo</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Katsuki</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakai</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugihara</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Naito</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oda</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayakawa</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujisawa</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hashimoto</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobara</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuga</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Takao</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawahara</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsumura</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Murai</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Akashi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanba</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Otsuka</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development of a 2-h suicide prevention program for medical staff including nurses and medical residents: a two-center pilot trial</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Affect. Disord.</source><volume>225</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>569</fpage><lpage>576</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28886497</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref26"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakagawa</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schielzeth</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A&#x000a0;general and simple method for obtaining R<sup>2</sup> from generalized linear mixed-effects models</article-title><source>Methods. Ecol. Evol.</source><volume>4</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>133</fpage><lpage>142</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref27"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwanaga</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakai</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimotsu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueda</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimada</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakano</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanazawa</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Help-seeking behavior in families of individuals in the state of &#x0201c;hikikomori&#x0201d;</article-title><source>Japn. J. Ment Health</source><volume>21</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>26</fpage><lpage>34</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref28"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nonaka</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakai</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ono</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of cognitive behavior group therapy for mothers of individuals with hikikomori: a trial intervention of community reinforcement and family training</article-title><source>Seishin Igaku</source><volume>55</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>283</fpage><lpage>291</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref29"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nonaka</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimada</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakai</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessing adaptive behaviors of individuals with hikikomori (prolonged social withdrawal): development and psychometric evaluation of the parent-report scale</article-title><source>Int. J. Cult. Ment. Health.</source><volume>11</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>280</fpage><lpage>294</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref30"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>R Core Team</collab></person-group><chapter-title>R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing</chapter-title><year>2018</year><publisher-name>R Foundation for Statistical Computing</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Vienna</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref31"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Hikikomori No Hyouka-Shien Ni Kansuru Gaido-Rain [Guidelines for Assessment and Support of Hikikomori]</chapter-title><year>2010</year><publisher-name>Ministry of Health, Labour and Welfare</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Tokyo</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref32"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Shishunki No Hikikomori Wo Motarasu Seishinkashikkan No Jittaihaaku to Seishin-Igakuteki Chiryou/Enjo Shistemu No Kouchiku Ni Kansuru Kenkyu [Research on Actual Conditions of Psychiatric Disorder in Adolescent Hikikomori and on Establishment of Psychiatric Treatment/supporting System]</chapter-title><year>2010</year><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mhlw-grants.niph.go.jp/niph/search/NIDD00.do?resrchNum=200935010A" id="interref0015">http://mhlw-grants.niph.go.jp/niph/search/NIDD00.do?resrchNum=200935010A</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref33"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Shakaiteki Hikikomori [Social Withdrawal]</chapter-title><year>1998</year><publisher-name>PHP Shinsho</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Tokyo</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref34"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sakai</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirakawa</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nonaka</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Okazaki</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yokose</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Inabata</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ushio</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mizoguchi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effectiveness of community reinforcement and family training (CRAFT) for parents of individuals with &#x0201c;hikikomori&#x0201d;</article-title><source>Jpn. J. Behav. Ther.</source><volume>41</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>167</fpage><lpage>178</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref35"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sakai</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishikawa</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakano</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development of hikikomori behavior checklist (HBCL) and examination of its reliability and validity</article-title><source>Jpn. J. Couns. Sci.</source><volume>37</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>210</fpage><lpage>222</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref36"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sakai</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nonaka</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>CRAFT Hikikomori No Kazoku-Shien Workbook [CRAFT Workbook for Supporting Family Members of Hikikomori]</chapter-title><year>2013</year><publisher-name>Kongoshuppan</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Tokyo</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref37"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sakai</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakano</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Behavioral group psychoeducation for parents whose adult children have withdrawn from social life (hikikomori)</article-title><source>Jpn. J. Behav. Ther.</source><volume>36</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>223</fpage><lpage>232</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref38"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shimotsu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakamoto</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Horikawa</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakano</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reliability and validity of the Link&#x02019;s devaluation-discrimination scale</article-title><source>Japanese Journal of Psychiatric Treatment</source><volume>21</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>521</fpage><lpage>528</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref39"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyers</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Motivating Substance Abusers to Enter Treatment: Working with Family Members</chapter-title><year>2004</year><publisher-name>Guilford Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref40"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimada</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miura</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Katayanagi</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Umano</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakano</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development of a new psychological stress response scale (SRS-18) and investigation of the reliability and the validity</article-title><source>Jpn. J. Behav. Med.</source><volume>4</volume><year>1997</year><fpage>22</fpage><lpage>29</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref41"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujisawa</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aoyama-Uehara</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hashimoto</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yonemoto</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukasawa</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Otsuka</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effectiveness of brief suicide management training programme for medical residents in Japan: a cluster randomized controlled trial</article-title><source>Epidemiol. Psychiatr. Sci.</source><volume>23</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>167</fpage><lpage>176</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23867112</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref42"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Teo</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J.I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kubo</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Katsuki</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato-Kasai</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimokawa</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayakawa</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Umene-Nakano</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aikens</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanba</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development and validation of the 25-item hikikomori questionnaire (HQ-25)</article-title><source>Psychiatry Clin. Neurosci.</source><volume>72</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>780</fpage><lpage>788</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29926525</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref43"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Teo</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fetters</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stufflebam</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tateno</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Balhara</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>T.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanba</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathews</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of the hikikomori syndrome of social withdrawal: psychosocial features and treatment preferences in four countries</article-title><source>Int. J. Soc. Psychiatry</source><volume>61</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>64</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24869848</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref44"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Teo</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stufflebam</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saha</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fetters</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tateno</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanba</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Psychopathology associated with social withdrawal: idiopathic and comorbid presentations</article-title><source>Psychiatry Res.</source><volume>228</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>182</fpage><lpage>183</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25977071</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref45"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>A.F.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ooi</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>P.W.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Catmur</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>J.Y.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evidence of pathological social withdrawal in non-Asian countries: a global health problem?</article-title><source>Lancet Psychiatry</source><volume>6</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>195</fpage><lpage>196</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30798886</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref46"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yong</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nomura</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hikikomori is most associated with interpersonal relationships, followed by suicide risks: a secondary analysis of a national cross-sectional study</article-title><source>Front. Psychiatry</source><volume>10</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>247</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31040799</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec id="appsec1" sec-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix A</label><title>Supplementary data</title><p id="p0300">The following is the supplementary data related to this article:<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc1"><caption><title>Supplementary material</title></caption><media xlink:href="mmc1.docx"><alt-text>Supplementary material</alt-text></media></supplementary-material></p></sec><ack id="ack0010"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors express gratitude to the following mentors and colleagues; Professor Anthony Jorm and Ms. Betty Kitchener for their mentorship in MHFA program; Dr. Ryoko Sato, Dr. Kumi Aoyama-Uehara, Mr. Makoto Kamisaki, Ms. Mayumi Otsuka of Mental Health First Aid Japan (MHFA-J: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mhfa.jp" id="intref0020">http://mhfa.jp</ext-link>), and Dr. Naoji Kondo for providing us kind suggestions on the research activities of hikikomori.</p></ack></back></article>