<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PeerJ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PeerJ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">peerj</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">peerj</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PeerJ</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2167-8359</issn><publisher><publisher-name>PeerJ Inc.</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Diego, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31938581</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6954686</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">8366</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.8366</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Anatomy and Physiology</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Diabetes and Endocrinology</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Drugs and Devices</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Kinesiology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Validity and reliability evidence of a point of care assessment of salivary cortisol and <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-amylase: a pre-registered study</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="author-1" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ducker</surname><given-names>Kagan J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">1</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lines</surname><given-names>Robin L.J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">1</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>Michael T.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">1</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Peeling</surname><given-names>Peter</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2">2</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-5" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>McKay</surname><given-names>Alannah K.A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-3">3</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-6" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Gucciardi</surname><given-names>Daniel F.</given-names></name><email>daniel.f.gucciardi@gmail.com</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="aff-1"><label>1</label><institution>School of Physiotherapy and Exercise Science, Curtin University</institution>, <city>Perth</city>, <state>Western Australia</state>, <country>Australia</country></aff><aff id="aff-2"><label>2</label><institution>School of Human Sciences (Exercise and Sport Science), The University of Western Australia</institution>, <city>Perth</city>, <state>Western Australia</state>, <country>Australia</country></aff><aff id="aff-3"><label>3</label><institution>Australian Institute of Sport</institution>, <city>Belconnen</city>, <state>Australian Capital Territory</state>, <country>Australia</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Gomez</surname><given-names>Shawn</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub" date-type="pub" iso-8601-date="2020-01-08"><day>8</day><month>1</month><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>e8366</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received" iso-8601-date="2019-08-09"><day>9</day><month>8</month><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted" iso-8601-date="2019-12-06"><day>6</day><month>12</month><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9;2020 Ducker et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Ducker et al.</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, reproduction and adaptation in any medium and for any purpose provided that it is properly attributed. For attribution, the original author(s), title, publication source (PeerJ) and either DOI or URL of the article must be cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/8366"/><abstract><sec><title>Purpose</title><p>The iPro Cube is a small portable point-of-care device designed to analyse salivary markers of stress in a user-friendly manner (e.g., fast, convenient). Our aim was to test the reliability and validity of the iPro Cube to measure salivary cortisol and <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-amylase as compared to the common laboratory standard method (ELISA immunoassay) prior to and after moderate intensity exercise.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>The study was a repeated measures, pre-registered design, and statistical framework that incorporated prior knowledge directly into the estimation process. Twenty-nine individuals (age = 27.4&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;6.6 y; body-mass = 70.8&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;11.3 kg; height = 1.74&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.92 m; 18 males) completed a single PWC<sub>75%HRmax</sub>, with repeated measures of salivary cortisol and -amylase pre, immediately post, and 30 min post-exercise.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Correlation between the iPro Cube and laboratory-based assessments of salivary cortisol was moderate-to-large (0.53 &#x0003e; <italic>r</italic> &#x0003c; 0.81) across all three testing points. In contrast, correlation between the iPro Cube and laboratory-based assessments of -amylase was small-to-moderate (0.25 &#x0003e; <italic>r</italic> &#x0003c; 0.46). We found a large correlation between duplicate samples of iPro Cube cortisol assessment (0.75 &#x0003e; <italic>r</italic> &#x0003c; 0.82), and a moderate-to-large correlation for -amylase (0.51&#x0003e; <italic>r</italic> &#x0003c; 0.77).</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>The iPro Cube is capable of taking measures of salivary cortisol that are moderately correlated to values obtained via ELISA immunoassay, however the unit underestimates salivary cortisol and overestimates salivary -amylase at rest and post-moderate intensity exercise. It is recommended that researchers continue using standard laboratory techniques to assess these salivary stress markers.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>Stress</kwd><kwd>Psychophysiology</kwd><kwd>Saliva</kwd><kwd>Exercise</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="fund-1"><funding-source> Australian Army and a Defence Science Partnerships</funding-source><award-id>ID7085</award-id></award-group><funding-statement>The Commonwealth of Australia supported this research through the Australian Army and a Defence Science Partnerships agreement of the Defence Science and Technology Group, as part of the Human Performance Research Network (ID7085). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>The stress placed on the body by exercise can be measured using various biological markers in saliva, hair, and blood. Two key systems in the neuroendocrine response to stress are the hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) axis and the autonomic nervous system (ANS), which drive responses to assist the body in coping with the applied stressor (<xref rid="ref-34" ref-type="bibr">Rutherford-Markwick et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="ref-37" ref-type="bibr">Strahler et al., 2017</xref>). Salivary markers of HPA axis and ANS activity have increased in popularity recently, as there are several metabolites that can be detected via this non-invasive technique, using only small sample volumes (i.e.,&#x000a0;&#x0223c;0.5&#x02013;1 ml) (<xref rid="ref-23" ref-type="bibr">Lee, Kim &#x00026; Choi, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="ref-32" ref-type="bibr">Papacosta &#x00026; Nassis, 2011</xref>). Collection of salivary metabolites offers a viable non-invasive alternative to serum and plasma methods where frequent venepuncture to sample blood may impact the analyte of interest (e.g.,&#x000a0;increasing cortisol response) or may be inappropriate, requiring less medical expertise, rapid collection, and can be performed in a variety of settings. Salivary cortisol (HPA axis) and alpha-amylase (<italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-amylase; ANS) are two such markers that can be measured in the saliva as a surrogate measure of psychophysiological stress.</p><p>Cortisol is a glucocorticoid released from the adrenal cortex by activation of the HPA axis when the body is stressed (<xref rid="ref-23" ref-type="bibr">Lee, Kim &#x00026; Choi, 2015</xref>). Only a thin layer of cells separate the salivary ducts from blood passing through the area, which ultimately results in trace levels of cortisol passing through the oral cavity into saliva; when measured, salivary cortisol typically provides a strong representation of plasma cortisol levels (<xref rid="ref-40" ref-type="bibr">T&#x000f6;rnhage, 2009</xref>), though disassociations have been observed under challenge situations, during the circadian cycle, and in terms of free versus protein-bound cortisol concentrations (<xref rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr">Levine et al., 2007</xref>) . Salivary cortisol is advocated for use within stress research because of the generally strong representation of plasma cortisol levels and stress free nature of collection (<xref rid="ref-18" ref-type="bibr">Hellhammer, W&#x000fc;st &#x00026; Kudielka, 2009</xref>). Cortisol has widespread effects (e.g.,&#x000a0;stimulation of protein and lipid catabolism, increased gluconeogenesis and reduced inflammation) that are aimed at enhancing the ability of the body to cope with stress and repair tissue damage (<xref rid="ref-23" ref-type="bibr">Lee, Kim &#x00026; Choi, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr">Levine et al., 2007</xref>). Importantly, when the HPA axis is chronically stimulated, the typical responsiveness of the axis may be supressed, which may inhibit immune function (<xref rid="ref-1" ref-type="bibr">Adam et al., 2017</xref>). The responsiveness of the HPA axis makes cortisol a useful marker for assessing the acute (short-term) and chronic (long-term) response to stress in individuals and athletes.</p><p>Alternatively, <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-amylase is an enzyme that is secreted directly into the saliva in response to ANS activation, as would commonly occur when humans experience psychophysiological stress (Bosch, Veerman, de Geus, &#x00026; Proctor, 2011; (<xref rid="ref-30" ref-type="bibr">Nater &#x00026; Rohleder, 2009</xref>). Importantly, the salivary concentration has a consistent circadian rhythm and is highly responsive to changes in ANS activity as it is produced within the salivary glands rather than being transported through into the salivary ducts from plasma like cortisol (<xref rid="ref-30" ref-type="bibr">Nater &#x00026; Rohleder, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="ref-33" ref-type="bibr">Rohleder &#x00026; Nater, 2009</xref>). During exercise, and particularly during high-intensity efforts, the ANS is activated, thereby making <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-amylase a potentially useful indicator of physiological stress in humans. Caution is advised when using <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-amylase as a measure of ANS activity (<xref rid="ref-6" ref-type="bibr">Bosch et al., 2011</xref>), as stress induced increases in <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-amylase have been found to correlate poorly with other indicators of ANS activity (e.g.,&#x000a0;catecholamines) (<xref rid="ref-39" ref-type="bibr">Thoma et al., 2012</xref>). Nevertheless, this poor degree of association is a common issue with indicators of ANS activity, and in turn is not considered a disqualifying factor (<xref rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr">Engeland, Bosch &#x00026; Rohleder, 2019</xref>).</p><p>Typically, stress markers such as cortisol and <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-amylase are assessed via a sample of saliva or blood, which are analysed in a laboratory by highly skilled technicians using processes that are expensive and can take several hours or days. However, small portable point-of-care (POC) devices are available to make this process easier to conduct in the field,</p><p>with analysis requiring short timeframes that allow the rapid generation of information to assess the stress response rapidly. Recently, Soma Bioscience (Oxfordshire, UK) have released two lateral flow device (LFD) readers, the iPro Lab<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn-1"><sup>1</sup></xref>
<fn id="fn-1"><label>1</label><p><italic>iPro Lab reader</italic>&#x02014;this is iPro&#x02019;s larger, and older, saliva analysis system. It reads the lateral flow device (LFD) that contains the samples of saliva. See <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://somabioscience.com/?page_id=214">http://somabioscience.com/?page_id=214</ext-link>. We will simply refer to this as the iPro Lab.</p></fn>and iPro Cube<xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn-2"><sup>2</sup></xref>
<fn id="fn-2"><label>2</label><p><italic>iPro Cube reader</italic> - this is iPro&#x02019;s smaller, and newer, portable saliva analysis system. It reads the lateral flow device (LFD) that contain the samples of saliva. See <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://somabioscience.com/?page_id=182">http://somabioscience.com/?page_id=182</ext-link>. We will simply refer to this as the iPro Cube.</p></fn>. Immunochromagraphic strips (lateral flow devices&#x02014;LFD <xref ref-type="fn" rid="fn-3"><sup>3</sup></xref>
<fn id="fn-3"><label>3</label><p><italic>iPro Cube LFD &#x02013;</italic> We will simply refer to this as a lateral flow device (LFD). The LFD&#x02019;s are the strips that contain the saliva samples and are inserted into either the iPro Lab or Cube devices to analyse the saliva samples.</p></fn>) containing a test line that responds to gold labelled anti-secretory antibodies are exposed to a saliva sample (and buffer) which can be assessed by the reader to obtain a measure of salivary cortisol and <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-amylase. The iPro Lab has been shown to be a valid and reliable unit to assess salivary cortisol at rest (<xref rid="ref-13" ref-type="bibr">Fisher, McLellan &#x00026; Sinclair, 2015</xref>) and following high-intensity exercise (sprinting) (<xref rid="ref-25" ref-type="bibr">MacDonald, Bellinger &#x00026; Minahan, 2017</xref>). The iPro Lab&#x02019;s utility in measuring salivary cortisol has been validated against traditional methods, demonstrating non-significant differences in resting cortisol levels with the Salimetrics oral swab (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.881) and the passive drool method (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.145) (<xref rid="ref-13" ref-type="bibr">Fisher, McLellan &#x00026; Sinclair, 2015</xref>). Evidence also advocates its use in assessing cortisol levels following high-intensity exercise (sprinting), demonstrating significant increases from resting to 15&#x000a0;min post exercise (<xref rid="ref-25" ref-type="bibr">MacDonald, Bellinger &#x00026; Minahan, 2017</xref>). Caution is urged when interpreting these findings as the sample sizes for the chosen designs were small. The iPro Lab has also been validated at assessing the immune marker, salivary immunoglobulin-A, at rest (<xref rid="ref-8" ref-type="bibr">Coad, Gray &#x00026; McLellan, 2016</xref>; <xref rid="ref-9" ref-type="bibr">Coad et al., 2015a</xref>; <xref rid="ref-10" ref-type="bibr">Coad et al., 2015b</xref>), and after team-sport (intermittent) exercise (<xref rid="ref-8" ref-type="bibr">Coad, Gray &#x00026; McLellan, 2016</xref>; <xref rid="ref-10" ref-type="bibr">Coad et al., 2015b</xref>). However, whether the newer and more portable version of this device (iPro Cube) can be used to assess <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-amylase at rest, and to measure relatively small changes in salivary cortisol and <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-amylase post-moderate intensity exercise remains unknown. This information is important for researchers, sports scientists, and health professionals who are seeking a POC device to assess markers of psychophysiological stress in a field setting. Therefore, our aim was to test in the field the reliability and validity of the iPro Cube to measure salivary cortisol and <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-amylase as compared to the common laboratory standard method (ELISA). On the basis of a conservative estimate from past research (<xref rid="ref-9" ref-type="bibr">Coad et al., 2015a</xref>; <xref rid="ref-10" ref-type="bibr">Coad et al., 2015b</xref>; <xref rid="ref-13" ref-type="bibr">Fisher, McLellan &#x00026; Sinclair, 2015</xref>), we hypothesised that;</p><list list-type="simple" id="list-1"><list-item><label> 1.</label><p>For salivary cortisol and <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-amylase, respectively, POC assessment will correlate positively and moderately (<italic>r</italic> &#x0223c;0.50) with a laboratory-based assessment (a) pre-exercise (resting baseline), (b) immediately post-exercise, and (c) 30 min post-exercise.</p></list-item><list-item><label> 2.</label><p>Duplicate samples collected concurrently of the POC assessment of salivary cortisol and <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-amylase, respectively, will correlate positively and strongly (<italic>r</italic> &#x0223c;0.80).</p></list-item></list></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Participants</title><p>Monte Carlo simulations (L. K. (<xref rid="ref-29" ref-type="bibr">Muth&#x000e9;n &#x00026; Muth&#x000e9;n, 2002</xref>) indicated that 15 participants would provide sufficient power (100%) to detect a conservative effect size (<italic>r</italic> &#x0223c;0.50) when incorporating prior beliefs informed by past research (<xref rid="ref-9" ref-type="bibr">Coad et al., 2015a</xref>; <xref rid="ref-10" ref-type="bibr">Coad et al., 2015b</xref>; <xref rid="ref-13" ref-type="bibr">Fisher, McLellan &#x00026; Sinclair, 2015</xref>) directly into the estimation process. Full details of these power simulations are available on the Open Science Framework (OSF; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bit.ly/2HCA6MR">http://bit.ly/2HCA6MR</ext-link>). Individuals were eligible to participate if they were university students aged &#x02265;18&#x000a0;years; we excluded people from taking part in the study if they had an illness or injury that prevented them from completing a sub-maximal exercise test. In total, 29 eligible individuals provided written informed consent and took part in this study (age = 27.4&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;6.6 y, range = 19&#x02013;48 y; body-mass = 70.8&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;11.3&#x000a0;kg; height = 1.74&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.92 m; BMI = 23&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;3; 18 males). The study was approved by Curtin University&#x02019;s Human Ethics Research Committee (HRE2017-0518).</p></sec><sec><title>Procedures</title><p>All study hypotheses, methods, procedures and data analysis plans were pre-registered on the OSF (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://osf.io/tshkc/">https://osf.io/tshkc/</ext-link>). The study design was a single-session exercise protocol with repeated measures of salivary cortisol and <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-amylase prior to completing a sub-maximal test of aerobic work capacity, immediately following this test, and after 30 min of rest. Each participant attended one testing session (08:00&#x02013;10:00 or 10:00&#x02013;12:00) to minimise any effect from circadian variations. Waking time was not recorded, however, there should have been &#x0003e;60 min between the participants waking to the start of salivary sampling, to ensure that the cortisol awakening response was avoided. Upon arriving in the laboratory and providing informed consent, participants completed a short survey including self-reported demographic information (e.g.,&#x000a0;gender and age). Participants next completed a sub-maximal test of aerobic work capacity (PWC<sub>75%HRmax</sub>; (<xref rid="ref-16" ref-type="bibr">Gore et al., 1999</xref>; <xref rid="ref-26" ref-type="bibr">Miyashita et al., 1985</xref>) where there would be some stimulation of the HPA. Briefly, this test involves completing three workloads of 3&#x02013;6 min at approximately 55, 65 and 75% of age predicted maximum heart rate (220 bpm &#x02013;age in years) on a cycle ergometer (Monark, Monark Exercise AB, Varnsbro, Sweden), which was used as a method of prescribing a bout of individualised moderate intensity physical activity. This validation study was part of a larger project our team was conducting with Army personnel, so we decided to focus on an intensity that was most representative of typical training scenarios (<xref rid="ref-14" ref-type="bibr">Friedl et al., 2012</xref>). Previous studies have reported increases in both salivary cortisol and <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-amylase in response to a single bout of exercise (<xref rid="ref-37" ref-type="bibr">Strahler et al., 2017</xref>). Heart rate and ratings of perceived exertion (<xref rid="ref-5" ref-type="bibr">Borg, 1982</xref>) were collected each minute during the test.</p><p>Participants were required to avoid high-intensity exercise and alcohol for 24 h and brushing their teeth or eating food for 2 h pre-exercise. Samples of saliva were taken pre-warm-up, immediately post-exercise and 30 min post-exercise. Participants rinsed their mouth with water 10 min prior to saliva collection at pre-warm-up. Nine unstimulated whole saliva samples were provided by each participant (3 &#x000d7;&#x000a0;pre-warm-up, 3 &#x000d7;&#x000a0; immediately post-exercise and 3 &#x000d7;&#x000a0; 30 min post-exercise). On each occasion duplicate oral swabs (iPro oral fluid collector; Soma Bioscience, Oxfordshire, UK) were placed in the mouth concurrently for assessment using a cortisol/ <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-amylase LFD before being analysed using a LFD reader (iPro Cube, Soma Bioscience, Oxfordshire, UK). The intra-sample coefficient of variation (CV) for the iPro salivary cortisol <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-amylase samples were 8.8 and 20.0%, respectively. Next, the third sample was collected by the passive drool method directly into a two mL cryovial immediately after the sample for the iPro Cube (Salimetrics LLC, Pennsylvania, USA). This sample was frozen at &#x02212;20 &#x000b0;<italic>C</italic> until analysis in duplicate for cortisol and <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-amylase using a validated, commercially available enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA; Salimetrics, USA) by Stratech Scientific APAC Pty Ltd. (Sydney, Australia). Freezing has minimal influence of samples at &#x02212;20 &#x000b0;<italic>C</italic> even after one year in storage (<xref rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr">Garde &#x00026; Hansen, 2005</xref>). The inter-assay and intra-assay CV for the salivary cortisol samples was 5.0 and 4.4%, respectively. The inter-assay and intra-assay CV for the salivary <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-amylase samples was 5.8 and 5.1%, respectively.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analyses</title><p>The registered study hypotheses were tested in M<italic>plus</italic> 8 (L. K. (<xref rid="ref-28" ref-type="bibr">Muth&#x000e9;n &#x00026; Muth&#x000e9;n, 1998-2017</xref>)-2017) using a series of bivariate correlations with a Bayesian estimator. The execution and reporting of these analyses were informed by recent guidelines for Bayesian statistics (<xref rid="ref-11" ref-type="bibr">Depaoli &#x00026; Van de Schoot, 2017</xref>). An overview of the priors for each hypothesis is available on the OSF. We also report and compare our weakly or informative priors with non-informative (diffuse) priors to examine the effect of prior information on the posterior distribution (<xref rid="ref-11" ref-type="bibr">Depaoli &#x00026; Van de Schoot, 2017</xref>). Briefly, the specification of non-informative priors allows the data at hand to drive the estimations within the posterior distribution because it reflects substantial uncertainty regarding the nature of the target parameter. Model convergence was assessed using statistical (i.e.,&#x000a0;potential scale reduction factor; PSR &#x0003c;1.05) and visual criteria (i.e.,&#x000a0;inspection of trace plots for stability in mean and variance of each chain). Posterior predictive checking is used to assess model fit in Bayesian estimation, where the posterior distribution is compared with the observed data to examine the degree to which the replicated data matches the observed data (B. O. (<xref rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr">Muth&#x000e9;n &#x00026; Asparouhov, 2012</xref>). The posterior predictive <italic>p</italic>-value (PPP) and associated 95% credibility interval (CI) is produced in M<italic>plus</italic>; values close to 0.50 reflect an excellent fitting model, though typically values greater than 0.05 are considered acceptable (B. O. (<xref rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr">Muth&#x000e9;n &#x00026; Asparouhov, 2012</xref>). Parameter estimates are considered credible when the 95% CI excludes zero. We classified &#x0201c;not a detectable&#x0201d; (NAN) readings as a missing value; missing data were handled with the Gibbs sampler that treats the missing observations as unknown values to be estimated and the algorithm used will correctly estimate the model under the missing at random (MAR) assumption (<xref rid="ref-3" ref-type="bibr">Asparouhov &#x00026; Muth&#x000e9;n, 2010</xref>). All M<italic>plus</italic> output files including analysis syntax together with Bland-Altman plots (<xref rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr">Bland &#x00026; Altman, 1986</xref>) are available on the OSF (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://osf.io/tshkc/">https://osf.io/tshkc/</ext-link>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p>The raw data file is available on the OSF. Descriptive statistics for the heart rate and perceived exertion response to the exercise stimulus are presented in <xref rid="table-1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. In total, 49 (47 of which were obtained with the iPro Cube) of 522 data points were recoded as missing due to an undetectable reading; 24 of the iPro Cube samples were recoded as 0 when the device provide a value that was &#x0003c;0.7.</p><table-wrap id="table-1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.8366/table-1</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Descriptive statistics for heart rate, percentage of age predicted heart rate maximum (%HR<sub><italic>max</italic></sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;220 bpm&#x02013;age in years), and rating of perceived exertion (RPE 6&#x02013;20; (<xref rid="ref-5" ref-type="bibr">Borg, 1982</xref>) during workloads 1&#x02013;3 of the PWC<sub>75%<italic>HRmax</italic></sub> test.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-08-8366-g001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Range</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minimum</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximum</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">SD</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Heart rate (bpm)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Workload 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">128</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">110</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Workload 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">97</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">158</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">129</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Workload 3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">124</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">170</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">149</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">%HR<sub>max</sub></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Workload 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Workload 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Workload 3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">87%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4%</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">RPE</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Workload 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Workload 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Workload 3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-1fn"><p><bold>Notes.</bold></p></fn><fn id="table-1fn1" fn-type="other"><p>
<def-list id="dl1"><def-item><term> bpm</term><def><p>beats per minute</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>%HR<sub>max</sub></term><def><p>Percentage of maximum heart rate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> REP</term><def><p>Rate of perceived exertion</p></def></def-item></def-list>
</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Group-level descriptive statistics for salivary cortisol and <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-amylase are presented in <xref rid="table-2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. Analysis of the Bland-Altman plots (available on the OSF; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://osf.io/tshkc/">https://osf.io/tshkc/</ext-link>) show a positive mean difference in cortisol concentrations at all time points of the assessment, indicating that the iPro Cube underestimates salivary cortisol. Additionally, the difference between the iPro Cube and immunoassay increases with greater cortisol concentrations. A negative mean difference in <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-amylase was also observed, indicating that the iPro Cube overestimates <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-amaylase. Further, this difference becomes greater with increasing levels of <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-amaylase.</p><table-wrap id="table-2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.8366/table-2</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Descriptive statistics for salivary cortisol and a-amylase pre-warm-up, immediately post- exercise and 30 min post-exercise.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-08-8366-g002"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Range</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>n</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minimum</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximum</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">SD</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="9" colspan="1">Salivary cortisol (nMol&#x000a0;L<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Pre-exercise</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">iPro Cube 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.40</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">iPro Cube 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.80</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.70</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.32</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ELISA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.92</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.96</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Post-exercise</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">iPro Cube 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.19</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">iPro Cube 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.76</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ELISA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.79</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.21</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">30 min post-exercise</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">iPro Cube 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.80</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.62</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">iPro Cube 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ELISA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.08</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="9" colspan="1">Salivary <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-amylase (nKat&#x000a0;L<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</td><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Pre-exercise</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">iPro Cube 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.30</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">iPro Cube 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.58</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.43</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.15</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ELISA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">Post-exercise</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">iPro Cube 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.40</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">iPro Cube 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.98</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.12</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ELISA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.62</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" colspan="1">30 min post-exercise</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">iPro Cube 1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.47</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.32</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">iPro Cube 2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.87</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.86</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.81</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ELISA</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.53</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><p>With regard to the main analyses, the probability of the data, given the hypothesised model, was acceptable for all models associated with each hypothesis (i.e., PPP &#x0003e;0.20). Inspections of the trace plots and PSR evolution through the simulations (i.e., started within 0.50 of 1 and reduced quickly close to 1 and remained stable throughout the entire sequence of iterations) verified support for model convergence. Full details of model-data fit and convergence are available in the output and supplementary material files located on the OSF. Parameter estimates of all models tested using weakly informative (uniform), informative, and non-informative (diffuse) priors are displayed in <xref rid="table-3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>. We also report in <xref rid="table-3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref> parameter estimates obtained using a robust maximum likelihood estimator for readers most familiar with frequentist statistics.</p><table-wrap id="table-3" orientation="landscape" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.8366/table-3</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Comparison of standardised correlation coefficients between Bayesian and maximum likelihood estimators.</title><p>The two correlation coefficients presented for each variable in the ELISA column are those between the ELISA and each of the two iPro Cube samples. The single value for each variable in the iPro Cube column is the correlation coefficient for the two iPro Cube samples; 95% credibility intervals are presented in parentheses; MLR = robust maximum likelihood estimator; ELISA = analysis via ELISA immunoassay; iPro be = correlation between duplicate samples via the point of care assessment; # SOE (size of effect) = [(initial prior / default/non-informative prior)/ initial prior] * 100 (see <xref rid="ref-11" ref-type="bibr">Depaoli &#x00026; Van de Schoot, 2017</xref>).</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-08-8366-g003"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Bayesian Uniform/Weakly Informative Prior</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Bayesian Non-informative Prior</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">SOE<sup>#</sup></th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">MLR</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ELISA</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">iPro Cube</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ELISA</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">iPro Cube</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ELISA</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">iPro Cube</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">ELISA</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">iPro Cube</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="6" colspan="1">Salivary cortisol (nMol&#x000a0;L<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Pre-exercise</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75 (0.56, 0.84)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79 (0.64, 0.88)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81 (0.61, 0.91)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81 (0.58, 0.92)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.00%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.53%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80 (0.58, 1.02)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82 (0.72, 0.91)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53 (0.21, 0.72)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58 (0.21, 0.80)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.43%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59 (0.35, 0.83)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Post-exercise</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54 (0.23, 0.71)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75 (0.60, 0.85)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59 (0.25, 0.80)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77 (0.51, 0.90)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.26%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.67%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59 (0.30, 0.87)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77 (0.62, 0.92)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81 (0.62, 0.89)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87 (0.69, 0.94)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.41%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87 (0.77, 0.97)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">30 min post-exercise</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53 (0.20, 0.71)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82 (0.67, 0.90)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59 (0.21, 0.81)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84 (0.63, 0.93)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.32%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.43%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59 (0.32, 0.86)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85 (0.72, 0.98)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71 (0.47, 0.83)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78 (0.53, 0.90)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.86%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78 (0.64, 0.92)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="6" colspan="1">Salivary <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-amylase (nKat&#x000a0;L<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>)</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Pre-exercise</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44 (0.15, 0.65)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51 (0.37, 0.64)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47 (0.10, 0.73)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23 (-0.23, 0.60)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.81%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.90%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47 (0.16, 0.77)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23 (-0.37, 0.82)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32 (0.10, 0.56)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29 (&#x02212;0.12, 0.62)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.38%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29 (0.07, 0.52)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Post-exercise</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.46 (0.16, 0.66)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50 (0.36, 0.63)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50 (0.13, 0.74)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24 (&#x02212;0.19, 0.37)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.69%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.00%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49 (0.26, 0.73)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24 (&#x02212;0.19, 0.68)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37 (0.11, 0.62)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38 (&#x02212;0.14, 0.72)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.70%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39 (&#x02212;0.04, 0.82)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">30 min post-exercise</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33 (0.10, 0.57)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77 (0.62, 0.86)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31 (&#x02212;0.09, 0.62)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80 (0.55, 0.92)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.06%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.90%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31 (.003, 0.61)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81 (0.57, 1.05)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25 (0.09, 0.51)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13 (&#x02212;0.33, 0.53)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.00%</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13 (&#x02212;0.15, 0.40)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><p>Overall, these analyses revealed mixed support for our hypotheses. Correlation between POC and laboratory-based assessments of salivary cortisol was moderate-to-large (0.53&#x0003e;<italic>r</italic>&#x0003c;0.81) across all three testing points. In contrast, correlation between POC and laboratory-based assessments of <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-amylase was small-to-moderate in magnitude (0.25&#x0003e;<italic>r</italic>&#x0003c;0.46). A similar trend in the findings was observed for hypothesis 2, where we found large correlation between duplicate samples of POC assessment of cortisol (0.75&#x0003e;<italic>r</italic>&#x0003c;0.82), but moderate-to-large correlation <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-amylase (0.51&#x0003e;<italic>r</italic>&#x0003c;0.77). A closer inspection of the findings revealed variation in the substantive interpretation of the results in two ways. First, the strength of association between the POC assessment and laboratory analysis of salivary cortisol and <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-amylase varied across the duplicate samples at each assessment point (24&#x02013;50%). Second, the discrepancies between the weakly informative and informative priors with the non-informative prior indicated moderate-to-large effects of the prior information on the posterior distribution, which represents a mismatch between prior expectation and the data at hand (<xref rid="ref-11" ref-type="bibr">Depaoli &#x00026; Van de Schoot, 2017</xref>).</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>We tested the reliability and validity of the iPro Cube as a rapid field assessment of salivary cortisol and <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-amylase, comparing the outcomes to the most common laboratory method (ELISA) utilising a pre-registered design and statistical framework that incorporated prior knowledge directly into the estimation process. Our findings revealed mixed support for the hypotheses.</p><p>During the exercise testing, participants experienced peak heart rates reflective of moderate- to vigorous-intensity exercise (<xref rid="ref-31" ref-type="bibr">Norton, Norton &#x00026; Sadgrove, 2010</xref>), and RPE that were indicative of light to somewhat hard efforts (<xref rid="ref-5" ref-type="bibr">Borg, 1982</xref>) (see <xref rid="table-1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Considering that this test was graded, and only involved short workloads, the overall physical stress placed on the participants was moderate, but only for a short period. Although the response of salivary cortisol to exercise can be variable, previous research suggests that moderate- to vigorous-intensity exercise, particularly when prolonged in nature, will stimulate the HPA and cause an increase in salivary cortisol (<xref rid="ref-17" ref-type="bibr">Hayes et al., 2015</xref>). However, due to the short duration and low to moderate initial workloads of the PWC <sub>75%HRmax</sub>, in our participants, a slight trend for a decrease in salivary cortisol may indicate that the stimulus was insufficiently stressful to activate the HPA axis. If the HPA axis was insufficiently stimulated to achieve an increase, the slight decrease may instead be reflective of the typical diurnal variation, particularly in the 10:00 participants, as cortisol decreases rapidly after an initial increase post-awakening (<xref rid="ref-7" ref-type="bibr">Clow et al., 2004</xref>). Both <xref rid="ref-41" ref-type="bibr">VanBruggen et al. (2011)</xref> and <xref rid="ref-20" ref-type="bibr">Jacks et al. (2002)</xref> identified no increase in salivary cortisol during low (40&#x02013;45% V O<sub>2peak</sub>) or moderate-intensity (60% V O<sub>2peak</sub>) cycling for 30&#x02013;60 min, but did see increases during high-intensity (75&#x02013;80% V O<sub>2peak</sub>) cycling. The intense and prolonged (in the case of (<xref rid="ref-20" ref-type="bibr">Jacks et al., 2002</xref>) nature of the high-intensity stimulus in these studies is likely responsibly for the increases in salivary cortisol observed.</p><p>The utility of the newer iPro Cube for assessing salivary cortisol in the field has yet to be assessed. In the current study, moderate to large correlations were found between the salivary cortisol measures obtained from the iPro Cube and immunoassay. Additionally, a large correlation was identified between duplicate saliva samples analysed using the iPro Cube. However, although the measures may be related, and duplicate samples are similar for the iPro Cube, there was a mean difference of 51.5&#x02013;64.6% (underestimate) between the iPro Cube and the immunoassay results. As noted in the data file available on the OSF, 47 of 348 possible samples returned an undetectable result from the iPro Cube. Importantly, the immunoassay has a lower reported limit of quantitation (LOQ) for salivary cortisol (ELISA immunoassay = 0.19 nmol &#x022c5;L<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> vs. iPro Cube = 0.58 nmol &#x022c5;L<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>; (<xref rid="ref-35" ref-type="bibr">Salimetrics, 2019a</xref>; <xref rid="ref-36" ref-type="bibr">Salimetrics, 2019b</xref>; <xref rid="ref-38" ref-type="bibr">The Soma IgA/Cortisol Test With the SOMA Cube Reader, 0000</xref>). These findings raise concerns regarding the reliability and validity of the iPro Cube to assess salivary cortisol and <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-amylase. <xref rid="ref-13" ref-type="bibr">Fisher, McLellan &#x00026; Sinclair (2015)</xref> have previously reported that the iPro Lab and OFC swab collection method provides valid results compared to ELISA when using both passive drool (<italic>r</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.45) and Salimetrics oral swab (<italic>r</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.52) to collect the sample. Additionally, they identified that the OFC swab and Lab LFD were reliable when assessing duplicate samples (OFC swab duplicates, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.81, ICC=0.89; iPro Lab duplicates, <italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.98, ICC=0.85). However, it is important to bear in the mind the sensitivity of their design (small sample) and relatively weak correlations between methods. The reason for the difference in our findings is unclear as the measurement and analysis techniques were similar, however, the contrast may be related to issues with the manufacturer supplied buffer solution, LFD&#x02019;s, or differences between the performance of the two models of iPro LFD readers.</p><p>Alpha-amylase concentrations were found to increase post-exercise before returning to baseline 30 min post-exercise in the current study. Previous research has suggested that <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-amylase is a sensitive marker of ANS activation as it is produced locally in the salivary glands rather than being a systemic marker (<xref rid="ref-33" ref-type="bibr">Rohleder &#x00026; Nater, 2009</xref>). Our results support the literature in suggesting that <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-amylase is sensitive to changes in stress induced by exercise, even during short-duration exercise efforts at moderate intensity. For example, <xref rid="ref-2" ref-type="bibr">Allgrove et al. (2008)</xref> reported that salivary <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-amylase concentrations were increased while cycling at an intensity as low as 50% V O <sub>2max</sub> for &#x0223c;22 min, and were undifferentiated from concentrations recorded at 75% V O <sub>2max</sub>, or exercise to fatigue during a graded exercise test. Similarly, <xref rid="ref-22" ref-type="bibr">Kunz et al. (2015)</xref> identified that <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-amylase was increased during a cycle for 30 min at &#x02212;5, +5 and +15% of the blood lactate threshold in experienced cyclists, yet the change in concentration was significantly greater in the +15% condition when compared to the &#x02212;5% condition even though concentrations were similar between trials. With this in mind, future research should investigate the sensitivity of <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-amylase to detect changes in exercise intensity, particularly during short duration and low to moderate-intensity efforts.</p><p>This study is the first to report the efficacy of using either of the iPro LFD readers to assess <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-amylase at rest and following moderate-intensity exercise. Importantly, it was identified that the validity of the iPro Cube was poor as it was identified that values obtained did not correlate well with the immunoassay (0.50&#x0003e;r&#x0003c;0.77) or between repeated concurrent samples (0.25&#x0003e;r&#x0003c;0.46). Furthermore, the CV within samples was very high for the POC device. Although there are differences in the way that each method determines <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-amylase, converting both sets of results to enzyme activity using the manufacturer&#x02019;s guidelines should lead to comparable results. The POC unit over-estimated <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-amylase activity by approximately 150%, which generates concern about the analysis process and/or LFD strips and reader. Early testing for <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-amylase with the unit encountered consistent &#x0201c;not a number&#x02014;NAN&#x0201d; error messages, which may relate to the unit measuring what it thought were very high or low concentrations of <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-amylase. In this instance, the manufacturer checked the buffering solutions and calibration (unique to each unit and buffer solution), which reduced the NAN error messages in subsequent trials, but evidently failed to allow an accurate or consistent assessment of <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-amylase by the unit. Importantly, the LOQ for the immunoassay is reported (0.58 nKat &#x022c5;L<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>; (<xref rid="ref-35" ref-type="bibr">Salimetrics, 2019a</xref>; <xref rid="ref-36" ref-type="bibr">Salimetrics, 2019b</xref>), yet we were unable to locate this value for the iPro Cube.</p><p>This study had several limitations that should be considered. First, we did not assess the waking time of our participants; although we presume that participants in the first test group (08:00) should have surpassed the peak of the cortisol awakening response, we cannot guarantee that this didn&#x02019;t impact our initial resting measurement in this group. Second, differences in the collection method may explain some variability in the concentrations of cortisol and <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-amylase. Although the manufacturer has reported that their oral fluid collector recovers &#x0003e;85% of analytes (IgA, cortisol, testosterone and DHEA) in a sample versus passive drool (<xref rid="ref-21" ref-type="bibr">Jehanli, Dunbar &#x00026; Skelhorn, 2011</xref>), this finding is yet to be supported in published, independent research, particularly with <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-amylase. The assessment of salivary markers is commonly completed using ELISA immunoassay, and immunoassay could potentially be considered the laboratory standard for these assessments, yet liquid-chromatography mass spectroscopy (LC-MSMS) is typically considered the gold standard (<xref rid="ref-19" ref-type="bibr">Inder, Dimeski &#x00026; Russell, 2012</xref>). It is likely these techniques would produce similar results, yet future research should look to compare the measures obtained using the iPro, ELISA and LC-MSMS. Additionally, comparisons between the more commonly used iPro Lab and new iPro Cube would be beneficial to determine if the units return similar results.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>We identified that the iPro Cube reader is capable of reporting measures of salivary cortisol that are moderately correlated to values obtained via the typical laboratory method (ELISA immunoassay). However, the unit was shown to underestimate salivary cortisol and overestimate salivary <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-amylase at rest and post-moderate intensity exercise when compared to the common laboratory standard ELISA approach. Collectively, therefore, the current findings provide little support for the utility of the iPro Cube as a tool for measuring salivary cortisol and <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-amylase in the field. As such, researchers, sports scientists, and health professionals are recommended to continue using standard laboratory techniques to assess these salivary stress markers.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="supplemental-information"><title> Supplemental Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="supp-1"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.8366/supp-1</object-id><label>Supplemental Information 1</label><caption><title>Overview of priors employed in Bayesian correlation analysis</title></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-08-8366-s001.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="supp-2"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.8366/supp-2</object-id><label>Supplemental Information 2</label><caption><title>Pre-registration document</title></caption><media xlink:href="peerj-08-8366-s002.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><sec sec-type="additional-information"><title>Additional Information and Declarations</title><fn-group content-type="competing-interests"><title>Competing Interests</title><fn id="conflict-1" fn-type="COI-statement"><p>The authors declare there are no competing interests.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="author-contributions"><title>Author Contributions</title><fn id="contribution-1" fn-type="con"><p><xref ref-type="contrib" rid="author-1">Biao Xiong</xref> conceived and designed the experiments, performed the experiments, analyzed the data, contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools, prepared figures and/or tables, authored or reviewed drafts of the paper, approved the final draft.</p></fn><fn id="contribution-2" fn-type="con"><p><xref ref-type="contrib" rid="author-2">Limei Zhang</xref> analyzed the data, prepared figures and/or tables, approved the final draft.</p></fn><fn id="contribution-3" fn-type="con"><p><xref ref-type="contrib" rid="author-3">Shubin Dong</xref> performed the experiments, contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools, prepared figures and/or tables, approved the final draft.</p></fn><fn id="contribution-4" fn-type="con"><p><xref ref-type="contrib" rid="author-4">Zhixiang Zhang</xref> conceived and designed the experiments, authored or reviewed drafts of the paper, approved the final draft.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="other"><title>Human Ethics</title><fn id="addinfo-1"><p>The following information was supplied relating to ethical approvals (i.e., approving body and any reference numbers):</p><p>The study was approved by Curtin University&#x02019;s Human Ethics Research Committee (HRE2017-0518).</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="other"><title>Data Availability</title><fn id="addinfo-2"><p>The following information was supplied regarding data availability:</p><p>Supporting documentation (e.g., power simulations, data, analysis scripts) is available on the Open Science Framework: Gucciardi, Daniel, Robin Lines, Michael Chapman, Alannah McKay, and Peter Peeling. 2019. &#x0201c;Assessment of Salivary Cortisol and a-Amylase via Point of Care Assessment (iPro).&#x0201d; OSF. November 4. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://osf.io/tshkc/">osf.io/tshkc</ext-link>.</p></fn></fn-group></sec><ref-list content-type="authoryear"><title>References</title><ref id="ref-1"><label>Adam et&#x000a0;al. (2017)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adam</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name><surname>Quinn</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Tavernier</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>McQuillan</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Dahlke</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilbert</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name></person-group><year>2017</year><article-title>Diurnal cortisol slopes and mental and physical health outcomes: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Psychoneuroendocrinology</source><volume>83</volume><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psyneuen.2017.05.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28578301</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-2"><label>Allgrove et&#x000a0;al. (2008)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Allgrove</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomes</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Hough</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gleeson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2008</year><article-title>Effects of exercise intensity on salivary antimicrobial proteins and markers of stress in active men</article-title><source>Journal of Sports Sciences</source><volume>26</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>653</fpage><lpage>661</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/02640410701716790</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18344136</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-3"><label>Asparouhov &#x00026; Muth&#x000e9;n (2010)</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Asparouhov</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Muth&#x000e9;n</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>Bayesian analysis using Mplus: technical implementation</article-title><uri xlink:href="http://www.statmodel.com/download/Bayes3.pdf">http://www.statmodel.com/download/Bayes3.pdf</uri></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-4"><label>Bland &#x00026; Altman (1986)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bland</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group><year>1986</year><article-title>Statistical methods for assessing agreement between two methods of clinical measurement</article-title><source>Lancet</source><volume>1</volume><fpage>307</fpage><lpage>310</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2868172</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-5"><label>Borg (1982)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Borg</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year>1982</year><article-title>Psychophysical bases of perceived exertion</article-title><source>Medicine and Science in Sports and Exercise</source><volume>14</volume><fpage>377</fpage><lpage>381</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1249/00005768-198205000-00012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7154893</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-6"><label>Bosch et&#x000a0;al. (2011)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bosch</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Veerman</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>De&#x000a0;Geus</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Proctor</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title><italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-Amylase as a reliable and convenient measure of sympathetic activity: don&#x02019;t start salivating just yet!</article-title><source>Psychoneuroendocrinology</source><volume>36</volume><fpage>449</fpage><lpage>453</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psyneuen.2010.12.019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21295411</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-7"><label>Clow et&#x000a0;al. (2004)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clow</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Thorn</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hucklebridge</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>The awakening cortisol response: methodological issues and significance</article-title><source>Stress</source><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>29</fpage><lpage>37</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10253890410001667205</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15204030</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-8"><label>Coad, Gray &#x00026; McLellan (2016)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coad</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>McLellan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year>2016</year><article-title>Seasonal analysis of mucosal immunological function and physical demands in professional Australian Rules footballers</article-title><source>International Journal of Sports Physiology and Performance</source><volume>11</volume><fpage>574</fpage><lpage>580</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1123/ijspp.2015-0242</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26389779</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-9"><label>Coad et&#x000a0;al. (2015a)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coad</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Wehbe</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>McLellan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><year>2015a</year><article-title>Physical demands and salivary immunoglobulin a responses of elite Australian Rules football athletes to match play</article-title><source>International Journal of Sports Physiology and Performance</source><volume>10</volume><fpage>613</fpage><lpage>617</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1123/ijspp.2014-0493</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25561572</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-10"><label>Coad et&#x000a0;al. (2015b)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coad</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>McLellan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitehouse</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year>2015b</year><article-title>Validity and reliability of a novel salivary immunoassay for individual profiling in applied sports science</article-title><source>Research in Sports Medicine</source><volume>23</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>140</fpage><lpage>150</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15438627.2015.1005300</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25639912</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-11"><label>Depaoli &#x00026; Van&#x000a0;de Schoot (2017)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Depaoli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Van&#x000a0;de Schoot</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year>2017</year><article-title>Improving transparency and replication in Bayesian statistics: the WAMBS-checklist</article-title><source>Psychological Methods</source><volume>22</volume><fpage>240</fpage><lpage>261</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/met0000065</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26690773</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-12"><label>Engeland, Bosch &#x00026; Rohleder (2019)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Engeland</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Bosch</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rohleder</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><year>2019</year><article-title>Salivary biomarkers in psychoneuroimmunology</article-title><source>Current Opinion in Behavioral Sciences</source><volume>28</volume><fpage>58</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cobeha.2019.01.007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-13"><label>Fisher, McLellan &#x00026; Sinclair (2015)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>McLellan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sinclair</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name></person-group><year>2015</year><article-title>The validity and reliability for a salivary cortisol point of care test</article-title><source>Journal of Athletic Enhancement</source><volume>4</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4172/2324-9080.1000204</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-14"><label>Friedl et&#x000a0;al. (2012)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Friedl</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Knapik</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hakkinen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Baumgartner</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Groeller</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Duarte</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Kyr&#x000f6;l&#x000e4;inen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kraemer</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Nindl</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012</year><article-title>Perspectives on aerobic and strength influences on military physical readiness: report of an international military physiology roundtable</article-title><source>Journal of Strength and Conditioning Research</source><volume>29</volume><fpage>S10</fpage><lpage>S23</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-15"><label>Garde &#x00026; Hansen (2005)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garde</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>&#x000c5;M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Long-term stability of salivary cortisol</article-title><source>Scandinavian Journal of Clinical and Laboratory Investigation</source><volume>65</volume><fpage>433</fpage><lpage>436</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00365510510025773</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16081365</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-16"><label>Gore et&#x000a0;al. (1999)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gore</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Booth</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Bauman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Neville</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>Utility of pwc75% as an estimate of aerobic power in epidemiological and population-based studies</article-title><source>Medicine and Science in Sports and Exercise</source><volume>31</volume><fpage>348</fpage><lpage>351</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00005768-199902000-00020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10063826</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-17"><label>Hayes et&#x000a0;al. (2015)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Grace</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Sculthorpe</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><year>2015</year><article-title>Exercise-induced responses in salivary testosterone, cortisol, and their rations in men: a meta-analysis</article-title><source>Sports Medicine</source><volume>45</volume><fpage>713</fpage><lpage>726</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40279-015-0306-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25655373</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-18"><label>Hellhammer, W&#x000fc;st &#x00026; Kudielka (2009)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hellhammer</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>W&#x000fc;st</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kudielka</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Salivary cortisol as a biomarker in stress research</article-title><source>Psychoneuroendocrinology</source><volume>34</volume><fpage>163</fpage><lpage>171</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psyneuen.2008.10.026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19095358</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-19"><label>Inder, Dimeski &#x00026; Russell (2012)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Inder</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dimeski</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012</year><article-title>Measurement of salivary cortisol in 2012&#x02014;laboratory techniques and clinical indications</article-title><source>Clinical Endocrinology</source><volume>77</volume><fpage>645</fpage><lpage>651</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2265.2012.04508.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22812714</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-20"><label>Jacks et&#x000a0;al. (2002)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jacks</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Sowash</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Anning</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>McGloughlin</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Andres</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Effect of exercise at three exercise intensities on salivary cortisol</article-title><source>Journal of Strength and Conditioning Research</source><volume>16</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>286</fpage><lpage>289</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11991783</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-21"><label>Jehanli, Dunbar &#x00026; Skelhorn (2011)</label><element-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jehanli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunbar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Skelhorn</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>Development and validation of an oral fluid collection device and its use in the immunoassay of salivary steroids and immunoglobins in sports persons</article-title><conf-name>Paper presented at the The International Society of Exercise Immunology Symposium, Oxford, United Kingdom</conf-name><uri xlink:href="http://www.isei.dk/index.php?pageid=21">http://www.isei.dk/index.php?pageid=21</uri></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-22"><label>Kunz et&#x000a0;al. (2015)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kunz</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Bishop</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Spielmann</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Pistillo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ograjsek</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Pierson</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2015</year><article-title>Fitness level impacts salivary antimicrobial protein responses to a single bout of cycling exercise</article-title><source>European Journal of Applied Physiology</source><volume>115</volume><fpage>1015</fpage><lpage>1027</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00421-014-3082-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25557386</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-23"><label>Lee, Kim &#x00026; Choi (2015)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>DY</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group><year>2015</year><article-title>Technical and clinical aspects of cortisol as a biochemical marker of chronic stress</article-title><source>Biochemistry and Molecular Biology Reports</source><volume>48</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>209</fpage><lpage>216</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5483/BMBRep.2015.48.4.275</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-24"><label>Levine et&#x000a0;al. (2007)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zagoory-Sharon</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Feldman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Weller</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Measuring cortisol in human psychobiology studies</article-title><source>Physiology and Behaviour</source><volume>90</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.physbeh.2006.08.025</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-25"><label>MacDonald, Bellinger &#x00026; Minahan (2017)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>MacDonald</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bellinger</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Minahan</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name></person-group><year>2017</year><article-title>Reliability of salivary cortisol and immunoglobulin&#x02014;a measurements from the IPRO<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> before and after sprint cycling exercise</article-title><source>Journal of Sports Medicine and Physical Fitness</source><volume>57</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1680</fpage><lpage>1686</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.23736/S0022-4707.16.06785-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27849116</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-26"><label>Miyashita et&#x000a0;al. (1985)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miyashita</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mutoh</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshioka</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Sadamoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year>1985</year><article-title>PWC75%HRmax: a measure of aerobic work capacity</article-title><source>Sports Medicine</source><volume>2</volume><fpage>159</fpage><lpage>164</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2165/00007256-198502030-00001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3848048</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-27"><label>Muth&#x000e9;n &#x00026; Asparouhov (2012)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muth&#x000e9;n</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name><name><surname>Asparouhov</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012</year><article-title>Bayesian structural equation modelling: a more flexible representation of substantive theory</article-title><source>Psychological Methods</source><volume>17</volume><fpage>313</fpage><lpage>335</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/a0026802</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22962886</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-28"><label>Muth&#x000e9;n &#x00026; Muth&#x000e9;n (1998-2017)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muth&#x000e9;n</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name><surname>Muth&#x000e9;n</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998-2017</year><source>Mplus users guide</source><publisher-name>Muth&#x000e9;n &#x00026; Muth&#x000e9;n</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Los Angeles</publisher-loc><edition designator="8">8th edition</edition></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-29"><label>Muth&#x000e9;n &#x00026; Muth&#x000e9;n (2002)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muth&#x000e9;n</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name><surname>Muth&#x000e9;n</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>How to use a Monte Carlo study to decide on sample size and determine power</article-title><source>Structural Equation Modelling</source><volume>9</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>599</fpage><lpage>620</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1207/S15328007SEM0904_8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-30"><label>Nater &#x00026; Rohleder (2009)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nater</surname><given-names>UM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rohleder</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Salivary alpha-amylase as a non-invasive biomarker for the sympathetic nervous system: current state of research</article-title><source>Psychoneuroendocrinology</source><volume>34</volume><fpage>486</fpage><lpage>496</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psyneuen.2009.01.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19249160</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-31"><label>Norton, Norton &#x00026; Sadgrove (2010)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Norton</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Norton</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sadgrove</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year>2010</year><article-title>Position statement on physical activity and exercise intensity terminology</article-title><source>Journal of Science and Medicine in Sport</source><volume>13</volume><fpage>496</fpage><lpage>502</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsams.2009.09.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20005170</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-32"><label>Papacosta &#x00026; Nassis (2011)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Papacosta</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Nassis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>Saliva as a tool for monitoring steroid, peptide and immune markers in sport and exercise science</article-title><source>Journal of Science and Medicine in Sport</source><volume>14</volume><fpage>424</fpage><lpage>434</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsams.2011.03.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21474377</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-33"><label>Rohleder &#x00026; Nater (2009)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rohleder</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Nater</surname><given-names>UM</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Determinants of salivary a-amylase in humans and methodological considerations</article-title><source>Psychoneuroendocrinology</source><volume>34</volume><fpage>469</fpage><lpage>485</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psyneuen.2008.12.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19155141</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-34"><label>Rutherford-Markwick et&#x000a0;al. (2017)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rutherford-Markwick</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Starck</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Dulson</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year>2017</year><article-title>Salivary diagnostic markers in males and females during rest and exercise</article-title><source>Journal of the International Society of Sports Nutrition</source><volume>14</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>34</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12970-017-0185-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28811748</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-35"><label>Salimetrics (2019a)</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Salimetrics</collab></person-group><year>2019a</year><article-title>Expanded range high sensitivity salivary cortisol enzyme immunoassay kit</article-title><uri xlink:href="https://salimetrics.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/03/salivary-cortisol-elisa-kit.pdf">https://salimetrics.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/03/salivary-cortisol-elisa-kit.pdf</uri></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-36"><label>Salimetrics (2019b)</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Salimetrics</collab></person-group><year>2019b</year><article-title>Salivary <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-amylase kinetic enzyme assay kit</article-title><uri xlink:href="https://salimetrics.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/03/alpha-amylase-saliva-elisa-kit.pdf">https://salimetrics.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/03/alpha-amylase-saliva-elisa-kit.pdf</uri></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-37"><label>Strahler et&#x000a0;al. (2017)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Strahler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Skoluda</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kappert</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Nater</surname><given-names>UM</given-names></name></person-group><year>2017</year><article-title>Simultaneous measurement of salivary cortisol and alpha-amylase: application and recommendations</article-title><source>Neuroscience &#x00026; Biobehavioral Reviews</source><volume>83</volume><fpage>657</fpage><lpage>677</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neubiorev.2017.08.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28864234</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-38"><label>The Soma IgA/Cortisol Test With&#x000a0;the SOMA Cube&#x000a0;Reader (0000)</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>The Soma IgA/Cortisol Test With&#x000a0;the SOMA Cube&#x000a0;Reader</collab></person-group><uri xlink:href="http://somabioscience.com/?page_id=281">http://somabioscience.com/?page_id=281</uri></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-39"><label>Thoma et&#x000a0;al. (2012)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thoma</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirschbaum</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rohleder</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><year>2012</year><article-title>Acute stress responses in salivary alpha-amylase predict increases of plasma norepinephrine</article-title><source>Biological Psychology</source><volume>91</volume><fpage>342</fpage><lpage>348</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopsycho.2012.07.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22954623</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-40"><label>T&#x000f6;rnhage (2009)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>T&#x000f6;rnhage</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2009</year><article-title>Salivary cortisol for assessment of hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal axis function</article-title><source>Neuroimmunomodulation</source><volume>16</volume><fpage>284</fpage><lpage>289</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000216186</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19571589</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-41"><label>VanBruggen et&#x000a0;al. (2011)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>VanBruggen</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Hackney</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>McMurray</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Ondrak</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name></person-group><year>2011</year><article-title>The relationship between serum and salivary cortisol levels in reponse to different intensities of exercise</article-title><source>International Journal of Sports Physiology and Performance</source><volume>6</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>396</fpage><lpage>407</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1123/ijspp.6.3.396</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21911864</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>