<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="case-report"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMJ Case Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMJ Case Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">bmjcr</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bmjcasereports</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMJ Case Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1757-790X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMJ Publishing Group</publisher-name><publisher-loc>BMA House, Tavistock Square, London, WC1H 9JR</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31924705</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6954786</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">bcr-2018-227379</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bcr-2018-227379</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Unusual Association of Diseases/Symptoms</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll"><subject>1506</subject><subject>1526</subject><subject>200</subject><subject>219</subject><subject>508</subject><subject>528</subject></subj-group><series-title>Case report</series-title></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Desquamative interstitial pneumonia in a non-smoker with neurofibromatosis type 1 (Von Recklinghausen syndrome)</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="author-64322273" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Ferrer</surname><given-names>Gustavo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-64192824" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Saleh</surname><given-names>Alwiya Omar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-38530424" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tazelaar</surname><given-names>Henry D</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-22000981" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Arrossi</surname><given-names>Andrea V</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<institution content-type="department">Pulmonary and Critical Care Medicine</institution>, <institution>Aventura Hospital and Medical Center</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Aventura</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Florida</addr-line>, <country>USA</country>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<institution content-type="department">Department of Laboratory Medicine/Pathology, Division of Anatomic Pathology</institution>, <institution>Mayo Clin Arizona</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Scottsdale</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Arizona</addr-line>, <country>USA</country>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<institution content-type="department">Anatomic Pathology</institution>, <institution>Cleveland Clinic Foundation</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">Cleveland</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">Ohio</addr-line>, <country>USA</country>
</aff><author-notes><corresp><label>Correspondence to</label> Dr Gustavo Ferrer; <email>gferrer@icehealthnet.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>9</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>9</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>13</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>e227379</elocation-id><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>26</day><month>12</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; BMJ Publishing Group Limited 2020. Re-use permitted under CC BY-NC. No commercial re-use. See rights and permissions. Published by BMJ.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" start_date="2020-01-09">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed in accordance with the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided the original work is properly cited and the use is non-commercial. See:&#x000a0;<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="bcr-2018-227379.pdf"/><abstract><p>Neurofibromatosis type 1 (NF1) is an autosomal dominant disorder with multiple systemic manifestations. Pulmonary involvement has been reported in the form of interstitial fibrosis, emphysema, pulmonary hypertension and thoracic neoplasm. We report a case of desquamative interstitial pneumonia in a non-smoker with NF1.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>interstitial lung disease</kwd><kwd>neuro genetics</kwd><kwd>tobacco related disease</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>special-feature</meta-name><meta-value>unlocked</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Background</title><p>Neurofibromatosis type 1 (NF1) is an autosomal dominant disorder that occurs in 1 per 3000 individuals, caused by a mutation of the NF1 gene that encodes the protein neurofibromin, which has a role in tumour suppression.<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> Inactivation of the gene leads to loss of function and subsequent development of many different tumours.<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> It is clinically characterised by cutaneous caf&#x000e9;-au-lait spots, freckling, hyperpigmentation, peripheral neurofibromas and iris hamartomas. Pulmonary involvement can occur in the form of interstitial fibrosis, emphysema, pulmonary hypertension and thoracic neoplasm. We report the first case of desquamative interstitial pneumonia (DIP) in a non-smoking patient with NF1.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Case presentation</title><p>A young man, in his early 40s, non-smoker with a history of NF1 presented with a 1-year history of cough and gradually worsening dyspnoea on exertion. His dyspnoea did not respond to inhaled bronchodilators or antibiotics. However, it improved significantly with a week course of prednisone, given for gouty arthritis, but returned once the prednisone was stopped.</p><p>His medical history included oesophageal varices, gastro-oesophageal reflux disease, hypothyroidism, hypertension, gout, cholelithiasis and he had had a splenectomy for an enlarged spleen at the age of 9. He also carried a history of emphysema of unclear origin and spontaneous pneumothorax at the age of 12. The patient worked in information technology and never had environmental exposure to toxic fumes, smoke or dust. Physical examination was notable for diffuse bilateral crackles, multiple cutaneous caf&#x000e9;-au-lait spots, neurofibromas and axillary freckles. There was no clubbing, rashes, ulcerations or arthropathy.</p></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Investigations</title><p>The CT of the chest showed diffuse peripheral ground glass opacities as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">figure 1</xref>. Pulmonary function tests revealed moderate restriction with total lung capacity 4.60&#x02009;L (60% predicted). Diffusing capacity of carbon monoxide was substantially reduced with an absolute value of 13.27&#x02009;mL/min/mm Hg (44% predicted). Alpha-1-antitrypsin was normal and autoimmune markers were all negative. Trans-thoracic echocardiography and right heart catheterisation were normal. The patient desaturated to 92% from 98% on room air after 420 m on a 6&#x02009;min walk test and his dyspnoea went from 2 to 6 on the Borg Scale. Bronchoalveolar lavage (BAL) cytology was markedly hypercellular with increased macrophages. Video-assisted thoracoscopic surgery was performed and lung wedge biopsies were obtained from the left upper and lower lobes. Cultures sent from the BAL did not grow bacteria, fungi or any other microbes.</p><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>CT scan of the chest showing diffuse peripheral ground glass opacities bilaterally.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="bcr-2018-227379f01"/></fig><sec id="s3-1"><title>Pathologic findings</title><p>Both left upper and lower lobe biopsies showed numerous histiocytes within the airspaces and the alveolar interstitium was mildly thickened by chronic inflammatory infiltrates (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">figure 2</xref>) consistent with a diagnosis of DIP. Emphysematous cysts were also present. The pulmonary arteries and veins showed moderate-to severe concentric and eccentric intimal thickening (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">figure 3</xref>).</p><fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Pathology slide of lung biopsy showing numerous histiocytes within the airspaces and the alveolar interstitium was mildly thickened by chronic inflammatory infiltrates.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="bcr-2018-227379f02"/></fig><fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Pathology slide of lung biopsy showing pulmonary arteries and veins with moderate-to-severe concentric and eccentric intimal thickening.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="bcr-2018-227379f03"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Treatment</title><p>Prednisone was restarted at 40&#x02009;mg daily for 1&#x02009;month followed by slow taper over 5 months.</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Outcome and follow-up</title><p>He remained clinically asymptomatic and radiologically stable after 1-year follow-up.</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s6"><title>Discussion</title><p>Interstitial lung disease has been reported in NF1 with an incidence of 5.5%&#x02013;23%.<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2 3</xref> Ground glass opacities, cystic lesions and emphysematous changes are the most common described radiological findings, but the association of these findings to NF1 is controversial since all those reported patients had history of smoking.<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3 4</xref> There are limited data of cases of NF1 with interstitial lung disease documented with tissue biopsy in the literature. The histopathological patterns reported include non-specific interstitial pneumonia (NSIP),<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> chronic eosinophilic pneumonia<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> and DIP.<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> To the best of our knowledge, there have been no reports of DIP-pattern of injury in non-smoker patients with NF1.</p><p>DIP is characterised by diffuse involvement of the lung by numerous histiocytes filling the airspaces with a sheet-like configuration and slight thickening of the alveolar septa. A histopathological pattern that is typical for DIP, commonly associated with smoking, has also been described in autoimmune disorders, after occupational exposures and drugs.<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> The absence of any drug or environmental exposures in the history of this patient argue in favour that his interstitial lung disease with the DIP-pattern is most likely associated with the NF1. Further, increased levels of circulating monocytes and increased expression of inflammatory cytokines are observed in NF1 patients providing evidence of chronic inflammation associated with NF1.<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> The mechanism of DIP in NF1 is unclear but it has been proposed that the connection between NF1 and interstitial lung disease could be linked to a mesenchymal defect in NF1<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref> leading to deposition of collagen. Patients with NF1 have also been noted to have increased levels of nerve growth factor which may have a pro-fibrogenic effect on lung tissue.<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>
</p><p>Pulmonary hypertension has also been described as a complication in patients with NF1, sometimes leading to right ventricular failure and death.<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10&#x02013;12</xref> Neoangiogenesis of the large, medium-sized and small vessel leading to pulmonary vasculopathy with intimal vascular smooth muscle cell (VSMC) proliferation and fibrosis is the possible pathogenic mechanism.<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> In addition to the DIP-pattern, pulmonary hypertensive changes were histologically seen in the biopsy from this patient, but there was no evidence of pulmonary hypertension on right heart catheterisation. Though these vascular changes might be secondary to the presence of interstitial disease, neurofibromin has clearly been established as a critical regulator of endothelial cell (EC), VSMC and bone marrow cell function. Excessive and chronic infiltration of macrophages into the neointima promoting EC senescence and increased VSMC proliferation may explain the endothelial changes found in our patient and the association between NF1 and pulmonary hypertension.<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>
</p><p>In summary, we report the first case of a non-smoker patient with NF1 with interstitial lung disease with DIP-pattern and pulmonary hypertensive vasculopathy.</p><boxed-text id="BX1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><caption><title>Learning points</title></caption><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Interstitial lung disease has been reported in neurofibromatosis type 1 (NF1) with an incidence of 5.5%&#x02013;23%, though in most cases smoking has been a confounding factor in the reported cases.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Pulmonary hypertension has also been described in patients with NF1 and can lead to right ventricular failure.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Histopathological pattern that is typical for desquamative interstitial pneumonia, commonly associated with smoking, has also been described in autoimmune disorders, occupational exposure and drugs.</p></list-item></list></boxed-text></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Contributors:</bold> GF performed substantial contributions to conception and design of the manuscript and has provided final approval of the version to be published. HDT contributed to review and confirmation of the interpretation of pathology results. AOS drafted, revised and submitted the manuscript. AVA performed substantial contributions to interpretation of the pathology results and contributions to the final manuscript.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Funding:</bold> The authors have not declared a specific grant for this research from any funding agency in the public, commercial or not-for-profit sectors.</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Competing interests:</bold> None declared.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Patient consent for publication:</bold> Not required.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Provenance and peer review:</bold> Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Browning</surname><given-names>GGP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nawroz</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Von Recklinghausen's neurofibromatosis: neurofibromatosis type 1</article-title>. <source>The Lancet</source>
<year>2003</year>;<volume>361</volume>:<fpage>1552</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(03)13166-2</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Massaro</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Fibrosing alveolitis: its occurrence, roentgenographic, and pathologic features in von Recklinghausen's neurofibromatosis</article-title>. <source>Am Rev Respir Dis</source>
<year>1966</year>;<volume>93</volume>:<fpage>934</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>42</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/arrd.1966.93.6.934</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4957481</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zamora</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Collard</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wolters</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Neurofibromatosis-Associated lung disease: a case series and literature review</article-title>. <source>Eur Respir J</source>
<year>2007</year>;<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>210</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/09031936.06.00044006</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16870664</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ryu</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Parambil</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McGrann</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Lack of evidence for an association between neurofibromatosis and pulmonary fibrosis</article-title>. <source>Chest</source>
<year>2005</year>;<volume>128</volume>:<fpage>2381</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1378/chest.128.4.2381</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16236898</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Katsenos</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nikolopoulou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rallis</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Chronic eosinophilic pneumonia associated with neurofibromatosis type 1: an unusual complication</article-title>. <source>J Med Invest</source>
<year>2009</year>;<volume>56</volume>:<fpage>64</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2152/jmi.56.64</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19262016</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>De Scheerder</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Elinck</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van Renterghem</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Desquamative interstitial pneumonia and scar cancer of the lung complicating generalised neurofibromatosis</article-title>. <source>Eur J Respir Dis</source>
<year>1984</year>;<volume>65</volume>:<fpage>623</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6440805</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tazelaar</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Churg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Desquamative interstitial pneumonia.</article-title>. <source>Histopathology</source>
<year>2011</year>;<volume>58</volume>:<fpage>509</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>16</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2559.2010.03649.x</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20854463</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lasater</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bessler</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Genetic and cellular evidence of vascular inflammation in neurofibromin-deficient mice and humans</article-title>. <source>J Clin Invest</source>
<year>2010</year>;<volume>120</volume>:<fpage>859</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>70</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI41443</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20160346</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Micera</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vigneti</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pickholtz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Nerve growth factor displays stimulatory effects on human skin and lung fibroblasts, demonstrating a direct role for this factor in tissue repair</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<year>2001</year>;<volume>98</volume>:<fpage>6162</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.101130898</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11344264</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cogan</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Is pulmonary arterial hypertension in neurofibromatosis type 1 secondary to a plexogenic arteriopathy?</article-title>
<source>Chest</source>
<year>2007</year>;<volume>132</volume>:<fpage>798</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>808</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1378/chest.06-3017</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17573495</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Simeoni</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Puccetti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chilosi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Type 1 neurofibromatosis complicated by pulmonary artery hypertension: a case report</article-title>. <source>J Med Invest</source>
<year>2007</year>;<volume>54</volume>:<fpage>354</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2152/jmi.54.354</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17878687</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aoki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kodama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mezaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Von Recklinghausen disease complicated by pulmonary hypertension</article-title>. <source>Chest</source>
<year>2001</year>;<volume>119</volume>:<fpage>1606</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1378/chest.119.5.1606</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11348977</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>