<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Heliyon</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Heliyon</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Heliyon</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2405-8440</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31938752</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6953707</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S2405-8440(20)30022-0</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2020.e03177</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e03177</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Land use/cover and eco-toxicity indices for identifying metal contamination in sediments of drains, Manzala Lake, Egypt</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name><surname>El-Alfy</surname><given-names>Muhammad A.</given-names></name><email>muhammad.elalfy@yahoo.com</email><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#x02217;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name><surname>El-Amier</surname><given-names>Yasser A.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3"><name><surname>El-Eraky</surname><given-names>Toka E.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Marine Pollution Department, National Institute of Oceanography and Fisheries, Alexandria, Egypt</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Botany Department, Faculty of Science, Mansoura University, Egypt</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x02217;</label>Corresponding author. <email>muhammad.elalfy@yahoo.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>09</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>1</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>09</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>e03177</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>10</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>19</day><month>10</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>6</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2020 Published by Elsevier Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder/><license license-type="CC BY-NC-ND" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="abs0010"><p>Six heavy metals in three main drains along the East Nile Delta were estimated to assess the environmental risk and employ land use/cover map of each drain. Composite sediment samples (n = 3) were collected from each drain. The elements were analyzed by Atomic Absorption Spectrophotometer. The order of metal ions in the sediments of three drains of Manzala lake take the following order: Fe &#x0003e; Co &#x0003e; Ni &#x0003e; Cr &#x0003e; Cd &#x0003e; Pb in El-Serw drain, Fe &#x0003e; Ni &#x0003e; Co &#x0003e; Cd &#x0003e; Cr &#x0003e; Pb in Hadous drain and Fe &#x0003e; Cd &#x0003e; Ni &#x0003e; Co &#x0003e; Pb &#x0003e; Cr in Bahr El-Baqar drain. Studied Pollution indices indicate that drains discharged into Manzala Lake are mostly contaminated by metals. Geo-accumulation index showed contamination by Cd in all sites especially in site 13 of Bahr El-Baqar drain and low values to others. The mean probable effect level quotient showed percent of 21% in Hadous and El-Serw drains and 73% probability of being toxic in Bahr El-Baqar drain. The mean effect range median quotient also showed 21% in Hadous and El-Serw to 49% probability of being toxic in Bahr El-Baqar drains. Index of anthropogenicity impact indicate that the man-made activity either agricultural, industrial or fisheries impacted in the appearance of metal ions in the following sequence; Cd &#x0003e; Co &#x0003e; Pb &#x0003e; Ni &#x0003e; Cr. Hazard severity according to hazard quotient and modified hazard quotient of Ni and Cd take the following sequence; El-Serw &#x0003c; Hadous &#x0003c; Bahr El-Baqar drains. For Cr is; Hadous &#x0003c; Bahr El-Baqar &#x0003c; El-Serw and Pb is; Hadous &#x0003c; Elserw &#x0003c; Bahr El-Baqar drains. According to contamination severity index showed low for Pb, Ni and Cr and severe for Co and Cd which take the sequence of; Bahr El-Baqar &#x0003e; El-Serw &#x0003e; Hadous.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="teaser" id="abs0015"><p>Environmental Science; Environmental Analysis; Environmental Assessment; Environmental Hazard; Environmental Health; Metal; Pollution; Toxicity; Hazard; LU/LC</p></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Environmental science</kwd><kwd>Environmental analysis</kwd><kwd>Environmental assessment</kwd><kwd>Environmental hazard</kwd><kwd>Environmental health</kwd><kwd>Metal</kwd><kwd>Pollution</kwd><kwd>Toxicity</kwd><kwd>Hazard</kwd><kwd>LU/LC</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0010">Surface waters are the most important economic resource for humans which provide water for agricultural, industrial and anthropogenic activities (<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">Afed Ullah et&#x000a0;al., 2018</xref>). Evaluating land use and land cover (LU/LC) and water quality relationship is valuable because it will give an idea about freshwater protection which would help us in fulfilling the growing demand of water in various sectors including industrial usage, agricultural consumption, municipal usage, potable water supply, and recreational use. Surface waters have natural sediment and nutrients deposited in them from the land by natural processes. However, as inland uses and land cover changes mostly from human development, land can provide excessive levels of nutrients and sediment to surface waters (<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Banner et&#x000a0;al., 2009</xref>). The sources of water quality pollution not only come from rivers and lakes but also from the land use/cover and the production activities of humans (<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">Qiang et&#x000a0;al., 2016</xref>).</p><p id="p0015">Sediment-associated contaminants especially the heavy metals have the potential to cause direct effects on sediment-dwelling organisms and can indirectly adversely affect a man and other animals at the higher trophic levels. Thus, information on sediment quality conditions is necessary to assess the overall status of aquatic ecosystems (<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">Ogbeibu et&#x000a0;al., 2014</xref>). The problem of high content of heavy metals in soils is related to the latter's geo- and bioaccumulation ability (<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">Oti Wilberforce, 2015</xref>).</p><p id="p0020">Heavy metals are characterized by two main features-the toxic effects on living organisms at relatively low concentrations and bioaccumulative abilities. Being rich in heavy metal sediments, plants and bottom sediments become toxic over time, posing a significant risk to all living organisms. (<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">Osunkiyesi et&#x000a0;al., 2008</xref>). Heavy metal contamination may have devastating effects on the ecological balance of the recipient environment and the diversity of aquatic organisms (<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">Farombi et&#x000a0;al., 2007</xref>). To determine heavy metal contamination in aquatic ecosystems, sediment quality guidelines and background values are widely used in ecological risk assessments (<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">Burton, 2002</xref>).</p><p id="p0025">Heavy metal bioaccumulation in the food chain can be especially highly dangerous to human health. These metals enter the human body mainly through two routes namely: inhalation and ingestion, and with ingestion being the main route of exposure to these elements in the human population (<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">Iheanacho et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>).</p><p id="p0030">In Egypt, the Nile water and coastal lakes (Manzala, Burullus, Idku and Mariut) and other aquatic ecosystems are directly and/or indirectly affected by various anthropogenic activities, due to hosts a number of highly populated cities. The irrigation and drainage system of East Nile Delta is complicated, and there is a large portion of the agricultural drainage water is reused to supplement the shortage of freshwater, which comprises many major drains south to Manzala lake namely El-Serw, Faraskur, El-Matria, Hadous and Bahr El-Baqar drains. After discharge of wastewater without proper care from different sources (industrial, fertilizer and sewage water), HMs accumulates in the sediment. Over time, the concentration of heavy metals in contaminated sediment frequently exceed those required as nutrients or background levels, resulting in uptake by plants and deposition to unacceptable levels. The research focus on three main drains which are El-Serw, Hadous and Bahr El-Baqar drains. The objectives of this search are: (i) the linkage between metal distribution with the LU/LC areas around studied drains, (ii) Identifying metal contamination, accumulation and ecotoxicology of it using different ecological indices, and (iii) Characterization of the environmental status in every studied drain based on studying metal analysis and data treatment using indices for giving interpretation.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><label>2</label><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="sec2.1"><label>2.1</label><title>Study area</title><p id="p0035">The northern Egyptian coastal lagoons (Mariout, Manzala, Idku, Burullus, and Bardawil Lake) are among the most productive natural systems in Egypt and are known globally for their abundant birdlife and fish production. A high level of lake water pollution, due to the industrial, agricultural and sewage wastes poured into the lakes through the drains (<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">El-Shazly et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">El Kafrawy et&#x000a0;al., 2018</xref>). The description of each drain is as shown in <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;1</xref>, georefernced 5 samples were collected from each drain (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;1</xref>). The number of sampling sites is 15.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1"><label>Table&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Description of studied drains.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0060">Table&#x000a0;1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Drain</th><th>Characterization</th><th>Inflow %</th><th>Sampling No</th><th>Ref.</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>El-Serw</td><td>Agriculture drain serves 68,700 feddans (152.8 km<sup>2</sup>).</td><td>13</td><td>1&#x02013;5</td><td rowspan="3"><xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">Zahran et&#x000a0;al., (2015)</xref></td></tr><tr><td>Hadous</td><td>Is the largest drain in the eastern delta, serving some of the agricultural lands of about 1756.96 km<sup>2</sup>.</td><td>49</td><td>6&#x02013;10</td></tr><tr><td>Bahr El-Baqar</td><td>Serves an agricultural area of about 119.2 km<sup>2</sup>, and receives about 300 million m<sup>3</sup>/year of treated and untreated sewage from Cairo.</td><td>25</td><td>11&#x02013;15</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig id="fig1"><label>Figure&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Map shows sampling sites in different drains, south Manzala Lake.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0010">Figure&#x000a0;1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><label>2.2</label><title>Landsat data and remote sensing indexes and GIS application</title><p id="p0040">Landsat image was downloaded from this site (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://earthexplorer.usgs.gov" id="intref0010"><italic>http://earthexplorer.usgs.gov</italic></ext-link>) with path 177 and row 38 of OLI_8 sensor type at the acquisition date of 2018. Clipping the studied areas for each drain was done using ArcGIS. The areas of agriculture, urban, industrial, canals are drawn in Google Earth in KML file then converted in shapefile in ArcGIS program. Normalized different vegetation index (NDVI) and Normalized different water index (NDWI) were measured according to the following Eqs. <xref rid="fd1" ref-type="disp-formula">(1)</xref> and <xref rid="fd2" ref-type="disp-formula">(2)</xref> respectively;<disp-formula id="fd1"><label>(1)</label><mml:math id="M1" altimg="si1.svg" alttext="Equation 1."><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>NDVI</mml:mtext><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>NIR&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>b</mml:mtext><mml:mn>5</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Red&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>b</mml:mtext><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>NIR&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>b</mml:mtext><mml:mn>5</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Red&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>b</mml:mtext><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="fd2"><label>(2)</label><mml:math id="M2" altimg="si2.svg" alttext="Equation 2."><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>NDWI</mml:mtext><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Green&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>b</mml:mtext><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>NIR&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>b</mml:mtext><mml:mn>5</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Green&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>b</mml:mtext><mml:mn>3</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mtext>NIR&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mtext>b</mml:mtext><mml:mn>5</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><label>2.3</label><title>Metal analysis in sediments of drains</title><p id="p0045">A total of 15 sediment samples were taken along three drains south Manzala Lake. Sampling sites were selected to be far between 30 and 40 km (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;1</xref>). In each site, A composite sediment sample consisted of three subsamples obtained using a stainless hand auger. The sediment samples were airdried for several days at room temperature and then ground and sieved using a 2 mm sieve to remove gravel and debris, and stored in plastic bags for subsequent chemical and physical analyses. Soil samples were digested for about two hours in a mixture of nitric acid, perchloric acid and hydrochloric acid as described by <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Oregioni and Astone (1984)</xref>. The studied heavy metals concentrations (&#x003bc;g/g) of Fe, Ni, Co, Cd, Cr and Pb were measured using Atomic Absorption Spectrophotometer (ASS, Buck Scientific Accusys 211).</p></sec><sec id="sec2.4"><label>2.4</label><title>Metal pollution indices in sediment</title><sec id="sec2.4.1"><label>2.4.1</label><title>Potential contamination index (PCI)</title><p id="p0050">The potential contamination index of metal i (PCI<sub>i</sub>) was calculated according to <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">Davaulter and Rognerud (2001)</xref> as the following <xref rid="fd3" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq. (3)</xref>:<disp-formula id="fd3"><label>(3)</label><mml:math id="M3" altimg="si3.svg" alttext="Equation 3."><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>PCI</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>C</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mtext>max</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>C</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>bkg</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>Ci (max): the maximum concentration of metal I in the sediment, C<sub>bkg</sub>: the background concentration of the metal. The contaminated classes according to PCI values are: PCI &#x0003c; 1 indicates low contamination, 1 &#x0003c; PCI &#x0003c; 3 as moderate contamination, and PCI &#x0003e; 3 being considered as severe or very severe contamination.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.4.2"><label>2.4.2</label><title>Geo-accumulation index (Igeo)</title><p id="p0055">Geoaccumulation index (Igeo) was used to define metal contamination in sediments<bold>.</bold> It's calculation is according to <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">Muller (1969)</xref> as <xref rid="fd4" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq. (4)</xref><bold>.</bold><disp-formula id="fd4"><label>(4)</label><mml:math id="M4" altimg="si4.svg" alttext="Equation 4."><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>I</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>geo</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>log</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>C</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>n</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1.5</mml:mn><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>B</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>n</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where C<sub>n</sub> is the measured concentration of the metal n in the sediment, B<sub>n</sub> is the background value for the metal and factor 1.5 is used for possible variations of the background data due to lithological variations.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec2.5"><label>2.5</label><title>Eco-toxicological assessment of heavy metal concentrations</title><sec id="sec2.5.1"><label>2.5.1</label><title>The mean probable effects level quotient (mPEL<sub>Q</sub>)</title><p id="p0060">The mean Probable Effects Level quotient (mPEL<sub>Q</sub>) was calculated to determine the possible biological effect using the formula of <xref rid="fd5" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq. (5)</xref>:<disp-formula id="fd5"><label>(5)</label><mml:math id="M5" altimg="si5.svg" alttext="Equation 5."><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>mPEL</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Q</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>n</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>C</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>PEL</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>n</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where C<sub>i</sub> is the metal concentration i, PEL<sub>i</sub> is the probable effect level value for metal i, and n is the sum of the metals considered. Moreover, the mPEL<sub>Q</sub> is classified into four grades: low degree of contamination (&#x02264;0.1), medium-low degree of contamination (0.11&#x02013;1.5), high-medium degree of contamination (1.51&#x02013;2.3), and high degree of contamination (&#x0003e;2.3), respectively having a 8%, 21%, 49% and 73% probability of being toxic (<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">Carr et&#x000a0;al., 1996</xref>; <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">Long et&#x000a0;al., 2006</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec2.5.2"><label>2.5.2</label><title>The mean effect range median quotient (mERM<sub>Q</sub>)</title><p id="p0065">The mean Effect Range Median quotient (mERM<sub>Q</sub>) was calculated according to the following <xref rid="fd6" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq. (6)</xref>:<disp-formula id="fd6"><label>(6)</label><mml:math id="M6" altimg="si6.svg" alttext="Equation 6."><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>mERM</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Q</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>n</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>C</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>ERM</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>n</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where ERMi is the ERM for metal i. The four levels classification of mERMQ is: low priority site (&#x02264;0.1), medium-low priority site (0.1&#x02013;0.5), high-medium priority site (0.5&#x02013;1.5), and high priority site (&#x0003e;1.5) with a 9%, 21%, 49% and 76% probability of being toxic, respectively (<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">Long et&#x000a0;al., 2000</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec2.5.3"><label>2.5.3</label><title>Contamination severity index (CSI)</title><p id="p0070">CSI is calculated based on Eqs. <xref rid="fd6" ref-type="disp-formula">(6)</xref> and <xref rid="fd7" ref-type="disp-formula">(7)</xref>:<disp-formula id="fd7"><label>(7)</label><mml:math id="M7" altimg="si7.svg" alttext="Equation 7."><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>W</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>L</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>f</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>xE</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>n</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>L</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>f</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>xE</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula><disp-formula id="fd8"><label>(8)</label><mml:math id="M8" altimg="si8.svg" alttext="Equation 8."><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>CSI</mml:mtext><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:munderover><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>w</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:munderover><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>W</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>t</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>C</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>ERL</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">/</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>C</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>ERM</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where W<sub>t</sub> is the weighted value for n number of heavy metals, L<sub>fi</sub> is the factor loading associated with individual metal, E<sub>v</sub> is the eigenvalue, C<sub>i</sub> is the measured concentration of metal in sediment, ERL<sub>i</sub> is the effects range low and ERM<sub>i</sub> is the effects range median. The following tiers are used for CSI values: CSI &#x0003c; 0.5 uncontaminated; 0.5 &#x02264; CSI &#x0003c; 1 very low severity of contamination; 1 &#x02264; CSI &#x0003c; 1.5 low severity; 1.5 &#x02264; CSI &#x0003c; 2 low to moderate; 2 &#x02264; CSI &#x0003c; 2.5 moderate; 2.5 &#x02264; CSI &#x0003c; 3 moderate to high; 3 &#x02264; CSI &#x0003c; 4 high; 4 &#x02264; CSI &#x0003c; 5 very high; and CSI &#x02265; 5 ultra-high severity of contamination.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.5.4"><label>2.5.4</label><title>Hazard quotients (HQ)</title><p id="p0075">HQ is calculated using the <xref rid="fd9" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq. (9)</xref>:<disp-formula id="fd9"><label>(9)</label><mml:math id="M9" altimg="si9.svg" alttext="Equation 9."><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>HQ</mml:mtext><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>C</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>metal</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>SQG</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where, C<sub>metal</sub> is the observed concentration of a metal in sediment and SQG is the sediment quality guideline (<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Urban and Cook, 1986</xref>). The SQG adopted for calculating the HQ in this study was the threshold effects level (TEL) (<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Macdonald et al., 2000</xref>). <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Feng et al. (2011)</xref> indicated another classification to HQ is HQ &#x0003c; 0.1 no adverse effects; 0.1 &#x0003c; HQ &#x0003c; 1 potential hazards; 1 &#x0003c; HQ &#x0003c; 10 moderate hazards; and HQ &#x0003e; 10 high hazards.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.5.5"><label>2.5.5</label><title>Modified hazard quotient</title><p id="p0080">According to the study of <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Benson et&#x000a0;al. (2018)</xref>, who put a basis for the newly heavy metal index to calculate the hazard quotient using metal concentration and threshold limits according to <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Macdonald et&#x000a0;al. (2000)</xref>. This index is as the following <xref rid="fd10" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq. (10)</xref>:<disp-formula id="fd10"><label>(10)</label><mml:math id="M10" altimg="si10.svg" alttext="Equation 10."><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>mHQ</mml:mtext><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">[</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>C</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>TEL</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>PEL</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">+</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>SEL</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>i</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac bevelled="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula></p><p id="p0085">Classification of modified hazard quotient (mHQ) is as follow: mHQ &#x0003e; 3.5 Extreme severity of contamination, 3.0 &#x0003c; mHQ &#x0003c; 3.5 Very high severity of contamination, 2.5 &#x0003c; mHQ &#x0003c; 3.0 High severity of contamination, 2.0 &#x0003c; mHQ &#x0003c; 2.5 Considerable severity of contamination, 1.5 &#x0003c; mHQ &#x0003c; 2.0 Moderate severity of contamination, 1.0 &#x0003c; mHQ &#x0003c; 1.5 Low severity of contamination, 0.5 &#x0003c; mHQ &#x0003c; 1.0 Very low severity of contamination and mHQ &#x0003c; 0.5 Nil to very low severity of contamination.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.5.6"><label>2.5.6</label><title>Anthropogenicity index (Apn%)</title><p id="p0090">It is calculated as the following <xref rid="fd11" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq. (11)</xref>:<disp-formula id="fd11"><label>(11)</label><mml:math id="M11" altimg="si11.svg" alttext="Equation 11."><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Apn&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mtext>%</mml:mtext><mml:mo linebreak="badbreak">=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>&#x003bc;</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>B</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>n</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;x&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mn>100</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>where: &#x003bc;: measured concentration, while B<sub>n</sub> = background value.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec2.6"><label>2.6</label><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="p0095">Mean heavy metals concentrations were subjected to one-way ANOVA (SPSS 16 for Windows) to analyze the correlation between heavy metals in sediments of the three drains. Cluster analyses based on Bray&#x02013;Curtis similarity index and Principle component analysis (PCA) were calculated using the PAST program (multivariate statistical package, ver. 1.72).</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><label>3</label><title>Results and discussion</title><sec id="sec3.1"><label>3.1</label><title>Land use/cover in studied areas</title><p id="p0100">The length of the studied area for each drain ranged between 37, 41.7 and 55.2 km for El-Serw, Hadous and Bahr El-Baqar drains, respectively. According to <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;2</xref>, the areas of agricultural areas represent (89.4, 461 and 239 km<sup>2</sup>); urban areas are (14.2, 8.5 and 11.3 km<sup>2</sup>); Fish farms are (ND, 41.8 and 188.5 km<sup>2</sup>); El-Salam canal (ND, 9.5 and 8.8 km<sup>2</sup>) and River Nile (3.4 km, ND and ND) for El-Serw, Hadous and Bahr El-Baqar drains, respectively.<fig id="fig2"><label>Figure&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Land use map of the three drains (a: El-Serw, b: Hadous and c: Bahr El-Baqar drains) discharged in Manzala Lake, Egypt.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0015">Figure&#x000a0;2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig></p><p id="p0105">Calculating the different indices as NDVI and NDWI using ArcGIS 10.5 aid in identifying the vegetation and water cover areas. Also, the area of urban was calculated. It is obvious that the vegetation cover represents 60, 71 and 39 %. While the water surface areas differ from 35, 27 and 58 % The area of urban areas were 5, 2 and 3% for El-Serw, Hadous and Bahr El-Baqar drains, respectively (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;3</xref>).<fig id="fig3"><label>Figure&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>(I) Land use/cover output to different activities, (np: non-present). (II) Charts represent land use/cover to water, urban and vegetative areas within; A) Elserw B) Hadous and C) Bahr El-Baqar drains.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0020">Figure&#x000a0;3</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr3"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec3.2"><label>3.2</label><title>Environmental assessment of heavy metals in sediments</title><p id="p0110">The order of metal ions in the sediments of three drains of Manzala lake take the following order: Fe &#x0003e; Co &#x0003e; Ni &#x0003e; Cr &#x0003e; Cd &#x0003e; Pb in El-Serw drain, Fe &#x0003e; Ni &#x0003e; Co &#x0003e; Cd &#x0003e; Cr &#x0003e; Pb in Hadous drain and Fe &#x0003e; Cd &#x0003e; Ni &#x0003e; Co &#x0003e; Pb &#x0003e; Cr in Bahr El-Baqar drain. The sequence of metal enrichment and abundance is related to the land use activities around the studied sites. It's obvious that iron is the most enriched in three drains as a normal in earth crust, followed by Co in El-Serw drain, may attributed to using fertilisers in the large agricultural areas in surrounded sites (<xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">Reimann and de Caritat, 1998</xref>), Ni in Hadous drain, as Nickel can end up in surface water when it is a part of wastewater streams and the larger part of Ni compounds that are released to the environment will adsorb to sediment particles and become immobile as a result (<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">Wuana and Okieimen, 2011</xref>) and Cd in Bahr El-Baqar, which characterized by more treated and untreated wastewater that add Cd to the water and sediment of drain. Statistical analysis of p-value showed non significant difference between mean concentrations of metal ions within three drains.</p><p id="p0115">From <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;2</xref>, Co exceeds the limits of <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">European Union (2002)</xref>. While the mean value of Cd in three drains is more than the mentioned limits, but Cr and Pb values are within the limit. The sediment quality guidelines SQGs are important tools for determining the magnitude of sediment pollution associated with a particular heavy metal through comparison of the detected metal concentration in sediment with the correlative reference criteria. The threshold effect level (TEL) and probable effect level (PEL) for some substances with potential environmental risks were applied to facilitate the interpretation of sediment quality (<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Macdonald et&#x000a0;al., 2000</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl2"><label>Table&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Microelement content (mg kg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) of sediment samples from different stations (S1-S15) representing three main drains of Manzala Lake, Egypt.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0065">Table&#x000a0;2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Drains</th><th>Station</th><th>Fe</th><th>Ni</th><th>Co</th><th>Cd</th><th>Cr</th><th>Pb</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="8">El-Serw</td><td>S1</td><td>1599</td><td>14.07</td><td>10.94</td><td>1.07</td><td>4.37</td><td>2.38</td></tr><tr><td>S2</td><td>891</td><td>18.88</td><td>20.97</td><td>8.22</td><td>15.93</td><td>12.85</td></tr><tr><td>S3</td><td>1306</td><td>10.05</td><td>14.17</td><td>9.41</td><td>2.42</td><td>11.62</td></tr><tr><td>S4</td><td>1243</td><td>24.96</td><td>11.44</td><td>12.33</td><td>5.23</td><td>9.18</td></tr><tr><td>S5</td><td>3250</td><td>9.42</td><td>23.45</td><td>16.45</td><td>30.37</td><td>6.71</td></tr><tr><td>Mean</td><td>1657.80</td><td>15.48</td><td>16.19</td><td>9.50</td><td>11.66</td><td>8.55</td></tr><tr><td>PCI</td><td>0.07</td><td>0.37</td><td>1.23</td><td>54.83</td><td>0.34</td><td>0.64</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000b1;SE</td><td>185.00</td><td>1.30</td><td>1.14</td><td>1.14</td><td>2.34</td><td>0.84</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="8">Hadous</td><td>S6</td><td>632</td><td>31.74</td><td>14.77</td><td>13.41</td><td>8.15</td><td>4.71</td></tr><tr><td>S7</td><td>875</td><td>11.3</td><td>19.51</td><td>13.17</td><td>13.63</td><td>4.52</td></tr><tr><td>S8</td><td>4196</td><td>12.62</td><td>8.44</td><td>9.03</td><td>4.92</td><td>6.43</td></tr><tr><td>S9</td><td>722</td><td>22.51</td><td>9.61</td><td>1.35</td><td>6.52</td><td>1.62</td></tr><tr><td>S10</td><td>607</td><td>14.28</td><td>19.64</td><td>12.07</td><td>13.89</td><td>15.33</td></tr><tr><td>Mean</td><td>1406.40</td><td>18.49</td><td>14.39</td><td>9.81</td><td>9.42</td><td>6.52</td></tr><tr><td>PCI</td><td>0.09</td><td>0.47</td><td>1.03</td><td>44.70</td><td>0.00</td><td>0.00</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000b1;SE</td><td>312.59</td><td>1.72</td><td>1.06</td><td>1.01</td><td>0.82</td><td>1.04</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="8">Bahr El-Baqar</td><td>S11</td><td>5934</td><td>9.79</td><td>15.5</td><td>14.02</td><td>2.94</td><td>13.42</td></tr><tr><td>S12</td><td>1691</td><td>27.88</td><td>12.77</td><td>32.54</td><td>5.4</td><td>10.15</td></tr><tr><td>S13</td><td>6013</td><td>6.82</td><td>24.78</td><td>45.66</td><td>34.26</td><td>12.6</td></tr><tr><td>S14</td><td>743</td><td>27.75</td><td>17.43</td><td>10.85</td><td>7.26</td><td>14.63</td></tr><tr><td>S15</td><td>2618</td><td>34.64</td><td>22.17</td><td>5.16</td><td>4.96</td><td>8.94</td></tr><tr><td>Mean</td><td>3399.80</td><td>21.38</td><td>18.53</td><td>21.65</td><td>10.96</td><td>11.95</td></tr><tr><td>PCI</td><td>0.13</td><td>0.51</td><td>1.30</td><td>152.20</td><td>0.00</td><td>0.00</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000b1;SE</td><td>488.27</td><td>2.46</td><td>0.98</td><td>3.38</td><td>2.62</td><td>0.47</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2"><italic>p-Value</italic></td><td>0.19<sup>ns</sup></td><td>0.63<sup>ns</sup></td><td>0.49<sup>ns</sup></td><td>0.17<sup>ns</sup></td><td>0.94<sup>ns</sup></td><td>0.15<sup>ns</sup></td></tr><tr><td colspan="8">Permissible limits worldwide</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">EU (2002)</td><td>-</td><td>75</td><td>11.6</td><td>3</td><td>150</td><td>300</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2"><xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">CSQGD (2007)</xref></td><td>-</td><td>50</td><td>40</td><td>1.4</td><td>64</td><td>70</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">Average Shale</td><td>47200</td><td>68</td><td>19</td><td>0.3</td><td>90</td><td>20</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">Toxic response factor</td><td>-</td><td>5</td><td>5</td><td>30</td><td>2</td><td>5</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>SE: standard error; EU: European Union Standard (2002); (CSQGD): Canadian soil quality guidelines for the protection of environmental and human health document (2007); Average shale, after <xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Turekian and Wedepohl (1961)</xref>; PCI: potential contamination index: ns: non significance.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="p0120">According to the limits of sediment quality guidelines SQGs (<xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;3</xref>), it indicated that 13.33% of samples is lower than ERL, 46.66% of samples is higher than TEL and 100 % of samples are lower than MET, ERM, PEL, SEL, TET and GBC for Ni. For Cd, 86.66, 100, 100, 73.33, 100, 60, 86.66 and 100% of samples are higher than ERL, TEL, MET, CRM, PEL, SEL, TET and GBC. While for Pb and Cr, 100% of samples are lower than used limits of SQGs. It's observed that Cd represent the highly hazard contaminant in this research, Cd in low concentrations can promote the activity of some microorganisms (<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">Shi and Ma, 2017</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl3"><label>Table&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Threshold, mid-range and extreme effects sediment guidelines for selected metals (mg/kg).</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0070">Table&#x000a0;3</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="2">SQG</th><th>Pb</th><th>Cd</th><th>Ni</th><th>Cr</th><th>Ref.</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="2">ERL</td><td>35</td><td>5</td><td>30</td><td>80</td><td rowspan="7"><xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">Macdonald et&#x000a0;al. (2000)</xref></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">TEL</td><td>35</td><td>0.6</td><td>18</td><td>37.3</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">MET</td><td>42</td><td>0.9</td><td>35</td><td>55</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">ERM</td><td>110</td><td>9</td><td>50</td><td>145</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">PEL</td><td>91.3</td><td>3.53</td><td>36</td><td>90</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">SEL</td><td>250</td><td>10</td><td>75</td><td>110</td></tr><tr><td colspan="2">TET</td><td>170</td><td>3</td><td>61</td><td>100</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">GBC</td><td>Shale standard</td><td>20</td><td>0.3</td><td>68</td><td>90</td><td><xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">Turekin and Wedephol, 1961</xref></td></tr><tr><td>Earth Crust</td><td>12.5</td><td>0.15</td><td>75</td><td>100</td><td><xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">Taylor, 1964</xref></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>ERL = effects range low, ERM = effects range median, PEL = probable effect level, TEL = threshold effect level, SEL = severe effect level, MET = minimal effect threshold, TET = toxic effect threshold, GBG = geochemical background.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="p0125">The calculated potential contamination index showed in <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;2</xref> for metal ions of Ni, Co, Cd, Cr and Pb indicated low contamination for Pb, Cr and Ni in three drains, except for Co which give moderate contamination and severe contamination by Cd. This severity of contamination by Co and Cd take the sequence of; Bahr El-Baqar &#x0003e; El-Serw &#x0003e; Hadous.</p><p id="p0130">Geoaccumulation index (Igeo) for measured metals showed unpolluted degree for all metals at all sites except for Cd, that there is accumulation for this metal in the drains. It showed unpolluted to a moderate degree in sites 1 of El-Serw drain and 9 of Hadous, other sites are moderately polluted by Cd except for site 13 of Bahr El-Baqar drain which gives moderately to strong polluted degree of metal accumulation (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;4</xref>). The high level of Cd in sediments of Bahr El-Baqar drain may be attributed to increased rate of non-treatment industrial waste which is discharged. This is agreed with <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">El-Amier et&#x000a0;al. (2018)</xref> who obtained high levels of Cd contamination at Mareotis coast.<fig id="fig4"><label>Figure&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>Average values of Geo-accumulation index (Igeo) of metals in sediments of El-Serw, Hadous and Bahr El-Baqar Drains.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0025">Figure&#x000a0;4</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr4"/></fig></p><p id="p0135"><xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">Hwang et&#x000a0;al. (2009)</xref> stated that contaminant levels in the surface sediments remain relatively constant over a period because toxic chemical input has been leveled and bioturbation mixes the surface sediments. The mean probable effect level quotient (mPELq) ranged between low to medium degree of contamination is Hadous and Elserw drains with 21% probability of being toxic. While in Bahr El-Baqar, it ranged between low to medium in sampling sites of 11, 14 and 15. In sites 12 and 13 showed a high degree of contamination with percent of 73% probability of being toxic. the mean effect range median quotient (mERMq) values as shown in <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;(5)</xref> showed medium-low priority in Elserw and Hadous. It showed high medium priority in Bahr El-Baqar with 49% probability of being toxic.<fig id="fig5"><label>Figure&#x000a0;5</label><caption><p>Values of mean probable effect level quotient (mPELq) and mean The mean effect range median quotient (mERMq) of metals in sediments of El-Serw, Hadous and Bahr El-Baqar Drains.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0030">Figure&#x000a0;5</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr5"/></fig></p><p id="p0140">Contamination severity index (CSI) is a newly proposed index developed by <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Pejman et&#x000a0;al. (2015)</xref> for ecological risk assessment of heavy metal pollution in sediments. According to <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;(6)</xref>, Mean values of CSI in El-Serw showed uncontaminated for Pb and Cr. And showed low severity of contamination for Ni; moderate and high severity for Cd. In Hadous drain, un-contamination level for Pb and Cr, very low severity for Ni and moderate to high for Cd. The order of CSI for Ni and Cd is El-Serw &#x0003c; Hadous &#x0003c; Bahr El-Baqar; for Cr, Hadous and Bahr El-Baqar &#x0003c; El-Serw and for Pb, Hadous &#x0003c; El-Serw &#x0003c; Bahr El-Baqar.<fig id="fig6"><label>Figure&#x000a0;6</label><caption><p>Contamination severity index (CSI) of metals in sediments of El-Serw, Hadous and Bahr El-Baqar drains.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0035">Figure&#x000a0;6</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr6"/></fig></p><p id="p0145">In aquatic ecosystems, the relative toxicities of trace metals to the environment and organisms can be evaluated from the hazard quotients (HQ) values. From <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;(7)</xref>, The hazard quotient HQ for Ni in sampling sites ranged between potential hazard in site 13 to moderate hazard in site 15. For Cd, HQ it varied from the moderate hazard in site 9 to high hazard in site 13. While for Cr, HQ varied from no adverse effect in site 11 to potential hazard in site 15. For Pb, it ranged between no adverse effect in site 9 to potential hazard in site 10.<fig id="fig7"><label>Figure&#x000a0;7</label><caption><p>Hazard quotients and modified hazard quotients (HQs and mHQs) of metals in sediments of El-Serw, Hadous and Bahr El-Baqar drains.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0040">Figure&#x000a0;7</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr7"/></fig></p><p id="p0150">The lowest mHQ of Ni was obtained in sampling site 13 with considerable severity contamination, while the highest mHQ was on site 15 with extreme severity contamination. For Cd, mHQ ranged between moderate severity contamination in sampling site 1 in Elserw drain to extreme severity in Bahr El-Baqar drain. For Cr, mHQ ranged between very low contamination severity in site 3 of Elserw drain to extreme severity contamination in site 13 of Bahr El-Baqar. While mHQ of Pb ranged between very low severity in site 9 of Hadous drain to 3.2 in site 10 of the same drain.</p><p id="p0155">The HQ and mHQ of Ni and Cd take the following sequence; Elserw &#x0003c; Hadous &#x0003c; Bahr El-Baqar drains. But for Cr is; Hadous &#x0003c; Bahr El-Baqar &#x0003c; Elserw and Pb is; Hadous &#x0003c; Elserw &#x0003c; Bahr El-Baqar drains (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;7</xref>). <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">Benson et&#x000a0;al. (2018)</xref> stated the mHQ is reliable and useful pollution tools that can be used to estimate the extent of pollution state, site-specific status and aggregative contamination effects by heavy metals in aquatic ecosystems.</p><p id="p0160">Anthropogenicity (Apn%) measures the effect of the anthropogenic activities on the metal concentrations in a percentage. The anthropogenicity percentage showed as <xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;(8)</xref> that the lowest Apn % for Ni was at site 10 (Hadous drain), while the highest value was obtained at site 13 of Bahr El-Baqar drain. Apn of Co varied between the low value at site 8 (Hadous) and site 13 of Bahr El-Baqar. While Apn of Cd recorded the lowest impact at site 1 of El-Serw drain to site 13 of Bahr El-Baqar drain. Apn for Cr varied in the effectivity of man-made activities between low at site 3 of Elserw and site 13 of Bahr El-Baqar drain. Finally, Pb produced from different activities, the lowest percent appeared in site 9 of Hadous drain and site 11 of Bahr El-Baqar drain. It's obvious that the heavy metal concentrations most influenced by man-made activities in the sediments of the three drains are Cd &#x0003e; Co &#x0003e; Pb &#x0003e; Ni &#x0003e; Cr. So the highest percentage or extent of anthropogenic addition on the environment showed that Cd has the highest percentage, followed by Co may be attributed to the agricultural activities that distributed in high percent as obtained in the land use/cover maps (<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">El-Amier et&#x000a0;al., 2017</xref>). Heavy metals introduced by anthropogenic activities has posed a considerable ecological risk to the biota in terms of the speciation (especially for Cd), and deserved enough attention (<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">Li et&#x000a0;al., 2016</xref>). Recent studies indicate that cadmium poses a serious ecological threat and contributes greatly to the toxicity response rates, as it is even more toxic than arsenic and lead (<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Min et&#x000a0;al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">Zeng and Wu, 2013</xref>).<fig id="fig8"><label>Figure&#x000a0;8</label><caption><p>Anthropogenic percentage (Apn%) for influenced heavy metals of sediments in El-Serw, Hadous and Bahr El-Baqar drains.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0045">Figure&#x000a0;8</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr8"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec3.3"><label>3.3</label><title>Principle component analysis (PCA)</title><p id="p0165">PCA applied for metal ions being measured in this study namely; Fe, Co, Ni, Cd, Cr and Pb. The eigen values of PC1 are considered to be very significant variables that could be associated with potential human-induced sources of the investigated heavy metals. The eigenvalues, therefore, were used in calculating the net ecological contamination index. The first two axes explained nearly 66.49% from data variance as shown in <xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;(9)</xref>. A percent of 47.6 % of data variance explained by axis PC1 and showed a positive correlation between Co, Cd and Pb and sites 2 and 10 of Hadous and El-Serw drains may be attributed to the use of agricultural fertilizers. PC2 explained 18.89 % of data variance and showed positive correlation within Ni and Pb that related to sites 2, 10 (Hadous and El-Serw drains) and sites 14, 15 related to Bahr El-Baqar drain (<xref rid="fig9" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;9</xref>).<fig id="fig9"><label>Figure&#x000a0;9</label><caption><p>Principle component analysis (PCA) of metal ions with different sampling sites distributed at studied three drains.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0050">Figure&#x000a0;9</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr9"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec3.4"><label>3.4</label><title>Cluster analysis (CA) and linkage to LU/LC maps</title><p id="p0170">The similarity analysis as shown in <xref rid="fig10" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;(10)</xref>, indicate relative relations within the land uses and activities obtained from the metal ions analysis. Sampling sites of 3 &#x00026; 4; 11 &#x00026; 13 were similar and 6 &#x00026; 10 of the same drains. With the differentiated distribution of sampling sites also as sites 6, 9, 10 (Hadous drain) are similar with site 14 (Bahr El-Baqar drain), may be attributed to the same use in land cover. As these sites characterized by agricultural activity. Site 2 of Elserw drain and site 7 of Hadous are lies in the same area of Elsalam canal. The affectivity of urban activity also observed in this analysis as site 5 of El-Serw drain and site 15 of Bahr Elbaqar drain were located nearby urban areas in LU/LC maps and may have similar results. <xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">Saleem et&#x000a0;al. (2018)</xref> observed relatively high content of HMs at sites which were adjacent to urban and semi-urban areas. Cd, Cr, Cu, Ni, and Pb indicate their origin mainly from natural sources. Also the impact of the areas immediately adjacent to the reservoirs is marked; moreover, in the case of Ni the number of road and river crossings plays an important role (<xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">Sojka et&#x000a0;al., 2018</xref>).<fig id="fig10"><label>Figure&#x000a0;10</label><caption><p>Cluster analysis or similarity for the different sampling sites based on the results of metal ions.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0055">Figure&#x000a0;10</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr10"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="sec4"><label>4</label><title>Conclusion</title><p id="p0175">The land use/cover maps and metal contamination indices aid in identifying the metal toxicity impacts in the studied drains. Remote sensing and GIS applications calculated the areas of different land uses and coverage. NDVI and NDWI calculated the vegetation and water areas in surrounded areas. Cd was the most contaminant in calculated indices, also Bahr El-Baqar drain enriched by most metals as it carries more different wastewaters either from industrial, fishfarms or agricultural wastes.</p></sec><sec id="sec5"><title>Declarations</title><sec id="sec5.1"><title>Author contribution statement</title><p id="p0180">Muhammad A. El-Alfy, Yasser A. El-Amier, Toka E. El-Eraky: Conceived and designed the experiments; Performed the experiments; Analyzed and interpreted the data; Contributed reagents, materials, analysis tools or data; Wrote the paper.</p></sec><sec id="sec5.2"><title>Funding statement</title><p id="p0185">This research did not receive any specific grant from funding agencies in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p></sec><sec id="sec5.3"><title>Competing interest statement</title><p id="p0190">The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec id="sec5.4"><title>Additional information</title><p id="p0195">No additional information is available for this paper.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Afed Ullah</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Land use impacts on surface water quality by statistical approaches</article-title><source>Global J. Environ. Sci. Manage.</source><volume>4</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>2</fpage><lpage>20</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Banner</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stahl</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dodds</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stream discharge and riparian land use influence in-stream concentrations and loads of phosphorus from central plains watersheds</article-title><source>J. Environ. Manag.</source><volume>44</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>552</fpage><lpage>565</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benson</surname><given-names>N.U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Adedapo</surname><given-names>A.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fred-Ahmadu</surname><given-names>O.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>A.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Essien</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Udosen</surname></name><name><surname>Ayejuyo</surname><given-names>O.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Olajire</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New ecological risk indices for evaluating heavy metals contamination in aquatic sediment: a case study of the Gulf of Guinea</article-title><source>Reg. Stud. Mar. Sci.</source><volume>18</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>44</fpage><lpage>56</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burton</surname><given-names>G.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sediment quality criteria in use around the world</article-title><source>Limnos</source><volume>3</volume><year>2002</year><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>75</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Canadian Soil Quality Guidelines (CSQG)</collab></person-group><chapter-title>Canadian soil quality guidelines (CSQG) for the protection of environmental and human health: summary tables. Updated September, 2007</chapter-title><source>Canadian Environmental Quality Guidelines, 1999, Canadian Council of Ministers of the Environment, Winnipeg.by Canadian Council of Ministers of the Environment (CCME)</source><year>2007</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carr</surname><given-names>R.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>E.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Windom</surname><given-names>H.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>D.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thursby</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sediment quality assessment studies at Tampa Bay, Florida</article-title><source>Environ. Toxicol. Chem.</source><volume>15</volume><year>1996</year><fpage>1218</fpage><lpage>1231</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davaulter</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rognerud</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Heavy metal pollution in sediments of the pasvik river drainage</article-title><source>Chemosphere</source><volume>42</volume><year>2001</year><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>18</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11142923</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>El Kafrawy</surname><given-names>S.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bek</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Negm</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>An overview of the Egyptian northern coastal lakes</chapter-title><source>Egyptian Coastal Lakes and Wetlands: Part I</source><year>2018</year><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Cham</publisher-loc><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>17</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>El-Amier</surname><given-names>Y.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alghanem</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>El-Alfy</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ecological risk assessment of heavy metal pollution in top soil of mediterranean coast: a case study of Mareotis coast, Egypt</article-title><source>Biosci. Res.</source><volume>15</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>2626</fpage><lpage>2639</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>El-Amier</surname><given-names>Y.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Elnaggar</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>El-Alfy</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation and mapping spatial distribution of bottom sediment heavy metal contamination in Burullus Lake, Egypt</article-title><source>Egy. J. Bas. Appl. Sci.</source><volume>4</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>66</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>El-Shazly</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Omar</surname><given-names>W.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Edmardash</surname><given-names>Y.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Elzayat</surname><given-names>E.I.</given-names></name><name><surname>El-Sebeay</surname><given-names>I.I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdel Rahman</surname><given-names>K.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Soliman</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Area reduction and trace element pollution in Nile Delta wetland ecosystems</article-title><source>Afri. J. Eco.</source><volume>55</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>391</fpage><lpage>401</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>European Union</surname></name></person-group><chapter-title>Heavy Metals in Wastes</chapter-title><year>2002</year><publisher-name>European Commission on Environment</publisher-name><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ec.europa.eu/environment/waste/studies/pdf/heavymetalsreport.pdf" id="intref0015">http://ec.europa.eu/environment/waste/studies/pdf/heavymetalsreport.pdf</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Farombi</surname><given-names>E.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Adelowo</surname><given-names>O.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ajimoko</surname><given-names>Y.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biomarkers of oxidative stress and heavy metal levels as indicators of environmental pollution in African Cat fish (Clarias gariepinus ) from Nigeria ogun river</article-title><source>Int. J. Environ. Res. Public Health</source><volume>4</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2007</year><fpage>158</fpage><lpage>165</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17617680</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref38"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>H.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>W.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weinstein</surname><given-names>M.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>L.Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>D.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metal contamination in sediments of the western Bohai Bay and adjacent estuaries</article-title><source>China J. Environ. Manag.</source><volume>92</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>1185</fpage><lpage>1197</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>H.-M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>P.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>T.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Historical trend of trace metals in a sediment core from a contaminated tidal salt marsh in San Francisco Bay</article-title><source>Environ. Geochem. Health</source><volume>31</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>421</fpage><lpage>430</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18679810</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iheanacho</surname><given-names>E.U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ndulaka</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Onuh</surname><given-names>C.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Environmental pollution and heavy metals</article-title><source>Euro. J. Biotech. Biosci.</source><volume>5</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>73</fpage><lpage>78</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chai</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>G.Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Distribution, fraction, and ecological assessment of heavy metals in sediment-plant system in mangrove forest, south China sea</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><volume>11</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>e0147308</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26800267</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>E.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ingersoll</surname><given-names>C.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>MacDonallad</surname><given-names>D.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Calculation and uses of mean sediment quality guideline quotients. Acritical review</article-title><source>Environ. Sci. Technol.</source><volume>40</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>1726</fpage><lpage>1736</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16570590</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>E.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>MacDonallad</surname><given-names>D.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Severn</surname><given-names>C.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>C.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Classifiying probabilities of acute toxicity in marine sediments with empirically derived sediment quality guideline</article-title><source>Environ. Toxicol. Chem.</source><volume>19</volume><year>2000</year><fpage>2598</fpage><lpage>2601</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref19"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Macdonald</surname><given-names>D.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ingersoll</surname><given-names>C.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development and Evaluation of consensus-based sediment quality guidelines for fresh water ecosystems</article-title><source>Arch. Environ. Contam. Toxicol.</source><volume>39</volume><year>2000</year><fpage>20</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10790498</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Min</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chai</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ke</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Environmental availability and ecological risk assessment of heavy metals in zinc leaching residue</article-title><source>Trans. Nonferrous Metals Soc. China</source><volume>23</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>208</fpage><lpage>218</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Index of geo-accumulation in sediments of the rhine river</article-title><source>Geo. J.</source><volume>2</volume><issue>3</issue><year>1969</year><fpage>108</fpage><lpage>118</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref23"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ogbeibu</surname><given-names>A.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Omoigberale</surname><given-names>M.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ezenwa</surname><given-names>I.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eziza</surname><given-names>J.O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Igwe</surname><given-names>J.O.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Using pollution load index and geoaccumulation index for the assessment of heavy metal pollution and sediment quality of the Benin river, Nigeria</article-title><source>Nat. Environ.</source><volume>2</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>9</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref24"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oregioni</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Astone</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>The Determination of Selected Trace Metals in marine Sediments by Flameless/flame-Atomic Absorption Spectrophotometry</chapter-title><year>1984</year><publisher-name>IAEA Monaco Laboratory</publisher-name><comment>Internal Report</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref25"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Osunkiyesi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Taiwo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Olawunmi</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Environmental impact of heavy metal contaminants and micro nutrients in soil samples of metal dumpsites in Abeokuta, Ogunstate, Nigeria</article-title><source>IOSR J. Appl. Chem.</source><volume>7</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2008</year><fpage>52</fpage><lpage>55</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref26"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oti Wilberforce</surname><given-names>J.O.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pollution indices and bioaccumulation factors of heavy metals in selected fruits and vegetables from a derelict mine and their associated health implications</article-title><source>Inte. J. Environ. Sci. Toxic. Res.</source><volume>3</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>15</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref27"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pejman</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bidhendi</surname><given-names>N.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ardestani</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saeedi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baghvand</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A new index for assessing heavy metals contamination in sediments: a case study</article-title><source>Ecol. Indicat.</source><volume>58</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>365</fpage><lpage>373</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref28"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qiang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mei</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dahlgren</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impacts of land use and population density on seasonal surface water quality using a modified geographically weighted regression</article-title><source>Sci. Tot. Environ.</source><volume>572</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>450</fpage><lpage>466</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref39"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reimann</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Caritat</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Chemical Elements in the Environment</chapter-title><year>1998</year><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Berlin</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref29"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saleem</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Iqbal</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Akhter</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>M.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fractionation, bioavailability, contamination and environmental risk of heavy metals in the sediments from a freshwater reservoir, Pakistan</article-title><source>J. Geochem. Explor.</source><volume>184</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>199</fpage><lpage>208</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref30"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of heavy metal Cd pollution on microbial activities in soil</article-title><source>Ann. Agric. Environ. Med.</source><volume>24</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>722</fpage><lpage>725</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29284254</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref31"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sojka</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jasku&#x00142;a</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Siepak</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Heavy metals in bottom sediments of reservoirs in the lowland area of western Poland: concentrations, distribution, sources and ecological risk</article-title><source>Water</source><volume>11</volume><issue>56</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>20</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref32"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>S.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Abundance of chemical elements in the continental crust: anew table</article-title><source>Geochem. Cosmochim. Acta</source><volume>28</volume><issue>8</issue><year>1964</year><fpage>1273</fpage><lpage>1285</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref33"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Turekian</surname><given-names>K.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wedepohl</surname><given-names>K.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Distribution of the elements in some major units of the earth&#x02019;s crust</article-title><source>Geol. Soc. Am. Bull.</source><volume>72</volume><issue>2</issue><year>1961</year><fpage>175</fpage><lpage>192</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref37"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Urban</surname><given-names>D.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>N.J.</given-names></name></person-group><chapter-title>Hazard Evaluation Division Standard Evaluation Procedure; Ecological Risk Assessment</chapter-title><year>1986</year><publisher-name>US Environmental Protection Agency</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc><comment>PP.9-85. EPA-540/-001</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref34"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wuana</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Okieimen</surname><given-names>F.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Heavy metals in contaminated soils: a review of sources, chemistry, risks and best available strategies for remediation</article-title><source>ISRN Ecol.</source><year>2011</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>20</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref35"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zahran</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>El-Amier</surname><given-names>Y.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Elnaggar</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abd El-Azim</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>El-Alfy</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessment and distribution of heavy metals pollutants in Manzala lake, Egypt</article-title><source>J. Geosci. Environ. Prot.</source><volume>3</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>107</fpage><lpage>122</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref36"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Heavy metal pollution of lakes along the mid-lower reaches of the Yangtze River in China: intensity, sources and spatial patterns</article-title><source>Int. J. Environ. Res. Public Health</source><volume>10</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>793</fpage><lpage>807</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23442559</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>