<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="correction"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31923205</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6953843</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0227443</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-19-35216</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Correction</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Correction:&#x000a0;Chl1 DNA helicase and Scc2 function in chromosome condensation through cohesin deposition</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Donglai</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Skibbens</surname><given-names>Robert V.</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>10</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>15</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>e0227443</elocation-id><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2020 Shen, Skibbens</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Shen, Skibbens</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="pone.0227443.pdf"/><related-article related-article-type="corrected-article" id="d35e74" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1371/journal.pone.0188739">
<article-title>Chl1 DNA helicase and Scc2 function in chromosome condensation through cohesin deposition</article-title>
</related-article><counts><fig-count count="4"/><table-count count="0"/><page-count count="5"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><p>The authors would like to provide clarifications and correct errors in Figs <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0227443.g001">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0227443.g002">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0227443.g003">4</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0227443.s001">S1</xref> of the published article [<xref rid="pone.0227443.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>].</p><fig id="pone.0227443.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0227443.g001</object-id><label>Fig 1</label><caption><title>Chl1 helicase promotes rDNA condensation.</title><p>A) Representative examples of micrographs that highlight condensed (loop and line) and decondensed (amorphous puff-like and other non-discrete configuration) rDNA structures. B) Flow cytometer of DNA content at times indicated throughout the experimental procedure. Cells were maintained in nocodazole for 3 hours at 23&#x000b0;C post-alpha factor arrest. C) Chromosome mass and rDNA detected using DAPI in wildtype (YBS1019) and <italic>chl1</italic> mutant (YBS1041) strains. D) Quantification of condensed (loop/line) and decondensed (puff/other) rDNA populations in wildtype and <italic>chl1</italic> mutant cells. Data quantified from 3 biological replicates, 100 cells for each strain analyzed per replicate and statistical analysis performed using Student's T-test (p = 0.005). E) rDNA structures visualized using Net1-GFP, genome DNA detected using DAPI, and cell morphology images obtained using Differential Interference Contrast (DIC) microscopy. Yellow arrows indicate condensed rDNA loop/line and red arrowhead indicates decondensed rDNA puff. F) Quantification of condensed (loop) and decondensed (puff) rDNA populations in wildtype (YBS2020) and <italic>chl1</italic> mutant (YBS2080) cells. Data quantified from 3 biological replicates, 100 cells for each strain analyzed per replicate and statistical analysis performed using Student's T-test (p = 0.006). Statistically significant differences (*) are based on p &#x0003c; 0.05.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0227443.g001"/></fig><fig id="pone.0227443.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0227443.g002</object-id><label>Fig 3</label><caption><title>Chl1 helicase promotes chromosome condensation through cohesin, but not condensin, regulation.</title><p>A) Flow cytometer data of DNA content throughout the experiment. Cells were maintained in nocodazole for 3 hours at 37&#x000b0;C post-alpha factor arrest. B) Fractionation of preanaphase-arrested wildtype (YDS101), <italic>chl1</italic> (YDS104) and <italic>scc2-4</italic> (YDS108) cells. Phosphoglycerate kinase (PGK) and Histone 2B (H2B) indicate levels of cytoplasmic and chromatin-bound proteins, respectively, in whole cell extracts (W), cytoplasmic soluble fractions (S) and chromatin bound fractions (C). C) Left: Titration of Smc2-HA indicates 1X sample concentration is in the linear range of detection. Right: Whole cell extracts of Smc2-HA in wildtype, <italic>chl1</italic> and <italic>scc2-4</italic> cells. H2B is shown as internal loading control. All samples reflect 1X concentration levels. D) Top: Chromatin-bound (CB) fraction of Smc2-HA in wildtype, <italic>chl1</italic> and <italic>scc2-4</italic> cells. Chromatin-bound H2B levels are shown as internal loading control. Bottom: Quantification of Smc2-HA binding to chromatin in <italic>chl1</italic> and <italic>scc2-4</italic> mutant cells, based on the ratio of Smc2-HA to H2B levels and normalized to wildtype levels of Smc2-HA obtained from 3 biological replicates. E) Top: Chromatin-bound fraction of Mcd1 in wildtype, <italic>chl1</italic> and <italic>scc2-4</italic> cells. Chromatin-bound H2B levels are shown as loading controls. Bottom: Quantification of Mcd1 binding to chromatin in <italic>chl1</italic> and <italic>scc2-4</italic> mutant cells, based on the ratio of Mcd1 to H2B levels and normalized to wildtype levels obtained from 3 biological replicates. Statistical analysis was performed using one-way ANOVA followed by post-hoc Tukey HSD Test. (p = 0.024 for chromatin bound Mcd1 in wildtype versus <italic>chl1</italic> mutant cells. p = 0.001 for chromatin bound Mcd1 in wildtype cells versus <italic>scc2-4</italic> mutant cells). Statistically significant differences (*) are based on p &#x0003c; 0.05.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0227443.g002"/></fig><fig id="pone.0227443.g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0227443.g003</object-id><label>Fig 4</label><caption><title>Condensation is irreversible in <italic>scc2-4</italic> mutants.</title><p>A) Flow cytometer data reveals DNA content throughout the experimental analyses. Cells were maintained in nocodazole, post-alpha factor release, for 3 hours at 37&#x000b0;C followed by an additional 1 hour at 23&#x000b0;C. Log phase wildtype and <italic>scc2-4</italic> mutant cells, arrested and then released from a G1 arrest, were used in experiments depicted in both <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0227443.g003">Fig 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0227443.g004">Fig 5</xref>, as such the DNA profiles shown for Log phase and Alpha factor are the same in these two figures. B) Chromosome mass and rDNA structures detected using DAPI in wildtype and <italic>scc2-4</italic> mutant strains. C) Quantification of condensed (loop/line) and decondensed (puff/other) rDNA populations in wildtype (YBS1039) and <italic>scc2-4</italic> mutant (YMM551) cells. Quantifications and statistical analyses of rDNA condensation were obtained from 3 biological replicates for each strain (wildtype and <italic>scc2-4</italic> mutant cells) in which each replicate included 100 cells for each strain. Statistical analyses of condensed populations were performed using one-way ANOVA followed by post-hoc Tukey HSD Test (p = 0.001 for wildtype versus <italic>scc2-4</italic> mutant cell rDNA condensation at 37&#x000b0;C; p = 0.001 for wildtype versus <italic>scc2-4</italic> mutant cell rDNA condensation at 23&#x000b0;C; p = 0.890 for wildtype cell rDNA condensation at 37&#x000b0;C versus 23&#x000b0;C; p = 0.301 for <italic>scc2-4</italic> mutant cell rDNA condensation at 37&#x000b0;C versus 23&#x000b0;C). Statistically significant differences (*) are based on p &#x0003c; 0.05.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0227443.g003"/></fig><fig id="pone.0227443.g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0227443.g004</object-id><label>Fig 5</label><caption><title>Scc2 is dispensable for condensation maintenance during M phase.</title><p>A) Flow cytometer data reveals DNA content throughout the experimental analyses. Cells were maintained in nocodazole, post-alpha factor release, for 3 hours at 23&#x000b0;C followed by an additional 1 hour at 37&#x000b0;C. Log phase wildtype and scc2-4 mutant cells, arrested and then released from a G1 arrest, were used in experiments depicted in both <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0227443.g003">Fig 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0227443.g004">Fig 5</xref>, as such the DNA profiles shown for Log phase and Alpha factor are the same in these two figures. B) Chromosome mass and rDNA structures detected using DAPI in wildtype and <italic>scc2-4</italic> mutant strains. C) Quantification of condensed (loop/line) and decondensed (puff/other) rDNA populations in wildtype (YBS1039) and <italic>scc2-4</italic> mutant (YMM551) cells. Quantifications and statistical analyses of rDNA condensation were obtained from 3 biological replicates for each strain (wildtype and <italic>scc2-4</italic> mutant cells) in which each replicate included 100 cells for each strain. Statistical analyses of condensed populations were performed using one-way ANOVA followed by post-hoc Tukey HSD Test (p = 0.014 for wildtype cell versus <italic>scc2-4</italic> mutant cell rDNA condensation at 23&#x000b0;C; p = 0.804 for wildtype cell versus <italic>scc2-4</italic> mutant cell rDNA condensation at 37&#x000b0;C; p = 0.133 for wildtype cell rDNA condensation at 23&#x000b0;C versus 37&#x000b0;C; p = 0.878 for <italic>scc2-4</italic> mutant cell rDNA condensation at 23&#x000b0;C versus 37&#x000b0;C). Statistically significant differences (*) are based on p &#x0003c; 0.05.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0227443.g004"/></fig><p>The wildtype flow cytometry DNA panels in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0227443.g001">Fig 1B</xref> were previously published in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0227443.s001">S1B Fig</xref> of another article [<xref rid="pone.0227443.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. The authors confirm that original images used are accurate representative examples and belong to the dataset analysed for the <italic>PLOS ONE</italic> study, as both studies used the same repository of cells and treatments, and therefore some data was re-used. A revised <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0227443.g001">Fig 1</xref> is provided here, using replacement images for all panels of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0227443.g001">Fig 1B</xref> from alternative replicates of the same study.</p><p>The <italic>PLOS ONE</italic> study [<xref rid="pone.0227443.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] was carried out using the raw images generated during the previous study [<xref rid="pone.0227443.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]; however, the authors confirm the analyses reported in [<xref rid="pone.0227443.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] are novel and unique.</p><p>In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0227443.g002">Fig 3</xref>, a duplicate of the Alpha factor DNA profile for wildtype cells was incorrectly used for the Alpha factor panel for <italic>chl1</italic> mutant cells. The incorrect panel is replaced in the revised <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0227443.g002">Fig 3</xref> provided here.</p><p>In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0227443.g003">Fig 4</xref>, a duplicate of the 3hr DNA profile for <italic>scc2-4</italic> cells was incorrectly used in the NZ 1hr panel for wildtype cells. The incorrect panel is replaced in the revised <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0227443.g003">Fig 4</xref> provided here.</p><p>In <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0227443.s001">S1D Fig</xref>, a duplicate of the log phase DNA profile for wildtype cells was incorrectly used in the panel for log phase <italic>chl1</italic> mutant cells. The incorrect panel is replaced in the revised <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0227443.s001">S1 Fig</xref> provided here.</p><p>The authors confirm that the above errors occurred in figure assembly and do not affect the analyses or findings of the study. The authors apologize for the errors.</p><p>The legends for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0227443.g003">Fig 4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0227443.g004">Fig 5</xref> are updated to clarify that the Log phase and Alpha factor DNA profiles in Figs <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0227443.g003">4A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0227443.g004">5A</xref> are the same. Additionally, the wildtype yeast strain was incorrectly named YBS1019; this is corrected to YBS1039 in both figure legends. Please see the complete, correct <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0227443.g004">Fig 5</xref> caption here.</p><p>The underlying data for the article is provided on Figshare: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.11412783.v2">https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.11412783.v2</ext-link>.</p><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec001"><title>Supporting information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0227443.s001"><label>S1 Fig</label><caption><title>Cell cycle progression in wildtype and <italic>chl1</italic> mutant.</title><p>A) Morphology quantification for both nocodazole-arrested wildtype and <italic>chl1</italic> mutant cells (N = 100 cells for each strain). B) 1N peak quantification for both wildtype and <italic>chl1</italic> mutant cells arrested in nocodazole for 3 hours at 23&#x000b0;C. C) Flow cytometer data reveals DNA contents in wildtype and <italic>chl1</italic> mutant cells after nocodazole arrest at 23&#x000b0;C for 2.5 hours and 3 hours. D) Flow cytometer data reveals DNA content in wildtype and <italic>chl1</italic> mutant cells analyzed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0227443.g001">Fig 1E and 1F</xref>.</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0227443.s001.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0227443.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Skibbens</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Chl1 DNA helicase and Scc2 function in chromosome condensation through cohesin deposition</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>12</volume>(<issue>11</issue>): <fpage>e0188739</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0188739</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29186203</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0227443.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Skibbens</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name> (<year>2017</year>) <article-title>Temperature-dependent regulation of rDNA condensation in Saccharomyces cerevisiae</article-title>. <source>Cell Cycle</source>
<volume>16</volume>(<issue>11</issue>): Pages <fpage>1118</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1127</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15384101.2017.1317409</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28426272</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>