<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Clin Cardiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Clin Cardiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.1002/(ISSN)1932-8737</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CLC</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Clinical Cardiology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0160-9289</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1932-8737</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Wiley Periodicals, Inc.</publisher-name><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31710764</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6954382</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/clc.23287</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">CLC23287</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Clinical Investigations</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Clinical Investigations</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Impact of immune thrombocytopenic purpura on clinical outcomes in patients with acute myocardial infarction</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="left-running-head">Chehab et al.</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="clc23287-cr-0001" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Chehab</surname><given-names>Omar</given-names></name><degrees>MD, MSc</degrees><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1698-0157</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="clc23287-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="clc23287-note-0001">
<sup>&#x02020;</sup>
</xref><address><email>omar.chehab@wayne.edu</email></address></contrib><contrib id="clc23287-cr-0002" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Abdallah</surname><given-names>Nadine</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="clc23287-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="clc23287-note-0001">
<sup>&#x02020;</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="clc23287-cr-0003" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kanj</surname><given-names>Amjad</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="clc23287-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="clc23287-cr-0004" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pahuja</surname><given-names>Mohit</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="clc23287-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="clc23287-cr-0005" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Adegbala</surname><given-names>Oluwole</given-names></name><degrees>MD, MPH</degrees><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1753-4717</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="clc23287-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="clc23287-cr-0006" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Morsi</surname><given-names>Rami Z.</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="clc23287-aff-0002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="clc23287-cr-0007" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mishra</surname><given-names>Tushar</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="clc23287-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="clc23287-cr-0008" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Afonso</surname><given-names>Luis</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="clc23287-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="clc23287-cr-0009" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Abidov</surname><given-names>Aiden</given-names></name><degrees>MD, PhD</degrees><xref ref-type="aff" rid="clc23287-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="clc23287-aff-0003">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="clc23287-aff-0001">
<label><sup>1</sup></label>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">Department of Internal Medicine</named-content>
<institution>Wayne State University</institution>
<city>Detroit</city>
<named-content content-type="country-part">Michigan</named-content>
</aff><aff id="clc23287-aff-0002">
<label><sup>2</sup></label>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">Department of Internal Medicine</named-content>
<institution>Brigham and Women's Hospital</institution>
<city>Boston</city>
<named-content content-type="country-part">Massachusetts</named-content>
</aff><aff id="clc23287-aff-0003">
<label><sup>3</sup></label>
<named-content content-type="organisation-division">Cardiology Section, Department of Internal Medicine</named-content>
<institution>John D. Dingell VA Medical Center</institution>
<city>Detroit</city>
<named-content content-type="country-part">Michigan</named-content>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="correspondenceTo"><label>*</label><bold>Correspondence</bold><break/>
Omar Chehab, Department of Internal Medicine, Wayne State University, Detroit Medical Center, 3990 John R., Detroit MI 48201.<break/>
Email: <email>omar.chehab@wayne.edu</email><break/></corresp><fn id="clc23287-note-0001"><label>&#x02020;</label><p>Omar Chehab and Nadine Abdallah contributed equally to this study.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>11</day><month>11</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>1</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>43</volume><issue>1</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/clc.v43.1</issue-id><fpage>50</fpage><lpage>59</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>06</day><month>8</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>14</day><month>10</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>10</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><!--<copyright-statement content-type="issue-copyright"> &#x000a9; 2020 Wiley Periodicals, Inc. <copyright-statement>--><copyright-statement content-type="article-copyright">&#x000a9; 2019 The Authors. <italic>Clinical Cardiology</italic> published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc.</copyright-statement><license license-type="creativeCommonsBy"><license-p>This is an open access article under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link> License, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="file:CLC-43-50.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><sec id="clc23287-sec-0001"><title>Background</title><p>Patients with immune thrombocytopenic purpura (ITP) admitted with acute myocardial infarction (AMI) may be challenging to manage given their increased risk of bleeding complications. There is limited evidence in the literature guiding appropriate interventions in this population. The objective of this study is to determine the difference in clinical outcomes in AMI patients with and without ITP.</p></sec><sec id="clc23287-sec-0002"><title>Methods</title><p>Using the United States national inpatient sample database, adults aged &#x02265;18&#x02009;years, who were hospitalized between 2007 and 2014 for AMI, were identified. Among those, patients with ITP were selected. A propensity&#x02010;matched cohort analysis was performed. The primary outcome was in&#x02010;hospital mortality. Secondary outcomes were coronary revascularization procedures, bleeding and cardiovascular complications, and length of stay (LOS).</p></sec><sec id="clc23287-sec-0003"><title>Results</title><p>The propensity&#x02010;matched cohort included 851 ITP and 851 non&#x02010;ITP hospitalizations for AMI. There was no difference in mortality between ITP and non&#x02010;ITP patients with AMI (6% vs7.3%, OR:0.81; 95% CI:0.55&#x02010;1.19; <italic>P</italic> = .3). When compared to non&#x02010;ITP patients, ITP patients with AMI underwent fewer revascularization procedures (40.9% vs 45.9%, OR:0.81; 95% CI:0.67&#x02010;0.98; <italic>P</italic> = .03), but had a higher use of bare metal stents (15.4% vs 11.3%, OR:1.43; 95% CI:1.08&#x02010;1.90; <italic>P</italic> = .01), increased risk of bleeding complications (OR:1.80; CI:1.36&#x02010;2.38; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;.0001) and increased length of hospital stay (6.14 vs 5.4&#x02009;days; mean ratio: 1.14; CI:1.05&#x02010;1.23; <italic>P</italic> = .002). More cardiovascular complications were observed in patients requiring transfusions.</p></sec><sec id="clc23287-sec-0004"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Patients with ITP admitted for AMI had a similar in&#x02010;hospital mortality risk, but a significantly higher risk of bleeding complications and a longer LOS compared to those without ITP. Further studies are needed to assess optimal management strategies of AMI that minimize complications while improving outcomes in this population.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-generated"><kwd id="clc23287-kwd-0001">acute myocardial infarction</kwd><kwd id="clc23287-kwd-0002">bleeding complications</kwd><kwd id="clc23287-kwd-0003">coronary revascularization</kwd><kwd id="clc23287-kwd-0004">immune thrombocytopenic purpura</kwd><kwd id="clc23287-kwd-0005">thrombocytopenia</kwd><kwd id="clc23287-kwd-0006">transfusion</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="2"/><table-count count="2"/><page-count count="10"/><word-count count="6965"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>source-schema-version-number</meta-name><meta-value>2.0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>January 2020</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>details-of-publishers-convertor</meta-name><meta-value>Converter:WILEY_ML3GV2_TO_JATSPMC version:5.7.4 mode:remove_FC converted:11.01.2020</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><p content-type="self-citation">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="clc23287-cit-9001">
<string-name>
<surname>Chehab</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Abdallah</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Kanj</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>Impact of immune thrombocytopenic purpura on clinical outcomes in patients with acute myocardial infarction</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Clin Cardiol</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>43</volume>:<fpage>50</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>59</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/clc.23287</pub-id>
</mixed-citation>
</p></notes></front><body id="clc23287-body-0001"><sec id="clc23287-sec-0005"><label>1</label><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Immune thrombocytopenic purpura (ITP) is an autoimmune hematological disorder where antibodies directed against platelets lead to premature platelet destruction, resulting in low platelet count and increased tendency for mucocutaneous bleeding. It is a relatively rare disease with an incidence of about 10&#x02010;125 cases per million per year.<xref rid="clc23287-bib-0001" ref-type="ref">1</xref>
</p><p>Despite thrombocytopenia, there is an increased risk of thrombotic complications due to the presence of abnormally enlarged immature platelets and increased antibody&#x02010;mediated damage to the endothelium.<xref rid="clc23287-bib-0002" ref-type="ref">2</xref> Additionally, the thrombotic risk is amplified by therapies targeting ITP such as steroids, intravenous immune globulins and rituximab.<xref rid="clc23287-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">3</xref>
</p><p>Patients with ITP are at increased risk of bleeding complications and as such, those presenting with acute myocardial infarction (AMI) requiring revascularization or antiplatelet therapy may be challenging to manage.<xref rid="clc23287-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">4</xref>, <xref rid="clc23287-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">5</xref> The exact incidence of AMI in ITP is not reported in the literature and the topic appears to be mostly addressed in brief reports.<xref rid="clc23287-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">6</xref>, <xref rid="clc23287-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">7</xref>, <xref rid="clc23287-bib-0008" ref-type="ref">8</xref>, <xref rid="clc23287-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">9</xref> Moreover, guidelines on the management of AMI in ITP patients are ambiguous as ITP patients were excluded from the majority of trials addressing therapy of AMI.<xref rid="clc23287-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">6</xref>, <xref rid="clc23287-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">10</xref>
</p><p>Given the low incidence of ITP in the general population, there are no large center studies focusing on the impact of ITP on the outcomes of myocardial ischemia. Herein, we resort to the US&#x02010;based national level inpatient data to study the impact of ITP in patients admitted with AMI on mortality, coronary revascularization therapy, in&#x02010;hospital complications and length of stay.</p></sec><sec id="clc23287-sec-0006"><label>2</label><title>METHODS</title><sec id="clc23287-sec-0007"><label>2.1</label><title>Study design</title><p>The study data was retrieved from the national inpatient sample (NIS), the largest all&#x02010;payer inpatient care database in the United States. The NIS contains discharge&#x02010;level data on more than seven million hospitalizations and approximates a sample of 20% of all US community hospitals. The sampling methodology adopted by the NIS allows the approximation of national estimates by applying weighting variables to the discharges.<xref rid="clc23287-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">11</xref> Hospitalizations within the database provide basic demographic information such as age, gender, and race as well as the international classification of diseases, ninth revision, clinical modification (ICD&#x02010;9&#x02010;CM) coded diagnoses, outcomes, total costs and lengths of hospital stay.<xref rid="clc23287-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">11</xref> Since we used a public database with no reports of patient personal identifying information, this study was deemed exempt by the Institutional Review Board.</p></sec><sec id="clc23287-sec-0008"><label>2.2</label><title>Study population</title><p>Our study population includes patients &#x02265;18&#x02009;years of age, admitted with a primary discharge diagnosis of AMI using the ICD&#x02010;9&#x02010;CM code 410 between 2007 and 2014, with or without ITP. A systematic review of the discharge diagnosis codes for AMI found that the ICD&#x02010;9&#x02010;CM code 410 had a 94% sensitivity and 99% specificity.<xref rid="clc23287-bib-0012" ref-type="ref">12</xref> ITP was identified using the ICD&#x02010;9 code 287.31 as a secondary diagnosis. Specific details of the study population are highlighted in Figure <xref rid="clc23287-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>. Those who were discharged on the same day, transferred between facilities, or with an elective admission, were excluded from the analysis. Those hospitalized with possible secondary causes of ITP such as coagulation disorders and other causes of thrombocytopenia, such as systemic lupus erythematosus, human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), sepsis, malignancies, disseminated intravascular coagulation (DIC), thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura (TTP), and pregnancy were excluded, as highlighted in the study by Danese et al.<xref rid="clc23287-bib-0013" ref-type="ref">13</xref> The ICD&#x02010;9 codes used to identify these conditions are listed in the supplementary file.</p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="clc23287-fig-0001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Flow chart of the study design and cohort selection. Sample size presented. Presence of the international classification of diseases, ninth revision, clinical modification (ICD&#x02010;9&#x02010;CM) codes 287.31 in the secondary diagnosis fields for ITP and clinical classifications software (ICD&#x02010;CCS) 100 for AMI in the primary diagnosis field. AMI, acute myocardial infarction; ITP, immune thrombocytopenic purpura</p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-1" xlink:href="CLC-43-50-g001"/></fig></sec><sec id="clc23287-sec-0009"><label>2.3</label><title>Outcomes</title><p>The primary outcome of interest was in&#x02010;hospital mortality. Secondary outcomes were revascularization therapies (percutaneous coronary intervention, bare metal stents, and drug eluting stents coronary bypass), bleeding (epistaxis, hematoma, gastrointestinal, genitourinary and intracranial bleeds), cardiovascular complications (cardiogenic shock, complete heart block, hemopericardium and cardiac tamponade, and iatrogenic cardiac complications), blood product transfusions and length of hospital stay. We further examined the outcomes in ITP and non&#x02010;ITP hospitalization in the following prespecified subgroups: patients with ST&#x02010;elevation myocardial infarction (STEMI) and patients with non&#x02010;ST&#x02010;elevation myocardial infarction (NSTEMI). Data pertaining to the outcomes were extracted from the NIS database using their corresponding ICD&#x02010;9 codes illustrated in the supplementary index.</p></sec><sec id="clc23287-sec-0010"><label>2.4</label><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>A propensity score matching model was developed to derive two matched groups for comparative outcome analysis, to account for potential confounding factors and reduce the effect of selection bias. We used a multivariable logistic regression model with AMI with ITP as the outcome variable, and all co&#x02010;morbidities in Table <xref rid="clc23287-tbl-0001" ref-type="table">1</xref> and patient&#x02010;level NIS weights as covariates. We used a one&#x02010;to&#x02010;one greedy matching protocol and a caliper width of 0.1 multiplied by the SD of the logit of the propensity score to create a matched cohort that includes matched demographics, comorbidities, and year of admission, between ITP and non&#x02010;ITP hospitalization with AMI.<xref rid="clc23287-bib-0014" ref-type="ref">14</xref>, <xref rid="clc23287-bib-0015" ref-type="ref">15</xref> We first conducted bivariate analyses to compare demographic, clinical and hospital characteristics in AMI admissions with and without ITP. Chi&#x02010;square tests were used for categorical variables and the <italic>t</italic>&#x02010;test for continuous variables with normal distribution. For matched variables, the mean and SD were reported for continuous variables, and percentages were reported for categorical variables. Binary outcomes were modeled with binomial logistic regressions, while discrete numeric variables were modeled with generalized linear model regressions. Subsequently, a stratified analysis was done on those hospitalized with ITP who received transfusions to identify the effect of transfusion on major outcomes in ITP hospitalization. Multivariable logistic regression was performed to identify the predictors of these major outcomes. Variables included in the model were age and sex, in addition to statistically and clinically significant variables derived from univariate analysis. Cumulative in&#x02010;hospital mortality among AMI hospitalization with and without ITP was characterized using a Kaplan&#x02010;Meier plot, with the log&#x02010;rank (Mantel&#x02010;Cox) test used for comparison between the two groups.</p><table-wrap id="clc23287-tbl-0001" xml:lang="en" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Baseline characteristics of acute myocardial infarction hospitalizations with and without immune thrombocytopenic purpura (ITP)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><thead valign="bottom"><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th rowspan="2" style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="1"/><th colspan="3" align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">Acute myocardial infarction (unmatched)</th><th colspan="3" align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">Acute myocardial infarction (matched)</th></tr><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No ITP</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ITP</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>P</italic>&#x02010;value</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No ITP</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ITP</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>P</italic>&#x02010;value</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No. of observations</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x02009;107&#x02009;021</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1002</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">851</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">851</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Demographics</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, mean (SD) (years)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.71&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;14.48</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.11&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;13.34</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;.001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.05&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;13.39</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.45&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;13.26</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.65</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male&#x02014;no. (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">671&#x02009;701 (60.7)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">585 (58.4)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.14</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">501 (58.9)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">496 (58.3)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.81</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Race&#x02014;no. (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:15%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">White</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">704&#x02009;584 (63.6)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">694 (69.3)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">564 (66.3)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">590 (69.3)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.06</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:15%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Black</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90&#x02009;544 (8.2)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53 (5.3)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75 (8.8)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47 (5.5)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:15%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hispanic</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70&#x02009;549 (6.4)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53 (5.3)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63 (7.4)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49 (5.8)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:15%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asians</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20&#x02009;829 (1.9)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (2.7)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (2.4)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (2.4)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CVD Risk Factors&#x02014;no. (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alcohol abuse</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32&#x02009;951 (3)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (2.7)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.6</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (2.9)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (2.7)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.77</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoking</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">395&#x02009;175 (35.7)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">284 (28.7)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;.001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">229 (26.9)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">244 (28.7)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.42</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Obesity</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">137&#x02009;276 (12.4)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">107 (10.7)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.09</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93 (10.9)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93 (10.9)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypertension</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">741&#x02009;137 (66.9)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">679 (67.8)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.58</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">601 (70.6)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">582 (68.4)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.32</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dyslipidemia</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">624&#x02009;713 (56.4)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">524 (52.3)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.008</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">447 (52.5)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">459 (53.9)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.56</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diabetes</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">374&#x02009;859 (339)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">379 (36.9)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.04</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">338 (39.7)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">319 (37.5)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.34</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Comorbidities&#x02014;no. (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hypothyroidism</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">104&#x02009;109 (9.4)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">124 (12.4)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">125 (14.7)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">114 (13.4)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.44</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Congestive heart failure</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x02009;098&#x02009;579 (0.8)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">992 (1)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.39</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (1.3)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (0.9)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.49</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Valvular disease</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2491 (0.2)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (0.4)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.25</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (0.6)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (0.4)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.48</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Atrial Fibrillation</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">175&#x02009;404 (15.8)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">232 (23.2)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;.001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">196 (23)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">205 (24.1)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.61</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Previous history of myocardial infarction</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">113&#x02009;246 (10.2)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">128 (12.8)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.008</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">112 (13.2)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">113 (13.3)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.94</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Previous history of percutaneous coronary intervention</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">131&#x02009;438 (11.9)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">124 (12.4)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.62</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">114 (13.4)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">113 (13.3)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.94</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Previous history of coronary bypass</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80&#x02009;916 (7.3)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">110 (11)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;.001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100 (11.8)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97 (11.4)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.82</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Previous history of pacemaker</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27&#x02009;166 (2.5)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34 (3.4)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.055</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (2.6)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 (3.8)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.17</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Carotid artery disease</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19&#x02009;665 (1.8)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (2.6)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.05</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (3.3)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (2.7)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.48</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Peripheral vascular disease</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">116&#x02009;908 (10.6)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">136 (13.6)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.002</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">107 (12.6)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">123 (14.5)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.26</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Previous history of cerebrovascular disease</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65&#x02009;360 (5.9)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67 (6.7)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.29</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60 (7.1)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62 (7.3)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.85</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chronic pulmonary disease</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">222&#x02009;643 (20.1)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">218 (21.8)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">175 (20.6)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">183 (21.5)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.63</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Liver disease</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12&#x02009;414 (1.1)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54 (5.4)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;.001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44 (5.2)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 (5.9)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.52</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Renal Failure</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">171&#x02009;980 (15.5)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">244 (24.4)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;.001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">230 (27)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">216 (25.4)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.44</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maintenance Dialysis</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29&#x02009;435 (2.7)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51 (5.1)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;.001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48 (5.6)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46 (5.4)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.83</td></tr><tr><td style="padding-left:10%" align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fluid and electrolyte disorders</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">203&#x02009;719 (18.4)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">242 (24.2)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;.001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">201 (23.6)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">211 (24.8)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.57</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Data extraction and analyses were performed with IBM SPSS statistics (Version 25.0 Armonk, NY). All statistical tests were two&#x02010;sided and a <italic>P</italic> value of &#x0003c;.05 was considered statistically significant.</p></sec></sec><sec id="clc23287-sec-0011"><label>3</label><title>RESULTS</title><sec id="clc23287-sec-0012"><label>3.1</label><title>Baseline characteristics and matched cohort</title><p>There were 1&#x02009;258&#x02009;788 hospitalizations with AMI between 2007 and 2014. After excluding patients with secondary causes of ITP, 1108023 hospitalization with AMI were collected and included in the study for analysis. When compared to those without ITP, those hospitalized with ITP were older, more likely to be smokers and had more comorbidities such as hypothyroidism, atrial fibrillation, previous history of liver disease and end stage renal disease and previous history of cardiovascular myocardial infarctions, coronary artery bypass surgeries, and peripheral vascular diseases (Table <xref rid="clc23287-tbl-0001" ref-type="table">1</xref>). After applying propensity matching, we obtained a sample of 1702 patients (851 in each group) with equally matched baseline characteristics (Table <xref rid="clc23287-tbl-0001" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="clc23287-sec-0013"><label>3.2</label><title>Outcomes</title><p>Figure <xref rid="clc23287-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref> summarizes the impact of ITP on the major in&#x02010;patient clinical outcomes of patients with AMI.</p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="clc23287-fig-0002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Bar graph presentation illustrating in&#x02010;hospital outcomes in AMI hospitalizations with and without ITP. AMI, acute myocardial infarction; ITP, immune thrombocytopenic purpura</p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-3" xlink:href="CLC-43-50-g002"/></fig></sec><sec id="clc23287-sec-0014"><label>3.3</label><title>In&#x02010;patient short&#x02010;term mortality</title><p>There was no significant difference between patient with AMI and ITP when compared to those without ITP (6% vs 7.3%, OR:0.81; 95% CI: 0.55&#x02010;1.19; <italic>P</italic> = .3). This is further illustrated in Kaplan&#x02010;Meier curves (Figure <xref rid="clc23287-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1</xref>) showing no difference in cumulative survival between hospitalizations for AMI of patients with and without ITP at different time intervals since admission (<italic>P</italic> = .5 using log&#x02010;rank test). When stratified based on the type of AMI (STEMI or NSTEMI), it was found that there was no difference in short&#x02010;term inpatient mortality between hospitalizations of ITP and non&#x02010;ITP patients for both STEMI (8.6% vs 14.9%, OR:0.54; 95%CI: 0.28&#x02010;1.00; <italic>P</italic> = .05) and NSTEMI (5.3% vs 4.6%, OR:1.15; 95%CI: 0.70&#x02010;1.91; <italic>P</italic> = .6) (Table <xref rid="clc23287-tbl-0002" ref-type="table">2</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="clc23287-tbl-0002" xml:lang="en" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Clinical outcomes of hospitalizations with and without ITP among AMI, STEMI, and NSTEMI</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="left" span="1"/><thead valign="bottom"><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" align="left" rowspan="2" valign="bottom" colspan="1">Patient sample</th><th colspan="4" align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">AMI (N = 1702)</th><th colspan="4" align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">STEMI (N = 409)</th><th colspan="4" align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1">NSTEMI (N = 1293)</th></tr><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No ITP (N = 851)</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ITP (N = 851)</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95%CI)</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>P</italic>&#x02010;value</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No ITP (N = 222)</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ITP (N = 187)</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95%CI)</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>P</italic>&#x02010;value</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No ITP (N = 629)</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ITP (N = 664)</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR (95%CI)</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>P</italic>&#x02010;value</th></tr></thead><tbody valign="top"><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">In&#x02010;patient mortality</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62 (7.3)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51 (6)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81 (0.55&#x02010;1.19)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.3</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (14.9)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (8.6)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54 (0.28&#x02010;1.00)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.05</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (4.6)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (5.3)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.15 (0.70&#x02010;1.91)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Revascularization</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">391 (45.9)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">348 (40.9)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81 (0.67&#x02010;0.98)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.03</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">136 (61.3)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">124 (66.3)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.24 (0.83&#x02010;1.87)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.3</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">255 (40.5)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">224 (33.7)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75 (0.59&#x02010;0.94)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percutaneous coronary intervention</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">323 (38)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">266 (31.3)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74 (0.61&#x02010;0.91)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.004</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">126 (56.8)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">112 (59.9)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14 (0.77&#x02010;1.69)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.5</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">197 (31.3)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">154 (23.2)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.66 (0.52&#x02010;0.85)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bare metal stents</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96 (11.3)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">131 (15.4)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.43 (1.08&#x02010;1.90)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.01</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 (17.1)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58 (31)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.2 (1.37&#x02010;3.47)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.0001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58 (9.2)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73 (11)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.22 (0.85&#x02010;1.75)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drug eluting stents</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">209 (24.6)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">108 (12.7)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45 (0.35&#x02010;0.58)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;.0001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74 (33.3)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43 (23)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59 (0.38&#x02010;0.93)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.02</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">135 (21.5)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65 (9.8)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39 (0.29&#x02010;0.55)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coronary bypass</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75 (8.8)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88 (10.3)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.19 (0.86&#x02010;1.65)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.3</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (6.3)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (8)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3 (0.61&#x02010;2.76)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.5</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61 (9.7)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73 (11)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.15 (0.80&#x02010;1.65)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.45</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">In&#x02010;hospital complications</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">123 (14.5)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">177 (20.8)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.55 (1.21&#x02010;2.00)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (12.2)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 (20.3)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.84 (1.08&#x02010;3.15)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.025</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96 (15.3)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">139 (20.9)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.47 (1.10&#x02010;1.96)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.008</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Use of mechanical circulatory support</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44 (5.2)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33 (3.9)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7 (0.47&#x02010;1.17)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.2</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (12.2)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (9.1)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72 (0.38&#x02010;1.37)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.3</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (2.7)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (2.4)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.9 (0.44&#x02010;1.78)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cardiovascular complications<xref ref-type="fn" rid="clc23287-note-0003">a</xref>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">142 (16.7)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">158 (18.6)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14 (0.89&#x02010;1.46)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.3</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (16.2)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34 (18.2)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.15 (0.69&#x02010;1.92)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.6</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">106 (16.9)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">124 (18.7)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.13 (0.85&#x02010;1.51)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cardiac complications<xref ref-type="fn" rid="clc23287-note-0004">b</xref>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43 (5.1)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44 (5.2)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03 (0.66&#x02010;1.58)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.9</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (6.8)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (6.4)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95 (0.43&#x02010;2.07)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.9</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 (4.5)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32 (4.8)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1 (0.65&#x02010;1.83)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">VTE</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">106 (12.5)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">120 (14.1)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.15 (0.87&#x02010;1.53)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.3</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24 (10.8)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (12.3)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.16 (0.63&#x02010;2.13)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.6</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82 (13)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97 (14.6)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14 (0.83&#x02010;1.57)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acute ischemic stroke</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39 (4.6)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40 (4.7)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03 (0.65&#x02010;1.61)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.9</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (4.5)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (3.2)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.7 (0.25&#x02010;1.97)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.5</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (4.6)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34 (5.1)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1 (0.67&#x02010;1.86)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bleeding complications<xref ref-type="fn" rid="clc23287-note-0005">c</xref>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90 (10.6)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">149 (17.5)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.80 (1.36&#x02010;2.38)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;.0001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (5.9)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (16.6)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.20 (1.62&#x02010;6.31)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;.0001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77 (12.2)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">118 (17.8)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.55 (1.14&#x02010;2.11)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.005</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transfusions<xref ref-type="fn" rid="clc23287-note-0006">d</xref>
</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89 (10.5)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">143 (16.8)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.73 (1.30&#x02010;2.30)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;.0001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (5.9)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (16.6)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.20 (1.62&#x02010;6.31)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;.001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76 (12.1)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">112 (16.9)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.48 (1.08&#x02010;2.02)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.015</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Platelet transfusion</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (0.8)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56 (6.6)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5 (3.85&#x02010;18.75)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;.0001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (0.8)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43 (6.5)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.6 (3.4&#x02010;21.96)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;.001</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (0.9)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (7)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.22 (1.8&#x02010;36.9</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Length of stay average(d)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.40</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.14</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14 (1.05, 1.23)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.002</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.02</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.09</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01 (0.86; 1.20)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.9</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.54</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.44</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.16 (1.06, 1.27)</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot id="clc23287-ntgp-0002"><fn id="clc23287-note-0002"><p>Abbreviations: AMI, acute myocardial infarction; ITP, immune thrombocytopenic purpura; STEMI, non&#x02010;ST&#x02010;elevation myocardial infarction; STEMI, ST&#x02010;elevation myocardial infarction; VTE, venous thromboembolic events.</p></fn><fn id="clc23287-note-0003"><label>a</label><p>Cardiovascular complications included cardiac complications, VTE, and acute ischemic stroke.</p></fn><fn id="clc23287-note-0004"><label>b</label><p>Cardiac complications include cardiogenic shock, complete heart block, pericardial complications such as hemopericardium and cardiac tamponade, and iatrogenic cardiac complications.</p></fn><fn id="clc23287-note-0005"><label>c</label><p>Bleeding complications includes gastrointestinal, genitourinary, and intracranial bleeding, hematomas, epistaxis, and bleeding requiring transfusions.</p></fn><fn id="clc23287-note-0006"><label>d</label><p>Transfusions included patients that either received blood or platelet products.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="clc23287-sec-0015"><label>3.4</label><title>Revascularization therapy</title><p>Compared to those without ITP, those hospitalized with AMI and ITP had fewer coronary revascularizations (40.9% vs 45.9%, OR: 0.81; 95%CI: 0.67&#x02010;0.98; <italic>P</italic> = .03), with less percutaneous coronary interventions (PCI) (31.3% vs 38%, OR: 0.74; CI: 0.61&#x02010;0.91; <italic>P</italic> = .004) and more coronary artery bypass grafting (CABG) (10.3% vs 8.8%, OR: 1.19; 95%CI: 0.861.65; <italic>P</italic> = .3). When analyzing hospitalizations for STEMI and NSTEMI, those who were admitted with ITP and STEMI had similar rates of revascularization with either PCI or CABG compared to non&#x02010;ITP (Table <xref rid="clc23287-tbl-0002" ref-type="table">2</xref>). However, those admitted with NSTEMI and ITP were less likely to undergo PCI (23.2% vs 31.3%, OR: 0.66; 95%CI: 0.52&#x02010;0.85; <italic>P</italic> = .001) compared to those hospitalized with no ITP, but no difference was noted using CABG as a method of revascularization.</p></sec><sec id="clc23287-sec-0016"><label>3.5</label><title>Implantation of bare metal vs drug eluting stent</title><p>Among patients admitted with AMI who had PCI, bare metal stents were used more in patients with ITP (15.4% vs11.3%, OR:1.43;95% CI:1.08&#x02010;1.90; <italic>P</italic> = .01) whereas drug eluting stents were used more in patient with non&#x02010;ITP (12.7% vs 24.6%, OR = 0.45; 95% CI:0.35&#x02010;0.58; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;.0001). The proportion of ITP vs non&#x02010;ITP patients among those who obtained a bare metal stent and those who obtained a drug eluting stent were 55% vs 45% and 32.3% vs 67.7%, respectively (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;.0001). Similar findings were noted in those admitted with STEMI and ITP, in which there was a greater tendency to use of bare metal stents and lesser utilization of drug eluting stents relative to those hospitalized without ITP. On the other hand, no difference was noted in the use of bare metal stents between ITP and non&#x02010;ITP admissions with NSTEMI, although there was a lesser tendency to use drug eluting stents in those admitted with ITP.</p></sec><sec id="clc23287-sec-0017"><label>3.6</label><title>In&#x02010;hospital complications</title><p>Overall, hospitalizations with ITP had a higher risk of in&#x02010;hospital complications (OR: 1.55; CI: 1.21&#x02010;2.00; <italic>P</italic> = .001). Similar rates were observed when stratified based on STEMI (OR: 1.84; 95% CI: 1.08&#x02010;3.15; <italic>P</italic> = .025) and NSTEMI (OR: 1.47; 95% CI:1.10&#x02010;1.96; <italic>P</italic> = .008).</p><sec id="clc23287-sec-0018"><label>3.6.1</label><title>Cardiovascular complications</title><p>Cardiovascular complications included cardiac complications (cardiogenic shock, complete heart block, pericardial complications such as hemopericardium and cardiac tamponade, and iatrogenic cardiac complications), venous thromboembolic events (VTE), and acute ischemic stroke. Similar rates of cardiac, VTE, and acute ischemic strokes were noted among all patients admitted with AMI, STEMI and NSTEMI, irrespective of their ITP status (Table <xref rid="clc23287-tbl-0002" ref-type="table">2</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="clc23287-sec-0019"><label>3.6.2</label><title>Bleeding complications</title><p>Bleeding complications were defined as any reports of gastrointestinal, genitourinary, and intracranial bleeding, hematomas, epistaxis, and bleeding requiring transfusions. Relative to those with no history of ITP, hospitalizations with AMI and ITP had increased risk of bleeding complications (OR:1.80; CI: 1.36&#x02010;2.38; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;.0001) and increased transfusions (OR: 1.73; CI: 1.30&#x02010;2.30; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;.0001). In addition, those admitted with ITP and AMI were more likely to require platelet transfusions compared to non&#x02010;ITP (OR: 8.50; CI: 3.85&#x02010;18.75; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;.0001). Similar findings were noted when stratified by STEMI and NSTEMI (Table <xref rid="clc23287-tbl-0002" ref-type="table">2</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="clc23287-sec-0020"><label>3.7</label><title>Length of hospital stay</title><p>Overall, hospitalizations with ITP had a longer hospital stay compared to non&#x02010;ITP (6.14 vs 5.4&#x02009;days; mean ratio: 1.14; CI: 1.05&#x02010;1.23; <italic>P</italic> = .002) with AMI. When stratified by STEMI and NSTEMI, those with ITP and NSTEMI had a significantly longer mean hospital stay compared to non&#x02010;ITP admissions (6.44 vs 5.54&#x02009;days, <italic>P</italic> = .001), but no difference was noted among STEMI hospitalizations (5.09 vs 5.02&#x02009;days, <italic>P</italic> = .9).</p></sec><sec id="clc23287-sec-0021"><label>3.8</label><title>Transfusion of blood products</title><p>We also explored whether transfusion of blood products (including both platelets and packed red blood cells) were predictors of major adverse events in those admitted with ITP (Table <xref rid="clc23287-supitem-0002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1</xref>). After adjusting for demographic variables and cardiovascular risk comorbidities, those who received transfusions had similar risk of death (OR:1.21; CI: 0.6&#x02010;2.46; <italic>P</italic> = .6), but a higher risk of acute ischemic stroke (OR:4.52; CI: 2.35&#x02010;8.69; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;.0001), VTE (OR:2.62; CI: 1.51&#x02010;4.53; <italic>P</italic> = .001), and cardiac complications (OR:3.06; CI: 1.61&#x02010;5.82; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;.0001) when compared to those who did not receive transfusions. Hospitalizations with ITP and AMI were then stratified based on whether they either received platelet transfusions or packed red blood cells alone. Among those who only received either platelet transfusions or packed red blood cell transfusions, mortality in either group was not found to be significant (Table <xref rid="clc23287-supitem-0002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1</xref>). Those who received platelet transfusions were highly associated with developing an acute ischemic stroke (OR:5.54; CI: 2.55&#x02010;12.03; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;.0001), VTE (OR:3.80; CI:1.88&#x02010;7.68; <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;.0001), and cardiac complications (OR:2.93; CI:1.24&#x02010;6.90; <italic>P</italic> = .01) when compared to those who did not receive platelet transfusions. In addition, among those who received packed red blood cell transfusions, there was a greater association with developing an acute ischemic stroke (OR:2.41; CI: 1.07&#x02010;5.43; <italic>P</italic> = .03) and cardiac complications (OR:2.40; CI:1.11&#x02010;5.18; <italic>P</italic> = .02) but no difference in VTE after adjustment (OR:1.54; CI:0.75&#x02010;3.13; <italic>P</italic> = .2).</p></sec></sec><sec id="clc23287-sec-0022"><label>4</label><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>The findings from this NIS&#x02010;based propensity matched cohort study over the period 2007&#x02010;2014, can be summarized as follows: patients with ITP and AMI were less likely to undergo revascularization, had more bleeding complications and a higher rate of transfusions compared to non&#x02010;ITP patients with AMI. There was no difference in short&#x02010;term inpatient mortality between ITP and non&#x02010;ITP patients with AMI. However, patients with ITP had a longer hospital stay compared to non&#x02010;ITP patients.</p><p>Despite being thrombocytopenic, ITP patients experience both arterial and venous thromboembolic events. Moreover, patients with ITP have been shown to be at increased risk for developing coronary artery disease and thrombosis.<xref rid="clc23287-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">4</xref> The heightened risk has been attributed to the presence of larger and more adhesive platelets, release of thrombotic platelet microparticles (PMP), hypercoagulability induced by steroid and/or IVIG treatment, and antibody&#x02010;mediated attack on endothelial cells caused by cross&#x02010;reactivity.<xref rid="clc23287-bib-0016" ref-type="ref">16</xref>, <xref rid="clc23287-bib-0017" ref-type="ref">17</xref>, <xref rid="clc23287-bib-0018" ref-type="ref">18</xref>, <xref rid="clc23287-bib-0019" ref-type="ref">19</xref> In addition, comorbid conditions in ITP patients may contribute to the added risk. In our study, ITP was associated with a significantly increased risk of diabetes, liver disease, renal failure, peripheral vascular disease, and previous history of myocardial infarction. On the other hand, ITP is associated with an increased risk of bleeding, which poses a challenge for clinicians in the management of ITP patients presenting with AMI. In this study, we observed a lower rate of revascularization in ITP patients compared to non&#x02010;ITP patients with AMI. This difference was due to lower rates of PCI in ITP patients, as there was no significant difference in the rates of CABG between the two groups. Specifically, the rate of PCI was similar in patients with STEMI, but lower in patients with NSTEMI. This finding can be potentially explained by a decreased tendency for clinicians to perform PCI in ITP patients with non&#x02010;emergent indications. Several studies also evaluated the trend in revascularization in patients with AMI, and similar findings were observed. A study by Kolte et al. (2016) highlighted, &#x0201c;revascularization rates were significantly higher in patients with cardiogenic shock versus without cardiogenic shock (72.5% vs. 62.6%, p &#x0003c;0.001) among patients who underwent coronary angiography.&#x0201d;<xref rid="clc23287-bib-0020" ref-type="ref">20</xref> However, in another study by Khera et al. (2015), revascularization rates were similar such that PCI was performed in 68.4% of women and 76.7% of men who experienced STEMI. This latter study primarily looked into patients ranging from 18 to 59&#x02009;years old.<xref rid="clc23287-bib-0021" ref-type="ref">21</xref> Thus, our data reflects a real&#x02010;world situation and the population which is much more heterogeneous compared to myocardial infarction&#x02010;research populations. Moreover, our study found that there is greater tendency to place bare metal stents and lesser tendency to place drug eluting stents in ITP patients with AMI compared to the non&#x02010;ITP patients. These findings were consistent with Ayoub et al, in which they found that patients with a history of chronic thrombocytopenia are more likely to undergo bare metal stentings and less likely to undergo drug eluting stents compared to patients with normal platelet levels.<xref rid="clc23287-bib-0022" ref-type="ref">22</xref> It is likely that physicians prefer the use of bare metal stents in patients with lower platelet levels to avoid longer treatment with dual anti&#x02010;platelet therapy as highlighted in a review by McCarthy et al.<xref rid="clc23287-bib-0023" ref-type="ref">23</xref> However, two new randomized controlled trials have demonstrated the safety and superiority of the use of second&#x02010;generation drug&#x02010;eluting stents compared to bare metal stents in patients with thrombocytopenia during an AMI.<xref rid="clc23287-bib-0023" ref-type="ref">23</xref>, <xref rid="clc23287-bib-0024" ref-type="ref">24</xref>, <xref rid="clc23287-bib-0025" ref-type="ref">25</xref> Currently, there is still limited evidence to guide management of ITP patients along other thrombocytopenic patients who develop AMI, including the preferred revascularization method, and the use of antiplatelets and anticoagulation.<xref rid="clc23287-bib-0023" ref-type="ref">23</xref>, <xref rid="clc23287-bib-0026" ref-type="ref">26</xref>, <xref rid="clc23287-bib-0027" ref-type="ref">27</xref> In addition, major trials such as the TRITON&#x02010;TIMI 38, PLATO, CHAMPION, PHOENIX, and CURE have excluded patients with thrombocytopenia.<xref rid="clc23287-bib-0023" ref-type="ref">23</xref>, <xref rid="clc23287-bib-0028" ref-type="ref">28</xref>, <xref rid="clc23287-bib-0029" ref-type="ref">29</xref>, <xref rid="clc23287-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">30</xref>, <xref rid="clc23287-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">31</xref> In a report by Russo et al, both PCI and CABG were successfully performed in patients with ITP (32 patients with CABG and 15 patients with PCI). However, this was associated with increased bleeding risk compared to the general population. The rate of significant bleeding was 12.5% and 6% in the CABG and PCI groups, respectively.<xref rid="clc23287-bib-0032" ref-type="ref">32</xref> In our study, there was a significantly increased risk of bleeding complications in patients with ITP and STEMI but not in ITP patients with NSTEMI. This may be explained by the higher rate of PCI and stenting in the group with STEMI which requires a more intensive antiplatelet regimen. Despite the higher rate of bleeding complications, there was no significant difference in inpatient mortality between the two groups, which may indicate that bleeding complications were not fatal. However, this only describes in&#x02010;patient/short&#x02010;term mortality. The impact of thrombocytopenia on prognosis after PCI has been studied by several groups, with conflicting results. In an NIS&#x02010;based study by Ayoub et al., PCI in patients with chronic thrombocytopenia was associated with an increased risk of bleeding complications, transfusions, vascular complications, ischemic but not hemorrhagic CVA, and in&#x02010;hospital mortality. However, the increased mortality was not explained by increased bleeding complications alone.<xref rid="clc23287-bib-0022" ref-type="ref">22</xref> In a pooled analysis of patients enrolled in two major clinical trials (ACUITY and HORIZONS&#x02010;AMI), Yadaz et al. found that baseline thrombocytopenia was an independent predictor for major cardiac events and all&#x02010;cause mortality at 1 year in ACS patients who underwent PCI.<xref rid="clc23287-bib-0033" ref-type="ref">33</xref> A pooled analysis of three large Japanese studies by Ito et al, showed that thrombocytopenia was associated with an increase of major bleeding events and all&#x02010;cause mortality during the entire 3&#x02010;year follow up period.<xref rid="clc23287-bib-0034" ref-type="ref">34</xref> On the other hand, a single center retrospective study at Mayo Clinic showed no significant difference in inpatient bleeding and inpatient deaths after PCI in patients with thrombocytopenia and a matched control group, but a significantly higher rate of transfusion in the thrombocytopenia group. Interestingly, there was an increase rate of long&#x02010;term bleeding in thrombocytopenia patients, which was not in excess in the first year where dual antiplatelets are used, compared to subsequent years.<xref rid="clc23287-bib-0035" ref-type="ref">35</xref> It is difficult to derive conclusions from these studies and extrapolate results to patients with ITP, as included patients had heterogenous causes of thrombocytopenia, where the pathophysiology, comorbidities and bleeding risks differ.</p><p>In this study, the length of hospitalization was found to be increased in ITP patients with AMI. Interestingly, this finding was seen in patients with NSTEMI, but not in patients with STEMI. A possible explanation for this is that STEMI patients require urgent revascularization compared to NSTEMI. A cross sectional study by Sugiyama et al, found that patients that underwent urgent PCI had shorter length of hospital stay.<xref rid="clc23287-bib-0036" ref-type="ref">36</xref> In addition, several other studies found that there is increased length of hospital stay with NSTEMI patients which require optimal risk stratification and medical management.<xref rid="clc23287-bib-0037" ref-type="ref">37</xref>, <xref rid="clc23287-bib-0038" ref-type="ref">38</xref> Limited data exist on length of hospital stay in ITP patients but according to Ayoub et al., patients with chronic thrombocytopenia who were admitted for PCI had a significantly longer hospital stay compared to those without thrombocytopenia.<xref rid="clc23287-bib-0022" ref-type="ref">22</xref> This was consistent with our results in ITP patients as bleeding complications and transfusions were higher than the general population and, as such, may contribute to increase length of hospital stay.</p><p>The increased need in transfusion rate observed in our study was consistent with findings by Ayoub et al. and Raphael et al. in patients with ACS and thrombocytopenia.<xref rid="clc23287-bib-0022" ref-type="ref">22</xref>, <xref rid="clc23287-bib-0035" ref-type="ref">35</xref> Although platelet transfusions have been associated with an increased risk of arterial thrombosis and mortality in patients with thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura and heparin&#x02010;induced thrombocytopenia, this finding has not been observed in patients with ITP.<xref rid="clc23287-bib-0039" ref-type="ref">39</xref> In a large meta&#x02010;analysis published on the effect of blood transfusions on patients with AMI, there was a 12% increased risk of mortality in these patients independent of hemoglobin level.<xref rid="clc23287-bib-0040" ref-type="ref">40</xref> On the other hand, a retrospective study on elderly patients with AMI showed an increased 1&#x02010;year mortality in those who received blood when hemoglobin was &#x0003e;10 g/dL but a 50% reduction in 1&#x02010;year mortality when hemoglobin was &#x0003c;8 g/dL.<xref rid="clc23287-bib-0041" ref-type="ref">41</xref> In our study, there was no difference in mortality among ITP patients admitted for AMI who had received either blood or platelet transfusions. Yet those patients had a significantly higher number of cardiovascular complications. It is not possible to determine if these complications preceded the transfusions. Patients with indications for blood product transfusion are generally at an advanced disease state and at risk for cardiovascular complications.<xref rid="clc23287-bib-0042" ref-type="ref">42</xref> To our knowledge, our study is the first to report an association between blood products transfusion in patients with ITP admitted for AMI and cardiovascular complications. This signifies future studies to look at transfusion and hemoglobin levels as part of a risk model in predicting cardiovascular outcomes.</p><p>Several limitations to this study need to be acknowledged. The NIS is a de&#x02010;identified administrative database and thus, it would not be possible to validate individual ICD&#x02010;9 codes. This could potentially have impacted our analysis, nevertheless, the same ICD&#x02010;9 codes were used through the entire study period. Furthermore, this database does not provide information on the severity of thrombocytopenia as this may have had an important prognostic effect on the study outcomes. In addition, no data on therapy (anticoagulation, antiplatelets, etc.) was available. Also, no reports were available for vascular access during PCI as undergoing coronary catheterization during femoral artery is associated with higher risk of bleeding complications.<xref rid="clc23287-bib-0043" ref-type="ref">43</xref> Since the study is cross sectional in the nature, establishment of causality was not possible.</p><p>Reverse causality is however less likely as the studied outcomes are not known to cause ITP. Finally, since the database relies heavily on reported diagnoses, our study is at high risk for misclassification bias. Misclassification in this case is more likely to be nondifferential, drawing the study results toward the null hypothesis. These limitations were compounded by a large sample size of an underrepresented population along with the use of propensity&#x02010;matched cohorts which significantly reduced the risk of both selection and confounding bias.</p></sec><sec id="clc23287-sec-0023"><label>5</label><title>CONCLUSION</title><p>Despite no difference in in&#x02010;hospital mortality between ITP and non&#x02010;ITP patients admitted for AMI, those with ITP were more likely to have bleeding complications and require a longer hospital stay. Bare metal stents were more likely to be utilized in ITP patients than drug eluting stents. Moreover, ITP patients who required transfusions were found to have a higher frequency of cardiovascular complications. This reflects the need for evidence&#x02010;based guidelines to standardize the management of patients with ITP and other thrombocytopenic disorders presenting with AMI, assess the best revascularization strategy, platelet cutoff for interventions, antiplatelet choice and duration, and perioperative strategies to minimize complications and improve outcomes in this under&#x02010;represented population.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="clc23287-sec-0025"><title>CONFLICT OF INTEREST</title><p>The authors declare no potential conflict of interests.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supporting information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="clc23287-supitem-0001"><caption><p>
<bold>Figure S1</bold> Comparison of in&#x02010;hospital mortality in AMI hospitalizations with and without ITP. Kaplan&#x02010;Meier curves showing difference between cumulative in&#x02010;hospital survival for both groups at different time interval since admission (<italic>P</italic> = 0.5 using log&#x02010;rank test).</p></caption><media xlink:href="CLC-43-50-s001.jpg"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="clc23287-supitem-0002"><caption><p>
<bold>Supplementary Table 1:</bold> Patients with ITP admitted with AMI stratified based by transfusion status</p><p>
<bold>Supplementary Table 2:</bold> Diagnosis Codes</p><p>
<bold>Supplementary Table 3:</bold> ICD&#x02010;9 codes for in&#x02010;hospital outcomes</p></caption><media xlink:href="CLC-43-50-s002.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="clc23287-sec-0024"><title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENT</title><p>We verify that each author had a role in analyzing the data and in writing the manuscript.</p></ack><ref-list id="clc23287-bibl-0001" content-type="cited-references"><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="clc23287-bib-0001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="clc23287-cit-0001">
<string-name>
<surname>Neskovic</surname>
<given-names>AN</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Stankovic</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Milicevic</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>Primary PCI for acute myocardial infarction in a patient with idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura. A case report and review of the literature</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Herz</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>43</fpage>&#x02010;<lpage>49</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20140789</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="clc23287-bib-0002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="clc23287-cit-0002">
<string-name>
<surname>Sert</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Ozdil</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Sunbul</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Acute myocardial infarction due to Eltrombopag therapy in a patient with immune thrombocytopenic purpura</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">J Turkish Soc Haematol</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>34</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>107</fpage>&#x02010;<lpage>108</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="clc23287-bib-0003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="clc23287-cit-0003">
<string-name>
<surname>Torbey</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Yacoub</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>McCord</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Lafferty</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Two cases and review of the literature: primary percutaneous angiography and antiplatelet management in patients with immune thrombocytopenic purpura</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">ISRN Hematol</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>2013</volume>:<fpage>4</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="clc23287-bib-0004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="clc23287-cit-0004">
<string-name>
<surname>Feudjo&#x02010;Tepie</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Le Roux</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Beach</surname>
<given-names>KJ</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Bennett</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Robinson</surname>
<given-names>NJ</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Comorbidities of idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura: a population&#x02010;based study</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Adv Hematol</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>2009</volume>:<fpage>963506</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19960044</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="clc23287-bib-0005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="clc23287-cit-0005">
<string-name>
<surname>Arnold</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Bleeding complications in immune thrombocytopenia</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Hematology Am Soc Hematol Educ Program</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>2015</volume>:<fpage>237</fpage>&#x02010;<lpage>242</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26637728</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="clc23287-bib-0006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="clc23287-cit-0006">
<string-name>
<surname>Li&#x02010;Sha</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Peng</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Yue&#x02010;Chun</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Recurrent acute coronary syndrome and restenosis after percutaneous coronary intervention in a patient with idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura: a case report and literature review</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">BMC Cardiovasc Disord</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>101</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26385102</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="clc23287-bib-0007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="clc23287-cit-0007">
<string-name>
<surname>Tasaki</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Yamada</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Nabeshima</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>An autopsy case of myocardial infarction due to idiopathic thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Diagn Pathol</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>52</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26022055</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="clc23287-bib-0008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="clc23287-cit-0008">
<string-name>
<surname>Kikuchi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Niimi</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Yamamoto</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Hasegawa</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Banno</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Nitta</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Acute myocardial infarction with idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura in an elderly patient</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Nihon Ronen Igakkai Zasshi</source>. <year>1996</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>867</fpage>&#x02010;<lpage>870</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8997108</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="clc23287-bib-0009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="clc23287-cit-0009">
<string-name>
<surname>Yagmur</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Cansel</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Acikgoz</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>Multivessel coronary thrombosis in a patient with idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Tex Heart Inst J</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>881</fpage>&#x02010;<lpage>883</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23304046</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="clc23287-bib-0010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="clc23287-cit-0010">
<string-name>
<surname>Fujino</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Niwa</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Fujioka</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>Primary percutaneous coronary intervention by a stentless technique for acute myocardial infarction with idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura: a case report and review of the literature</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Inter Med (Tokyo, Japan)</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>55</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>147</fpage>&#x02010;<lpage>152</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="clc23287-bib-0011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="miscellaneous" id="clc23287-cit-0011">
<article-title>(HCUP) HCaUP. Agency for healthcare research and quality, Rockville, MD. 2019</article-title>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="clc23287-bib-0012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="clc23287-cit-0012">
<string-name>
<surname>Metcalfe</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Neudam</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Forde</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>Case definitions for acute myocardial infarction in administrative databases and their impact on in&#x02010;hospital mortality rates</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Health Serv Res</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>48</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>290</fpage>&#x02010;<lpage>318</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22742621</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="clc23287-bib-0013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="clc23287-cit-0013">
<string-name>
<surname>Danese</surname>
<given-names>MD</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Lindquist</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Gleeson</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Deuson</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Mikhael</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Cost and mortality associated with hospitalizations in patients with immune thrombocytopenic purpura</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Am J Hematol</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>84</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>631</fpage>&#x02010;<lpage>635</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19705429</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="clc23287-bib-0014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="clc23287-cit-0014">
<string-name>
<surname>Haukoos</surname>
<given-names>JS</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Lewis</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>The propensity score</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">JAMA</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>314</volume>(<issue>15</issue>):<fpage>1637</fpage>&#x02010;<lpage>1638</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26501539</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="clc23287-bib-0015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="clc23287-cit-0015">
<string-name>
<surname>Dugoff</surname>
<given-names>EH</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Schuler</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Stuart</surname>
<given-names>EA</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Generalizing observational study results: applying propensity score methods to complex surveys</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Health Serv Res</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>49</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>284</fpage>&#x02010;<lpage>303</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23855598</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="clc23287-bib-0016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="clc23287-cit-0016">
<string-name>
<surname>Jy</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Horstman</surname>
<given-names>LL</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Arce</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Ahn</surname>
<given-names>YS</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Clinical significance of platelet microparticles in autoimmune thrombocytopenias</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">J Lab Clin Med</source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>119</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>334</fpage>&#x02010;<lpage>345</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1583382</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="clc23287-bib-0017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="clc23287-cit-0017">
<string-name>
<surname>Crouch</surname>
<given-names>ED</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Watson</surname>
<given-names>LE</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Intravenous immunoglobulin&#x02010;related acute coronary syndrome and coronary angiography in idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura&#x02013;a case report and literature review</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Angiology</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>53</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>113</fpage>&#x02010;<lpage>117</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11863304</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="clc23287-bib-0018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="clc23287-cit-0018">
<string-name>
<surname>Paolini</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Fabris</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Cella</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Acute myocardial infarction during treatment with intravenous immunoglobulin for idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura (ITP)</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Am J Hematol</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>65</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>177</fpage>&#x02010;<lpage>178</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10996840</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="clc23287-bib-0019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="clc23287-cit-0019">
<string-name>
<surname>Shen</surname>
<given-names>FNT</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Bajwa</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Recurrent acute myocardial infarction in patients with immune thrombocytopenic purpura</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">J Patient&#x02010;Center Res Rev</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>1</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>41</fpage>&#x02010;<lpage>45</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="clc23287-bib-0020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="clc23287-cit-0020">
<string-name>
<surname>Kolte</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Khera</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Dabhadkar</surname>
<given-names>KC</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>Trends in coronary angiography, revascularization, and outcomes of cardiogenic shock complicating non&#x02010;ST&#x02010;elevation myocardial infarction</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Am J Cardiol</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>117</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02010;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26541908</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="clc23287-bib-0021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="clc23287-cit-0021">
<string-name>
<surname>Khera</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Kolte</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Gupta</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>Temporal trends and sex differences in revascularization and outcomes of ST&#x02010;segment elevation myocardial infarction in younger adults in the United States</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">J Am Coll Cardiol</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>66</volume>(<issue>18</issue>):<fpage>1961</fpage>&#x02010;<lpage>1972</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26515998</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="clc23287-bib-0022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="clc23287-cit-0022">
<string-name>
<surname>Ayoub</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Marji</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Ogunbayo</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>Impact of chronic thrombocytopenia on in&#x02010;hospital outcomes after percutaneous coronary intervention</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">JACC Cardiovasc Interv</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>18</issue>):<fpage>1862</fpage>&#x02010;<lpage>1868</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30172792</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="clc23287-bib-0023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="clc23287-cit-0023">
<string-name>
<surname>McCarthy</surname>
<given-names>CP</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Steg</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Bhatt</surname>
<given-names>DL</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>The management of antiplatelet therapy in acute coronary syndrome patients with thrombocytopenia: a clinical conundrum</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Eur Heart J</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>47</issue>):<fpage>3488</fpage>&#x02010;<lpage>3492</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29020292</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="clc23287-bib-0024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="clc23287-cit-0024">
<string-name>
<surname>Valgimigli</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Patialiakas</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Thury</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>Zotarolimus&#x02010;eluting versus bare&#x02010;metal stents in uncertain drug&#x02010;eluting stent candidates</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">J Am Coll Cardiol</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>65</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>805</fpage>&#x02010;<lpage>815</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25720624</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="clc23287-bib-0025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="clc23287-cit-0025">
<string-name>
<surname>Urban</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Meredith</surname>
<given-names>IT</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Abizaid</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>Polymer&#x02010;free drug&#x02010;coated coronary stents in patients at high bleeding risk</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">N Engl J Med</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>373</volume>(<issue>21</issue>):<fpage>2038</fpage>&#x02010;<lpage>2047</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26466021</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="clc23287-bib-0026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="clc23287-cit-0026">
<string-name>
<surname>Ibanez</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>James</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Agewall</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>2017 ESC guidelines for the management of acute myocardial infarction in patients presenting with ST&#x02010;segment elevation: the task force for the management of acute myocardial infarction in patients presenting with ST&#x02010;segment elevation of the European Society of Cardiology (ESC)</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Eur Heart J</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>119</fpage>&#x02010;<lpage>177</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28886621</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="clc23287-bib-0027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="clc23287-cit-0027">
<string-name>
<surname>Levine</surname>
<given-names>GN</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Bates</surname>
<given-names>ER</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Bittl</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>ACC/AHA guideline focused update on duration of dual antiplatelet therapy in patients with coronary artery disease: a report of the American College of Cardiology/American heart association task force on clinical practice guidelines: an update of the 2011 ACCF/AHA/SCAI guideline for percutaneous coronary intervention, 2011 ACCF/AHA guideline for coronary artery bypass graft surgery, 2012 ACC/AHA/ACP/AATS/PCNA/SCAI/STS guideline for the diagnosis and management of patients with stable ischemic heart disease, 2013 ACCF/AHA guideline for the management of ST&#x02010;elevation myocardial infarction, 2014 AHA/ACC guideline for the management of patients with non&#x02010;ST&#x02010;elevation acute coronary syndromes, and 2014 ACC/AHA guideline on perioperative cardiovascular evaluation and management of patients undergoing noncardiac surgery</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Circulation</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>134</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>e123</fpage>&#x02010;<lpage>e155</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27026020</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="clc23287-bib-0028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="clc23287-cit-0028">
<string-name>
<surname>Wiviott</surname>
<given-names>SD</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Braunwald</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>McCabe</surname>
<given-names>CH</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>Prasugrel versus clopidogrel in patients with acute coronary syndromes</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">N Engl J Med</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>357</volume>(<issue>20</issue>):<fpage>2001</fpage>&#x02010;<lpage>2015</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17982182</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="clc23287-bib-0029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="clc23287-cit-0029">
<string-name>
<surname>James</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Akerblom</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Cannon</surname>
<given-names>CP</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>Comparison of ticagrelor, the first reversible oral P2Y(12) receptor antagonist, with clopidogrel in patients with acute coronary syndromes: rationale, design, and baseline characteristics of the PLATelet inhibition and patient outcomes (PLATO) trial</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Am Heart J</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>157</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>599</fpage>&#x02010;<lpage>605</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19332184</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="clc23287-bib-0030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="clc23287-cit-0030">
<string-name>
<surname>Bhatt</surname>
<given-names>DL</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Stone</surname>
<given-names>GW</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Mahaffey</surname>
<given-names>KW</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effect of platelet inhibition with cangrelor during PCI on ischemic events</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">N Engl J Med</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>368</volume>(<issue>14</issue>):<fpage>1303</fpage>&#x02010;<lpage>1313</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23473369</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="clc23287-bib-0031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="clc23287-cit-0031">
<string-name>
<surname>Yusuf</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Mehta</surname>
<given-names>SR</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effects of clopidogrel in addition to aspirin in patients with acute coronary syndromes without ST&#x02010;segment elevation</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">N Engl J Med</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>345</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>494</fpage>&#x02010;<lpage>502</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11519503</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="clc23287-bib-0032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="clc23287-cit-0032">
<string-name>
<surname>Russo</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Cannizzo</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Ghetti</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>Idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura and coronary artery disease: comparison between coronary artery bypass grafting and percutaneous coronary intervention</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Interact Cardiovasc Thorac Surg</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>153</fpage>&#x02010;<lpage>157</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21576275</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="clc23287-bib-0033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="clc23287-cit-0033">
<string-name>
<surname>Yadav</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Genereux</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Giustino</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effect of baseline thrombocytopenia on ischemic outcomes in patients with acute coronary syndromes who undergo percutaneous coronary intervention</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Can J Cardiol</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>226</fpage>&#x02010;<lpage>233</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26341303</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="clc23287-bib-0034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="clc23287-cit-0034">
<string-name>
<surname>Ito</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Watanabe</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Morimoto</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>Impact of baseline thrombocytopenia on bleeding and mortality after percutaneous coronary intervention</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Am J Cardiol</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>121</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1304</fpage>&#x02010;<lpage>1314</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29628128</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="clc23287-bib-0035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="clc23287-cit-0035">
<string-name>
<surname>Raphael</surname>
<given-names>CE</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Spoon</surname>
<given-names>DB</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Bell</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>Effect of preprocedural thrombocytopenia on prognosis after percutaneous coronary intervention</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Mayo Clin Proc</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>91</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1035</fpage>&#x02010;<lpage>1044</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27492910</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="clc23287-bib-0036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="clc23287-cit-0036">
<string-name>
<surname>Sugiyama</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Hasegawa</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Kobayashi</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Takahashi</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Fukui</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Tsugawa</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Differential time trends of outcomes and costs of care for acute myocardial infarction hospitalizations by ST elevation and type of intervention in the United States, 2001&#x02010;2011</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">J Am Heart Assoc</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<elocation-id>e001445</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25801759</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="clc23287-bib-0037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="clc23287-cit-0037">
<string-name>
<surname>Vavalle</surname>
<given-names>JP</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Lopes</surname>
<given-names>RD</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>AY</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>Hospital length of stay in patients with non&#x02010;ST&#x02010;segment elevation myocardial infarction</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Am J Med</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>125</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1085</fpage>&#x02010;<lpage>1094</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22921886</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="clc23287-bib-0038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="clc23287-cit-0038">
<string-name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Zhao</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Xie</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>Recent trends in hospitalization for acute myocardial infarction in Beijing: increasing overall burden and a transition from ST&#x02010;segment elevation to non&#x02010;ST&#x02010;segment elevation myocardial infarction in a population&#x02010;based study</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Medicine (Baltimore)</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>95</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<elocation-id>e2677</elocation-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26844503</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="clc23287-bib-0039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="clc23287-cit-0039">
<string-name>
<surname>Goel</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Ness</surname>
<given-names>PM</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Takemoto</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Krishnamurti</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>King</surname>
<given-names>KE</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Tobian</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Platelet transfusions in platelet consumptive disorders are associated with arterial thrombosis and in&#x02010;hospital mortality</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Blood</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>125</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1470</fpage>&#x02010;<lpage>1476</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25588677</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="clc23287-bib-0040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="clc23287-cit-0040">
<string-name>
<surname>Chatterjee</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Wetterslev</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Sharma</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Lichstein</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Mukherjee</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Association of blood transfusion with increased mortality in myocardial infarction: a meta&#x02010;analysis and diversity&#x02010;adjusted study sequential analysis</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">JAMA Intern Med</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>173</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>132</fpage>&#x02010;<lpage>139</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23266500</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="clc23287-bib-0041"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="clc23287-cit-0041">
<string-name>
<surname>Putot</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Zeller</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Perrin</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>Blood transfusion in elderly patients with acute myocardial infarction: data from the RICO survey</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Am J Med</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>131</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>422</fpage>&#x02010;<lpage>429</lpage>. e424.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29030059</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="clc23287-bib-0042"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="clc23287-cit-0042">
<string-name>
<surname>Silvain</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Pena</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Cayla</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>Impact of red blood cell transfusion on platelet activation and aggregation in healthy volunteers: results of the transfusion study</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">Eur Heart J</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>22</issue>):<fpage>2816</fpage>&#x02010;<lpage>2821</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20591842</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="clc23287-bib-0043"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="clc23287-cit-0043">
<string-name>
<surname>Agostoni</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Biondi&#x02010;Zoccai</surname>
<given-names>GG</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>de Benedictis</surname>
<given-names>ML</given-names>
</string-name>, et al. <article-title>Radial versus femoral approach for percutaneous coronary diagnostic and interventional procedures; systematic overview and meta&#x02010;analysis of randomized trials</article-title>. <source xml:lang="en">J Am Coll Cardiol</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>44</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>349</fpage>&#x02010;<lpage>356</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15261930</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>