<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31924840</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6954250</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">57014</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-57014-5</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The only complete articulated early Miocene chameleon skull (Rusinga Island, Kenya) suggests an African origin for Madagascar&#x02019;s endemic chameleons</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>&#x0010c;er&#x00148;ansk&#x000fd;</surname><given-names>Andrej</given-names></name><address><email>cernansky.paleontology@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Herrel</surname><given-names>Anthony</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kibii</surname><given-names>Job M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>Christopher V.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Boistel</surname><given-names>Renaud</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lehmann</surname><given-names>Thomas</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000000109409708</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.7634.6</institution-id><institution>Department of Ecology, Laboratory of Evolutionary Biology, Faculty of Natural Sciences, </institution><institution>Comenius University in Bratislava, </institution></institution-wrap>84215 Bratislava, Mlynsk&#x000e1; dolina Slovakia </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2174 9334</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.410350.3</institution-id><institution>D&#x000e9;partement Adaptation du Vivant, </institution><institution>UMR 7179C.N.R.S/ Mus&#x000e9;um National d&#x02019;Histoire Naturelle, </institution></institution-wrap>55 rue Buffon, 75005 Paris, France </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.425505.3</institution-id><institution>Earth Sciences Department, National Museums of Kenya, Nairobi, </institution></institution-wrap>Kipande Road P.O. BOX, 40658&#x02013; 00100 Nairobi, Kenya </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2293 1795</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.267169.d</institution-id><institution>University of South Dakota, Department of Biology, </institution></institution-wrap>414 E. Clark Street &#x02013; UCL 191, Vermillion South Dakota, USA </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2174 9334</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.410350.3</institution-id><institution>Mus&#x000e9;um National d&#x02019;Histoire Naturelle, UMR 7179C.N.R.S/M.N.H.N., B&#x000e2;timent d&#x02019;Anatomie Compar&#x000e9;e, 55 rue Buffon, CP 55, </institution></institution-wrap>75005 Paris, France </aff><aff id="Aff6"><label>6</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0944 0975</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.438154.f</institution-id><institution>Senckenberg Research Institute and Natural History Museum Frankfurt, Department of Messel Research and Mammalogy, </institution></institution-wrap>Senckenberganlage 25, 60325 Frankfurt, am Main Germany </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>10</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>109</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>14</day><month>11</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>13</day><month>12</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">We here present the first detailed study of the specimen KNM-RU 18340 from Rusinga Island (Kenya), the only known complete early Miocene chameleon skull, using micro-CT. This specimen represents one of the oldest chameleon fossils ever recovered. For the first time, the skull bone internal surfaces, their sutures, and elements contained inside the rocky matrix are observed. Our morphological comparisons and phylogenetic analyses place this specimen confidently in the genus <italic>Calumma</italic> and a new species, <italic>Calumma benovskyi</italic> sp. nov., is erected for it. Since all species of this genus are endemic to Madagascar, this fossil uniquely demonstrates the existence of <italic>Calumma</italic> on continental Africa in the past. Our results challenge the long-held view that chameleons originated on Madagascar and dispersed over water to Africa, and provide a strong evidence of an African origin for some Malagasy lineages. The Oligocene&#x02013;early Miocene dispersal to Madagascar, using oceanic currents that favoured eastward dispersal at that time, is a highly supported scenario matching the suggested dispersal of lemurs to this island. This is consistent with a previously suggested hypothesis based on molecular data.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Ecology</kwd><kwd>Evolution</kwd><kwd>Zoology</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">The Chamaeleonidae is an unusual family of lizards including extant species from Africa, Madagascar, the Middle East, southern India, Sri Lanka, and the Mediterranean region of Europe. It is a highly characteristic and morphologically specialized clade of acrodont iguanians. This clade is mainly composed of arboreal forms, but includes a ground-dwelling desert form &#x02013;the Namaqua chameleon<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. About half of the accepted species of chameleons occur in Madagascar. This island has therefore been suggested to be a centre of diversity of the clade from where it likely radiated via oceanic dispersal<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. Later, in contrast, the molecular phylogeny of Tolley <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup> suggested that the family most probably originated in Africa, with two separate oceanic dispersal events to Madagascar during the Palaeocene and the Oligocene, when prevailing oceanic currents would have favoured eastward dispersal. The fossil record of these animals, the only form of direct evidence regarding the early evolution and palaeobiogeography of these animals, is unfortunately scant. Thus, a key element for resolving this conundrum is lacking.</p><p id="Par3">Molecular data suggest a Cretaceous origin<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>, but the oldest known fossil record of crown members only dates back to the early Miocene (MN3)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. Chamaeleonid fossils are mostly reported from the Miocene of Europe<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup> and are also known from Africa<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup> and potentially India<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. Further African fossils have been documented from early Pliocene deposits<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. The vast majority of the fossil record is represented by isolated elements, mostly jaw fragments, which renders taxonomical identification to the genus or species level often difficult or impossible. Only two notable exceptions exist - <italic>Chamaeleo intermedius</italic>, based on a natural calcite cast described by Hillenius<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup> from the middle Miocene of Fort Ternan in Kenya; and <italic>Ch. andrusovi</italic> from the early (and potentially middle) Miocene of Europe, based on well-documented isolated cranial elements described by &#x0010c;er&#x00148;ansk&#x000fd;<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par4">The fossil locality of Rusinga Island (early Miocene, Lake Victoria, Kenya) is famous for its numerous fossil mammals<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup> (for geology see Supplementary Data&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>), but this locality also yielded numerous reptile specimens such as varanids, crocodiles<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>, as well as the almost complete, and remarkably three-dimensionally preserved, skull of a fossil chamaeleonid (KNM-RU 18340; National Museums of Kenya). The skull is not fully freed from the rock, as matrix fills the entire internal region and covers many bone elements (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). The specimen has been only preliminary reported by Rieppel <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>. These authors suggested that it may be an early representative of the genus <italic>Rhampholeon</italic>, but their report was based on a cast of the specimen and photographs of the original only. Importantly, this specimen represents the only known complete fossil chameleon skull from the early Miocene. Thus, detailed knowledge on the morphology of this fossil African chameleon and its taxonomy is crucial to our understanding of the evolution of this lizard clade and for understanding African paleobiogeography and possible dispersal events.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><italic>Calumma benovskyi</italic> sp. nov., the holotype KNM-RU 18340 from the lower Miocene of Kenya in (<bold>a</bold>,<bold>f</bold>) dorsal; (<bold>b</bold>,<bold>g</bold>) ventral; (<bold>c</bold>,<bold>h</bold>) anterior; (<bold>d</bold>,<bold>i</bold>) right; and (<bold>e</bold>,<bold>j</bold>) left views. These 3D models of the specimen were obtained by &#x000b5;CT and show the specimen in its original preservation condition (with a sedimentary matrix) on the upper side (<bold>a</bold>&#x02013;<bold>e</bold>), whereas the lower side (<bold>f</bold>&#x02013;<bold>j</bold>) shows the specimen with the sediment virtually removed by digital means.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_57014_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e470"/></fig></p><p id="Par5">The aims of this paper are: 1) to use high-resolution X-ray microcomputed tomography (&#x003bc;CT) to virtually prepare all skeletal elements of KNM-RU 18340; 2) to discover potentially hidden bones embedded in the sediment not visible from the outside; and 3) on the basis the obtained new anatomical data to evaluate the possible taxonomic position of KNM-RU 18340 and shed light on scenarios for the origin and diversification of chameleons.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Systematic Palaeontology</title><p id="Par6">Squamata Oppel, 1811<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup></p><p id="Par7">Chamaeleonidae Gray, 1825<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup></p><p id="Par8"><italic>Calumma</italic> Gray, 1865<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup></p><p id="Par9"><italic>Calumma benovskyi</italic> sp. nov.</p><sec id="Sec3"><title>Etymology</title><p id="Par10">After Count M&#x000f3;ric Be&#x00148;ovsk&#x000fd; (also spelled Benyovszky). He was born in Slovakia (Vrbov&#x000e9;, 9. 20. 1746) and died at the age of 39 in Madagascar (5. 23. 1786). He is known as an important traveler and adventurer - the first European to sail in the North Pacific Ocean (seven years before James Cook) and the first person who explored Saint Lawrence Island. He traveled to Madagascar, where local tribal chiefs elected him as a &#x0201c;king&#x0201d; (ampansacabe) of Madagascar in 1776. His story parallels the history of <italic>Calumma</italic> - born abroad, he reached the island by sailing across the ocean.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Holotype</title><p id="Par11">KNM-RU 18340 (field number RU 1916'87; National Museums of Kenya, Nairobi): skull, mandible and three cervical vertebrae in connection (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> and Supplementary Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">13</xref>).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><italic>Calumma benovskyi</italic> sp. nov., the holotype KNM-RU 18340 from the lower Miocene of Kenya with virtually segmented bones from the dorsal and right side (best preserved elements) in (<bold>a</bold>) dorsal view; (<bold>b</bold>) the reconstruction of the complete specimen in dorsal view restored by mirror imaging; and (<bold>c</bold>) virtually segmented bones in right lateral view.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_57014_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e541"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Type locality</title><p id="Par12">Rusinga Island (Lake Victoria, Kenya, Africa), site R107.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Age</title><p id="Par13">Early Miocene, base of the Hiwegi Formation.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Diagnosis</title><p id="Par14">A species of <italic>Calumma</italic> distinguishable from other species by the posterior corners of the frontal, forming well-developed posterolateral processes. Besides this feature, this taxon is characterized by the unique combination of the following characters: (1) nasal-frontal contact present; (2) prefrontal fenestra present and connected to external naris; (3) prefrontal inclined laterally in dorsal view; (4) contact between prefrontal and postorbitofrontal, excluding the frontal from the orbit; (5) orbital margin medially concave rather than straight in dorsal view; (6) single line of protuberances on the external surface of jugal; (7) hour-glass shaped parietal, bearing sculpture arrangement roughly resembling the Greek letter &#x003a8; (psi); (8) well-developed and rather regularly distributed sculpture formed by protuberances on the dorsal surface of the frontal; (9) frontal completely pierced by the parapineal foramen; (10) posterodorsal process of postorbitofrontal reaching above the orbit, inducing an horizontal upper temporal fenestra, dorsally open, and not visible in lateral view; (11) posterodorsal process of squamosal more or less horizontal rather than vertical; and (12) the maximum width of the skull in dorsal view located at the level of the frontal-parietal contact rather than posterior to it.</p><sec id="Sec8"><title>General description and comparison</title><p id="Par15">In dorsal view, the skull presents an ovoid shape, with its widest dimension being at the level of the frontal-parietal contact (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2A,B</xref>). In lateral aspect, the skull is triangular and gradually tapers anteriorly (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2C</xref>). The orbits are large, their anteroposterior length forms 1/3 of the complete anteroposterior length of the skull. The casque is flat and weakly elevated posteriorly, without a dorsally convex parietal. For detailed description and ilustration of each virtually isolated element, see Supplementary Data&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>. The specimen KNM-RU 18340 shares the following features mainly with members of extant <italic>Calumma</italic> (see also Supplementary Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">14</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">16</xref>):<list list-type="order"><list-item><p id="Par16">The contact of the premaxilla with the frontal. This is present in <italic>Calumma globifer</italic>, <italic>Ca. boettgeri</italic> and <italic>Ca. gubei</italic>, but not in <italic>Ca. parsonii</italic>, <italic>Ca. brevicorne</italic>, <italic>Ca. nasutum</italic>, <italic>Ca. fallax</italic>, and <italic>Ca. juliae</italic>. It is present in <italic>Furcifer pardalis</italic> and occasionally in <italic>F. oustaleti</italic> (but not in <italic>F. bifidus</italic> and <italic>F. campani</italic>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. Is is also present in <italic>Rhampholeon</italic> and <italic>Rieppeleon</italic>, but not in <italic>Bradypodion</italic>, <italic>Chamaeleo</italic>, <italic>Kinyongia</italic>, <italic>Trioceros</italic> and <italic>Brookesia</italic>. The premaxilla-frontal contact is absent in the outgroup and character optimization in Mesquite supports this character state as being the condition at the basal node of the Chamaeleonidae clade. Character optimization in Mesquite shows that the contact of these two bones evolved independently in <italic>Rieppeleon</italic>, <italic>Rhampholeon</italic> and some members of <italic>Calumma</italic>. Among <italic>Calumma</italic>, the absence of the contact is at the basal node of the clade. So its presence can be regarded as derived among of this clade.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par17">The paired nasals do not contact one another and are separated by a strut of bone formed by the premaxilla and the frontal. The majority of the chameleons have paired nasals, whereas <italic>Bradypodion</italic> and <italic>Brookesia</italic> often have a single nasal<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par18">The prefrontal fenestra is connected to the external naris (contra Rieppel <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>). This character state can be observed in some extant chameleons, such as <italic>Calumma nasutum</italic>, <italic>Ca. fallax</italic>, <italic>Ca. vatosoa</italic>, <italic>Ca. guibei</italic> (but not in <italic>Ca. globifer</italic>, <italic>Ca. parsonii</italic>, <italic>Ca. brevicorne, Ca. boettgeri</italic> and <italic>Ca. gehringi</italic>), but also in <italic>Rhampholeon</italic>, <italic>Archaius</italic> and <italic>Trioceros melleri</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>. This connection is absent in e.g., <italic>Brookesia</italic>, <italic>Rieppeleon</italic>, <italic>Nadzikambia</italic>, <italic>Bradypodion</italic>, <italic>Chamaeleo</italic> and <italic>Furcifer</italic>. As for <italic>Calumma</italic>, character optimization in Mesquite supports absence of the connection as being the condition at the basal node of the clade, whereas its presence is derived.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par19">The single line of protuberances on the postorbital process of the jugal. Two lines are present e.g., <italic>Calumma ambreense</italic>, <italic>Ca. parsonii</italic> and in the European early Miocene <italic>Chamaeleo andrusovi</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>, whereas one line is present in <italic>Ca. brevicorne</italic>.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par20">The suborbital process of the jugal in lateral aspect; only a dorsal narrow portion of this process is exposed dorsal to maxilla. This is present in <italic>Calumma</italic>, <italic>Chamaeleo</italic>, <italic>Trioceros</italic>, <italic>Kinyongia</italic>, <italic>Rhampholeon</italic> and <italic>Brookesia</italic>. It is largerly exposed in <italic>Rieppeleon</italic> and <italic>Bradypodion</italic>, where, moreover, the process often bears a sculpture formed by protuberances. It is also largerly exposed in <italic>Uromastyx</italic> (outgroup). However, the suborbital process in lateral view is covered by the maxilla in <italic>Archaius</italic> and many <italic>Furcifer</italic> species (not in, e.g, <italic>F. lateralis</italic>, where a narrow portion is exposed)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par21">The absence of jugal - squamosal contact. This contact is absent in <italic>Calumma</italic> (except for <italic>Ca. parsonii</italic>), <italic>Brookesia</italic>, <italic>Rieppeleon</italic> and <italic>Bradypodion</italic>, whereas the contact is usually present in members of the genera <italic>Chamaeleo</italic>, <italic>Nadzikambia</italic>, <italic>Archaius</italic>, <italic>Kinyongia</italic>, and some members of <italic>Furcifer</italic> (not in e.g., <italic>F. campani</italic>) and <italic>Trioceros</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. The character optimization in Mesquite supports the absence of jugal - squamosal contact as being the condition at the basal node of the clade formed by all chameleons. Character optimization in Mesquite shows that presence of this contact is the condition at the basal node of the clade [<italic>Chamaeleo</italic>&#x02009;+&#x02009;<italic>Trioceros</italic>&#x02009;+&#x02009;<italic>Kinyongia</italic>&#x02009;+&#x02009;<italic>Furcifer</italic>&#x02009;+&#x02009;<italic>Calumma</italic>], whereas the contact of these bones in <italic>Archaius</italic> evolved independently. The absence of this contact in members of <italic>Calumma</italic> is regarded as a reversal.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par22">The exclusion of the frontal fom the orbital margin, due to the prefrontal-postorbitofrontal contact. The prefrontal and postorbitofrontal meet in many chameleons, such as <italic>Calumma globifer</italic>, <italic>Ca. ambreense</italic> and <italic>Ca. brevicorne</italic> (not in <italic>Ca. nasutum</italic>, <italic>Ca. fallax</italic>, <italic>Ca. boettgeri</italic>, <italic>Ca. linotum</italic>, <italic>Ca. vatosoa</italic>, <italic>Ca. guibei</italic> and <italic>Ca. gehringi</italic>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>, <italic>Chamaeleo</italic>, <italic>Trioceros</italic> and it can vary among <italic>Furcifer -</italic> present in <italic>F. pardalis</italic> and <italic>F. lateralis</italic>, but not in <italic>F. campani</italic> and <italic>F. bifidus</italic>. Conversely, these two elements do not meet in many small chamaeleonids like <italic>Brookesia</italic>, <italic>Rhampholeon</italic> and <italic>Rieppeleon</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>, but also in <italic>Bradypodion thamnobates</italic>, <italic>Bra. setaroi</italic> and <italic>Nadzikambia mlanjensis</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. The character optimization in Mesquite supports the prefrontal - postorbitofrontal contact as being the condition at the basal node of the clade formed by [<italic>Chamaeleo</italic>&#x02009;+&#x02009;<italic>Trioceros</italic>&#x02009;+&#x02009;<italic>Kinyongia</italic>&#x02009;+&#x02009;<italic>Furcifer</italic>&#x02009;+&#x02009;<italic>Calumma</italic>]. Its absence in some members of this clade can be regarded as a reversal.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par23">The orbital margin, formed by the prefrontal and postorbitofrontal, is medially concave rather than straight in dorsal view. This varies among members of <italic>Calumma</italic>: while the margin is concave in <italic>Ca. nasutum</italic>, <italic>Ca. fallax</italic>, <italic>Ca. guibei</italic> and <italic>Ca. juliae</italic>, it is straight in <italic>Ca. globifer</italic>, <italic>Ca. ambreense</italic>, <italic>Ca. parsonii</italic>, <italic>Ca. brevicorne</italic> and <italic>Ca. boettgeri</italic>. Besides <italic>Calumma</italic>, a concave margin occurs in <italic>Rhampholeon</italic> and some <italic>Furcifer</italic> (<italic>F. bifidus</italic> and <italic>F. campani</italic>, but not in <italic>F. pardalis</italic> and <italic>F. oustaleti</italic>). It is straight in <italic>Brookesia</italic>, <italic>Palleon</italic>, <italic>Rieppeleon</italic>, <italic>Archaius</italic>, <italic>Bradypodion</italic>, <italic>Trioceros</italic>, <italic>Kinyongia</italic>, <italic>Chamaeleo</italic> and <italic>Nadzikambia</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par24">The sculpture formed by protuberances is well-developed and rather regularly distributed on the dorsal surface of the frontal. Among <italic>Calumma</italic>, an ornamentation formed by protuberances in the central region of the frontal is present in <italic>Ca. globifer</italic>, <italic>Ca. ambreense</italic>, <italic>Ca. parsonii</italic>, <italic>Ca. brevicorne</italic> and <italic>Ca. lefona</italic>, but not in <italic>Ca. nasutum</italic> or <italic>Ca. beottgeri</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. Except for <italic>Calumma</italic>, this can be observed in <italic>Brookesia</italic>, <italic>Rieppeleon</italic> and <italic>Bradypodion</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>, but also in some large males of <italic>Trioceros jacksonii</italic>. Character optimization in Mesquite evaluated its presence in members of <italic>Calumma</italic> in two equally parsimonious ways: as the condition at the basal node in this lineage with an additional reversal in <italic>Ca. nasutum</italic> and <italic>Ca. boettgeri</italic>, or as representing a derived condition in <italic>Ca. globifer</italic>&#x02009;+&#x02009;<italic>Ca. parsonii</italic> and <italic>Ca. brevicorne</italic>.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par25">The hour-glass shaped parietal (mid-constriction present) with a triangular wide posterior portion, which does not form a posteriorly narrowing terminus (laterally compressed crest). The parietal is flat and does not form a dorsally elevated casque. This can be observed in members of the extant <italic>Calumma</italic> (note that the additional widening of the posterior portion is usually less developed or absent in <italic>Ca. nasutum</italic>). Athough a flat parietal is present even in <italic>Bradypodion</italic>, <italic>Rhampholeon</italic> and <italic>Rieppeleon</italic>, it gradually narrows posteriorly, being triangular rather than hour-glass shaped. The posterior portion is usually laterally compressed, forming a crest, in <italic>Archaius</italic>, <italic>Chamaeleo</italic>, <italic>Furcifer</italic>, <italic>Nadzikambia</italic>, <italic>Kinyongia</italic> and <italic>Trioceros</italic>. <italic>Brookesia</italic> species and <italic>Palleon</italic> can be distinguished by a presence of the supratemporal processes of the parietal<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. Character optimization in Mesquite evaluated the change of laterally compressed parietal in two equally parsimonious ways: the laterally compresed parietal as being the condition at the basal node of the [<italic>Chamaeleo</italic>&#x02009;+&#x02009;<italic>Trioceros</italic>&#x02009;+&#x02009;<italic>Kinyongia</italic>&#x02009;+&#x02009;<italic>Furcifer</italic>&#x02009;+&#x02009;<italic>Calumma</italic>] lineage, showing its additional reversal in <italic>Calumma</italic>, or the lateral compresion as representing an independent derived character in <italic>Chamaeleo</italic>, <italic>Furcifer</italic> and <italic>Trioceros</italic>. Character optimization in Mesquite evaluated the change of additional widening of the posterior portion of the parietal (hour-glass shape) as well as the absence of a dorsally elevated casque as being the conditions at the basal node of the <italic>Calumma</italic> clade.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par26">The posterodorsal process of the postorbitofrontal reaches above the orbit and thus, the upper temporal fenestra is horizontal, dorsally open, being not visible in lateral view. Among <italic>Calumma</italic>, this is present in <italic>Ca. globifer</italic>, <italic>Ca. parsonii</italic>, <italic>Ca. ambreense</italic> and <italic>Ca. brevicorne</italic>, but not in <italic>Ca. nasutum</italic>, <italic>Ca. gallus, Ca. boetgeri</italic>, <italic>Ca. uetzi</italic>, <italic>Ca. lefona</italic>, <italic>Ca. juliae</italic>, <italic>Ca. guibei</italic> and <italic>Ca. gehringi</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. The upper temporal fenestra is well visible laterally in many chamaeleonid genera, e.g. <italic>Brookesia</italic>, <italic>Rieppeleon</italic>, <italic>Rhampholeon</italic>, <italic>Bradypodion</italic>, <italic>Furcifer</italic> and <italic>Chamaeleo</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. The polarity of this character in Mesquite is unresolved. However, the upper temporal fenestra being horizontal, dorsally open, not visible in lateral view appears to be consistently present in the lineage [<italic>Ca. parsonii</italic>&#x02009;+&#x02009;<italic>Ca. globifer</italic>&#x02009;+&#x02009;<italic>Ca. ambreense</italic>] sister to all other species of <italic>Calumma</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par27">The presence of a well-developed supratemporal. The supratemporal is absent in <italic>Brookesia</italic> and <italic>Rieppeleon</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par28">The absence of a lacrimal. The lacrimal is absent in <italic>Calumma</italic> (except for <italic>Ca. parsonii</italic>), <italic>Rhampholeon</italic>, <italic>Bradypodion</italic> and <italic>Brookesia</italic>, but present in <italic>Chamaeleo</italic>, <italic>Kinyongia</italic> and <italic>Trioceros</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. Character optimization in Mesquite evaluated this change in two equally parsimonious ways: as the condition at the basal node in the [<italic>Chamaeleo</italic>&#x02009;+&#x02009;<italic>Trioceros</italic>&#x02009;+&#x02009;<italic>Kinyongia</italic>&#x02009;+&#x02009;<italic>Furcifer</italic>&#x02009;+&#x02009;<italic>Calumma</italic>] lineage with an additional reversal in <italic>Calumma</italic>&#x02009;+&#x02009;<italic>Furcifer</italic>, or as representing independent derivations of the presence of lacrimal in <italic>Chamaeleo</italic> and <italic>Kinyongia</italic>&#x02009;+&#x02009;<italic>Trioceros</italic>. As for the outgroup, the lacrimal is absent in <italic>Uromastyx</italic>, but present in <italic>Leiolepis</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. The presence of lacrimal can be regarded as a plesiomorphic state among lizards<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par29">The partial fusion of the vomers (at least in the posterior portion). Rieppel and Crumly<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup> noted that the vomer in chamaeleons may be represented by: (a) a single fused bone; (b) an element divided anteriorly but fused posteriorly; or (c) two separate bones. Most extant chamaeleons possess a vomer that is only partly divided or fused into a single element. Paired vomers are present e.g., in <italic>Archaius</italic>.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par30">The broad anteriormost region of the palate formed by the vomers and the anterior portions of the vomerine processes of the palatine. It is rather narrow in e.g., <italic>Rhampoleon spectrum</italic>, <italic>Furcifer pardalis</italic> and <italic>Chamaeleo calyptratus</italic>, but wide in <italic>Calumma globifer</italic>.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par31">The dentary tooth row ends far anterior to the dorsal process of the coronoid<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par32">The presence of an angular<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par33">The wide skull (its width is more than 50% of the maximum anteroposterior length). It is present in the outgroup (<italic>Uromastyx</italic>) and character optimization in Mesquite supports wide skull as being the condition at the basal node of the clade formed by all chameleons. Character optimization in Mesquite shows that narrow, laterally compressed skull is the condition at the basal node of the clade [<italic>Chamaeleo</italic>&#x02009;+&#x02009;<italic>Trioceros</italic>&#x02009;+&#x02009;<italic>Kinyongia</italic>&#x02009;+&#x02009;<italic>Furcifer</italic>&#x02009;+&#x02009;<italic>Calumma</italic>], whereas the condition in <italic>Calumma</italic> is regarded as a reversal.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par34">The absence of synapophyses on the axis. They are absent in <italic>Calumma</italic>, but also in <italic>Furcifer</italic> and <italic>Chamaeleo</italic>. Their presence is documented in <italic>Rhampholeon</italic> and <italic>Brookesia</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>.</p></list-item></list></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Phylogenetic placement of KNM-RU 18340</title><p id="Par35">In all analyses (see methods), despite the different topologies within the Chamaeleoninae, specimen KNM-RU 18340 is consistently recovered as a member of the <italic>Calumma</italic> clade (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3a,b</xref>).<list list-type="order"><list-item><p id="Par36">In analysis 1, a New Technology (NT) search in TNT produced a single most parsimonious tree. The position of KNM-RU 18340 within <italic>Calumma</italic> is recovered as sister to <italic>Ca. brevicorne</italic> (Bremer value 1, relative Bremer 40), whereas <italic>Ca. globifer</italic> (Bremer value 1, relative Bremer 40) and <italic>Ca. parsonii</italic> (Bremer value 1, relative Bremer 17) are sister to this clade (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3a</xref>). Remarkably, <italic>Ca. nasutum</italic> is separated from the other <italic>Calumma</italic> species and appears as the sister taxon of the clade <italic>Bradypodion</italic>&#x02009;+&#x02009;<italic>Calumma</italic> (the remaining species used in the analysis). According to Hillenius<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>, the skull of <italic>Ca. nasutum</italic> is very similar to that of <italic>Rhampholeon</italic>. As was already stated by Rieppel and Crumly<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>, <italic>Ca. nasutum</italic> lacks numerous apomorphies, possibly due to its small size.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par37">In analysis 2, a traditional heuristic Traditional search in T.N.T. produced a single parsimonious tree. The topology of the examined taxa is identical to that recovered from the NT search (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3a</xref>); KNM-RU 18340 is nested within the genus <italic>Calumma</italic> (except for <italic>Ca. nasutum</italic> still recovered sister to <italic>Bradypodion</italic> and other <italic>Calumma</italic> species), as sister to <italic>Ca. brevicorne</italic>.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par38">In the third analysis, the molecular phylogeny of Tolley <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup> was used to constrain the ingroup relationships. The analysis produces a single tree, in which KNM-RU 18340 is again nested within <italic>Calumma</italic>, as sister to <italic>Ca. nasutum</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3b</xref>).</p></list-item></list><fig id="Fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Phylogenetic position of KNM-RU 18340 (<italic>Calumma benovskyi</italic> sp. nov.) within Chamaeleonidae. (<bold>a</bold>) single parsimonious tree recovered by TNT using NT (New Technology) search (with ratchet) and 1000 iterations, showing Bremer (above node)/relative Bremer (below node) values at nodes recovered by TNT; (<bold>b</bold>) tree recovered by TNT using constraint based on Tolley <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>, circles in (<bold>b</bold>) indicate distribution of taxa: yellow African, green Madagascar, red Seychelles and purple India. (<bold>c</bold>) Neighbour joining tree illustrating the phenetic similarity between the skull of the chameleons included in the analyses. The tree was constructed using the PC axes representing 99.6% of the overall variance. The analysis shows how the fossil is morphologically similar to a group of species including <italic>Chamaeleo dilepis</italic>, <italic>Calumma brevicorne</italic>, <italic>Ch. namaquensis</italic>, <italic>Ca. globifer</italic>, <italic>Ch. calyptratus</italic>, <italic>Furcifer pardalis</italic> and <italic>Trioceros melleri</italic>. The skull of extant <italic>Calumma brevicorne</italic> in (<bold>d</bold>) dorsal and (<bold>e</bold>) lateral views, and (<bold>f</bold>) a living representative of this species (photo by C.V.A). (<bold>g</bold>) Distribution of the <italic>Calumma</italic> species. Blue dot indicates a location of the early Miocene member <italic>Ca. benovskyi</italic>; red lines indicate the distribution of extant species endemic to Madagascar. White arrows indicate potential eastward dispersal routes (the map has been modified from the NASA satellite orthographic map which is in the public domain).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_57014_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e1766"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Geometric morphometric analyses</title><p id="Par39">Both the principal component analysis and the neighbour joining tree performed on the 3D landmarks showed that KNM-RU 18340 is morphologically most similar to a group of species including two <italic>Chamaeleo</italic> (<italic>Ch. namaquensis</italic> and <italic>Ch. dilepis</italic>) and two <italic>Calumma</italic> species (<italic>Ca. brevicorne</italic> and <italic>Ca. globifer</italic>) providing further support for the phylogenetic analysis which unambiguously places the fossil within the <italic>Calumma</italic> group (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3c</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec11" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><sec id="Sec12"><title>Taxonomic allocation of KNM-RU 18340</title><p id="Par40">Rieppel <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup> only wrote a preliminary report on the KNM-RU 18340 specimen as their study was based only on a cast and on photographs of the original material. These authors suggested that this fossil may potentionally be an early representative of the genus <italic>Rhampholeon</italic>, although as acknowledged by them, no living species of the genus <italic>Rhampholeon</italic> shows a fully separated prefrontal fenestra (called &#x0201c;prefrontal fontanelle&#x0201d; in their report) - they claimed (erroneously as we know now) the complete separation of external nares from the prefrontal fenestra in KNM-RU 18340.</p><p id="Par41">Thanks to micro-computed tomography (&#x003bc;CT), we were able to identify all skull bones and observe their internal sides as well as their sutures. Moreover, the micro-CT revealed elements that are hidden by the rocky matrix and could not be studied before, such as an almost complete braincase with stapes, the palate region, a ceratohyal and the first three cervical vertebrae (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, Supplementary Data&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>).</p><p id="Par42">The morphological comparisons are in agreement with the results of the phylogenetic analyses that specimen KNM-RU 18340 can be distinguished from all extant genera, except from <italic>Calumma</italic>. Overall the morphology of the fossil skull most closely resembles that seen in the extant <italic>Ca. brevicorne</italic> (see Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3d&#x02013;f</xref>), especially the shape of the parietal, the arrangement of protuberances on the parietal, the dorsal opening of the supratemporal fenestra (not visible in lateral aspect; this is also present in <italic>Ca. parsonii</italic>, <italic>Ca. globifer</italic> and <italic>Ca. ambreense</italic>), the presence of the prefrontal-postorbitofrontal contact over the orbit and the maximum width of the skull being located at the level of the frontal-parietal contact in dorsal view (the maximum width in <italic>Ca. parsonii</italic>, <italic>Ca. globifer</italic> and <italic>Ca. ambreense</italic> is posterior to this region, in the mid-section of upper temporal fenestra). But there are also some differences, e.g. the absence of the premaxilla-frontal contact, the separation of the external naris from the prefrontal fenestra, and the straight orbital margin in dorsal view in the extant species (see above).</p><p id="Par43">The preserved elements of KNM-RU 18340 possess a unique combination of character states (see Diagnosis), and a new taxon name is therefore erected: <italic>Calumma benovskyi</italic> sp. nov. There is also one unique character: well defined and laterally expanded triangular posterolateral processes of the frontal. Although in some species of <italic>Calumma</italic> (e.g., <italic>Ca. nasutum</italic> and <italic>Ca. vatosoa</italic>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup> the posterolateral corners of the frontal expand laterally, they do not form a well-defined triangular processes as present in the early Miocene <italic>Ca. benovskyi</italic> sp. nov. The processes are not developed in <italic>Brookesia</italic> and <italic>Palleon</italic>, but are well-expanded laterally in the outgroup taxon <italic>Uromastyx</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Biogeographic history of malagasy chameleons</title><p id="Par44">Our results show that KNM-RU 18340 represents the first evidence of a member of the <italic>Calumma</italic> lineage on continental Africa. The extant species of this genus (together with the Brookesiinae, see; Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3b</xref> here) are endemic to the island of Madagascar (<italic>Furcifer</italic> is distributed on Madagascar, but there are two species on the Comoros as well)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>, which harbours an exceptional biodiversity. The separation of this island from Africa occurred already in the early Cretaceous<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>. Although the presence of a Malagasy lineage in continental Africa during the early Miocene might appear as a surprise, similar patterns have been observed for Madagascar&#x02019;s endemic terrestrial extant mammals. Based on phylogenetic analyses, tenrecs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>, euplerid carnivores<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup> and nesomyine rodents<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup> appear to be monophyletic taxa, whose sister group is found in Africa. They each result from a single colonization event and subsequent radiation within the island<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup>. Likewise, recent palaeontological discoveries suggest that two lemur lineages likely dispersed from Africa to Madagascar across the Mozambique Channel independently, and thus have an African origin<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>. The dispersal window for these four endemic clades is estimated to span from the Oligocene to the early Miocene<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>. It is also worth noting that some other squamate lineages such as pythons and varanids did not manage to follow this dispersal route.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>The origin of chameleons?</title><p id="Par45">Raxworthy <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup> suggested that chameleons originated on Madagascar and dispersed over water at least three times to Africa, and once each to the Seychelles, to the Comoros archipelago (where they occupy two islands) and to Reunion. In contrast, Tolley <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup> suggested that the family originated in Africa, with two separate oceanic dispersal events to Madagascar during the Palaeocene (Brookesiinae lineage) and the Oligocene, when prevailing oceanic currents would have favoured eastward dispersal. The early Miocene <italic>Calumma benovskyi</italic> sp. nov. supports an African continental origin for Malagasy chamaeleonine lineages, at least for the <italic>Calumma</italic> clade. The oceanic dispersal using currents that favoured eastward dispersal appears to be the most probable scenario (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3g</xref>). The existence of such eastward currents from the African shore to Madagascar between the Palaeocene and the early Miocene is well documented<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>. Lizards such as chameleons might have used floating islands&#x02014;rafts of trees (this is especially plausible for arboreal lizards) &#x02014;to cross such distances<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>. Rafting has been suggested for anole lizards migrating around the Caribbean<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup> or for mabuyid skink <italic>Trachylepis atlantica</italic> on the island of Fernando de Noronha (Brazil), where the ancestors of this species are believed to have rafted from Africa, across the Atlantic, during the last 9 million years<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>; <italic>Trachylepis</italic> is otherwise distributed in Africa and Madagascar<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par46">The African origin of <italic>Calumma</italic> is also supported by the distribution of members forming a clade [<italic>Chamaeleo</italic>&#x02009;+&#x02009;<italic>Trioceros</italic>&#x02009;+&#x02009;<italic>Kinyongia</italic>&#x02009;+&#x02009;<italic>Furcifer</italic>&#x02009;+&#x02009;<italic>Calumma</italic>]; where only the latter two taxa are found in Madagascar<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. According to Tolley <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>, <italic>Calumma</italic> and <italic>Furcifer</italic> are sister taxa and the split of these two lineages occured in the Eocene. But within these genera, species-level divergence occured during the Oligocene and Miocene. However, if the split is older than the documented early Miocene occurrence of the extinct continental species <italic>Ca. benovskyi</italic> sp. nov., this might suggest that the last common ancestor of these two lineages most likely lived on the continent. This then suggests a continental origin for both, <italic>Calumma</italic> and <italic>Furcifer</italic>.</p><p id="Par47">Although the Miocene <italic>Calumma benovskyi</italic> sp. nov. represents the oldest known member of this genus and shares some characters with the basal node of this clade, based on our current knowledge we can assume that <italic>Ca. beniovskyi</italic> most likely does not form an ancestral lineage for the <italic>Calumma</italic> clade. It is recovered as sister to <italic>Ca. brevicorne</italic> rather than in a basal position to all <italic>Calumma</italic>. Moreover, molecular data suggest that the ancestral lineage should be older than the early Miocene<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>; yet, this remains to be verified with fossil data of an older age. For now the diversity and morphological disparity of the Oligocene and early Miocene <italic>Calumma</italic> in Africa remains unknown. However, the assignment of KNM-RU 18340 to the genus <italic>Calumma</italic> and its presence in the early Miocene of Kenya demonstrates that the <italic>Calumma</italic> lineage was present in Africa at a time when oceanic currents supported eastward dispersal<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>. This is consistent with the previously suggested hypothesis of Tolley <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup> based on molecular data.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Is the alternative scenario possible?</title><p id="Par48">The above scenario challenges a dispersal of the genus <italic>Calumma</italic> from Madagascar to Africa through oceanic dispersal, as previously suggested by Raxworthy <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. According to several authors (e.g., Ali and Huber<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>, Samonds <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>), the prevailing oceanic currents at that time support dispersal from Africa to Madagascar, and not the other way around. According to McCall<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup>, some areas of the Mozambique Channel were dry land during the middle Eocene - early Miocene. Even if animals used several intervening islands in a stepping-stone chain, eastward currents would have hindered their westward dispersal. Moreover, chameleons are relatively poor swimmers rendering the westward route scenario even less probable. Ali and Huber<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup> also pointed out that shortly after the early Miocene, the currents between Africa and Madagascar turned in the opposite direction (i.e. westwards, toward Africa), like in present-day surface-water circulation. From the middle Miocene onwards, currents would thus have hindered journey to Madagascar for any non-volant and non-swimming taxa, and could have supported the development of insular endemism for terrestrial animals there.</p><p id="Par49">Hence, the &#x0201c;out of Madagascar&#x0201d; dispersal scenario would have required the existence of fully terrestrial land bridge between the late Oligocene and the early Miocene. Of note is that the separation of Africa and Madagascar occurred already during the Mesozoic<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>. But such a bridge would have enabled any taxon, even large animals (e.g., elephants), to disperse. This scenario would neither explain the quasi absence of large-bodied terrestrial mammals, nor the limited number of mammal families that live on the island today.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec17"><title>Material</title><p id="Par50">The skull KNM-RU 18340 (field number RU 1916'87) is housed at the National Museums of Kenya, Nairobi. The specimen comes from the early Miocene locality Rusinga Island and is remarkably complete and three-dimensionally well-preserved. Its maximum anteroposterior length (from the snout to the end of parietal) is 32.1&#x02009;mm. The specimen has not been fully prepared from the rock and this matrix still fills the whole internal region and hides many bony elements.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>X-ray microtomography and three-dimensional visualization</title><p id="Par51">We &#x000b5;CT scanned this skull at the University of Witswatersrand (South Africa), using a Nikon Metrology XTH 225/320 LC Xray microtomograph, with an acceleration tension of 100&#x02009;kV and an intensity of 50&#x02009;&#x000b5;A. As much as 2000 radiographs were acquired with an exposure time of 4&#x02009;s and an averaging of 1. The resolution was 18.83&#x02009;&#x000b5;m. The micro-CT data were analyzed using VG Studio Max 3.2 and Avizo 8.1. The right side of the skull is in better condition and more completely preserved than the left side. For this reason, we focused our reconstruction efforts on the right side, and supplemented certain areas with elements from the left side, when better preserved. For the reconstruction of the whole skull in dorsal view, missing areas were restored by mirror imaging.</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Phylogenetic analysis</title><p id="Par52">A morphological data matrix (see Supplementary Data&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2</xref>) was developed based on characters taken primarily from Rieppel and Crumly<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup> (see Supplementary Data&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). Nineteen characters of relevance for chameleons were added. The matrix comprises 43 characters scored for 23 extant chameleon ingroup taxa (<italic>Archaius tigris</italic>, <italic>Bradypodion ventrale</italic>, <italic>Bra. pumilum</italic>, <italic>Brookesia superciliaris</italic>, <italic>Bro. stumpffi</italic>, <italic>Calumma globifer</italic>, <italic>Ca. parsonii</italic>, <italic>Ca. brevicorne</italic>, <italic>Ca. nasutum</italic>, <italic>Chamaeleo zeylanicus</italic>, <italic>Ch. chamaeleon</italic>, <italic>Ch. dilepis</italic>, <italic>Furcifer campani</italic>, <italic>F. oustaleti</italic>, <italic>F. pardalis</italic>, <italic>Kinyongia fischeri</italic>, <italic>Rhampholeon spectrum</italic>, <italic>Rh. platyceps</italic>, <italic>Rieppeleon kerstenii</italic>, <italic>Ri. brevicaudatus</italic>, <italic>Trioceros melleri</italic>, <italic>T. johnstoni</italic> and <italic>T. jacksonii</italic>), in addition to the extinct taxon represented by the Kenyan material described here. <italic>Uromastyx</italic> was used as the outgroup. The principal goal of this analysis is to understand the relationship of the Kenyan early Miocene taxon among Chamaeleonidae. The data matrix was analysed using maximum parsimony as an optimality criterion in the program TNT and the NT (New Technology) search (with ratchet) with 1000 iterations<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref></sup>. All characters were treated as unordered and were equally weighted. Support was estimated through Bremer support indices<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup>. Mesquite v.2.75<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup> was used to visualize all trees. In the third analysis (see above), the molecular phylogeny of Tolley <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup> was used to constrain the ingroup relationships. The command used was: [force&#x02009;=&#x02009;((1 2) (((14 (3 4))) ((((5 6) ((8 9) ((17 (16 15)) ((((18 (19 20))((12 13) (10 11)))((7 ((23 (21 22)))); constrain=;]. KNM-RU 18340 was the only taxon excluded from the constraint tree, leaving it free to float.</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Geometric morphometric analyses</title><p id="Par53">We ran a 3D geometric morphometric analysis on 27 species of chameleons in addition to the fossil. Extant species covered all genera with most genera represented by two or three species. Specimens were micro CT-scanned and surfaces were cleaned in Geomagic Studio and imported in the &#x02018;Landmark&#x02019; software<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref></sup>. Forty-three landmarks (see Supplementary Data&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref> - Supplementary Tab.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>) were taken on the right side of each skull to describe the overall shape (Supplementary Data&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref> - Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">17</xref>). A general Procrustes analysis (GPA)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref></sup> was run and was followed by a principal component analysis (PCA) performed on the Procrustes residuals. We constructed a neighbor-joining tree on the PC axes that jointly explained 99.6% of the variance to evaluate phenotypic proximity between the fossil and the extant genera. All analyses were performed in R (v. 2.15.3; R Core Team 2016) using the libraries RMORPH<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref></sup>, MASS<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref></sup>, APE<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref></sup> and ADE4<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Character reconstruction</title><p id="Par54">Mesquite v.2.75<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup> was used for optimizations and ancestral state determinations using parsimony (see Supplementary Data&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref> - Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">18</xref>). The Mesquite tree is based on Tolley <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. KNM-RU 18340 is excluded here due to its uncertain topology within <italic>Calumma</italic>. In contrast, <italic>Ca. boettgeri</italic> is added to increase taxon sampling in regards of <italic>Calumma</italic>.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary information</title><sec id="Sec22"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41598_2019_57014_MOESM1_ESM.nex"><caption><p>Supplementary Information.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="41598_2019_57014_MOESM2_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Supplementary Information2.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s note</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Supplementary information</title><p>is available for this paper at 10.1038/s41598-019-57014-5.</p></sec><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>For access to the specimen KNM-RU 18340, we thank Dr. Fredrick Manthi (National Museums of Kenya, Nairobi). We are indebted to Dr. Kudakwashe Jakata (University of the Witwatersrand, Johannesburg, South Africa) for his help with the &#x000b5;CT. We are also indebted to J. D. Daza (Sam Houston State University, TX, USA) for his help with Bremer value processing in TNT and to the Willi Hennig Society for making the TNT program freely available. A.H. thanks Anne-Claire Fabre for help with the morphometric analysis. We thank NASA for the public domain regarding the map in Figure&#x000a0;3g. We acknowledge Dr. Georgios Georgalis (Dipartimento di Scienze della Terra, Universit&#x000e0; degli Studi di Torino, Italy), and an anonymous reviewer for their comments and revisions on the manuscript. A.&#x0010c;. acknowledges financial support from the Scientific Grant Agency of Ministry of Education of Slovak Republic and Slovak Academy of Sciences, Grant Nr. 1/0209/18.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>A.&#x0010c;. and T.L. conceived the study. A.&#x0010c;. virtually segmented individual elements of the skull, made descriptions and performed the phylogenetical analyses. J.M.K. and T.L. scanned the fossil skull and collected the data on geology. A.H. performed GM analyses. A.&#x0010c;., A.H., R.B. and C.V.A. made 3D models of extant chameleons. A.&#x0010c;., A.H., C.V.A. and T.L. wrote the paper.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>Digital surface models of the figured fossil specimen KNM-RU 18340 are available on the Dryad Digital Repository (10.5061/dryad.msbcc2fts). The following items are available in this collection: KNM-RU 18340, holotype: 3D printable surface file in STL format.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par55">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Estes, R. Sauria terrestria, Amphisbaenia. Handbuch der Pal&#x000e4;oherpetologie, Part 10A. (Gustav Fischer Verlag, Stuttgart, 1983).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Glaw</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Taxonomic checklist of chameleons (Squamata: Chamaeleonidae)</article-title><source>Vertebr Zool</source><year>2015</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>167</fpage><lpage>246</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raxworthy</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Forstner</surname><given-names>MRJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Nussbaum</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chameleon radiation by oceanic dispersal</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2002</year><volume>415</volume><fpage>784</fpage><lpage>787</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/415784a</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11845207</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tolley</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Townsend</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Vences</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Large scale phylogeny of chameleons suggests African origins and rapid Eocene radiation</article-title><source>Proc. R. Soc. B</source><year>2013</year><volume>280</volume><fpage>20130184</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rspb.2013.0184</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23536596</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fejfar</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Schleich</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ein Cham&#x000e4;leon fund aus dem unteren Orleanium des Braunkohlen-Tagebaus Merkur-Nord (Nordb&#x000f6;hmen)</article-title><source>Cour. Forsch-Inst. Senckenberg</source><year>1994</year><volume>173</volume><fpage>167</fpage><lpage>173</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>&#x0010c;er&#x00148;ansk&#x000fd;</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A revision of chamaeleonids from the Lower Miocene of the Czech Republic with description of a new species of Chamaeleo (Squamata, Chamaeleonidae)</article-title><source>Geobios</source><year>2010</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>605</fpage><lpage>613</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.geobios.2010.04.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moody</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ro&#x0010d;ek</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chamaeleo caroliquarti (Chamaeleonidae Sauria): a new species from the Lower Miocene of central Europe</article-title><source>V&#x0011b;st. &#x000da;st&#x00159;. &#x000da;st. geol.</source><year>1980</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>92</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schleich</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Die mittelmioz&#x000e4;ne Fossil-Lagerst&#x000e4;tte Sandelhausen 13. Chamaeleo bavaricus sp. nov., ein neuer Nachweis aus dem Jungterti&#x000e4;r S&#x000fc;ddeutschlands</article-title><source>Mitt. Bayer. Staatssamml. Pal&#x000e4;ontol. Hist. Geol.</source><year>1983</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>81</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schleich</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neue Reptilienfunde aus dem Terti&#x000e4;r Deutschlands 2. Chamaeleo pfeili sp. nov. Von der untermioz&#x000e4;nen Fossilfundstelle Rauscher&#x000f6;d/Niederbayern (Reptilia, Sauria Chamaeleonidae)</article-title><source>Mitt. Bayer. Staatssamml. Pal&#x000e4;ontol. Hist. Geol.</source><year>1984</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>97</fpage><lpage>103</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>&#x0010c;er&#x00148;ansk&#x000fd;</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A revision of the chameleon species Chamaeleo pfeili Schleich (Squamata; Chamaeleonidae) with description of anew material of chamaeleonids from the Miocene deposits of southern Germany</article-title><source>Bull. Geosci.</source><year>2011</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>275</fpage><lpage>282</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3140/bull.geosci.1259</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>&#x0010c;er&#x00148;ansk&#x000fd;</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Szyndlar</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000f6;rs</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fossil squamate faunas from the Neogene of Hambach (northwestern Germany)</article-title><source>Palaeobio. Palaeoenv.</source><year>2017</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>329</fpage><lpage>354</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12549-016-0252-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Georgalis</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Villa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Delfino</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>First description of a fossil chamaeleonid from Greece and its relevance for the European biogeographic history of the group</article-title><source>Sci. Nat.</source><year>2016</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>12</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00114-016-1336-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hillenius</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Notes on chameleons IV. A new chameleon, from the Miocene of Fort Ternan, Kenya (Chamaeleonidae, Reptilia)</article-title><source>Beaufortia</source><year>1978</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>15</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rieppel</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Odhiambo</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A preliminary report on a fossil Chamaeleonine (Reptilia: Chamaeleoninae) skull from the Miocene of Kenya</article-title><source>J. Herpetol.</source><year>1992</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>80</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/1565027</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sankhyan</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>&#x0010c;er&#x00148;ansk&#x000fd;</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A first possible chameleon from the late Miocene of India (the hominoid site of Haritalyangar): a tentative evidence for an Asian dispersal of chameleons</article-title><source>Sci. Nat.</source><year>2016</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>94</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00114-016-1419-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tolley</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Burger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Matthee</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biogeographic patterns and phylogeography of dwarf chameleons (Bradypodion) in an African biodiversity hotspot</article-title><source>Mol. Ecol.</source><year>2006</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>781</fpage><lpage>793</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-294X.2006.02836.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16499702</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Dollion, A.Y. <italic>et al</italic>. Morphometric analysis of chameleon fossil fragments from the Early Pliocene of South Africa: a new piece of the chamaeleonid history. <italic>Sci. Nat.</italic><bold>102</bold>(2) (2015).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Werdelin, L. &#x00026; Sanders, W. J. Cenozoic Mammals of Africa. (University of California Press, Berkeley, California, 2010).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clos</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A new species of Varanus (Reptilia:Sauria) from the Miocene of Kenya</article-title><source>J. Vertebr. Paleont.</source><year>1995</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>254</fpage><lpage>267</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/02724634.1995.10011228</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Conrad</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>New specimens of &#x02018;Crocodylus&#x02019; pigotti (Crocodylidae) from Rusinga Island, Kenya, and generic reallocation of the species</article-title><source>J. Vertebr. Paleont.</source><year>2013</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>629</fpage><lpage>646</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/02724634.2013.743404</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Oppel, M. Die ordnungen, familien und gattungen der reptilien als prodromeiner naturgeschichte derselben. (M&#x000fc;nchen: Joseph Lindauer Verlag, 1811).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A Synopsis of the genera of reptiles and amphibia, with a description of some new species</article-title><source>Ann. Philos.</source><year>1825</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>193</fpage><lpage>217</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Revision of the genera and species of Chamaeleonidae, with the description of some new species</article-title><source>Ann. Mag. Nat. Hist.</source><year>1865</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>340</fpage><lpage>354</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rieppel</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Crumly</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Paedomorphosis and skull structurein Malagasy chamaeleons (Reptilia: Chamaeleoninae)</article-title><source>J. Zool.</source><year>1997</year><volume>243</volume><fpage>351</fpage><lpage>380</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-7998.1997.tb02788.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pr&#x000f6;tzel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Vences</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Scherz</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Vieites</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Glaw</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Splitting and lumping: An integrative taxonomic assessment of Malagasy chameleons in the Calumma guibei complex results in the new species C. gehringi sp. nov</article-title><source>Vertebr. Zool.</source><year>2017</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>231</fpage><lpage>249</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pr&#x000f6;tzel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruthensteiner</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Glaw</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>No longer single! Description of female Calumma vatosoa (Squamata, Chamaeleonidae) including a review of the species and its systematic position</article-title><source>Zoosyst. Evol.</source><year>2016</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/zse.92.6464</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pr&#x000f6;tzel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruthensteiner</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Scherz</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Glaw</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Systematic revision of the Malagasy chameleons Calumma boettgeri and C. linotum (Squamata: Chamaeleonidae)</article-title><source>Zootaxa</source><year>2015</year><volume>4048</volume><fpage>211</fpage><lpage>231</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.11646/zootaxa.4048.2.4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26624746</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rieppel</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The phylogenetic relationships within the Chamaeleonidae, with comments on some aspects of cladistic analysis</article-title><source>Zool. J. Linn. Soc.</source><year>1987</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>62</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1096-3642.1987.tb01343.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hillenius</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The skull of Chamaeleo nasutus adds more information to the relationship of Chamaeleo with Rhampholeon and Brookesia (Chamaeleonidae, Reptilia)</article-title><source>Bijdragen tot de Dierkunde</source><year>1988</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>7</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1163/26660644-05801002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pr&#x000f6;tzel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Endangered beauties: micro-CT cranial osteology, molecular genetics and external morphology reveal three new species of chameleons in the Calumma boettgeri complex (Squamata: Chamaeleonidae)</article-title><source>Zool. J. Linn. Soc.</source><year>2018</year><volume>184</volume><fpage>471</fpage><lpage>498</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/zoolinnean/zlx112</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Estes, R., de Queiroz, K. &#x00026; Gauthier, J. A. Phylogenetic relationships within squamata. (Eds. Estes, R. &#x00026; Pregill, G. K.) Phylogenetic relationships of the lizard families (Stanford: Stanford University Press, 119&#x02013;281, 1988).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>&#x0010c;er&#x00148;ansk&#x000fd;</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The atlas-axis complex in chamaeleonids (Squamata: Chamaeleonidae), with description of a new anatomical structure of the skull</article-title><source>Anat. Rec.</source><year>2014</year><volume>297</volume><fpage>369</fpage><lpage>396</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ar.22859</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hillenius</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The relationship of Brookesia, Rhampholeon and Chamaeleo (Chamaeleonidae, Reptilia)</article-title><source>Bijdr. Dierkd.</source><year>1986</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>29</fpage><lpage>38</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1163/26660644-05601003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Townsend</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Tolley</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Glaw</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x000f6;hme</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Vences</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Eastward from Africa: palaeocurrent-mediated chameleon dispersal to the Seychelles islands</article-title><source>Biol. Lett.</source><year>2011</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>225</fpage><lpage>228</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsbl.2010.0701</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20826471</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rabinowitz</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Coffin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Falvey</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The separation of Madagascar and Africa</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1983</year><volume>220</volume><fpage>67</fpage><lpage>69</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.220.4592.67</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17736163</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Poux</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Asynchronous colonization of Madagascar by the four endemic clades of primates, tenrecs, carnivores, and rodents as inferred from nucleargenes</article-title><source>Syst. Biol.</source><year>2005</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>719</fpage><lpage>730</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10635150500234534</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16243759</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Everson</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Soarimalala</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multiple loci and complete taxonomic sampling resolve the phylogeny and biogeographichistory of tenrecs (Mammalia: Tenrecidae) and reveal higher speciation ratesin Madagascar&#x02019;s humid forests</article-title><source>Syst. Biol.</source><year>2016</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>890</fpage><lpage>909</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/sysbio/syw034</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27103169</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoder</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Single origin of Malagasy Carnivora from an African ancestor</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2003</year><volume>421</volume><fpage>734</fpage><lpage>737</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature01303</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12610623</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoder</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Nowak</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Has Vicariance or Dispersal Been the Predominant Biogeographic Force in Madagascar? Only Time.Will Tell</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Ecol. Evol. Syst.</source><year>2006</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>405</fpage><lpage>431</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.ecolsys.37.091305.110239</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gunnell</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Fossil lemurs from Egypt and Kenya suggest an African origin for Madagascar&#x02019;s aye-aye</article-title><source>Nat. Commun.</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>3193</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-018-05648-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30131571</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mammalian biodiversity on Madagascar controlled by ocean currents</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2010</year><volume>463</volume><fpage>653</fpage><lpage>657</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature08706</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20090678</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Samonds</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Spatial and temporal arrival patterns of Madagascar&#x02019;s vertebrate fauna explained by distance, ocean currents, and ancestor type</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2012</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>5352</fpage><lpage>5357</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1113993109</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22431643</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Houle</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Floating islands: a mode of long distance dispersal for small and medium-sized terrestrial vertebrates</article-title><source>Divers. Distrib.</source><year>1998</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>201</fpage><lpage>216</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Losos, J. B. Lizards in an evolutionary tree: ecology and adaptive radiation of anoles. (University of California Press, Oakland, California, 2009).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carranza</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>EN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Investigating the origin of transoceanic distributions: mtDNA shows Mabuya lizards (Reptilia, Scincidae) crossed the Atlantic twice</article-title><source>Syst. Biodivers.</source><year>2003</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>275</fpage><lpage>282</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S1477200003001099</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mausfeld</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Phylogenetic affinities of Mabuya atlantica Schmidt, 1945, endemic to the Atlantic Ocean archipelago of Fernando de Noronha (Brazil): necessity of partitioning the genus Mabuya Fitzinger, 1826 (Scincidae: Lygosominae)</article-title><source>Zool. Anz.</source><year>2002</year><volume>241</volume><fpage>281</fpage><lpage>293</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1078/0044-5231-00081</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCall</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Implications of recent geological investigations of the Mozambique Channel for the mammalian colonization of Madagascar</article-title><source>Proc Biol Sci</source><year>1997</year><volume>264</volume><fpage>663</fpage><lpage>665</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rspb.1997.0094</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9178538</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goloboff</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Farri</surname><given-names>SJS</given-names></name><name><surname>Nixon</surname><given-names>KCTNT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>a free program for phylogenetic analysis</article-title><source>Cladistics</source><year>2008</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>774</fpage><lpage>786</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1096-0031.2008.00217.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bremer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Branch support and tree stability</article-title><source>Cladistics</source><year>1994</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>295</fpage><lpage>304</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1096-0031.1994.tb00179.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Maddison, W. P. &#x00026; Maddison, D. R. Mesquite: a modular system for evolutionary analysis. Version 2.75. (2011). Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mesquiteproject.org/">http://mesquiteproject.org/</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wiley, D. F. <italic>et al</italic>. Evolutionary morphing. Proceedings of IEEE Visualization 2005 (2005).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rohlf</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Slice</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Extensions of the procrustes method for the optimal superimposition of landmarks</article-title><source>Syst Zool</source><year>1990</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>40</fpage><lpage>59</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/2992207</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Baylac, M. Rmoprh: a geometric and multivariate morphometrics library. (2013). Available from the author: baylac@mnhn.fr.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Venables, W. N. &#x00026; Ripley, B. D. Modern applied statistics with R. Fourth edition. (Springer, 2002. ISBN 0-387-95457-0).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paradis</surname><given-names>Emmanuel</given-names></name></person-group><source>Analysis of Phylogenetics and Evolution with R</source><year>2012</year><publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer New York</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dray</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dufour</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Chessel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The ade4 package-II: two-table and K-table methods</article-title><source>R News</source><year>2007</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>47</fpage><lpage>52</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>