<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Transl Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Transl Med</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Translational Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1479-5876</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31924244</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6954611</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2210</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12967-020-02210-5</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Transcriptome analysis defines myocardium gene signatures in children with ToF and ASD and reveals disease-specific molecular reprogramming in response to surgery with cardiopulmonary bypass</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Raggi</surname><given-names>Federica</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Cangelosi</surname><given-names>Davide</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Becherini</surname><given-names>Pamela</given-names></name><address><email>pamy.bekke@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Blengio</surname><given-names>Fabiola</given-names></name><address><email>fabiola.blengio@inserm.fr</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Morini</surname><given-names>Martina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Acquaviva</surname><given-names>Massimo</given-names></name><address><email>acquaviva.massimo@hsr.it</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Belli</surname><given-names>Maria Luisa</given-names></name><address><email>marialuisabelli@gaslini.org</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Panizzon</surname><given-names>Giuseppe</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cervo</surname><given-names>Giuseppe</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" deceased="yes"><name><surname>Varesio</surname><given-names>Luigi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Eva</surname><given-names>Alessandra</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" equal-contrib="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-1857-7193</contrib-id><name><surname>Bosco</surname><given-names>Maria Carla</given-names></name><address><email>mariacarlabosco@gaslini.org</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.419504.d</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1760 0109</institution-id><institution>Laboratory of Molecular Biology, </institution><institution>IRCSS Istituto Giannina Gaslini, </institution></institution-wrap>Padiglione 2, L.go G.Gaslini 5, 16147 Genova, Italy </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.419504.d</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1760 0109</institution-id><institution>Department of Cardiology, </institution><institution>IRCSS Istituto Giannina Gaslini, </institution></institution-wrap>Genova, Italy </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5606.5</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2151 3065</institution-id><institution>Present Address: Department of Internal Medicine, </institution><institution>University of Genova, </institution></institution-wrap>Genova, Italy </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.462410.5</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0386 3258</institution-id><institution>Present Address: INSERM U955 Equipe 16, </institution></institution-wrap>Creteil, France </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.18887.3e</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000000417581884</institution-id><institution>Present Address: Immunobiology of Neurological Disorders Unit, Institute of Experimental Neurology INSPE, </institution><institution>Ospedale San Raffaele, </institution></institution-wrap>Milano, Italy </aff><aff id="Aff6"><label>6</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.419504.d</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1760 0109</institution-id><institution>Present Address: Cytomorphology Laboratory, Heamo-Onco-TMO Department, </institution><institution>IRCSS Istituto Giannina Gaslini, </institution></institution-wrap>Genova, Italy </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>10</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>18</volume><elocation-id>21</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>6</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>3</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated in a credit line to the data.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Tetralogy of Fallot (ToF) and Atrial Septal Defects (ASD) are the most common types of congenital heart diseases and a major cause of childhood morbidity and mortality. Cardiopulmonary bypass (CPB) is used during corrective cardiac surgery to support circulation and heart stabilization. However, this procedure triggers systemic inflammatory and stress response and consequent increased risk of postoperative complications. The aim of this study was to define the molecular bases of ToF and ASD pathogenesis and response to CPB and identify new potential biomarkers.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">Comparative transcriptome analysis of right atrium specimens collected from 10 ToF and 10 ASD patients was conducted before (Pre-CPB) and after (Post-CPB) corrective surgery. Total RNA isolated from each sample was individually hybridized on Affymetrix HG-U133 Plus Array Strips containing 38,500 unique human genes. Differences in the gene expression profiles and functional enrichment/network analyses were assessed using bioinformatic tools. qRT-PCR analysis was used to validate gene modulation.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">Pre-CPB samples showed significant differential expression of a total of 72 genes, 28 of which were overexpressed in ToF and 44 in ASD. According to Gene Ontology annotation, the mostly enriched biological processes were represented by matrix organization and cell adhesion in ToF and by muscle development and contractility in ASD specimens. GSEA highlighted the specific enrichment of hypoxia gene sets in ToF samples, pointing to a role for hypoxia in disease pathogenesis. The post-CPB myocardium exhibited significant alterations in the expression profile of genes related to transcription regulation, growth/apoptosis, inflammation, adhesion/matrix organization, and oxidative stress. Among them, only 70 were common to the two disease groups, whereas 110 and 24 were unique in ToF and ASD, respectively. Multiple functional interactions among differentially expressed gene products were predicted by network analysis. Interestingly, gene expression changes in ASD samples followed a consensus hypoxia profile.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par4">Our results provide a comprehensive view of gene reprogramming in right atrium tissues of ToF and ASD patients before and after CPB, defining specific molecular pathways underlying disease pathophysiology and myocardium response to CPB. These findings have potential translational value because they identify new candidate prognostic markers and targets for tailored cardioprotective post-surgical therapies.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Gene expression profiling</kwd><kwd>Congenital heart disease</kwd><kwd>Cardiopulmonary bypass</kwd><kwd>Atrial myocardium</kwd><kwd>Hypoxia</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100004710</institution-id><institution>Fondazione Umberto Veronesi</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Italian Ministry of Health</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par22">Congenital heart diseases (CHDs) are the most frequent types of birth defects in humans, affecting over 1% of all live births worldwide (estimated incidence 8 per 1000), and represent a major cause of morbidity and mortality in children [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. CHDs can be classified into three broad categories: cyanotic heart disease, left-sided obstructive defects, and septation defects [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Tetralogy of Fallot (ToF) is the main form of cyanotic CHDs (estimated incidence 5 per 10,000 live births), characterized by a conal septum malalignment which leads to aorta rightward deviation. This defect results in a large ventricular septal malformation and stenosis of the pulmonary valve with consequent pressure and volume overload of the right ventricle, adaptive ventricular hypertrophy associated with reduced pulmonary flow, impaired myocardial nutrient and oxygen supply, and finally heart failure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. ToF patients require primary surgical repair during the first year of life to close the ventricular defect and remove the obstruction in order to relieve hypoxemia, eliminate the hypertrophic stimulus, and preserve the function of the right ventricle. However, long-term complications and probability of secondary corrective surgery later in life remain important clinical challenges [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Atrial Septal Defects (ASD) are the third most common types of CHD (estimated incidence 10 per 10,000 live births). They are characterized by several defects in the cardiac terminations of systemic and pulmonary veins and in the intratrial septum, which result in the communication of the heart left and right sides and blood shunt between pulmonary and systemic circulations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Only a few ASD patients present with severe problems during infancy and require primary cardiac surgery within the first year of life to prevent the onset of irreversible changes in the pulmonary vasculature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Most ASD patients are asymptomatic throughout infancy and childhood but may develop complications that increase with age, which include ventricle dysfunction, atrial arrhythmias, pulmonary hypertension, and heart failure. Life expectancy is reduced if defects remain untreated, recommending surgery at the age of 4/5&#x000a0;years [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Surgical closure of atrial septal defects is usually associated with normal life expectancy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>].</p><p id="Par23">Cardiopulmonary bypass (CPB) with aortic crossclamping (AoXC) and hypothermic cardioplegic arrest (CA) is a commonly used technique in cardiac surgery to support circulation and heart stabilization and maintain organ perfusion. It facilitates the repair of cardiac lesions resulting in the reduction of surgical mortality and achievement of complete repair of heart defects also at an early age [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. However, despite the efforts to minimize organ damage, cardiac surgery with CPB is associated with postoperative morbidity and multiorgan dysfunction syndrome. It is well documented that CPB triggers a systemic inflammatory response, whose activation in the setting of major surgery and trauma can be exaggerated in some patients, resulting in the inappropriate recruitment and hyperactivation of leukocytes (mainly neutrophils and monocyte/macrophages), increased release of proinflammatory cytokines, excessive stimulation of the complement and coagulation systems, and endothelial dysfunction, eventually leading to unwarranted organ damage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. In addition, myocardium subjected to CA undergoes an obligate period of ischemia lasting about 1&#x000a0;h. Subsequent reperfusion of ischemic myocardium (I/R) causes the release of reactive oxygen species (ROS), apoptosis, and necrosis which can further aggravate CPB-induced inflammatory and stress response, contributing to organ dysfunction and increasing the risk of postoperative complications and myocardial failure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>].</p><p id="Par24">Although significant advances in the clinical management of ToF and ASD patients have been made in the last few decades, much remains to be elucidated regarding the molecular mechanisms underlying disease pathogenesis and myocardial response to corrective surgery with CPB. In the field of cardiomyopathy, microarray-based gene expression profiling has become an important approach for the characterization of the molecular bases of disease pathogenesis, progression, and response to surgery/therapy, contributing to the identification of novel biomarkers essential for the refinement of patient diagnostic and prognostic evaluation and the design of tailored treatment strategies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>].</p><p id="Par25">In this study, we conducted a comparative transcriptome analysis of right atrium biopsies obtained from children affected by ToF and ASD undergoing primary surgical defect repair before and after CPB. Our results define disease-specific myocardial transcriptional signatures and identify distinct patterns of gene expression occurring in response to CPB in the two pathologies, providing a framework for the identification of new potential prognostic markers and targets for tailored post-surgical treatment strategies.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Study population</title><p id="Par26">Ten patients affected by cyanotic ToF (6 males, 4 females, mean age 1&#x000a0;year) and ten patients affected by ASD (4 males, 6 females, mean age 5&#x000a0;years) undergoing primary corrective surgery with CPB at the Department of Cardiosurgery of the Gaslini Institute were enrolled in the study from July 2008 through December 2013. The surgical procedure used has been previously standardized, as reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. ToF patients were classified as cyanotic according to arterial blood oxygen saturation. All patients were in stable conditions without preoperative respiratory or ionotropic support and were admitted to the intensive care unit of the Gaslini Institute after surgery. The protocol was reviewed and approved by the Ethical Committee of the Gaslini Institute prior to starting the study, and the procedures were carried out according to the approved guidelines and in adherence to the general ethical principles set forth in the&#x000a0;Declaration of Helsinki. Written informed consent was obtained from the parents or a legally authorized representatives of the patients enrolled in the study prior to sample collection.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Tissue sample collection</title><p id="Par27">Pre- and post-operative biopsy specimens from right atrium were collected at the time of surgical defect correction. The first biopsy was harvested about 5&#x000a0;min before AoXC (Pre-CPB), whereas the second biopsy was harvested about 15&#x000a0;min after AoXC removal (Post-CPB) (average CPB duration did not exceed 70&#x000a0;min). Specimens were harvested with cold sharp dissection, immediately snap-frozen in liquid nitrogen, and stored until use at &#x02212;&#x000a0;80&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C in the Integrating Tissueomics Biobank (BIT)&#x02013;Gaslini, which was set up for storing tissue and genomic specimens for diagnostic and research purposes under the initial approval of the Ethical Committee of the Gaslini Institute and the subsequent ratification of the Ethical Committee of the Regione Liguria (Approval 8/2014). Atrial sampling was&#x000a0;atraumatic, provided full-thickness specimens, and was clinically reproducible, as previously reported by Voisine et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>RNA isolation and cRNA synthesis</title><p id="Par28">Tissue specimens were mechanically homogenized in lysis reagent from Qiagen (Milano, Italy). The procedure of RNA isolation and cRNA synthesis has been previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Briefly, total RNA was purified and DNase treated using the RNeasy MiniKit (Quigen), controlled for integrity by nanoelectrophoresis using an Agilent 2100 Bioanalyzer (Agilent Technologies Europe, Waldbroon, Germany), quantified by spectrophotometry using a NanoDrop ND-1000 (NanoDrop Technologies, Wilmington, USA), and reverse-transcribed into double-stranded cDNA on a GeneAmp PCR System 2700 thermal cycler (Applied Biosystems, Milano) using the one-cycle cDNA synthesis kit (Affymetrix, Milano). cDNA was purified, transcribed into cRNA, and biotin labeled using the GeneChip IVT kit (Affymetrix). Labeled cRNA was fragmented according to Affymetrix&#x02019;s instructions.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>GeneChip hybridization and microarray data analysis</title><p id="Par29">Gene expression profiling of the samples was performed by microarray analysis as detailed previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Briefly, fragmented cRNA was hybridized on Affymetrix Human Genome U133 Plus PM Array Strips (Thermo Fisher) containing 54,675 probe sets coding for 47,000 transcripts and variants, including 38,500 unique human genes on a single array. Chips were stained with streptavidin&#x02013;phycoerythrin (Invitrogen Life Technologies, Milano) and scanned using an Affymetrix GeneChip Scanner 3000. Expression values were quantified, and data were processed by RMA normalization utilizing the &#x02018;Affy&#x02019; R package. Statistical analysis using Student&#x02019;s t-test was performed to identify differentially expressed probe sets. Specifically, unpaired Student&#x02019;s t-test was used to assess whether there were significant differentially expressed probe sets between ASD and ToF, whereas paired Student&#x02019;s t-test was used to identify differences in the probe set expression levels between Pre-CPB and Post-CPB in ASD or in ToF. Student T test was calculated by GraphPad Prism version 6.0 for Windows (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.graphpad.com">http://www.graphpad.com</ext-link>). We corrected the p value by Benjamini- Hochberg method for false discovery rate (FDR) control. Only probe sets differences that passed the test at a FDR&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;0.05&#x000a0;were considered significant.&#x000a0;Fold-change (FC) was calculated to determine the magnitude of the difference.&#x000a0;Probe sets were considered significantly differentially expressed if they exhibited a&#x000a0;FDR&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;0.05&#x000a0;and FC&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;2 or&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;0.5.&#x000a0;We filtered out probe sets having a coefficient of variation (CV) lower than 0.7, because they did not substantially change between the two diseases under consideration, and those having an expression value lower than 100 in at least 20% of the samples because they were not sufficiently expressed in our data set to provide a reliable transcriptional level. Filtering was carried out by &#x02018;GeneFilter&#x02019; R package, as described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. We converted the Affymetrix probe sets into the corresponding gene symbol by Netaffix tool. When multiple probe sets were associated with the same gene symbol, the probe set with the highest expression signal was considered [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. The full set of data from each microarray experiment has been deposited at the Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO) public repository at NCBI (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov</ext-link>) and can be accessed to through GEO Series accession number GSE132176. Differentially expressed genes (DEGs) were visualized by heat-map representation obtained by Morpheus heat map building tool (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.broadinstitute.org/cancer/software/morpheus/">http://www.broadinstitute.org/cancer/software/morpheus/</ext-link>) available from the Broad Institute.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Gene Ontology annotation and gene network analysis</title><p id="Par30">Gene Ontology (GO) enrichment analysis of DEGs was carried out using the Cytoscape BINGO plugin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. DEGs were classified according to the biological process and cellular component GO collections. Terms with p value and FDR lower than 0.05 were considered significantly enriched. Correction for multiple hypothesis testing was carried out by the Benjamini&#x02013;Hochberg method, as described by Maere et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. The Search Tool for the Retrieval of Interactive Gene Database (STRING-DB) Version 9.1. (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://string-db.org/">http://string-db.org/</ext-link>) was used to construct functional interaction networks among DEGs-encoded proteins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. To this end, we performed a STRING-DB multiple proteins search using the DEGs as input list and extracted all the potential connection among encoded proteins. We set up a required minimum interaction score of 0.7 (high confidence) and considered significant an enrichment p-value&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;0.05.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Gene set enrichment analysis</title><p id="Par31">Gene Set Enrichment Analysis (GSEA) was carried out on all probe sets of the Affymetrix HG-U133 Plus 2.0 PM GeneChip microarray to evaluate the enrichment of hypoxia-related genes in ToF and ASD expression profiles, as described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. To this end, we built a custom gene set collection, named &#x0201c;HeartHypoxia&#x0201d;, by selecting 109 gene sets among the curated collections of the Broad Institute Molecular Signature v5 Database (MSigDB) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Available gene sets were listed using &#x0201c;hypoxia&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;heart&#x0201d; as keywords. We considered gene sets containing between 15 and 500 probe sets and collapsed the expression set to gene symbol before running the analysis. An enrichment with FDR q-values&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;0.2 and nominal p values&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;0.05 was considered significant.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Real-time RT-PCR</title><p id="Par32">cDNA was prepared from purified total RNA using SuperScript Double-Stranded cDNA synthesis kit (Invitrogen). Quantitative real time PCR (qRT-PCR) was performed on a 7500 Real Time PCR System (Applied) using SYBR Green PCR Master Mix and sense/antisense oligonucleotide primers synthesized by TIBMolbiol (Genova), as previously detailed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. Expression data were normalized on the values obtained in parallel for three reference genes (actin related protein 2/3 complex subunit 1B, ARCP1B; lysosomal-associated multispanning membrane protein-5, LAPTM5; and ribosomal protein S3, RSP3), using the Bestkeeper software, and relative expression values were calculated using Q-gene software, as described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec10" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec11"><title>Comparative transcriptome analysis of atrium specimens from ToF and ASD patients</title><p id="Par33">To identify genes involved in ToF and ASD pathogenesis, we compared by microarray analysis the transcriptome of right atrial specimens collected from 10 ToF and 10 ASD patients at the time of corrective surgery. cRNA derived from total RNA isolated from each sample was individually hybridized to human Affymetrix HG-U133 Plus PM Array Strips (GEO database accession number GSE132176), and raw data were processed as described in &#x0201c;<xref rid="Sec2" ref-type="sec">Methods</xref>&#x0201d; section. Probe set expression differences of&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;twofold and p-value&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;0.05 between ToF and ASD samples were considered statistically significant. Using these selection criteria, we identified a total of 89 differentially expressed probe sets (see Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S1) corresponding to 72 unique DEGs in ToF vs ASD samples. Among them, 28 were overexpressed in ToF respect to ASD patients while 44 were overexpressed in ASD respect to ToF. Heat map visualization of the expression values showed a clear separation between the two diagnostic groups, with substantial homogeneity among patients affected by the same pathology (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Heat-map representation of DEGs in ToF compared to ASD atrium tissues. Data shown are relative to gene expression of atrium tissues from 10 ToF and 10 ASD patients undergoing cardiac surgery profiled by microarray. The heat-map shows the expression levels of genes differentially expressed in ToF vs ASD samples. Expression levels were z-scored and log2 transformed and are indicated by a 2-color scale ranging from blue (lowest values) to red (highest values). The 2-color scale is reported in the horizontal bar at the top of the figure. Each column represents a patient and each row represents a gene. The gene symbols are listed on the right side of the heatmap, whereas the disease type is indicated on the top side</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12967_2020_2210_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p><p id="Par34">GO analysis was then carried out on the 72 DEGs to assess their biologic function. GO terms with significant enrichment score were selected. The analysis based on the biological process collection identified a total of 86 significantly enriched (p-value&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;0.05 and FDR&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;0.05) GO terms that differed between the two disease groups (70 in ToF and 16 in ASD). As depicted in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a, the mostly enriched biologic process in ToF atrial samples was represented by developmental processes, followed by extracellular matrix (ECM) organization, response to wounding and to endogenous stimulus, and regulation of cell adhesion. Conversely, the top functional processes in ASD samples were implicated in muscle development and contraction. GO annotation for cellular components was also evaluated, identifying 37 significantly enriched GO terms (18 in ToF and 19 in ADS) among which extracellular region and extracellular matrix were dominant in ToF, whereas extracellular region, extracellular space, and cell surface were mostly enriched in ASD (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Functional enrichment and network analyses of DEGs in ToF vs ASD samples. <bold>a</bold> GO enrichment analysis. Genes showing at least twofold expression differences between ToF and ADS specimens were analyzed using the GO biological process (BP, <italic>full columns</italic>) and cellular component (CC, <italic>empty columns</italic>) collections. A GO term was significantly enriched if p-value&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;0.05 and FDR&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;0.05. Genes could be comprised in more than one term depending on the function of the encoded protein. The graph shows the most relevant GO terms. The GO term name is reported on the <italic>y</italic>-<italic>axis</italic>; the number of enriched DEGs for each term is indicated on the <italic>x</italic>-<italic>axis</italic>. GO terms are listed by decreasing number of DEGs. The p value for each GO term is indicated. <bold>b</bold> Network analysis. The STRING-DB software was used to construct functional interaction networks among DEGs products. Networks are displayed graphically as nodes (DEGs products) and edges (predicted protein&#x02013;protein associations). Colored nodes indicate query DEGs and first shell of interactors. Filled nodes indicate some 3D structure known or predicted. The color of the edge indicates the type of interaction inferred by experimental evidence (<italic>magenta lines</italic>), text-mining (<italic>light green lines</italic>), curated databases (<italic>cyan lines</italic>), encoded-protein homology (<italic>purple lines</italic>), and co-expression (<italic>violet lines</italic>). The thickness of the line indicates the degree of confidence prediction of the association. Only associations with a high degree of confidence (0.7) are displayed in the plot</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12967_2020_2210_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p><p id="Par35">Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> shows a selection of DEGs in the two disease types.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Relative expression of selected DEGs in ToF vs ASD specimens</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Function</th><th align="left">Gene symbol</th><th align="left">Gene description</th><th align="left">Fold change<sup>a</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><italic>ToF</italic></td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="15">Matrix organization and cell adhesion</td><td align="left">ELN</td><td align="left">Elastin</td><td char="." align="char">3.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left">POSTN</td><td align="left">Periostin, osteoblast specific factor</td><td char="." align="char">3.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ADAMTS5</td><td align="left">ADAM metallopeptidase with thrombospondin type 1 motif, 5</td><td char="." align="char">3.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left">COL1A1</td><td align="left">Collagen, type I, alpha 1</td><td char="." align="char">3.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left">COL1A2</td><td align="left">Collagen, type I, alpha 2</td><td char="." align="char">2.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ADAMTS2</td><td align="left">ADAM metallopeptidase with thrombospondin type 1 motif, 2</td><td char="." align="char">2.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">COL5A1</td><td align="left">Collagen, type V, alpha 1</td><td char="." align="char">2.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left">VCAN</td><td align="left">Versican</td><td char="." align="char">2.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left">COL5A2</td><td align="left">Collagen, type V, alpha 2</td><td char="." align="char">2.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left">MMP16</td><td align="left">Matrix metallopeptidase 16 (membrane-inserted)</td><td char="." align="char">2.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left">NID1</td><td align="left">Nidogen 1</td><td char="." align="char">2.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">COL4A4</td><td align="left">Collagen, type IV, alpha 4</td><td char="." align="char">2.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">COL4A1</td><td align="left">Collagen, type IV, alpha 1</td><td char="." align="char">2.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">THBS1</td><td align="left">Thrombospondin 1</td><td char="." align="char">2.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">LAMA2</td><td align="left">Laminin, alpha 2</td><td char="." align="char">2.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5">Trascription factors</td><td align="left">EGR1</td><td align="left">Early growth response 1</td><td char="." align="char">4.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left">FOS</td><td align="left">FBJ murine osteosarcoma viral oncogene homolog</td><td char="." align="char">4.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">HIF3A</td><td align="left">Hypoxia inducible factor 3, alpha subunit</td><td char="." align="char">2.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">IER2</td><td align="left">Immediate early response 2</td><td char="." align="char">2.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">NFIL3</td><td align="left">Nuclear factor, interleukin 3 regulated</td><td char="." align="char">2.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4"><italic>ASD</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="11">Muscle development and contraction</td><td align="left">ACTA1</td><td align="left">Actin, alpha 1, skeletal muscle</td><td char="." align="char">9.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left">NEB</td><td align="left">Nebulin</td><td char="." align="char">7.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left">MYOT</td><td align="left">Myotilin</td><td char="." align="char">6.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left">MYL3</td><td align="left">Myosin, light chain 3, alkali; ventricular, skeletal, slow</td><td char="." align="char">5.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">KLHL41</td><td align="left">Kelch-like family member 41</td><td char="." align="char">4.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">MUSTN1</td><td align="left">Musculoskeletal, embryonic nuclear protein 1</td><td char="." align="char">4.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">PPP1R3A</td><td align="left">Protein phosphatase 1, regulatory subunit 3A</td><td char="." align="char">3.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ENO3</td><td align="left">Enolase 3 (beta, muscle)</td><td char="." align="char">3.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SYNPO2</td><td align="left">Synaptopodin 2</td><td char="." align="char">3.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left">MYH11</td><td align="left">Myosin, heavy chain 11, smooth muscle</td><td char="." align="char">2.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">MURC</td><td align="left">Muscle-related coiled-coil protein</td><td char="." align="char">2.0</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Comparative analysis of gene expression in ToF and ASD samples was conducted as described in &#x0201c;<xref rid="Sec2" ref-type="sec">Methods</xref>&#x0201d; section. A function, a gene symbol, a brief gene description, and the fold change values are specified for each gene</p><p>Genes for each functional category are ordered according to decreasing fold changes</p><p><sup>a</sup>Fold change&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;2 are considered significant</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par36">Among them, genes coding for different types of collagen, namely COL1A1, COL1A2, COL5A1, COL5A2, COL4A1, and COL4A4, and matrix metalloproteinases (MMPs), such as ADAMTS5, ADAMTS2, and MMP16, were significantly upregulated in ToF samples. ToF profile also revealed significant increased expression of genes with transcription regulatory activity, such&#x000a0;as EGR1, FOS, and HIF-3&#x003b1;. Functional interactions among DEGs-encoded proteins involved in matrix organization/cell adhesion and transcription regulation were predicted by network analysis (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b). In contrast, the most relevant upregulated genes in ASD were those coding for constituents of the muscle contractile apparatus such as ACTA1, MYOT, MYL3, MUSTN1, MYH11, NEB, MURC, and ENO3 (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>), whose functional interactions were predicted by network analysis (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b).</p><p id="Par37">To confirm differential gene expression in the two pathologies, mRNA levels of a representative gene, EGR1, were quantified by qRT-PCR in 6 ToF and 6 ASD samples analyzed by microarray. This gene was chosen based on its known association with hypoxia and role in myocardial injury [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. As shown in the Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Figure S1A, qRT-PCR confirmed EGR1 overexpression in ToF respect to ASD patients. The extent of modulation was higher according to qRT-PCR respect to Affymetrix data, in agreement with previous findings showing that microarray can often underestimate the degree of gene regulation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>].</p><p id="Par38">Previous evidence demonstrated chronic exposure to hypoxia in cyanotic ToF patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. GSEA was applied to determine the contribution of hypoxia to ToF myocardial transcriptome. One hundred nine gene sets belonging to all curated collections of the MSigDB v5 database were selected utilizing &#x0201c;hypoxia&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;heart&#x0201d; as keywords. Fourteen hypoxia-related gene sets were significantly enriched (FDR q-value&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;0.2 and nominal p-value&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;0.05) in the transcriptional profile of atrial tissues from ToF compared to ASD patients (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>), whereas none was found significantly enriched in the ASD compared to ToF transcriptome (data not shown).<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Hypoxia-related gene sets enriched in ToF vs ASD samples</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">GSEA term<sup>a</sup></th><th align="left">NOM p-val<sup>b</sup></th><th align="left">FDR q-val<sup>c</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">BIOCARTA_AMI_PATHWAY</td><td char="." align="char">0.00</td><td char="." align="char">0.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left">FARDIN_HYPOXIA_11</td><td char="." align="char">0.00</td><td char="." align="char">0.03</td></tr><tr><td align="left">IKEDA_MIR30_TARGETS_DN</td><td char="." align="char">0.02</td><td char="." align="char">0.09</td></tr><tr><td align="left">QI_HYPOXIA</td><td char="." align="char">0.00</td><td char="." align="char">0.14</td></tr><tr><td align="left">MAINA_VHL_TARGETS_DN</td><td char="." align="char">0.01</td><td char="." align="char">0.16</td></tr><tr><td align="left">KIM_HYPOXIA</td><td char="." align="char">0.02</td><td char="." align="char">0.16</td></tr><tr><td align="left">MENSE_HYPOXIA_UP</td><td char="." align="char">0.02</td><td char="." align="char">0.17</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ELVIDGE_HYPOXIA_BY_DMOG_UP</td><td char="." align="char">0.05</td><td char="." align="char">0.18</td></tr><tr><td align="left">MANALO_HYPOXIA_UP</td><td char="." align="char">0.02</td><td char="." align="char">0.18</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ELVIDGE_HIF1A_AND_HIF2A_TARGETS_DN</td><td char="." align="char">0.01</td><td char="." align="char">0.19</td></tr><tr><td align="left">JIANG_HYPOXIA_VIA_VHL</td><td char="." align="char">0.04</td><td char="." align="char">0.19</td></tr><tr><td align="left">HARRIS_HYPOXIA</td><td char="." align="char">0.04</td><td char="." align="char">0.19</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ELVIDGE_HIF1A_TARGETS_DN</td><td char="." align="char">0.00</td><td char="." align="char">0.19</td></tr><tr><td align="left">LEONARD_HYPOXIA</td><td char="." align="char">0.04</td><td char="." align="char">0.20</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Gene sets are ordered according to increasing FDR q-val</p><p><sup>a</sup>Gene sets enriched in the GSEA analysis. Gene sets belonging to all curated collections of the MSigDB were selected using the keywords &#x0201c;hypoxia&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;heart&#x0201d; and filtering out those having less than 15 probe sets and more than 500</p><p><sup>b</sup>NOM p-val measures the statistical significance of the normalized enriched score by an empirical permutation test using 1.000 gene permutations. Values&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;0.05 are considered significant</p><p><sup>c</sup>FDR q-value is the estimated probability that the normalized enrichment score represents a false positive finding. Values&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;0.2 are considered significant</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par39">A representative enrichment plot, &#x0201c;FARDIN_HYPOXIA_11&#x0201d; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>], showing a clear enrichment of the Fardin gene set at the top of the ranked list of genes is presented in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> for a visual inspection of the GSEA results. These data indicate that gene expression changes in ToF atrium samples follow a consensus hypoxia transcriptional profile.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>GSEA enrichment plot for the &#x0201c;FARDIN_HYPOXIA_11&#x0201d; gene set in the ToF transcriptome. The ranked list of genes identified by microarray analysis between the ToF and the ASD transcriptomes was compared with previously published gene sets of hypoxia-regulated genes by GSEA. Enrichment plot of the &#x0201c;FARDIN_HYPOXIA_11&#x0201d; gene set is shown. Signal2noise was used as metric to generate the ranked gene list</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12967_2020_2210_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p><p id="Par40">Taken together, these results reveal disease-specific gene signatures in atrium samples from ToF and ASD patients, with overexpression of genes involved in myocardium remodeling and coding for hypoxia targets in the former and genes related to myocardium contractility and function in the latter.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Gene expression changes induced by CPB in the ToF and ASD myocardium</title><p id="Par41">Limited information is currently available on the molecular mechanisms mediating CPB pathogenic effects in ToF and ASD. To address this issue, we compared the transcriptional profile of right atrium tissues from ToF and ASD patients before (Pre-CPB) and after (Post-CPB) surgery. A total of 267 and 136 probe sets were identified as differentially regulated in Post- vs Pre-CPB samples from ToF and ASD patients, respectively (see Additional file <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>: Table S2 and Additional file <xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">4</xref>: Table S3), which corresponded to 180 and 94 unique DEGs. As shown by the Venn diagram in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>, 70 DEGs were commonly modulated by CPB in the two disease groups, whereas 110 and 24 were identified as specifically affected in ToF and ASD, respectively. Gene up-regulation was the predominant change that differentiated Post-CPB from Pre-CPB samples, although a large subset of genes was also found downregulated in ASD patients (Tables&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>, <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>, and <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>; Additional file <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>: Table S2 and Additional file <xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">4</xref>: Table S3). These data indicate that CPB induces distinct cardiac gene expression changes in these two forms of CHDs.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>Venn diagram of DEGs induced by CPB in ToF and ASD atrium tissues. The gene expression profile of atrium tissues from 10 ToF and 10 ADS patients was compared before and after CPB, as described in &#x0201c;<xref rid="Sec2" ref-type="sec">Methods</xref>&#x0201d; section. The diagram shows the number of common and unique DEGs in Post-CBP vs Pre-CBP samples in the two patient groups</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12967_2020_2210_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Relative expression of selected genes commonly regulated in&#x000a0;Post- vs Pre-CPB right atrial samples from ToF and ASD patients</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Function</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">Gene symbol</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">Gene description</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Fold change<sup>a</sup></th></tr><tr><th align="left">ToF</th><th align="left">ASD</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="22">Trascription regulation</td><td align="left">ATF3</td><td align="left">Activating transcription factor 3</td><td char="." align="char">35.8</td><td align="left">13.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left">EGR3</td><td align="left">Early growth response 3</td><td char="." align="char">27.0</td><td align="left">13.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">NR4A2</td><td align="left">Nuclear receptor subfamily 4, group A, member 2</td><td char="." align="char">20.7</td><td align="left">18.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">NR4A3</td><td align="left">Nuclear receptor subfamily 4, group A, member 3</td><td char="." align="char">19.6</td><td align="left">4.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">FOSB</td><td align="left">FBJ murine osteosarcoma viral oncogene homolog B</td><td char="." align="char">14.9</td><td align="left">28.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">MAFF</td><td align="left">v-maf avian musculoaponeurotic fibrosarcoma oncogene homolog F</td><td char="." align="char">12.0</td><td align="left">8.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left">JUNB</td><td align="left">Jun B proto-oncogene</td><td char="." align="char">10.3</td><td align="left">9.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left">EGR2</td><td align="left">Early growth response 2</td><td char="." align="char">9.8</td><td align="left">5.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left">EGR1</td><td align="left">Early growth response 1</td><td char="." align="char">8.8</td><td align="left">20.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left">NR4A1</td><td align="left">Nuclear receptor subfamily 4, group A, member 1</td><td char="." align="char">6.5</td><td align="left">5.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">NFKBIZ</td><td align="left">Nuclear factor of kappa light polypeptide gene enhancer in B-cells inhibitor, zeta</td><td char="." align="char">6.3</td><td align="left">2.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">MYC</td><td align="left">v-myc avian myelocytomatosis viral oncogene homolog</td><td char="." align="char">6.0</td><td align="left">3.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">FOS</td><td align="left">FBJ murine osteosarcoma viral oncogene homolog</td><td char="." align="char">5.9</td><td align="left">13.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left">JUN</td><td align="left">Jun proto-oncogene</td><td char="." align="char">5.9</td><td align="left">3.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left">KLF4</td><td align="left">Kruppel-like factor 4 (gut)</td><td char="." align="char">5.7</td><td align="left">4.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CSRNP1</td><td align="left">Cysteine-serine-rich nuclear protein 1</td><td char="." align="char">5.6</td><td align="left">4.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">IER3</td><td align="left">Immediate early response 3</td><td char="." align="char">4.6</td><td align="left">2.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">FOSL2</td><td align="left">FOS-like antigen 2</td><td char="." align="char">4.5</td><td align="left">2.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">IER2</td><td align="left">Immediate early response</td><td char="." align="char">2 4.0</td><td align="left">5.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">HES1</td><td align="left">Hes family bHLH transcription factor 1</td><td char="." align="char">3.9</td><td align="left">2.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">NFIL3</td><td align="left">Nuclear factor, interleukin 3 regulated</td><td char="." align="char">3.9</td><td align="left">2.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left">KLF2</td><td align="left">Kruppel-like factor 2</td><td char="." align="char">2.3</td><td align="left">2.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="12">Regulation of cell growth and apoptosis</td><td align="left">MIR21/VMP1</td><td align="left">MicroRNA 21/vacuole membrane protein 1</td><td char="." align="char">11.4</td><td align="left">5</td></tr><tr><td align="left">DUSP5</td><td align="left">Dual specificity phosphatase 5</td><td char="." align="char">5.4</td><td align="left">3.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">GADD45B</td><td align="left">Growth arrest and DNA-damage-inducible, beta</td><td char="." align="char">5.2</td><td align="left">2.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CDKN1A</td><td align="left">Cyclin-dependent kinase inhibitor 1A (p21, Cip1)</td><td char="." align="char">5.1</td><td align="left">2.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left">MIR22/MIR22HG</td><td align="left">MicroRNA 22/MIR22 host gene</td><td char="." align="char">4.5</td><td align="left">2.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">MCL1</td><td align="left">Myeloid cell leukemia 1</td><td char="." align="char">4.4</td><td align="left">2.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left">MIR23A/MIR24-2</td><td align="left">MicroRNA 23a/24-2</td><td char="." align="char">4.3</td><td align="left">3.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">BTG2</td><td align="left">BTG family, member 2</td><td char="." align="char">4.0</td><td align="left">2.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left">DUSP6</td><td align="left">Dual specificity phosphatase 6</td><td char="." align="char">3.7</td><td align="left">3.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CCNL1</td><td align="left">Cyclin L1</td><td char="." align="char">3.7</td><td align="left">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">PPP1R15A/GADD34</td><td align="left">Protein phosphatase 1, regulatory subunit 15A/growth arrest and DNA-damage-inducible</td><td char="." align="char">3.3</td><td align="left">2.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">DUSP1</td><td align="left">Dual specificity phosphatase 1</td><td char="." align="char">2.2</td><td align="left">2.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="8">Inflammatory response</td><td align="left">SOCS3</td><td align="left">Suppressor of cytokine signaling 3</td><td char="." align="char">23.0</td><td align="left">24.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left">PTGS2</td><td align="left">Prostaglandin-endoperoxide synthase 2 (prostaglandin G/H synthase and cyclooxygenase)</td><td char="." align="char">12.2</td><td align="left">6.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CCL2</td><td align="left">Chemokine (C&#x02013;C motif) ligand 2</td><td char="." align="char">10.4</td><td align="left">6.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CXCL2</td><td align="left">Chemokine (C&#x02013;X&#x02013;C motif) ligand 2</td><td char="." align="char">9.3</td><td align="left">11.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left">RGS1</td><td align="left">Regulator of G-protein signaling 1</td><td char="." align="char">4.0</td><td align="left">4.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">RGS2</td><td align="left">Regulator of G-protein signaling 2</td><td char="." align="char">3.6</td><td align="left">2.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C3</td><td align="left">Complement component 3</td><td char="." align="char">0.4</td><td align="left">0.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ITLN1</td><td align="left">Intelectin 1 (galactofuranose binding)</td><td char="." align="char">0.05</td><td align="left">0.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5">Cell adhesion and matrix organization</td><td align="left">ADAMTS1</td><td align="left">ADAM metallopeptidase with thrombospondin type 1 motif, 1</td><td char="." align="char">6.5</td><td align="left">3.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CYR61 (CCN1)</td><td align="left">Cysteine-rich, angiogenic inducer, 61</td><td char="." align="char">5.5</td><td align="left">5.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">THBD</td><td align="left">Thrombomodulin</td><td char="." align="char">4.6</td><td align="left">2.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left">EFEMP1</td><td align="left">EGF containing fibulin-like extracellular matrix protein 1</td><td char="." align="char">0.4</td><td align="left">0.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left">COL3A1</td><td align="left">Collagen, type III, alpha 1</td><td char="." align="char">0.2</td><td align="left">0.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">Antioxidant activity</td><td align="left">MT1M</td><td align="left">Metallothionein 1M</td><td char="." align="char">14.3</td><td align="left">5.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left">NCOA7</td><td align="left">Nuclear receptor coactivator 7</td><td char="." align="char">4.7</td><td align="left">2.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">MT2A</td><td align="left">Metallothionein 2A</td><td char="." align="char">3.1</td><td align="left">2.0</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Comparative analysis of gene expression in Pre-CPB and Post-CPB ToF and ASD samples was conducted as described in &#x0201c;<xref rid="Sec2" ref-type="sec">Methods</xref>&#x0201d; section. A function, a gene symbol, a brief gene description, and fold change values are specified for each gene</p><p>Genes for each functional category are ordered according to decreasing fold changes of ToF genes</p><p><sup>a</sup>Fold change was calculated as the ratio between the mean expression value of Post-CPB and Pre-CPB samples for each gene. Fold change&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;2 or&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;0.5 are considered significant</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>Relative expression of genes selectively modulated in Post- vs Pre-CPB ToF samples</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Function</th><th align="left">Gene symbol</th><th align="left">Gene description</th><th align="left">Fold change<sup>a</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="12">Transcription regulation</td><td align="left">IRF1</td><td align="left">Interferon regulatory factor 1</td><td char="." align="char">10.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">BHLHE40</td><td align="left">Basic helix-loop-helix family, member e40</td><td char="." align="char">4.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left">MIR612/NEAT1</td><td align="left">MicroRNA 612/ nuclear paraspeckle assembly transcript 1</td><td char="." align="char">3.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left">KLF10</td><td align="left">Kruppel-like factor 10</td><td char="." align="char">3.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">BCL3/MIR8085</td><td align="left">B-cell CLL/lymphoma 3/microRNA 8085</td><td char="." align="char">3.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">IFRD1</td><td align="left">Interferon-related developmental regulator 1</td><td char="." align="char">2.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left">DDIT3</td><td align="left">DNA-damage-inducible transcript 3</td><td char="." align="char">2.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SOX9</td><td align="left">SRY (sex determining region Y)-box 9</td><td char="." align="char">2.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ETS2</td><td align="left">v-ets avian erythroblastosis virus E26 oncogene homolog 2</td><td char="." align="char">2.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CEBPB</td><td align="left">CCAAT/enhancer binding protein (C/EBP), beta</td><td char="." align="char">2.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CEBPD</td><td align="left">CCAAT/enhancer binding protein (C/EBP), delta</td><td char="." align="char">2.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">AFF4</td><td align="left">AF4/FMR2 family, member 4</td><td char="." align="char">2.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="10">Inflammatory responses</td><td align="left">CXCL8</td><td align="left">Chemokine (C-X-C motif) ligand 8</td><td char="." align="char">19.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left">IL6</td><td align="left">Interleukin 6</td><td char="." align="char">18.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left">AREG</td><td align="left">Amphiregulin</td><td char="." align="char">10.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">TNFAIP3</td><td align="left">Tumor necrosis factor, alpha-induced protein 3</td><td char="." align="char">3.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">IL1RL1</td><td align="left">Interleukin 1 receptor-like 1</td><td char="." align="char">2.8</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SQSTM1</td><td align="left">Sequestosome 1</td><td char="." align="char">2.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left">HSPA1A,1B</td><td align="left">Heat shock 70kDa protein 1A,1B</td><td char="." align="char">2.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">KDM6B</td><td align="left">Lysine (K)-specific demethylase 6B</td><td char="." align="char">2.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C1QC</td><td align="left">Complement component 1, q subcomponent, C chain</td><td char="." align="char">0.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C1QB</td><td align="left">Complement component 1, q subcomponent, B chain</td><td char="." align="char">0.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="8">Cell adhesion, cytoskeleton and matrix organization</td><td align="left">ABRA</td><td align="left">Actin-binding Rho activating protein</td><td char="." align="char">8.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left">THBS1</td><td align="left">Thrombospondin 1</td><td char="." align="char">7.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left">PDLIM3</td><td align="left">PDZ and LIM domain 3</td><td char="." align="char">5.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">MMP19</td><td align="left">Matrix metallopeptidase 19</td><td char="." align="char">4.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left">FBN2</td><td align="left">Fibrillin 2</td><td char="." align="char">2 4</td></tr><tr><td align="left">XIRP1 (CMYA1)</td><td align="left">Xin actin-binding repeat containing 1</td><td char="." align="char">3.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left">HBEGF</td><td align="left">Heparin-binding EGF-like growth factor</td><td char="." align="char">2.6</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CTNNB1</td><td align="left">Catenin (cadherin-associated protein), beta 1, 88&#x000a0;kDa</td><td char="." align="char">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="6">Antioxidant activity</td><td align="left">MT1X</td><td align="left">Metallothionein 1X</td><td char="." align="char">3.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left">MT1F</td><td align="left">Metallothionein 1F</td><td char="." align="char">3.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">MT1HL1</td><td align="left">Metallothionein 1H-like 1</td><td char="." align="char">3.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">MT1H</td><td align="left">Metallothionein 1H</td><td char="." align="char">2.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left">MT1E</td><td align="left">Metallothionein 1E</td><td char="." align="char">2.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left">MT1G</td><td align="left">Metallothionein 1G</td><td char="." align="char">2.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">DNA repair</td><td align="left">SPIDR</td><td align="left">Scaffolding protein involved in DNA repair</td><td char="." align="char">5.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left">PPP1R10</td><td align="left">Protein phosphatase 1, regulatory subunit 10</td><td char="." align="char">2.1</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Comparative analysis of gene expression in Pre-CPB and Post-CPB ToF samples was conducted as described in &#x0201c;<xref rid="Sec2" ref-type="sec">Methods</xref>&#x0201d; section. A main function, a gene symbol, a brief gene description, and the fold change values are specified for each gene</p><p>Genes for each functional category are ordered according to decreasing fold changes</p><p><sup>a</sup>Fold change was calculated as the ratio between the mean expression value of Post-ToF and Pre-ToF samples for each gene. Fold changes &#x02265;&#x000a0;2 or &#x02264;&#x000a0;0.5 are considered significant</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab5"><label>Table&#x000a0;5</label><caption><p>Relative expression of genes selectively modulated in Post- vs Pre-CPB ASD samples</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Function</th><th align="left">Gene symbol</th><th align="left">Gene description</th><th align="left">Fold change<sup>a</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5">Inflammatory response</td><td align="left">KDR (FLK1, VEGFR)</td><td align="left">Kinase insert domain receptor (type III receptor tyrosine kinase), VEGF receptor</td><td char="." align="char">0.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C4A/C4B</td><td align="left">Complement component 4A (Rodgers blood group)/4B (Chido blood group)</td><td char="." align="char">0.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CFIv</td><td align="left">Complement factor I</td><td char="." align="char">0.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CFB</td><td align="left">Complement factor B</td><td char="." align="char">0.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SLPI</td><td align="left">Secretory leukocyte peptidase inhibitor</td><td char="." align="char">0.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4">Cell adhesion</td><td align="left">PTPRF</td><td align="left">Protein tyrosine phosphatase, receptor type, F</td><td char="." align="char">0.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left">FLRT3</td><td align="left">Fibronectin leucine rich transmembrane protein 3</td><td char="." align="char">0.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">MSLN</td><td align="left">Mesothelin</td><td char="." align="char">0.16</td></tr><tr><td align="left">PRG4</td><td align="left">Proteoglycan 4</td><td char="." align="char">0.13</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Oxidative stress</td><td align="left">PTGIS</td><td align="left">Prostaglandin I2 (prostacyclin) synthase</td><td char="." align="char">0.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left">AOX1</td><td align="left">Aldehyde oxidase 1</td><td char="." align="char">0.5</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Comparative analysis of gene expression in Pre-CPB and Post-CPB ToF samples was conducted as described in &#x0201c;<xref rid="Sec2" ref-type="sec">Methods</xref>&#x0201d; section. A main function, a gene symbol, a brief gene description, and the fold change values are specified for each gene</p><p>Genes for each functional category are ordered according to decreasing fold changes</p><p><sup>a</sup>Fold change was calculated as the ratio between the mean expression value of Post-ToF and Pre-ToF samples for each gene. Fold changes &#x02265;&#x000a0;2 or &#x02264;&#x000a0;0.5 are considered significant</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par42">To gain insights into the functional processes modulated by CPB, DEGs were then analyzed by GO based on the biological process collection. We identified 61 significantly enriched processes in Post-CPB compared to Pre-CBP samples, of which 46 in ToF and 15 in ASD. Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>a shows a selection of the functional terms with the most significant enrichment score, the majority of which was represented in both ToF and ASD samples. Regulation of biologic and metabolic processes and response to stimulus were the top terms in post-CPB specimens from both groups of patients. The post-CPB transcriptional profile was also highly related to response to stress, regulation of cell proliferation, and inflammatory response, being a significant proportion of modulated genes significantly enriched in these processes in both disease states. The number of genes within all common processes was lower in ASD respect to ToF specimens. System development, regulation of transcription, and signaling pathways emerged as the main functional processes enriched exclusively in the Post-CPB ToF transcriptome, whereas Post-CPB ASD samples displayed specific enrichment of genes functionally implicated in the regulation of development process. Specific analysis of the 70 gene set common to both pathologies showed significant GO term enrichment in Post-CPB compared to Pre-CBP samples, most of which have been already identified by the analysis of all DEGs. In addition, we found a few terms, namely negative regulation of cell communication (p 5.76E&#x02212;04), organ morphogenesis (p 4.22E&#x02212;04), embryonic development (p 5.55E&#x02212;05), and regulation of cytokine production (p 1.94E&#x02212;03), specifically enriched in the common gene set (data not shown), indicating a substantial, but not complete, concordance between the analysis performed on the common and all DEGs after CPB. Multiple functional interactions among DEGs-encoded proteins were predicted by network analysis (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>b).<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;5</label><caption><p>DEGs functional enrichment/network analyses in Post-CPB vs Pre-CPB atrial samples from ToF and ASD patients. <bold>a</bold> GO enrichment analysis. Genes showing at least twofold expression changes between Post-CPB and Pre-CPB conditions were analyzed using the GO biological processes collection, as detailed in the legend of Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a. The graph shows the most relevant GO terms. The GO term name is reported on the <italic>y</italic>-<italic>axis</italic>; the number of enriched DEGs for each term is indicated on the <italic>x</italic>-<italic>axis</italic>. The <italic>blue columns</italic> represent DEGs modulated in ToF patients; the <italic>red columns</italic> represent DEGs modulated in ASD patients. GO terms are listed by decreasing number of DEGs in ToF samples. The p value for each GO term is indicated. <bold>b</bold> Network analysis. Functional interaction networks among DEGs products were constructed using the STRING-DB software as detailed in the legend of Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b. Networks are displayed graphically as nodes (DEGs products) and edges (predicted protein&#x02013;protein associations). Only associations with a high degree of confidence (0.7) are displayed in the plot</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12967_2020_2210_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p><p id="Par43">A list of the most significantly commonly regulated genes is presented in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>.</p><p id="Par44">Among them, we found genes coding for various transcription factor family members, such as ATF, JUN, JUNB, FOS, FOSL2, NR4A1, 2, 3, EGR1,2, and 3, and IER2,3, that were upregulated in response to CPB, with the highest changes observed in the ToF group. Increased expression of genes coding for molecules with a primary role in cell proliferation and apoptosis, including CDKN1A, CCNL1, GADD45B and 34, BTG2, DUSP1, DUSP5, DUSP6, MCL1, and microRNAs 21, 22, and 23A, was also shared by the two disease groups following CPB. Another important set of genes increased in Post-CPB samples from both ToF and ASD patients coded for proinflammatory and chemotactic mediators (SOCS3, PTGS2, CCL2, CXCL2, RGS1, RGS2) and for molecules with metalloprotease (CYR61, ADAMTS1) and antioxidant activity (MT1M, MT2A). Only a few genes involved in inflammatory responses and matrix organization, namely C3, ITNL1, EFEMP1, and COL3A1, showed decreased expression in response to CPB in both disease groups.</p><p id="Par45">Of the 110 genes specifically modulated by CBP in the ToF myocardium, the majority was upregulated and coded for additional regulators of transcription (such as IRF1, BHLHE40, DDIT3, ETS2, CEBPB, KLF10, BCL3, SOX9), inflammation (namely CXCL8, IL6, AREG, TNFAIP3, IL1RL1, and HSPA1A,1B), anti-oxidant response (such as MT1X, MT1F, MT1HL1, MT1H, MT1E, MT1G), cell adhesion, cytoskeleton and matrix organization (including ABRA, THBS1, XIRP1, HBEGF, and MMP19) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>).</p><p id="Par46">The complement component-coding genes, 1QB and 1QC, were the only genes selectively downregulated in Post-CPB ToF samples (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). Conversely, post-CPB ASD samples were characterized by the specific downregulation of several genes, the most relevant of which were those involved in the regulation of the complement system (C4a,/C4b, CFI, CFB) and inflammation (VEGFR, SLP1), cell adhesion (PRG4, MSLN), and oxidative stress (PTGIS and AOX1) (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>).</p><p id="Par47">To validate gene regulation in response to CPB, we analyzed by qRT-PCR a subset of genes upregulated in the two disease groups, selected because of their critical role as mediators of myocardial inflammatory damage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>], and determined their expression levels in Post-CPB respect to pre-CPB samples from 3 ToF and 3 ASD patients analyzed by microarray. As depicted in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Figure S1B, we found a 100% concordance between qRT-PCR and Affymetrix data with respect to the direction of the expression changes, with the magnitude of gene induction higher in qRT-PCR than microarray data.</p><p id="Par48">The myocardium subjected to CPB undergoes an obligate period of ischemia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. We were, thus, interested to investigate the contribution of hypoxia to the post-CPB transcriptome. To this aim, we used GSEA to determine the enrichment of hypoxia gene sets in the transcriptional profile of Post-CPB specimens. As shown in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab6" ref-type="table">6</xref>, eleven hypoxia gene sets were specifically enriched in the ASD transcriptome (FDR q-value&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;0.2 and nominal p&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;0.05), whereas none was enriched in the ToF transcriptome (data non shown).<table-wrap id="Tab6"><label>Table&#x000a0;6</label><caption><p>Hypoxia-related gene sets enriched in Post- vs Pre-CPB ASD samples</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">GSEA term<sup>a</sup></th><th align="left">NOM p-val<sup>b</sup></th><th align="left">FDR q-val<sup>c</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">GROSS_ELK3_TARGETS_DN</td><td char="." align="char">0.002</td><td char="." align="char">0.012</td></tr><tr><td align="left">CHEN_LVAD_SUPPORT_OF_FAILING_HEART_UP</td><td char="." align="char">0.018</td><td char="." align="char">0.014</td></tr><tr><td align="left">BIOCARTA_CARDIACEGF_PATHWAY</td><td char="." align="char">0.002</td><td char="." align="char">0.014</td></tr><tr><td align="left">LEONARD_HYPOXIA</td><td char="." align="char">0.002</td><td char="." align="char">0.011</td></tr><tr><td align="left">GROSS_HYPOXIA_VIA_ELK3_DN</td><td char="." align="char">0.026</td><td char="." align="char">0.030</td></tr><tr><td align="left">GROSS_HYPOXIA_VIA_ELK3_ONLY_UP</td><td char="." align="char">0.016</td><td char="." align="char">0.043</td></tr><tr><td align="left">MENSE_HYPOXIA_UP</td><td char="." align="char">0.012</td><td char="." align="char">0.042</td></tr><tr><td align="left">KRIEG_HYPOXIA_VIA_KDM3A</td><td char="." align="char">0.042</td><td char="." align="char">0.095</td></tr><tr><td align="left">HARRIS_HYPOXIA</td><td char="." align="char">0.053</td><td char="." align="char">0.096</td></tr><tr><td align="left">HU_ANGIOGENESIS_UP</td><td char="." align="char">0.048</td><td char="." align="char">0.101</td></tr><tr><td align="left">KIM_HYPOXIA</td><td char="." align="char">0.050</td><td char="." align="char">0.142</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Gene sets are ordered according to increasing FDR q-val</p><p><sup>a</sup>Gene sets enriched in the GSEA analysis. Gene sets belonging to all curated collections o f the MSigDB were selected using the keywords &#x0201c;hypoxia&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;heart&#x0201d; and filtering out those having less than 15 probe sets and more than 500 probe sets</p><p><sup>b</sup>NOM p-val measures the statistical significance of the normalized enriched score by an empirical permutation test using 1.000 gene permutations. NOM p-val&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;0.05 are considered significant</p><p><sup>c</sup>FDR q-value is the estimated probability that the normalized enrichment s core represents a false positive finding. Values &#x02264; 0.2 are considered significant</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par49">These results indicate that CPB causes profound alterations in the myocardial transcriptome of ToF and ASD patients, modulating both shared and distinct gene sets, and suggest a reprogramming response to CPB-induced acute ischemia specifically in the ASD myocardium.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec13" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par50">In the last years, several studies have demonstrated the value of myocardium transcriptome analysis for elucidating the molecular mechanisms underlying cardiovascular disease pathogenesis and identifying novel biomarkers for prognostic and therapeutic purposes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. In this study, we carry out the first comparative gene expression profiling of ToF and ASD right atrial specimens before and after surgery with CPB. Our results define disease-specific myocardial transcriptional signatures and demonstrate distinct molecular reprogramming in response to CPB in the two pathologies through the modulation of both common and unique genes involved in myocardial damage, inflammatory response, and oxidative stress.</p><p id="Par51">ToF and ASD patients could be clearly separated into two groups based on the differential expression of 72 genes, among which 28 were specifically upregulated in ToF and 44 in ASD atrial tissues. DEGs mainly coded for extracellular proteins in both disease groups, but were involved in distinct functional processes, suggesting specific adaptive transcriptional response of the heart to the defect. ToF signature displayed enrichment of genes encoding proteins involved in ECM organization and regulation of cell adhesion, whereas ASD transcriptome was characterized by the enrichment of genes coding for proteins implicated in myocardium development and contractility.</p><p id="Par52">Excessive production and deposition of ECM components represent key events in adverse cardiac remodeling, leading to fibrosis, hypertrophy, and loss of function [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. It is, thus, conceivable that abnormal expression of genes coding for various collagen types observed in ToF atrial tissues may play an important role in disease pathogenesis. Our results are consistent with and extend previous observations showing COL1A2 and COL3A1 gene upregulation in right ventricular biopsies from ToF patients compared to age-matched controls [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Increased COL1A1 gene expression was also reported in cyanotic vs acyanotic ToF right ventricles [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. Of relevance is also our evidence that MMP-coding genes were upregulated in ToF right atrium samples, given the essential contribution of ECM-degrading enzymes to cardiac remodeling and the correlation of their overexpression with the failing myocardium [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. Interestingly, MMP gene expression has been previously shown to remain unchanged or decrease in ToF right ventricles [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. These conflicting results could be explained by the different types of specimens analyzed in the two studies (atrium vs ventriculum) and origin of control samples used for comparison (ASD patients vs healthy children).</p><p id="Par53">Previous reports have demonstrated induction of ECM proteins and MMPs by hypoxia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>], a common hallmark of pathologic conditions including cardiovascular disorders [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>], and hypoxia was suggested to affect gene expression in the ToF myocardium. Dysregulation of genes involved in oxidative phosphorylation and energy metabolism, which is a general response to conditions of reduced oxygenation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>], was in fact reported in right ventricular specimens from cyanotic ToF children compared to age-matched controls [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>], and upregulation of tissue remodeling genes was demonstrated in the cyanotic respect to the acyanotic ToF myocardium [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. Hence, the observed increase in collagen and MMP genes in ToF respect to ASD could probably be ascribed to the chronic hypoxic environment of the ToF myocardium. In line with this conclusion is the finding that ToF samples exhibited significant enrichment of several hypoxia-related gene sets, including genes encoding the known hypoxia transcription factors, EGR1, FOS, and HIF-3&#x003b1;, whose overexpression has been previously implicated in cardiac ECM remodeling, myocardial I/R, and hypertrophy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>] and whose functional interaction with collagen- and MMP-coding genes was predicted by network analysis. Taken together, these data provide novel mechanistic evidence of the contribution of the cardiac chronic hypoxic state to ToF pathogenesis. On the basis of published findings suggesting age-associated changes in the expression of genes encoding molecules associated with extracellular matrix, cytoskeletal structure, collagen deposition, adhesion, and transcription in both mice and human hearts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>], it is possible that the observed gene alterations in ToF respect to ASD patients may result from a combined effect of disease state and lower patient age. Further large-scale studies are needed to specifically address this issue.</p><p id="Par54">Another significant difference between ToF and ASD transcriptomes was related to the enrichment of sarcomeric protein-coding genes in ASD atrial samples. Although only MYL3 dysregulation has been previously linked to ASD pathogenesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>], ACTA1 and MURC overexpression was reported to contribute to cardiac contractile dysfunction and conduction disturbances in mouse models [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>], whereas MYL3, MURC, and MYH11 gene mutations or copy number variants were found associated with cardiomyopathy or CHDs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. Based on this evidence, we hypothesize that the observed upregulation of contractile fiber genes in the ASD myocardium and functional interactions among their products, predicted by network analysis, are critical for disease development.</p><p id="Par55">It was documented that the use of CPB during cardiac surgery can cause both peripheral blood and cardiac gene expression pattern alterations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>], and modulation of ventricular transcriptome has been reported in ToF by Ghorbel et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. However, no data are available on CPB effects on the gene expression profile of the ASD myocardium or of ToF atrial tissues. We found significant gene expression changes in Post- vs Pre-CPB right atrial samples from both ToF and ASD patients, that were qualitatively and/or quantitatively different between the two groups suggesting that both common and distinct molecular mechanisms may underlie CPB effects in the two pathologies. Importantly, several of the identified genes have never been associated with CPB. A high degree of interactions among dysregulated gene products could be predicted, indicating that CPB affected important functional networks. Interestingly, we observed selective enrichment of hypoxia-related gene sets in the ASD transcriptome following CPB, suggesting the specific contribution of CPB-induced acute ischemia to gene reprogramming in the ASD myocardium.</p><p id="Par56">A high number of genes up-regulated by CPB in ToF and ASD coded for early regulators of transcription, the majority of which have been previously implicated in various cardiovascular pathological processes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>] and found increased in Post vs Pre-CPB cardiac tissues from adult patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. Microarray results also revealed common induction of transcription factor-coding genes whose modulation in response to CPB has not been described, among which IER2, IER3, and FOSL2 play critical role in cardiac remodeling and apopotosis, myocardial dysfunction, and heart failure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]. In addition, several transcription factor-coding genes were upregulated by CPB selectively in ToF samples, including IRF1, a member of the interferon signaling pathway with a central role in the regulation of cardiac remodeling and the induction of heart hypertrophy, fibrosis, and dysfunction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>] and proposed as a candidate biomarker in ischemic cardiomyopathy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>]. Our findings are in line with previous evidence showing increased IRF1 expression in Post-CPB biopsies from adult patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. CPB also selectively induced in ToF specimens KLF10, Bcl3, SOX9, and CEBPB genes, whose expression changes have been implicated in hypertrophic and ischenic cardiomyopathies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>], but have never been documented in response to CPB. Collectively, these findings highlight CPB-dependent activation of both shared and unique transcription pathways involved in myocardial damage in patients affected by different CHDs.</p><p id="Par57">Increased circulating levels of several proinflammatory cytokines and chemokines have been detected in the early post-CPB phase of patients undergoing heart surgery [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>] and were suggested to contribute to post-CPB systemic inflammatory response syndrome and multiorgan damage and to represent potential markers of early postoperative morbidity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>]. Interestingly, the myocardium was identified as a major source of cytokines/chemokines in patients with ischemic heart disease after CPB [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. We provide the first evidence that CCL2 and CXCL2 genes were upregulated in Post-CPB atrial tissues from both ToF and ASD patients, whereas only the ToF myocardium exhibited increased expression of IL-6 and CXCL8 genes after CPB. These data are intriguing and suggest that myocardial cytokine/chemokine gene expression may be differentially affected by CPB in distinct CHDs. Because the association of hypoxic preconditioning and oxygen stress is critical for CXCL8 and IL-6 gene regulation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>], it is conceivable that their induction in ToF is related to the preoperative chronic ischemic state of the myocardium which increases susceptibility to the effects of reoxygenation that follows CPB.</p><p id="Par58">TOFs and ASD post-CPB specimens also shared the upregulation of other genes with proinflammatory properties, such as SOCS3 and PTGS2, which encode important regulators of inflammation and may represent key mediators of myocardial cell damage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>]. Our findings extend previous evidence showing SOCS3 and PTGS2 upregulation in the left ventricles of adult ischemic hearts after CPB [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>] and suggest their potential contribution to myocardial inflammatory injury triggered by CPB in ToF and ASD. Increased expression of AREG gene in the ToF myocardium after CPB is also of note, given the role of the encoded protein in inflammation, tissue remodeling, and fibrosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>]. These results suggest the potential therapeutic efficacy of targeting these genes as a cardioprotective strategy in ToF and ASD patients undergoing CPB.</p><p id="Par59">Among genes linked to inflammation, we observed downregulation of those coding for C3, ITNL1, and SLP1, following CPB in ToF and/or ASD. Complement C3 was recently shown to contribute to myocardial function preservation and regeneration in a mouse model of chronic myocardial infarction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>]. The ITLN1-encoded circulating protein, Omentin 1, has a recognized role in cardiovascular disease as a &#x0201c;protective adipokine&#x0201d; able to ameliorate heart damage and function in patients with acute myocardial infarction and in mice models of I/R injury [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>]. SLP1 is a potent secreted inhibitor of neutrophil proteases and recruitment, shown to contribute to the recovery of post-ischemic myocardium function [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>]. ITLN1 and SLP1 products were identified as promising candidates for treatment/prevention of I/R injury and post-ischemic inflammation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>]. Based on these evidences, we can hypothesize that decreased C3, ITLN1, and SLPI gene expression may contribute to CPB-induced myocardium damage in ToF and ASD patients. Our findings support previous data showing downregulation of these genes in cardiac transcriptome of patients undergoing aortic valve replacement with CPB [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>], thus warranting further investigation.</p><p id="Par60">The complexity of myocardial response to CPB is emphasized by the overexpression of several genes encoding cardioprotective factors, such as HSPA1A,1B, RGS2, IL1RL1, and TNFAIP3, among which only HSPA1A,1B gene up-regulation was reported in earlier studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>]. HSPA1A,1B encodes the inducible HSP-70i isoform, whose role in myocardium protection against I/R injury was demonstrated in transgenic mice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>] and confirmed in cyanotic ToF patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>]. The G protein receptor regulator, RGS2, has received increasing interest as a potential therapeutic target in cardiovascular disease given to its&#x000a0;strong cardioprotective effects observed in preclinical mouse models [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>]. IL1RL1 codes for the receptor of IL-33, an important biomarker of myocardial stress, fibrosis, and chronic heart failure secreted in response to cell damage. Interaction between IL-33 and IL1RL1 in experimental models results in the reduction of myocardial fibrosis and apoptosis and the improvement of cardiac function [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>]. TNFAIP3 encodes an anti-inflammatory protein whose overexpression in the heart was shown to attenuate myocardial hypertrophic response and post-infarction remodeling and inflammation in transgenic mouse models, improving cardiac function [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>]. Our finding extend the list of genes with cardioprotective functions previously identified in response to CPB, confirming that pro-inflammatory and cardioprotective effects are highly intertwined and defining new potential markers of adaptive myocardial response to surgical stress and potential targets of postsurgical therapy in CHD patients. The higher number of cardioprotective markers detected in ToF vs ASD myocardium is probably due to its preoperative chronic ischemic state that may induce various adaptive pathways to limit tissue damage.</p><p id="Par61">Consistent with the view that CPB activates cardioprotective mechanisms in the ToF and ASD myocardium is the observation that Post- respect to Pre-CBP atrial tissues expressed higher levels of genes coding for metallothionein (MT) family members, metal-binding proteins highly inducible under stress conditions and endowed with anti-oxidant activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>]. Oxidative stress is one of the main causes of myocardial I/R injury, and reduction of ROS generated upon I/R challenge represents an important mechanism conferring cardiac cell protection from oxidative stress [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>]. MT genes upregulation may thus represent an important cardioprotective mechanism against CPB-induced oxidative stress, in agreement with previous studies in mouse models of I/R myocardial injury [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>]. Upregulation of a higher number of MT genes in ToF than ASD samples indicates a positive correlation between preoperative hypoxia and expression of antioxidant genes.</p><p id="Par62">Another important finding of this study is the upregulation in Post-CPB biopsies of a gene cluster coding for cell-cycle regulators and mediators of apoptosis. Among them, those coding for DUSP family members, CDKN1A, BTG2, GADD45B,34, and MCL-1 have been previously shown to be upregulated in human myocardial tissues&#x000a0;in response to stress and/or DNA damage and to play a role in the regulation of cardiac hypertrophy and remodeling in animal models [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>]. A cause-effect link between their enhanced expression and CPB has also been suggested [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Particularly intriguing is the observation that CPB increased the expression of genes coding for microRNAs (miRs) 21, 22, and 23. miRs are becoming increasingly recognized as key regulators of heart development and function, and altered miR expression has been linked to heart diseases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref>], including CHDs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref>]. miR-21, miR22, and miR-23 dysregulated levels have been reported to affect cardiac function and to have potential prognostic and/or therapeutic relevance in various cardiovascular disorders [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">85</xref>], although conflicting results have indicated a cardioprotective role for miR-21 and miR-22 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">86</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">87</xref>]. A recent report demonstrated changes in the heart miRNome of CHD patients after CPB [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">88</xref>]. However, our study is the first to provide specific evidence of miR-21, miR-22, and miR-23 upregulation in the post-CPB myocardium, identifying new potential molecular biomarkers and therapeutic targets for future investigations in CHDs.</p><p id="Par63">Finally, the expression pattern of genes functionally implicated in cell adhesion and cytoskeleton/matrix organization was also found modulated by CPB, further confirming activation of a remodelling response within the post-CPB myocardium. Among them, CYR61 and ADAMTS1 upregulation was shared by the two groups of patients. The secreted matricellular CYR61 protein was previously found highly expressed in remodeling atrial cardiomyocytes after myocardial infarction and proposed as an early prognostic biomarker of cardiac injury [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">89</xref>], while its mutations have been associated with ASD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">90</xref>]. ADAMTS1 protein is a metalloprotease induced in the early phase of acute myocardial infarction playing an essential role in the repair of infarcted tissue and the development of heart fibrosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">91</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">92</xref>]. Other genes selectively upregulated in the ToF myocardium, such as ABRA, XIRP1, THBS1, and HB-EGF, have been previously shown to be associated with pathological cardiac phenotypes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93">93</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95">95</xref>]. Conversely, a few adhesion-related genes were inhibited in ASD atrial samples, among which PRG4 has been found downregulated in the post-CPB ventricular trancriptome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. Collectively, our data provide the first evidence that CPB targets different genes involved in cell adhesion/ECM regulation in ToF and ADS, improving our understanding of the mechanisms contributing to cardiac dysfunction after surgery with CPB.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14" sec-type="conclusion"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par64">In conclusion, results from this study provide a better understanding of the molecular pathways specifically involved in ToF and ASD pathogenesis and mediating myocardium response to CPB, demonstrating that gene expression profiling can differentiate these two major forms of CHDs and complement ongoing biomarker development efforts. Early discrimination of patients that may develop intraoperative inflammatory and stress response and associated organ damage is critical to direct tailored post-surgical treatment strategies aimed at minimizing morbid effects of CPB. Our data have important translational value because they enable the identification of candidate genes/pathways that might serve as potential biomarkers of inflammatory response, oxidative stress, and myocardial damage, instrumental for a better prediction of patient prognosis after CPB, as well as possible targets for guiding the development of new specific cardioprotective modalities of intervention in these diseases, that may result in more effective patient management after corrective surgery. In this regard, the demonstration of increased expression of genes encoding critical mediators of myocardial inflammatory injury, such as proinflammatory chemokines, SOCS3, and PTGS2, both in ToF and ASD after CPB is of particular relevance, suggesting that the development of therapeutic approaches that target these genes may be effective in controlling the inflammatory response triggered by CPB in patients affected by different CHDs. On the other hand, it is conceivable that targeting transcription factor-coding genes implicated in the induction of heart hypertrophy, fibrosis, and dysfunction, such as IRF1 KLF10, Bcl3, SOX9, and CEBPB, may represent a new therapeutic opportunity to reduce CPB-dependent damage to cardiac tissues specifically in ToF patients, given their selective upregulation in the ToF myocardium. Hypoxia-associated transcription factors, such as EGR1, may also be regarded as potentially promising therapeutic targets to limit hypoxia pathogenic effects both before (ToF) and after (ToF and ASD) CPB. We acknowledge that the study has some limitations, such as the relatively small sample size analyzed and the fact that patients have not been followed postoperatively to allow evaluation of clinical outcome. Independent experimental validation of the observed transcriptomic patterns in a larger cohort of patients is certainly needed to confirm their prognostic relevance and lead to the development of targeted therapies aimed at reducing the risk of postoperative complications and organ dysfunction after CPB in ToF and ASD.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary information</title><sec id="Sec15"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="12967_2020_2210_MOESM1_ESM.xlsx"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 1: Table S1.</bold> Differentially expressed probe sets in TOF vs ASD right atrial samples.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="12967_2020_2210_MOESM2_ESM.pdf"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 2: Figure S1.</bold> qRT-PCR validation of genes selected from the microarray profile.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3"><media xlink:href="12967_2020_2210_MOESM3_ESM.xlsx"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 3: Table S2.</bold> Differentially expressed probe sets in Post-CPB vs Pre-CPB right atrial samples from ToF patients.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM4"><media xlink:href="12967_2020_2210_MOESM4_ESM.xlsx"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 4: Table S3.</bold> Differentially expressed probe sets in Post-CPB vs Pre-CPB right atrial samples from ASD patients.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>CHDs</term><def><p id="Par5">congenital heart diseases</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ToF</term><def><p id="Par6">Tetralogy of Fallot</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ASD</term><def><p id="Par7">Atrial Septal Defect</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CPB</term><def><p id="Par8">cardiopulmonary bypass</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CA</term><def><p id="Par9">cardioplegic arrest</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>AoXCL</term><def><p id="Par10">aortic cross-clamping</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>I/R</term><def><p id="Par11">ischemia/reperfusion</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ROS</term><def><p id="Par12">reactive oxygen species</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FDR</term><def><p id="Par13">false discovery rate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FC</term><def><p id="Par14">fold change</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CV</term><def><p id="Par15">coefficient of variation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DEGs</term><def><p id="Par16">differentially expressed genes</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GEO</term><def><p id="Par17">Gene Expression Omnibus</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GO</term><def><p id="Par18">gene ontology</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GSEA</term><def><p id="Par19">Gene Set Enrichment Analysis</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MSigDB</term><def><p id="Par20">Broad Institute Molecular Signature v5 Database</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>miRs</term><def><p id="Par21">microRNAs</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher's Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn><fn><p>Federica Raggi and Davide Cangelosi contributed equally to this work</p></fn><fn><p>Alessandra Eva and Maria Carla Bosco share senior authorship</p></fn><fn><p>Luigi Varesio&#x02014;Deceased. The authors dedicate the manuscript to the memory of Luigi Varesio who prematurely passed away during the course of the study</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Supplementary information</title><p><bold>Supplementary information</bold> accompanies this paper at 10.1186/s12967-020-02210-5.</p></sec><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>Not applicable.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>FR conducted the experiments, acquired the results, and drafted the manuscript; DC performed bioinformatics analysis of the data and prepared the figures; PB, FB, MM, and MLB made substantial contribution to the experimental work and the interpretation of data; MA contributed to data acquisition and analysis. GP and GC diagnosed patients, performed the operation, and collected atrium specimens; LV conceived and designed the study and provided financial support; AE supervised the work; MCB participated in the experimental design and the interpretation of data, edited, and approved final version of the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This work was supported by grants from the Fondazione Umberto Veronesi (to L.V.) and the Italian Ministry of Health (to the Laboratory of Molecular Biology, Gaslini; funding source Ricerca Corrente).</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>The datasets generated and analyzed during the current study are available in the GEO public repository at NCBI (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov</ext-link>) and can be accessed to through GEO Series accession number GSE132176.</p></notes><notes><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par65">The study has been conducted under the approval of the Ethics Committee of the Gaslini Institute, and the procedures have been performed in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki. Specimens were stored in the Integrating Tissueomics Biobank (BIT)&#x02013;Gaslini under the initial approval of the Ethical Committee of the Gaslini Institute and the subsequent ratification of the Ethical Committee of the Regione Liguria (Approval 8/2014). Written informed consent to participate in the study was obtained from the parents or a legally authorized representatives of the patients enrolled in the study.</p></notes><notes><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par66">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par67">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van der Linde</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Konings</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name><surname>Slager</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Witsenburg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Helbing</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name><surname>Takkenberg</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Birth prevalence of congenital heart disease worldwide: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source><year>2011</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>2241</fpage><lpage>2247</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jacc.2011.08.025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22078432</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bruneau</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name><name><surname>Srivastava</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Congenital heart disease: entering a new era of human genetics</article-title><source>Circ Res</source><year>2014</year><volume>114</volume><fpage>598</fpage><lpage>599</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIRCRESAHA.113.303060</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24526674</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Monaco</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tetralogy of Fallot: fetal diagnosis to surgical correction</article-title><source>Minerva Pediatr</source><year>2012</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>461</fpage><lpage>470</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22992529</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zannini</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Borini</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>State of the art of cardiac surgery in patients with congenital heart disease</article-title><source>J Cardiovasc Med</source><year>2007</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2459/01.JCM.0000247427.44204.0d</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Geva</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Martins</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Wald</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Atrial septal defects</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2014</year><volume>383</volume><fpage>1921</fpage><lpage>1932</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(13)62145-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24725467</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lammers</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hager</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Eicken</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lange</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hauser</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hess</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Need for closure of secundum atrial septal defect in infancy</article-title><source>J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg</source><year>2005</year><volume>129</volume><fpage>1353</fpage><lpage>1357</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jtcvs.2004.10.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15942577</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Whiting</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>DiNardo</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cardiopulmonary bypass in the pediatric population</article-title><source>Best Pract Res Clin Anaesthesiol.</source><year>2015</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>241</fpage><lpage>256</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bpa.2015.03.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26060033</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kozik</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Tweddell</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterizing the inflammatory response to cardiopulmonary bypass in children</article-title><source>Ann Thorac Surg</source><year>2006</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>S2347</fpage><lpage>S2354</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.athoracsur.2006.02.073</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16731102</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>OJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Alexiou</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Jawad</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Vincent</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The inflammatory response to cardiopulmonary bypass: part 1&#x02013;mechanisms of pathogenesis</article-title><source>J Cardiothorac Vasc Anesth</source><year>2009</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>223</fpage><lpage>231</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.jvca.2008.08.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18930659</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liangos</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Domhan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwager</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Addabbo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Whole blood transcriptomics in cardiac surgery identifies a gene regulatory network connecting ischemia reperfusion with systemic inflammation</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2010</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>e13658</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0013658</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21048961</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caputo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mokhtari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Miceli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghorbel</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Angelini</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name><surname>Parry</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Controlled reoxygenation during cardiopulmonary bypass decreases markers of organ damage, inflammation, and oxidative stress in single-ventricle patients undergoing pediatric heart surgery</article-title><source>J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg</source><year>2014</year><volume>148</volume><fpage>792</fpage><lpage>801</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jtcvs.2014.06.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25052821</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Calza</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Lerzo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Perfumo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Borini</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Panizzon</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Moretti</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Clinical evaluation of oxidative stress and myocardial reperfusion injury in pediatric cardiac surgery</article-title><source>J Cardiovasc Surg</source><year>2002</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>441</fpage><lpage>447</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12124549</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Voisine</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bianchi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kohane</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Differences in gene expression profiles of diabetic and nondiabetic patients undergoing cardiopulmonary bypass and cardioplegic arrest</article-title><source>Circulation</source><year>2004</year><volume>110</volume><fpage>II280</fpage><lpage>II286</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/01.CIR.0000138974.18839.02</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15364876</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bianchi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Liddicoat</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Voisine</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Gene expression profile after cardiopulmonary bypass and cardioplegic arrest</article-title><source>J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg</source><year>2003</year><volume>126</volume><fpage>1521</fpage><lpage>1530</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0022-5223(03)00969-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14666028</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name><surname>Moorhouse</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Spek</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bogers</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>DNA microarray analysis for human congenital heart disease</article-title><source>Cell Biochem Biophys</source><year>2006</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1385/CBB:44:1:001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16456230</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Comparative transcriptome analysis of atrial septal defect identifies dysregulated genes during heart septum morphogenesis</article-title><source>Gene</source><year>2016</year><volume>575</volume><fpage>303</fpage><lpage>312</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gene.2015.09.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26375510</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>YE</given-names></name><name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>HX</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>RZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microarray analysis reveals key genes and pathways in Tetralogy of Fallot</article-title><source>Mol Med Rep.</source><year>2017</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>2707</fpage><lpage>2713</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3892/mmr.2017.6933</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28713939</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parodi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Raggi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Cangelosi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Manzini</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Balsamo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Blengio</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Hypoxia modifies the transcriptome of human NK cells, modulates their immunoregulatory profile, and influences NK cell subset migration</article-title><source>Front Immunol.</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>2358</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2018.02358</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30459756</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cangelosi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Muselli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Parodi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Blengio</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Becherini</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Versteeg</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Use of attribute driven incremental discretization and logic learning machine to build a prognostic classifier for neuroblastoma patients</article-title><source>BMC Bioinform</source><year>2014</year><volume>15</volume><issue>Suppl 5</issue><fpage>S4</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-15-S5-S4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maere</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Heymans</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuiper</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>BiNGO: a Cytoscape plugin to assess overrepresentation of gene ontology categories in biological networks</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2005</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>3448</fpage><lpage>3449</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/bti551</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15972284</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Szklarczyk</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Franceschini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wyder</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Forslund</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Heller</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Huerta-Cepas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>STRING v10: protein&#x02013;protein interaction networks, integrated over the tree of life</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2015</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>D447</fpage><lpage>D452</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gku1003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25352553</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liberzon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Subramanian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinchback</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Thorvaldsdottir</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamayo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mesirov</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular signatures database (MSigDB) 3.0</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2011</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>1739</fpage><lpage>1740</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btr260</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21546393</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bosco</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Puppo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Santangelo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Anfosso</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Pfeffer</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Fardin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Hypoxia modifies the transcriptome of primary human monocytes: modulation of novel immune-related genes and identification of CC-chemokine ligand 20 as a new hypoxia-inducible gene</article-title><source>J Immunol.</source><year>2006</year><volume>177</volume><fpage>1941</fpage><lpage>1955</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.177.3.1941</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16849508</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raggi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Blengio</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Eva</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pende</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Varesio</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bosco</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of CD300a as a new hypoxia-inducible gene and a regulator of CCL20 and VEGF production by human monocytes and macrophages</article-title><source>Innate Immun.</source><year>2014</year><volume>120</volume><fpage>721</fpage><lpage>734</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1753425913507095</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramadas</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajaraman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuppuswamy</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Vedantham</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Early growth response-1 (EGR-1)&#x02014;a key player in myocardial cell injury</article-title><source>Cardiovasc Hematol Agents Med Chem.</source><year>2014</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>66</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/1871525713666150123152131</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25613031</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ghorbel</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Cherif</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Mokhtari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kenny</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Angelini</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transcriptomic analysis of patients with tetralogy of Fallot reveals the effect of chronic hypoxia on myocardial gene expression</article-title><source>J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg</source><year>2010</year><volume>140</volume><fpage>337</fpage><lpage>345</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jtcvs.2009.12.055</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20416888</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fardin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Barla</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mosci</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosasco</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Verri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Versteeg</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A biology-driven approach identifies the hypoxia gene signature as a predictor of the outcome of neuroblastoma patients</article-title><source>Mol Cancer.</source><year>2010</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>185</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1476-4598-9-185</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20624283</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lotan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Zilberman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Dagan</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ben-Abraham</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Weinbroum</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Beta-chemokine secretion patterns in relation to clinical course and outcome in children after cardiopulmonary bypass: continuing the search to abrogate systemic inflammatory response</article-title><source>Ann Thorac Surg</source><year>2001</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>233</fpage><lpage>237</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0003-4975(00)02020-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11216753</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nagata</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yasukawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kyogoku</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Oba</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nohara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cardiac-specific SOCS3 deletion prevents in vivo myocardial ischemia reperfusion injury through sustained activation of cardioprotective signaling molecules</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2015</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>e0127942</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0127942</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26010537</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ghorbel</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Cherif</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mokhtari</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruno</surname><given-names>VD</given-names></name><name><surname>Caputo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Angelini</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Off-pump coronary artery bypass surgery is associated with fewer gene expression changes in the human myocardium in comparison with on-pump surgery</article-title><source>Physiol Genomics</source><year>2010</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>67</fpage><lpage>75</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/physiolgenomics.00174.2009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20332183</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chistiakov</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Orekhov</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Bobryshev</surname><given-names>YV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of cardiac fibroblasts in post-myocardial heart tissue repair</article-title><source>Exp Mol Pathol</source><year>2016</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>231</fpage><lpage>240</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.yexmp.2016.09.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27619160</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Osorio</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Duque</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaufman</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Failure of right ventricular adaptation in children with tetralogy of Fallot</article-title><source>Circulation</source><year>2006</year><volume>114</volume><fpage>I37</fpage><lpage>I42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.105.001248</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16820602</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spinale</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Matrix metalloproteinases: regulation and dysregulation in the failing heart</article-title><source>Circ Res</source><year>2002</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>520</fpage><lpage>530</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/01.RES.0000013290.12884.A3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11909815</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beyer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Schett</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Gay</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Distler</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Distler</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hypoxia. Hypoxia in the pathogenesis of systemic sclerosis</article-title><source>Arthritis Res Ther.</source><year>2009</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>220</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/ar2598</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19473554</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bentovim</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Amarilio</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Zelzer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>HIF1alpha is a central regulator of collagen hydroxylation and secretion under hypoxia during bone development</article-title><source>Development.</source><year>2012</year><volume>139</volume><fpage>4473</fpage><lpage>4483</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dev.083881</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23095889</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Semenza</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oxygen sensing, hypoxia-inducible factors, and disease pathophysiology</article-title><source>Annu Rev Pathol</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>47</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-pathol-012513-104720</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23937437</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bosco</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Delfino</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferlito</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Battaglia</surname><given-names>FPM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gregorio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gambini</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Hypoxic synovial environment and expression of macrophage inflammatory protein MIP-3a/CCL20 in juvenile idiopathic arthritis</article-title><source>Arthritis Rheum</source><year>2008</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>1833</fpage><lpage>1838</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/art.23516</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18512817</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gene expression analysis in cardiac tissues from infants identifies candidate agents for Tetralogy of Fallot</article-title><source>Pediatr Cardiol</source><year>2013</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>1637</fpage><lpage>1644</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00246-013-0689-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23563574</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Palomer</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Capdevila-Busquets</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Botteri</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez-Gonzalez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>miR-146a targets Fos expression in human cardiac cells</article-title><source>Dis Model Mech.</source><year>2015</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>1081</fpage><lpage>1091</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/dmm.020768</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26112171</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Volkova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Garg</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Dick</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Boheler</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aging-associated changes in cardiac gene expression</article-title><source>Cardiovasc Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>194</fpage><lpage>204</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cardiores.2004.11.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15820188</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tatman</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Woulfe</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>Karimpour-Fard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeffrey</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaggers</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cleveland</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Pediatric dilated cardiomyopathy hearts display a unique gene expression profile</article-title><source>JCI Insight.</source><year>2017</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/jci.insight.94249</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28724804</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Joehanes</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Pilling</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Schurmann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Conneely</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name><name><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The transcriptional landscape of age in human peripheral blood</article-title><source>Nat Commun.</source><year>2015</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>8570</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms9570</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26490707</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Petralia</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Argmann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Synchronized age-related gene expression changes across multiple tissues in human and the link to complex diseases</article-title><source>Sci Rep.</source><year>2015</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>15145</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep15145</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26477495</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Spallotta</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Southon</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Essential role of the zinc finger transcription factor Casz1 for mammalian cardiac morphogenesis and development</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2014</year><volume>289</volume><fpage>29801</fpage><lpage>29816</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M114.570416</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25190801</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ogata</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Isodono</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tagawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Takehara</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawashima</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>MURC, a muscle-restricted coiled-coil protein that modulates the Rho/ROCK pathway, induces cardiac dysfunction and conduction disturbance</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>2008</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>3424</fpage><lpage>3436</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/MCB.02186-07</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18332105</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jay</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Chikarmane</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Poulik</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Misra</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Infantile hypertrophic cardiomyopathy associated with a novel MYL3 mutation</article-title><source>Cardiology</source><year>2013</year><volume>124</volume><fpage>248</fpage><lpage>251</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000347138</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23594557</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carey</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Brandt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mei</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharp</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effect of copy number variants on outcomes for infants with single ventricle heart defects</article-title><source>Circ Cardiovasc Genet.</source><year>2013</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>444</fpage><lpage>451</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIRCGENETICS.113.000189</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24021551</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueyama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogata</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Czernuszewicz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Dorn</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Molecular genetic and functional characterization implicate muscle-restricted coiled-coil gene (MURC) as a causal gene for familial dilated cardiomyopathy</article-title><source>Circ Cardiovasc Genet.</source><year>2011</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>349</fpage><lpage>358</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIRCGENETICS.111.959866</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21642240</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muehlschlegel</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Christodoulou</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>McKean</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorham</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mazaika</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Heydarpour</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Using next-generation RNA sequencing to examine ischemic changes induced by cold blood cardioplegia on the human left ventricular myocardium transcriptome</article-title><source>Anesthesiology</source><year>2015</year><volume>122</volume><fpage>537</fpage><lpage>550</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/ALN.0000000000000582</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25581909</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamashita</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Horimai</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Kruppel-like factor 4 protein regulates isoproterenol-induced cardiac hypertrophy by modulating myocardin expression and activity</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2014</year><volume>289</volume><fpage>26107</fpage><lpage>26118</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M114.582809</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25100730</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Hahn</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Neupane</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Aidery</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Labeit</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gawaz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dysregulated IER3 expression is associated with enhanced apoptosis in titin-based dilated cardiomyopathy</article-title><source>Int J Mol Sci</source><year>2017</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>723</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms18040723</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5412309</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Interferon regulatory factor 1 is required for cardiac remodeling in response to pressure overload</article-title><source>Hypertension</source><year>2014</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>86</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/HYPERTENSIONAHA.114.03229</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24732887</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Huo</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Huo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of biomarkers for ischemic cardiomyopathy based on microarray data analysis</article-title><source>Cardiol J.</source><year>2017</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>305</fpage><lpage>313</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5603/CJ.a2017.0005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28150292</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TIEG1 deficiency confers enhanced myocardial protection in the infarcted heart by mediating the Pten/Akt signalling pathway</article-title><source>Int J Mol Med</source><year>2017</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>569</fpage><lpage>578</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3892/ijmm.2017.2889</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28204828</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Herrer</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosello-Lleti</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ortega</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tarazon</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Molina-Navarro</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Trivino</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Gene expression network analysis reveals new transcriptional regulators as novel factors in human ischemic cardiomyopathy</article-title><source>BMC Med Genomics</source><year>2015</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>14</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12920-015-0088-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25884818</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lacraz</surname><given-names>GPA</given-names></name><name><surname>Junker</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Gladka</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Molenaar</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Scholman</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name><name><surname>Vigil-Garcia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Tomo-seq identifies SOX9 as a key regulator of cardiac fibrosis during ischemic injury</article-title><source>Circulation</source><year>2017</year><volume>136</volume><fpage>1396</fpage><lpage>1409</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.117.027832</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28724751</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>C/EBPbeta knockdown protects cardiomyocytes from hypertrophy via inhibition of p65-NFkappaB</article-title><source>Mol Cell Endocrinol</source><year>2014</year><volume>390</volume><fpage>18</fpage><lpage>25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mce.2014.03.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24704266</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Altmann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Smits</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Krawczeski</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Edelstein</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Devarajan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Serum interleukin-6 and interleukin-8 are early biomarkers of acute kidney injury and predict prolonged mechanical ventilation in children undergoing cardiac surgery: a case-control study</article-title><source>Crit Care</source><year>2009</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>R104</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/cc7940</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19570208</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Metinko</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Kunkel</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Standiford</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Strieter</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anoxia-hyperoxia induces monocyte-derived interleukin-8</article-title><source>J Clin Investig</source><year>1992</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>791</fpage><lpage>798</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI115953</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1522234</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zidar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Dolenc-Strazar</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeruc</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jerse</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Balazic</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gartner</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Expression of cyclooxygenase-1 and cyclooxygenase-2 in the normal human heart and in myocardial infarction</article-title><source>Cardiovasc Pathol.</source><year>2007</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>300</fpage><lpage>304</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.carpath.2007.02.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17868881</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Koff</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Amphiregulin, an epidermal growth factor receptor ligand, plays an essential role in the pathogenesis of transforming growth factor-beta-induced pulmonary fibrosis</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2012</year><volume>287</volume><fpage>41991</fpage><lpage>42000</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M112.356824</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23086930</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wysoczynski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Solanki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Borkowska</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>van Hoose</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Brittian</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Prabhu</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Complement component 3 is necessary to preserve myocardium and myocardial function in chronic myocardial infarction</article-title><source>Stem Cells.</source><year>2014</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>2502</fpage><lpage>2515</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/stem.1743</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24806427</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kataoka</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Shibata</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohashi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kambara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Enomoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Uemura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Omentin prevents myocardial ischemic injury through AMP-activated protein kinase- and Akt-dependent mechanisms</article-title><source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source><year>2014</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>2722</fpage><lpage>2733</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jacc.2014.03.032</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24768874</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schneeberger</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hautz</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Wahl</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Brandacher</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Sucher</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Steinmassl</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The effect of secretory leukocyte protease inhibitor (SLPI) on ischemia/reperfusion injury in cardiac transplantation</article-title><source>Am J Transplant</source><year>2008</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>773</fpage><lpage>782</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-6143.2008.02158.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18294346</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yavuz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kasap</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Parlar</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Agirbas</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Torol</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Heat shock proteins and myocardial protection during cardiopulmonary bypass</article-title><source>J Int Med Res</source><year>2011</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>499</fpage><lpage>507</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/147323001103900217</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21672353</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trost</surname><given-names>SU</given-names></name><name><surname>Omens</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Karlon</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mestril</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Covell</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Protection against myocardial dysfunction after a brief ischemic period in transgenic mice expressing inducible heat shock protein 70</article-title><source>J Clin Investig</source><year>1998</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>855</fpage><lpage>862</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI265</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9466981</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name><name><surname>McCaig</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Pollock</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>MacArthur</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lyall</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Danton</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Myocardial expression of heat shock protein 70i protects early postoperative right ventricular function in cyanotic tetralogy of Fallot</article-title><source>J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg</source><year>2011</year><volume>141</volume><fpage>1184</fpage><lpage>1191</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jtcvs.2011.01.047</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21397265</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mende</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional role, mechanisms of regulation, and therapeutic potential of regulator of G protein signaling 2 in the heart</article-title><source>Trends Cardiovasc Med</source><year>2014</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>93</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tcm.2013.07.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23962825</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR69"><label>69.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pascual-Figal</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Januzzi</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The biology of ST2: the International ST2 Consensus Panel</article-title><source>Am J Cardiol</source><year>2015</year><volume>115</volume><fpage>3B</fpage><lpage>7B</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.amjcard.2015.01.034</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25665766</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR70"><label>70.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>QZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Tumor suppressor A20 protects against cardiac hypertrophy and fibrosis by blocking transforming growth factor-beta-activated kinase 1-dependent signaling</article-title><source>Hypertension</source><year>2010</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>232</fpage><lpage>239</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/HYPERTENSIONAHA.110.149963</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20585109</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR71"><label>71.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nath</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Singal</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metallothioneins, oxidative stress and the cardiovascular system</article-title><source>Toxicology</source><year>2000</year><volume>155</volume><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0300-483X(00)00273-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11154793</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR72"><label>72.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kohler</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Sag</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Maier</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reactive oxygen species and excitation-contraction coupling in the context of cardiac pathology</article-title><source>J Mol Cell Cardiol</source><year>2014</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>92</fpage><lpage>102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.yjmcc.2014.03.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24631768</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR73"><label>73.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antiapoptotic effect and inhibition of ischemia/reperfusion-induced myocardial injury in metallothionein-overexpressing transgenic mice</article-title><source>Am J Pathol</source><year>2003</year><volume>163</volume><fpage>1579</fpage><lpage>1586</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0002-9440(10)63514-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14507664</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR74"><label>74.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Molkentin</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of cardiac hypertrophy and remodeling through the dual-specificity MAPK phosphatases (DUSPs)</article-title><source>J Mol Cell Cardiol</source><year>2016</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>44</fpage><lpage>49</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.yjmcc.2016.08.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27575022</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR75"><label>75.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>YZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>p21 protects cardiomyocytes against ischemia-reperfusion injury by inhibiting oxidative stress</article-title><source>Mol Med Rep.</source><year>2018</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>4665</fpage><lpage>4671</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29328456</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR76"><label>76.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kubli</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Quinsay</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Owens</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Loss of MCL-1 leads to impaired autophagy and rapid development of heart failure</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>2013</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>1365</fpage><lpage>1377</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gad.215871.113</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23788623</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR77"><label>77.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Masumura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Higo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Asano</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kato</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishino</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Btg2 is a negative regulator of cardiomyocyte hypertrophy through a decrease in cytosolic RNA</article-title><source>Sci Rep.</source><year>2016</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>28592</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep28592</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27346836</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR78"><label>78.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>GADD45B inhibits MKK7-induced cardiac hypertrophy and the polymorphisms of GADD45B is associated with inter-ventricular septum hypertrophy</article-title><source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><year>2008</year><volume>372</volume><fpage>623</fpage><lpage>628</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbrc.2008.05.122</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18515079</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR79"><label>79.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ikeda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bisping</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Altered microRNA expression in human heart disease</article-title><source>Physiol Genomics</source><year>2007</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>367</fpage><lpage>373</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/physiolgenomics.00144.2007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17712037</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR80"><label>80.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fiedler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Thum</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cardiovascular importance of the microRNA-23/27/24 family</article-title><source>Microcirculation.</source><year>2012</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>208</fpage><lpage>214</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1549-8719.2011.00153.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22136461</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR81"><label>81.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajakaruna</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Caputo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Emanueli</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MicroRNAs in congenital heart disease</article-title><source>Ann Transl Med.</source><year>2015</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>333</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26734643</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR82"><label>82.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MicroRNA-21 in cardiovascular disease</article-title><source>J Cardiovasc Transl Res.</source><year>2010</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>251</fpage><lpage>255</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12265-010-9169-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20560046</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR83"><label>83.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thum</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fiedler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kissler</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bussen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>MicroRNA-21 contributes to myocardial disease by stimulating MAP kinase signalling in fibroblasts</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2008</year><volume>456</volume><fpage>980</fpage><lpage>984</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature07511</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19043405</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR84"><label>84.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>ZP</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>DZ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>miR-22 in cardiac remodeling and disease</article-title><source>Trends Cardiovasc Med</source><year>2014</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>267</fpage><lpage>272</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tcm.2014.07.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25218673</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR85"><label>85.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Cong</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Upregulation of microRNA-22 contributes to myocardial ischemia-reperfusion injury by interfering with the mitochondrial function</article-title><source>Free Radic Biol Med.</source><year>2016</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>406</fpage><lpage>417</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.freeradbiomed.2016.05.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27174562</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR86"><label>86.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>XT</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cardioprotective effect of MicroRNA-21 in murine myocardial infarction</article-title><source>Cardiovasc Ther</source><year>2015</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>109</fpage><lpage>117</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1755-5922.12118</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25809568</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR87"><label>87.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cardioprotective effect of miRNA-22 on hypoxia/reoxygenation induced cardiomyocyte injury in neonatal rats</article-title><source>Gene</source><year>2016</year><volume>579</volume><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gene.2015.12.037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26707060</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR88"><label>88.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abu-Halima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Poryo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ludwig</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Mark</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Marsollek</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Giebels</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Differential expression of microRNAs following cardiopulmonary bypass in children with congenital heart diseases</article-title><source>J Transl Med.</source><year>2017</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>117</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12967-017-1213-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28558735</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR89"><label>89.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klingenberg</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Aghlmandi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Liebetrau</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Raber</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Gencer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Nanchen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cysteine-rich angiogenic inducer 61 (Cyr61): a novel soluble biomarker of acute myocardial injury improves risk stratification after acute coronary syndromes</article-title><source>Eur Heart J</source><year>2017</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>3493</fpage><lpage>3502</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/eurheartj/ehx640</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29155984</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR90"><label>90.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Perrot</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmitt</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Stiller</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Posch</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Browne</surname><given-names>EN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>CCN1 mutation is associated with atrial septal defect</article-title><source>Pediatr Cardiol</source><year>2015</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>295</fpage><lpage>299</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00246-014-1001-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25135600</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR91"><label>91.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirohata</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Murakami</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyoshi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Demircan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Oohashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dynamic induction of ADAMTS1 gene in the early phase of acute myocardial infarction</article-title><source>J Biochem</source><year>2004</year><volume>136</volume><fpage>439</fpage><lpage>446</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jb/mvh138</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15625312</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR92"><label>92.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>RZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>YZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>YZ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Association between myocardial ADAMTS-1 expression and myocardial fibrosis in a murine model of viral myocarditis</article-title><source>Zhonghua Xin Xue Guan Bing Za Zhi.</source><year>2007</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>854</fpage><lpage>858</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18070483</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR93"><label>93.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ounzain</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Motterle</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Samani</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cardiac expression of ms1/STARS, a novel gene involved in cardiac development and disease, is regulated by GATA4</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>2012</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>1830</fpage><lpage>1843</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/MCB.06374-11</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22431517</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR94"><label>94.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Erives</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New insights into the roles of Xin repeat-containing proteins in cardiac development, function, and disease</article-title><source>Int Rev Cell Mol Biol.</source><year>2014</year><volume>310</volume><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>128</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/B978-0-12-800180-6.00003-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24725425</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR95"><label>95.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fujiu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagai</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fibroblast-mediated pathways in cardiac hypertrophy</article-title><source>J Mol Cell Cardiol</source><year>2014</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>64</fpage><lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.yjmcc.2014.01.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24492068</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>