<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Open Forum Infect Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Open Forum Infect Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ofid</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Open Forum Infectious Diseases</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2328-8957</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>US</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31950069</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6954469</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ofid/ofz492</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ofz492</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Major Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Oral Vancomycin May Be Associated With Earlier Symptom Resolution Than Metronidazole for Hospitalized Children With Nonsevere <italic>Clostridiodes difficile</italic> Infections</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>Jianyi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kociolek</surname><given-names>Larry K</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0003">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Same</surname><given-names>Rebecca G</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0004">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>Alice J</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0005">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Amoah</surname><given-names>Joe</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0004">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tamma</surname><given-names>Pranita D</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0004">4</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1"/><!--<email>ptamma1@jhmi.edu</email>--></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="AF0001"><label>1</label>
<institution>Division of Gastroenterology and Hepatology, Department of Medicine, The Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine</institution>, Baltimore, Maryland</aff><aff id="AF0002"><label>2</label>
<institution>Ann &#x00026; Robert H. Lurie Children&#x02019;s Hospital of Chicago</institution>, Chicago, Illinois</aff><aff id="AF0003"><label>3</label>
<institution>Division of Pediatric Infectious Diseases, Department of Pediatrics, Northwestern University Feinberg School of Medicine</institution>, Chicago, Illinois</aff><aff id="AF0004"><label>4</label>
<institution>Division of Pediatric Infectious Diseases, Department of Pediatrics, The Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine</institution>, Baltimore, Maryland</aff><aff id="AF0005"><label>5</label>
<institution>The Johns Hopkins Hospital, Department of Pharmacy</institution>, Baltimore, Maryland</aff><author-notes><corresp id="c1"><bold>Correspondence:</bold> Pranita D. Tamma, MD, MHS, Department of Pediatrics, Division of Pediatric Infectious Diseases, The Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine, 200 North Wolfe Street, Suite 3149, Baltimore, Maryland 21287 (<email>ptamma1@jhmi.edu</email>).</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>12</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2019-11-14"><day>14</day><month>11</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>14</day><month>11</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>6</volume><issue>12</issue><elocation-id>ofz492</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>19</day><month>9</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>12</day><month>11</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="editorial-decision"><day>06</day><month>11</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of Infectious Diseases Society of America.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><license license-type="cc-by-nc-nd" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs licence (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits non-commercial reproduction and distribution of the work, in any medium, provided the original work is not altered or transformed in any way, and that the work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="ofz492.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><sec id="s0100"><title>Objective</title><p>National guidelines recommend oral vancomycin over oral metronidazole as first-line treatment for nonsevere <italic>Clostridioides difficile</italic> infection (CDI) in adults. Guidelines recommend metronidazole for children with nonsevere CDI, emphasizing that comparative effectiveness studies comparing the relative efficacy of vancomycin and metronidazole are lacking in children.</p></sec><sec id="s0101"><title>Method</title><p>We conducted an observational study of hospitalized children with nonsevere CDI treated with metronidazole versus vancomycin using an inverse probability of treatment-weighted propensity-score analysis. All of the following criteria had to be present for children with positive CDI testing for study eligibility: (1) &#x02265;3 new-onset unformed stools within a 24-hour period; (2) 2&#x02013;17 years of age; (3) hospitalization for &#x02265;48 hours for CDI; (4) no laxative use &#x02264;48 hours; (5) no alternate etiology for diarrhea; (6) no previous episode of CDI &#x02264;3 months; (7) no concurrent non-CDI&#x02013;targeted antibiotic therapy, and (8) no severe or fulminant CDI.</p></sec><sec id="s0102"><title>Results</title><p>One hundred ninety-two patients met eligibility criteria; 141 (73.4%) received oral metronidazole and 51 (26.6%) children received oral vancomycin. Baseline characteristics were similar between the 2 groups in the weighted cohort. Of 141 patients, 101 (71.7%) children receiving metronidazole had clinical improvement by day 5, whereas 44 of 51 (86.3%) cases resolved with vancomycin (odds ratio, 0.40; 95% confidence interval, 0.17&#x02013;0.97; <italic>P</italic> = .04). The odds of CDI recurrence within 12 weeks were similar between the groups.</p></sec><sec id="s0103"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Our study suggests that children with nonsevere CDI have earlier resolution of clinical symptoms when prescribed vancomycin compared with metronidazole. Large interventional studies are necessary to evaluate the reproducibility of our findings.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd><italic>C. difficile</italic></kwd><kwd><italic>Clostridium difficile</italic></kwd><kwd>CDAD</kwd><kwd>diarrhea</kwd><kwd>pediatrics</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source><named-content content-type="funder-name">National Institutes of Health</named-content><named-content content-type="funder-identifier">10.13039/100000002</named-content></funding-source><award-id>K23-AI127935</award-id><award-id>T32-AI052071</award-id><award-id>K23-AI123525</award-id></award-group></funding-group><counts><page-count count="6"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>
<italic>Clostridioides difficile</italic> infections (CDI) are the leading cause of healthcare-associated infections in the United States and are associated with significant morbidity [<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Historically, both oral metronidazole and oral vancomycin were commonly used for the treatment of nonsevere CDI. As of 2018, the Infectious Diseases Society of America (IDSA) and Society for Healthcare Epidemiology of America (SHEA) recommend vancomycin over metronidazole as the first-line treatment for nonsevere CDI in adults [<xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. This is a strong recommendation based primarily on the results of 2 randomized controlled trials [<xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], in which findings were driven mostly by severe CDI cases, as well as the findings of an observational study that focused on mild to moderate CDI cases [<xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Others have shown that the median duration of CDI symptoms is shorter with vancomycin compared to metronidazole [<xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].</p><p>Studies evaluating the relative efficacy of metronidazole versus vancomycin for nonsevere CDI in children are lacking. Because of the scarcity of evidence addressing this question in the pediatric population, the IDSA/SHEA guidelines recommend oral metronidazole as a weak recommendation with a low quality of evidence for children with nonsevere CDI, specifically stating, &#x0201c;Either metronidazole or vancomycin is recommended for the treatment of children with an initial episode or first recurrence of nonsevere CDI.&#x0201d; [<xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] Though data for the management of children with severe or fulminant CDI also are limited, experts agree because of the significant risk of poor outcomes and the strength of the evidence supporting oral vancomycin in the adult population that oral vancomycin should be used as first line therapy for both children and adults with severe or fulminant CDI.</p><p>A concern that has been raised frequently with the use of oral vancomycin for CDI therapy is the association with the subsequent emergence of vancomycin-resistant enterococci (VRE) [<xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]; however, this has not been consistently demonstrated in the published literature. The most robust study to date, including patients diagnosed with CDI at more than 1200 Veterans Affairs hospitals and clinics, suggests the risk of isolating VRE from a clinical culture within the subsequent 3 months is similar for the 2 agents [<xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">9&#x02013;15</xref>]. Our objective was to compare the clinical outcomes of hospitalized children with nonsevere CDI treated with oral metronidazole versus oral vancomycin using a multicenter, observational cohort.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials" id="s2"><title>METHODS</title><sec id="s3"><title>Study Setting and Design</title><p>This study included patients under 18 years of age hospitalized at The Johns Hopkins Hospital, Bayview Medical Center, or Howard County General Hospital with nonsevere CDI between January 2012 and December 2018. As there is no validated definition for nonsevere CDI in children, the adult criteria (developed by expert opinion [<xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]) of peripheral white blood cell count &#x0003c;15 000 cells/mm<sup>3</sup> and a serum creatinine level of &#x0003c;1.5 mg/dL in addition to no hypotension, ileus, or megacolon, and not requiring intensive care unit care was used to define nonsevere CDI.</p><p>The clinical microbiology laboratory provided the investigators with a list of all children with a positive stool nucleic acid amplification test (NAAT) for <italic>C. difficile</italic> toxin B during the study period. The microbiology laboratory routinely rejects samples for CDI testing from children (1) with formed stool, (2) who had previous CDI testing within 7 days, or (3) who received a laxative within 48 hours. Infectious diseases consultation is recommended for any child under 2 years of age for whom CDI testing is requested.</p><p>Manual chart review was conducted for all children with a positive <italic>C. difficile</italic> NAAT to identify those meeting eligibility criteria. The Epic Care Everywhere network that includes inpatient and outpatient records from a large number of healthcare facilities in the United States was reviewed for all patients to identify relevant pre- and post-discharge data. Similarly, the Chesapeake Regional Information System for Our Patients (CRISP), which includes inpatient, outpatient, and emergency department information for children in the state of Maryland and the District of Columbia, also was reviewed. This study was approved by The Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine Institutional Review Board with a waiver of informed consent.</p><p>All of the following criteria had to be present for children with positive CDI testing for inclusion in the study: (1) at least 3 new-onset unformed stools within a 24 hour period; (2) at least 2 years of age and under 18 years of age; (3) hospitalization for at least 48 hours for CDI; (4) no laxative use within the previous 48 hours; (5) no plausible alternate explanation for diarrhea (as determined by adjudication by both a gastroenterologist (J.W.) and an infectious diseases physician (P.D.T.); (6) receipt of either oral metronidazole or oral vancomycin therapy (as explained in more detail below); (7) no previous episode of CDI within the past 3 months [<xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] (children who had a nonsevere episode of CDI more than 3 months prior to the current episode with complete resolution of symptoms were included); (8) no concurrent non-CDI&#x02013;targeted antibiotic therapy while receiving CDI treatment; and (9) not meeting criteria for severe or fulminant CDI.</p></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Exposures and Outcomes</title><p>The primary exposure was receipt of oral metronidazole therapy. To be eligible for the oral metronidazole group, patients had to receive oral metronidazole from day 1 of treatment and for at least 5 days. Patients initially prescribed oral vancomycin who were converted to oral metronidazole within the first 48 hours of antibiotic therapy (and remained on metronidazole for the duration of therapy) also were designated to the exposed group. Unexposed patients were those prescribed oral vancomycin as initial therapy for the duration of therapy. As with the exposed group, patients transitioned from oral metronidazole to oral vancomycin within 48 hours of the initiation of CDI-targeted therapy were included in the unexposed group. Any patient receiving oral metronidazole or oral vancomycin and transitioned to the alternate treatment after 48 hours were excluded from further analysis. Furthermore, any child who received vancomycin as a tapered and pulsed regimen also were excluded.</p><p>The primary outcome was documented resolution or improvement of diarrhea (by the treating clinician) within 5 days of antibiotic treatment initiation. For patients discharged prior to day 5 with no post-discharge records available (after evaluating the medical chart, Epic Care Everywhere, and CRISP) an assumption was made that resolution or improvement of diarrhea occurred by day 5.</p><p>Recurrence of disease, defined as occurrence of another episode of CDI following resolution of the previous episode of CDI, within a 12-week period was a secondary outcome. To be considered a recurrent episode, the same clinical and laboratory criteria as the initial CDI episode was necessary. Additionally, incident VRE isolation from clinical cultures within 12 weeks after the initiation of treatment for CDI was collected for both groups.</p><p>Demographic, pre-existing medical conditions, microbiology, treatment, and outcomes data were manually collected and entered into a secure REDCap database. Surveillance case definitions included the following: community-onset (symptoms within 3 days of admission and no previous admission within the past 28 days), facility-associated community-onset healthcare (history of hospital admission in the past 28 days), and healthcare facility-onset (onset greater than 3 days after admission) [<xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>Using multivariable logistic regression, propensity scores were calculated for each patient with the dependent variable being metronidazole therapy. Covariates used for generating propensity scores included: previous episode of CDI (ie, nonsevere episode of CDI more than 3 months prior to the current episode with complete resolution of symptoms), chemotherapy within the previous 6 months, hematologic stem-cell transplantation (HSCT) within the previous 12 months, solid organ transplant recipient, ulcerative colitis, Crohn&#x02019;s disease, and surveillance case definitions of CDI.</p><p>Patients who received metronidazole treatment were weighted by the inverse of the propensity score and patients who received oral vancomycin were weighted by the inverse of 1 minus the propensity score. A new weighted pseudo-population was created to ensure improved balance of baseline characteristics between the groups. Individuals who received an &#x0201c;unexpected&#x0201d; antibiotic (ie, received oral vancomycin when the propensity score suggested the patient would be more likely to receive oral metronidazole) based on their baseline characteristics were given an increased weight and individuals who received the &#x0201c;expected&#x0201d; antibiotic were assigned a decreased weight as they already were represented adequately in the study population. Weighted <italic>t</italic> test or &#x003c7;&#x0200a;<sup>2</sup> tests were used to compare baseline characteristics after inverse probability of treatment weighting was applied. Stabilized weights were used to reduce the influence of extreme weights. Standardized differences&#x02014;that describe the between-group differences in standard deviation units&#x02014;also were used to assess balance, with values less than 10% considered appropriately balanced. In the final analysis, weighted logistic regression was used to estimate odds ratios and 95% confidence intervals (CI) for the outcome, adjusting for variables with standardized differences greater than 10%. A 2-sided <italic>P</italic> value &#x0003c;.05 was considered statistically significant for all tests. Statistical analysis was completed using STATA version 13.0 (StataCorp, College Station, TX).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s6"><title>RESULTS</title><p>There were 273 hospitalized children with a positive <italic>C. difficile</italic> NAAT for the toxin B gene identified between January 2012 and December 2018 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>). A total of 192 patients met eligibility criteria, of which 141 (73.4%) received oral metronidazole and 51 (26.6%) children received oral vancomycin. As shown in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, there was no significant difference in demographics, pre-existing medical conditions, including immunocompromised status or underlying inflammatory bowel disease (IBD) or surveillance categories between children in the metronidazole group and the vancomycin group. However, children in the vancomycin group had a higher likelihood of having a previous CDI episode within 2 years of the current episode 9.9% versus 29.4%.</p><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Comparison of Baseline Characteristics of 192 Hospitalized Children With Mild to Moderate <italic>Clostridioides difficile</italic> Infection Treated With Oral Metronidazole Versus Oral Vancomycin in the Full Cohort and Propensity-Score Weighted Cohort</p></caption><table frame="vsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Full Cohort</th><th colspan="4" rowspan="1">Weighted Cohort<sup><sup>a</sup></sup></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metronidazole (n = 141, 73 %)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vancomycin (n = 51, 27 %)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>P</italic> value</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Standardized difference</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metronidazole (n = 142, 74 %)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vancomycin (n = 50, 26%)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>P</italic> value</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Standardized difference</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, median (interquartile range)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 years (4&#x02013;13)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 years (4&#x02013;15)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.242</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.188</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 years (8&#x02013;13)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 years (4&#x02013;15)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.212</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.215</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76 (53.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 (52.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.906</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.019</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77 (54.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (51.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.740</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.058</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Race/ethnicity, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Black</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (25.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (21.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.573</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.093</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (24.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (20.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.614</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.087</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;White</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77 (54.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (68.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.082</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.289</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">81 (56.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">34 (68.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.191</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.231</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Latino</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (5.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (3.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.763</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.050</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (4.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 (3.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.783</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.045</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Asian</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (5.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.082</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.346</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (5.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.094</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.347</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Other</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13 (9.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (5.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.460</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.126</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (8.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (7.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.855</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.034</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Previous episode of <italic>Clostridioides difficile</italic> infection within past 2 years, n (%)<sup>b</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (9.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (29.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.502</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (15.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (16.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.967</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pre-existing medical conditions, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Chemotherapy within the past 6 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (20.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (11.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.163</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.239</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 (17.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (16.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.823</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.043</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Hematopoietic stem cell transplant in past 12 months</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (10.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (9.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.867</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.027</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (10.2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (10.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.955</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.010</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Solid organ transplant recipient</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (5.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (5.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.956</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (5.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (5.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.917</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.018</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Crohn&#x02019;s disease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (7.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (9.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.536</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.097</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (8.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (8.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.989</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Ulcerative colitis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (5.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (11.7)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.152</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.215</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (7.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (8.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.970</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Surveillance categories<sup>c</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Community-onset</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35 (24.8)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (35.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.152</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.228</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 (28.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (30.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.813</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.040</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Community-onset healthcare, facility-associated</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48 (34.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (29.4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.546</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.099</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45 (31.9)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (30.0)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.817</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.041</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Healthcare facility-onset</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58 (41.1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 (35.3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.465</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.120</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56 (39.5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (39.6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.993</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="fn-0100"><p>
<sup>a</sup>Weighted cohort numbers rounded to whole numbers.</p></fn><fn id="fn-0101"><p>
<sup>b</sup>Children who experienced a previous <italic>Clostridioides difficile</italic> infection episode within the past 3 months were excluded.</p></fn><fn id="fn-0102"><p>
<sup>c</sup>
<uri xlink:href="www.cdc.gov/nhsn/PDFs/pscManual/12pscMDRO_CDADcurrent.pdf">www.cdc.gov/nhsn/PDFs/pscManual/12pscMDRO_CDADcurrent.pdf</uri>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Eligibility criteria for observational study comparing oral metronidazole and oral vancomycin for the treatment of nonsevere Clostridioides difficle infection in hospitalized children.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ofz492f0001"/></fig><p>In the weighted propensity-score cohort, 101 of 141 (71.7%) children with nonsevere CDI receiving oral metronidazole had clinical improvement by day 5, whereas 44 of 51 (86.3%) cases resolved with oral vancomycin treatment. The odds of clinical resolution were lower in the metronidazole group than in the vancomycin group (odds ratio [OR], 0.40; 95% CI, 0.17&#x02013;0.97; <italic>P</italic> = .04), after additional adjustment for variables with standard biases greater than 0.10. Among the 40 children not experiencing clinical resolution by day 5 of initial oral metronidazole, 20 (50%) of these children were changed to oral vancomycin. The median duration of CDI treatment was 10 days (interquartile range [IQR] 10&#x02013;13 versus IQR 10&#x02013;12) in both treatment arms (<italic>P</italic> = .98).</p><p>Limiting the evaluation to children with resolution of symptoms by day 5, recurrence of disease within 12 weeks following complete resolution of the prior CDI episode was observed in 22 of 101 (21.7%) children treated with metronidazole and 7 of 44 (15.9%) children treated with oral vancomycin. The overall odds of CDI recurrence within 12 weeks were similar between the metronidazole and vanocmycin groups (OR, 1.47; 95% CI, 0.58&#x02013;3.75; <italic>P</italic> = .42). There were 6 incident episodes of VRE isolated from clinical cultures in the 192 children meeting eligibility criteria: 4 (2.8%) in the metronidazole arm and 2 (3.9%) in the vancomycin arm, <italic>P</italic> = .43.</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>In this multicenter, observational, propensity-score&#x02013;weighted cohort of 192 children with nonsevere CDI, patients receiving vancomycin were more likely to experience clinical resolution by day 5 compared with those receiving metronidazole. The odds of recurrent CDI within 12 weeks were similar between the 2 groups. Consistent with data from adult patients [<xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">6&#x02013;8</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>], our findings suggest that vancomycin may have more favorable clinical efficacy than metronidazole for children with nonsevere CDI. To our knowledge, this is the first comparative effectiveness study of metronidazole and vancomycin for children hospitalized with nonsevere CDI.</p><p>Metronidazole has been traditionally prescribed for both children and adults as the first-line treatment for CDI due to its reported clinical efficacy, lower cost, and perceived reduced risk of adverse events, including subsequent VRE colonization, compared to oral vancomycin [<xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. This practice was supported by initial small-scale randomized controlled trials (RCTs) in adults, which suggested that metronidazole and vancomycin were equivalent for the treatment of CDI [<xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Recent RCTs studies have refuted these findings, particularly for patients with severe CDI [<xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Although the measurable impact of oral vancomycin being associated with improved outcomes compared to oral metronidazole for nonsevere CDI has not been apparent across all studies that have attempted to address this question [<xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">4&#x02013;6</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], <italic>no studies</italic> have demonstrated improved clinical outcomes with the use of metronidazole. Interventional studies comparing oral metronidazole and oral vancomycin for nonsevere CDI do not exist in the pediatric population. Although some observational studies have attempted to explore this question, insufficient sample sizes have precluded its adequate investigation [<xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>].</p><p>There are several possible explanations for the apparent improved effectiveness of vancomycin compared to metronidazole for the treatment of CDI. Some studies have suggested that metronidazole minimum inhibitory concentrations against <italic>C. difficile</italic> are rising, although vancomycin resistance remains rare [<xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">24&#x02013;27</xref>]. The reduced effectiveness of oral metronidazole may be compounded by the differential absorption and fecal concentrations of the 2 agents. Vancomycin is poorly absorbed, which results in high fecal concentrations after oral administration [<xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. In contrast, metronidazole is very well absorbed; only 6&#x02013;15% is excreted in stool [<xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>].</p><p>An important consideration with the use of oral vancomycin is the cost of vancomycin capsules&#x02014;even when generic [<xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. For hospitalized patients, as a cost-containment measure, inpatient pharmacies often compound an oral solution from intravenous vancomycin [<xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>], but this can prove challenging for outpatients or for patients at the time of hospital discharge if the duration of the outpatient treatment course is not provided by the inpatient pharmacy. Ideally, with the publication of the most recent CDI guidelines [<xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>], both the cost and barriers associated with the inconsistent coverage of oral vancomycin by insurance coverage will be reduced. In the meantime, it is incumbent upon clinicians to weigh the costs of oral vancomycin&#x02014;particularly for outpatients&#x02014;into their decision making.</p><p>Approximately 15% of our cohort consisted of children with IBD, with equal distribution in both treatment groups. The small numbers of patients with IBD limited a meaningful subgroup analysis of this population. Differentiating IBD exacerbations from CDI remains challenging due to the overlapping clinical presentations of the 2 conditions. To complicate matters, patients with IBD are at an increased risk for CDI. Inflammatory bowel disease is associated with a 4.8-fold increased risk of CDI compared to the absence of IBD, with no differences observed between ulcerative colitis and Crohn&#x02019;s disease [<xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Unique underlying IBD-related risk factors include the use of chronic immunosuppression, frequent healthcare exposures, and an ongoing inflammatory state, which disrupts the normal intestinal symbiotic state [<xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Ultimately, we included patients with IBD if we were in agreement with the treating gastroenterologist that more likely than not the presenting symptoms seemed consistent with CDI and warranted CDI-targeted therapy. We realize some misclassification still may have occurred; however, when taking into consideration real-world clinical decision making for patients with IBD, we believe the practical constraints in confidently assigning a diagnosis of CDI should not prohibit them from inclusion in comparative effectiveness studies for the management of CDI.</p><p>This study has several limitations. First, only 192 children were included. We deliberately imposed a strict eligibility criteria&#x02014;including the need for hospitalization&#x02014;even though in reality the majority of patients with nonsevere CDI are not hospitalized [<xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. We did so understanding that this would compromise the sample size of our population but would increase the validity of our findings. Second, although this study involved 3 hospitals, all 3 hospitals are located within the same geographic region, have a central laboratory, and share the same local CDI diagnosis and treatment guidelines. Further studies are needed to verify the generalizability of our findings across regions where the epidemiology of <italic>C. difficile</italic> ribotypes and general clinical management practices may differ. Third, this is a retrospective observational study. In addition to institutional electronic medical records, the Epic Care Everywhere and CRISP databases were accessed to identify relevant healthcare encounters before and after discharge, but the possibility of missing data remains. In the absence of records to suggest treatment failure, we assumed clinical resolution. As a result, the proportions of clinical resolution may have been overestimated, although there is no reason to suspect that missing data would have had a greater impact on 1 treatment group compared with the other. Fourth, we used propensity score inverse probability of treatment weighting to address imbalances in measured confounders. Because patients were not randomized to treatment, the possibility of unmeasured confounding remains. Finally, this study used the IDSA/SHEA definitions to stratify disease severity [<xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. These definitions were developed for adult patients and may not be able to accurately identify children with severe disease, potentially leading to some misclassification. However, available data suggest that these definitions likely &#x0201c;overcall&#x0201d; severe CDI in children [<xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] and therefore is unlikely to have impacted our results.</p><p>All limitations notwithstanding, our study suggests that children hospitalized with nonsevere CDI have earlier resolution of clinical findings when prescribed oral vancomycin compared with oral metronidazole. Larger interventional studies are necessary to evaluate the reproducibility of our findings.</p></sec></body><back><ack id="a1"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>
<bold><italic>Financial support.</italic></bold> The work was supported by funding from the National Institutes of Health (K23-AI127935 [P.D.T.], T32-AI052071 [R.G.S.], and K23-AI123525 [L.K.K.]).</p><p>
<bold><italic>Potential conflicts of interest.</italic></bold> L.K.K. is a scientific advisor for Synthetic Biologics. All other authors: No reported conflicts of interest. All authors have submitted the ICMJE Form for Disclosure of Potential Conflicts of Interest. Conflicts that the editors consider relevant to the content of the manuscript have been disclosed.</p></ack><ref-list id="r1"><title>References</title><ref id="CIT0001"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lessa</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bamberg</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Burden of <italic>Clostridium difficile</italic> infection in the United States</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2015</year>; <volume>372</volume>:<fpage>825</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>34</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25714160</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0002"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sammons</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Localio</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>Coffin SE, Zaoutis T.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>
<italic>Clostridium difficile</italic> infection is associated with increased risk of death and prolonged hospitalization in children</article-title>. <source>Clin Infect Dis</source><year>2013</year>; <volume>57</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23532470</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0003"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gerding</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Clinical practice guidelines for <italic>Clostridium difficile</italic> infection in adults and children: 2017 update by the Infectious Diseases Society of America (IDSA) and Society for Healthcare Epidemiology of America (SHEA)</article-title>. <source>Clin Infect Dis</source><year>2018</year>; <volume>66</volume>:<lpage>e1</lpage>&#x02013;48.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0004"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zar</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bakkanagari</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moorthi</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A comparison of vancomycin and metronidazole for the treatment of <italic>Clostridium difficile</italic>-associated diarrhea, stratified by disease severity</article-title>. <source>Clin Infect Dis</source><year>2007</year>; <volume>45</volume>:<fpage>302</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17599306</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0005"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Louie</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gerding</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>; <person-group><collab>Polymer Alternative for CDI Treatment (PACT) investigators</collab></person-group>
<article-title>Vancomycin, metronidazole, or tolevamer for <italic>Clostridium difficile</italic> infection: results from two multinational, randomized, controlled trials</article-title>. <source>Clin Infect Dis</source><year>2014</year>; <volume>59</volume>:<fpage>345</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>54</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24799326</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0006"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Siegfried</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, Dubrovskaya Y, <name name-style="western"><surname>Flagiello</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Initial therapy for mild to moderate <italic>Clostridium difficile</italic> infection</article-title>. <source>Infect Dis Clin Pract</source><year>2016</year>; <volume>24</volume>:<fpage>210</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0007"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilcox</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Howe</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Diarrhoea caused by <italic>Clostridium difficile</italic>: response time for treatment with metronidazole and vancomycin</article-title>. <source>J Antimicrob Chemother</source><year>1995</year>; <volume>36</volume>:<fpage>673</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8591942</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0008"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Nassir</surname><given-names>WN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sethi</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nerandzic</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Comparison of clinical and microbiological response to treatment of <italic>Clostridium difficile-</italic>associated disease with metronidazole and vancomycin</article-title>. <source>Clin Infect Dis</source><year>2008</year>; <volume>47</volume>:<fpage>56</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>62</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18491964</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0009"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Karanfil</surname><given-names>LV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Josephson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>A cluster of vancomycin-resistant <italic>Enterococcus faecium</italic> in an intensive care unit</article-title>. <source>Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol</source><year>1992</year>; <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>195</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>200</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1593099</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0010"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boyle</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Soumakis</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rendo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Epidemiologic analysis and genotypic characterization of a nosocomial outbreak of vancomycin-resistant enterococci</article-title>. <source>J Clin Microbiol</source><year>1993</year>; <volume>31</volume>:<fpage>1280</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8501230</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0011"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carmeli</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eliopoulos</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Samore</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Antecedent treatment with different antibiotic agents as a risk factor for vancomycin-resistant Enterococcus</article-title>. <source>Emerg Infect Dis</source><year>2002</year>; <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>802</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12141965</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0012"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Donskey</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chowdhry</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hecker</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Effect of antibiotic therapy on the density of vancomycin-resistant enterococci in the stool of colonized patients</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2000</year>; <volume>343</volume>:<fpage>1925</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>32</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11136263</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0013"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>VW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Khader</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Echevarria</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Use of oral vancomycin for <italic>Clostridioides difficile</italic> infection (CDI) and the risk of vancomycin-resistant Enterococci (VRE)</article-title>. <source>Clin Infect Dis</source><year>2019</year>; ciz871. doi:10.1093/cid/ciz871. [Epub ahead of print]</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0014"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Al-Nassir</surname><given-names>WN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sethi</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pultz</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Riggs</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Donskey</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Both oral metronidazole and oral vancomycin promote persistent overgrowth of vancomycin-resistant enterococci during treatment of <italic>Clostridium difficile</italic>-associated disease</article-title>. <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><year>2008</year>; <volume>52</volume>:<fpage>2403</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18443120</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0015"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McKinnell</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kunz</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moser</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Patient-level analysis of incident vancomycin-resistant enterococci colonization and antibiotic days of therapy</article-title>. <source>Epidemiol Infect</source><year>2016</year>; <volume>144</volume>:<fpage>1748</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>55</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27125574</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0016"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kociolek</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shulman</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gerding</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Molecular epidemiology of <italic>Clostridium difficile</italic> infections in children: a retrospective cohort study</article-title>. <source>Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol</source><year>2015</year>; <volume>36</volume>:<fpage>445</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>51</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25782900</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0017"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<collab>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</collab>. MDRO and CDI Module. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/nhsn/PDFs/pscManual/12pscMDRO_CDADcurrent.pdf">https://www.cdc.gov/nhsn/PDFs/pscManual/12pscMDRO_CDADcurrent.pdf</ext-link>. Accessed<comment> September 19, 2019</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0018"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Musher</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aslam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Logan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Relatively poor outcome after treatment of <italic>Clostridium difficile</italic> colitis with metronidazole</article-title>. <source>Clin Infect Dis</source><year>2005</year>; <volume>40</volume>:<fpage>1586</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>90</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15889354</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0019"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Teasley</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gerding</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Prospective randomised trial of metronidazole versus vancomycin for <italic>Clostridium-difficile</italic>-associated diarrhoea and colitis</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source><year>1983</year>; <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>1043</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6138597</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0020"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wenisch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Parschalk</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hasenh&#x000fc;ndl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Comparison of vancomycin, teicoplanin, metronidazole, and fusidic acid for the treatment of <italic>Clostridium difficile</italic>-associated diarrhea</article-title>. <source>Clin Infect Dis</source><year>1996</year>; <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>813</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8722937</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0021"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>VW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schwab-Daugherty</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Comparative effectiveness of vancomycin and metronidazole for the prevention of recurrence and death in patients with <italic>Clostridium difficile</italic> infection</article-title>. <source>JAMA Intern Med</source><year>2017</year>; <volume>177</volume>:<fpage>546</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>53</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28166328</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0022"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khanna</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baddour</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huskins</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>The epidemiology of <italic>Clostridium difficile</italic> infection in children: a population-based study</article-title>. <source>Clin Infect Dis</source><year>2013</year>; <volume>56</volume>:<fpage>1401</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23408679</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0023"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shaklee</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smathers</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Risk factors and outcomes associated with severe <italic>Clostridium difficile</italic> infection in children</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Infect Dis J</source><year>2012</year>; <volume>31</volume>:<fpage>134</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22031485</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0024"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miller-Roll</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bradenstein</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>A national survey of the molecular epidemiology of <italic>Clostridium difficile</italic> in Israel: the dissemination of the ribotype 027 strain with reduced susceptibility to vancomycin and metronidazole</article-title>. <source>Diagn Microbiol Infect Dis</source><year>2015</year>; <volume>83</volume>:<fpage>21</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26116225</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0025"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Snydman</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McDermott</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jacobus</surname><given-names>NV</given-names></name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>U.S.-based national sentinel surveillance study for the epidemiology of <italic>Clostridium difficile-</italic>associated diarrheal isolates and their susceptibility to fidaxomicin</article-title>. <source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><year>2015</year>; <volume>59</volume>:<fpage>6437</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>43</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26239985</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0026"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vernon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>; <person-group><collab>Pan-European Longitudinal Surveillance of Antibiotic Resistance among Prevalent Clostridium difficile Ribotypes&#x02019; Study Group</collab></person-group>
<article-title>Pan-European longitudinal surveillance of antibiotic resistance among prevalent <italic>Clostridium difficile</italic> ribotypes</article-title>. <source>Clin Microbiol Infect</source><year>2015</year>; <volume>21</volume>:<fpage>248.e9</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>248.e16</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0027"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Molecular epidemiology of <italic>Clostridium difficile</italic> infection in hospitalized patients in Eastern China</article-title>. <source>J Clin Microbiol</source><year>2017</year>; <volume>55</volume>:<fpage>801</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27974547</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0028"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Keighley</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Burdon</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arabi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Randomised controlled trial of vancomycin for pseudomembranous colitis and postoperative diarrhoea</article-title>. <source>Br Med J</source><year>1978</year>; <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>1667</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">367509</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0029"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bolton</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Culshaw</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Faecal metronidazole concentrations during oral and intravenous therapy for antibiotic associated colitis due to <italic>Clostridium difficile</italic></article-title>. <source>Gut</source><year>1986</year>; <volume>27</volume>:<fpage>1169</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>72</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3781329</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0030"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bunnell</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Danziger</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Economic barriers in the treatment of Clostridium difficile infection with oral vancomycin</article-title>. <source>Open Forum Infect Dis</source><year>2017</year>; <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>ofx078</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28638841</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0031"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bass</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bauer</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Neuner</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Comparison of oral vancomycin capsule and solution for treatment of initial episode of severe Clostridium difficile infection</article-title>. <source>J Pharm Pract</source><year>2015</year>; <volume>28</volume>:<fpage>183</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24375999</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0032"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nugent</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Higher incidence of <italic>Clostridium difficile</italic> infection among individuals with inflammatory bowel disease</article-title>. <source>Gastroenterology</source><year>2017</year>; <volume>153</volume>:<fpage>430</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>438.e2</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28479377</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0033"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ananthakrishnan</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Detecting and treating <italic>Clostridium difficile</italic> infections in patients with inflammatory bowel disease</article-title>. <source>Gastroenterol Clin North Am</source><year>2012</year>; <volume>41</volume>:<fpage>339</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>53</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22500522</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0034"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kociolek</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shulman</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gerding</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Concomitant medical conditions and therapies preclude accurate classification of children with severe or severe complicated <italic>Clostridium difficile</italic> infection</article-title>. <source>J Pediatric Infect Dis Soc</source><year>2015</year>; <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>e139</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>42</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26582882</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0035"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tschudin-Sutter</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tamma</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Milstone</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Perl</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The prediction of complicated <italic>Clostridium difficile</italic> infections in children</article-title>. <source>Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol</source><year>2014</year>; <volume>35</volume>:<fpage>901</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24915226</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>