<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Public Health</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Public Health</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2458</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31924188</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6954514</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">8150</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12889-020-8150-x</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Knowledge of heart attack and stroke symptoms among US Native American Adults: a cross-sectional population-based study analyzing a multi-year BRFSS database</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8144-6511</contrib-id><name><surname>Van Hooser</surname><given-names>Jared C.</given-names></name><address><email>jvh@d.umn.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rouse</surname><given-names>Krista L.</given-names></name><address><email>krista.rouse@essentiahealth.org</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>Mandy L.</given-names></name><address><email>mandy.meyer034@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Siegler</surname><given-names>Amanda M.</given-names></name><address><email>aklos@uwalumni.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fruehauf</surname><given-names>Beth M.</given-names></name><address><email>beth.fruehauf@essentiahealth.org</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ballance</surname><given-names>Elliot H.</given-names></name><address><email>elliot.ballance@essentiahealth.org</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Solberg</surname><given-names>Sarah M.</given-names></name><address><email>sarah.solberg@essentiahealth.org</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dibble</surname><given-names>Michael J.</given-names></name><address><email>dibblemj26@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" deceased="yes"><name><surname>Lutfiyya</surname><given-names>M. Nawal</given-names></name><address><email>nlutfiyy@umn.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9540 9781</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.266744.5</institution-id><institution>University of Minnesota, College of Pharmacy, </institution></institution-wrap>Duluth, MN 55812 USA </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0449 6525</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.428919.f</institution-id><institution>Essentia Health System, </institution></institution-wrap>Duluth, MN 55805 USA </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>Oakeaf Surgical Hospital, Altoona, WI 54720 USA </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label>Security Health Plan, Marshfield, WI 54449 USA </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.428994.a</institution-id><institution>Lutheran Hospital, </institution></institution-wrap>Fort Wayne, IN 46804 USA </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>10</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>20</volume><elocation-id>40</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>1</day><month>7</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>31</day><month>12</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s). 2020</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Heart disease and stroke are among the leading causes of death in Native Americans. Knowledge of heart attack and stroke symptomology are essential for prompt identification of symptoms and for appropriate action in seeking care. Knowledge of heart attack and stroke symptoms among US Native American adults was this study&#x02019;s focus.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">Multivariate techniques were used to analyze national surveillance data. Native American adults comprised the study population. Low heart attack and stroke knowledge score was the dependent variable.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">Logistic regression analysis yielded that Native American adults with low heart attack and stroke composite knowledge scores were more likely to be: older, less educated, poorer, uninsured, a rural resident, male, without a primary health care provider, and lacking a recent medical checkup.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par4">The identified characteristics of Native American adults with heart attack and stroke knowledge deficits or disparities should guide educational initiatives by health care providers focusing on improving such knowledge.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Heart attack symptoms</kwd><kwd>Stroke symptoms</kwd><kwd>Knowledge of heart attack and stroke symptomology</kwd><kwd>Native American adults</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par17">The disease burden of heart attacks and strokes is considerable, not only in the United States (US) but worldwide [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Globally, an estimated 17.9 million people died from cardiovascular disease (CVD) in 2016, representing 31% of all global deaths. Of these deaths, 85% were due to heart attacks and strokes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Annually, in the US the costs of CVD and stroke is an estimated $316.1 billion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>] of which $189.7 billion are direct costs and $126.4 billion indirect costs. Direct costs include the cost of health care professionals, hospitalizations, prescription medication, and home health care (not including nursing home care), while indirect costs include lost productivity associated with premature CVD and stroke related death. Stroke and CVD comprise 14% of total health expenditures in the US, which is greater than any other major diagnostic group [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>].</p><p id="Par18">Native Americans, including both American Indians (AI) and Alaskan Natives (AN), are more susceptible to heart disease and stroke than non-Hispanic Caucasians [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. At the time of the last US Census, Native Americans comprised an estimated 2.0% (6.2 million people) of the US population [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Native Americans are part of 569 federally recognized tribes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Thirty-four percent of Native Americans live on reservations located in rural areas and another 55% live in urban communities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Since 1955 Native Americans have been eligible for healthcare from the Indian Health Service (IHS) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Despite being eligible for healthcare, Native Americans experience greater health disparities when compared with other US populations. For instance, compared to the average life expectancy of the general US population, Native Americans have an average life expectancy that is 5.5&#x02009;years lower [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Also, heart disease is the first and stroke the seventh leading cause of death for Native Americans as well as causes of major morbidity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>].</p><p id="Par19">Over the past few decades there has been a stark change in heart disease death rates among Native Americans. Although heart disease death rates for Native Americans were 21% lower than the total US population in the early 1970s, they were 20% higher by the late 1990s [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Likewise, the incidence of stroke has increased since the 1970s. From 1972 to 1985, stroke death rates for Native Americans declined, albeit slower than the total US population [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. From 1985 to 1997 there was little to no decline in stroke death rates for Native Americans [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. However, at the end of the 1990s, stroke death rates were 14% higher for Native Americans than for the total US population [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. There is some evidence that this trend has continued [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>].</p><p id="Par20">Additionally, Native Americans have 2.3 greater odds of being diagnosed with diabetes than non-Hispanic Caucasians [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>], a condition that is a risk factor for heart attack and stroke [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Death from heart disease is approximately two to four times higher in adults with diabetes than adults without diabetes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Also, stroke risk is two to four times higher in adults with diabetes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Further, over 25% of Native Americans have high blood pressure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>], another risk factor for heart attack and stroke [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Finally, Native Americans die from heart disease at younger ages than other racial and ethnic groups in the US [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Thirty&#x02013;6 % of Native Americans who die from of heart disease die before age 65, over double the rate of the total US population (17%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>].</p><p id="Par21">Knowledge is the first line of prevention for heart attack and stroke, making it essential to assess symptom knowledge for these conditions in this high-risk population. Studies have shown that there are disparities in adult awareness of heart attack warning signs and symptoms with regard to race, sex and ethnicity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. Recent research has shown that Native Americans are aware of their risk for heart disease and stroke [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. However, a small, recent study among Native Americans in the urban southwest, provided preliminary evidence suggesting that awareness of heart attack and stroke symptoms was lower than that of the total US population [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>].</p><p id="Par22">Heart attack and stroke are medical emergencies that need immediate recognition of symptoms and appropriate prompt decisions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. Patients who receive treatment more quickly are more likely to avoid the disabling effects of stroke, and have decreased mortality compared to those whose treatment is delayed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. A recent study suggests less than 27% of stroke victims receive tissue plasminogen activator within 60&#x02009;min of presentation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. Heart attack is primarily treated by coronary revascularization, or procedures to restore blood flow to heart muscle, via percutaneous coronary intervention (PCI) or coronary artery bypass graft (CABG) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. It is crucial that the PCI and CABG procedures are performed in a timely fashion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>].</p><p id="Par23">This study sought to investigate the knowledge levels of heart attack and stroke symptoms among Native American adults. The findings of this study could inform the development of clinical or public health interventions to ameliorate possible knowledge disparities.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><p id="Par24">Multiple years of the heart attack and stroke module from the Behavioral Risk Factor Surveillance System (BRFSS) were studied using complex samples bivariate and multivariable techniques. BRFSS is a health related telephone survey that is overseen by the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. It is completed is all 50 US states and several US territories, collecting information from adults <underline>&#x0003e;</underline>&#x02009;18&#x02009;years of age. After being collected, BRFSS data are weighted in order to represent the noninstitutionalized US population by surveyed state. Complex multi-stage sampling techniques are used for data collection. The BRFSS survey design, data collection, and sampling measures have been previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>], as well as similar methods on the BRFSS heart attack and stroke module in different populations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>].</p><p id="Par25">The study population was Native American adults. Data from the BRFSS module on heart attack and stroke symptomology were used in these analyses. This optional module is available for data collection every other year and different states use this module in different years. In order to include as many US states and US territories as possible and to include as large a sample of Native American adults as possible, data from 2005, 2007, and 2009 was merged. Further, since BRFSS weighting methodology was amended we chose the 3&#x000a0;years of data to merge that we did to ensure consistency in the data weighting. Data from 25 states, the United States Virgin Islands (USVI), and the District of Columbia were used in these analyses. If a state used the heart attack and stroke symptomology module in multiple years, only the data from the most recent year were used.</p><p id="Par26">The BRFSS heart and stroke symptomology module consisted of 13 questions which assess a person&#x02019;s knowledge of early symptoms of heart attack and stroke. Six of the questions were on heart attack symptoms. BRFSS participants were asked if the following were symptoms of a heart attack: pain or discomfort in the jaw, neck, or back; feeling weak, lightheaded, or faint; chest pain or discomfort; pain or discomfort in the arms or shoulders; shortness of breath. An incorrect symptom, trouble seeing in one or both eyes, a symptom of a stroke, was included to examine the possibility that participants would answer &#x0201c;yes&#x0201d; to every question. Six questions were on stroke symptoms. BRFSS participants were asked if the following were symptoms of stroke: sudden confusion; trouble speaking or understanding; sudden numbness or weakness of face, arm, or leg; sudden trouble seeing in one or both eyes; sudden trouble walking, dizziness, or loss of balance or coordination; or sudden, severe headache with no known cause. In a similar fashion to the questions on heart attack symptoms, an incorrect symptom for stroke, sudden chest pain, was included to examine the possibility that participants would answer &#x0201c;yes&#x0201d; to every question. The last question asked participants what would be the first thing they would do if they thought someone was having a heart attack or a stroke: take them to the hospital, tell them to call their doctor, call 911, call their spouse or family member, or do something else [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>].</p><p id="Par27">The questions from the heart attack and stroke symptom module were grouped together for analysis because both heart attack and stroke are vascular medical emergencies that require the immediate identification of the symptoms by patients and bystanders. The questions were also grouped together because any public health endeavors will likely need to focus both heart attack and stroke symptom knowledge together, as strokes are frequently called &#x0201c;brain attacks,&#x0201d; and many facets of initial stroke care are similar to initial heart attack care [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>].</p><p id="Par28">For each BRFSS participant, we calculated a heart attack and stroke knowledge score where one point for assigned for each correct response. To categorize the knowledge scores, a low score was assigned 0&#x02013;5 points, a midrange score 6&#x02013;9 points, and high score 10&#x02013;13 points. Albeit somewhat arbitrary like many scales, the cut points were based on the possible range, 0&#x02013;13, from the BRFSS module. This scale and similar ones used with the heart attack and stroke module have been previously published and allow for the standardized comparison of knowledge scores [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>].</p><p id="Par29">The covariates for the analysis included: sex, age, annual median household income, education completed, marital status, geographic locale, timing of last routine medical checkup, having a personal health care provider (HCP), having health insurance, deferment of medical care because of cost, and self-defined health status. Similar covariates have been studied in heart attack and stroke composite knowledge scores [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>].</p><p id="Par30">Respondents geographic location was recoded as rural or non-rural using the Metropolitan Statistical Area (MSA) variable from BRFSS. Rural residents were defined as all participants living outside an MSA or living within an MSA that had no center city. Non-rural residents were defined as people living in a center city of an MSA, outside the center city of an MSA but inside the county containing the center city, or inside a suburban county of an MSA.</p><p id="Par31">The BRFSS variables that were recoded for the analyses included: age, education completed, marital status, and annual household income. Age was collapsed and recoded as a categorical variable and split into three levels: 18&#x02013;44&#x02009;years, 45&#x02013;64&#x02009;years, and&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;65&#x02009;years. For some variables with multiple responses options, education, marital status and household income, recoding was done to reduce the number of categories. Education completed was collapsed into less than high school, at least high school, or university graduate. Annual household income was recoded into the groups of &#x0003c;$50,000 and&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;$50,000. Marital status was recoded into two groups: married or living with a partner and not married or living with a partner.</p><p id="Par32">The following BRFSS variables that focus on access to health care were also included in the analyses: having a HCP, deferment of medical care because of cost, and health insurance status. Any response recorded as &#x0201c;don&#x02019;t know&#x0201d; or &#x0201c;refused to answer&#x0201d; were treated as missing data and were omitted from the analyses.</p><p id="Par33">The statistical analysis of national survey data such as BRFSS must reflect the survey&#x02019;s complex sample design [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. As such complex samples bivariate and multivariable analysis were performed. Saylor, et al., states, &#x0201c;Complex sample data analysis adjusts for weights, cluster, and stratification of the sampling design to produce unbiased national estimates of population means and frequencies from the sample after taking into account weights for over- or undersampling of specific groups. Complex sample analysis provides estimates of variability based on the number of cases in the sample rather than the number of cases in the population.&#x0201d; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]</p><p id="Par34">Complex bivariate analysis describing the three-level composite scores (low, midrange, and high score) by each covariate was completed. Correct and incorrect answers for each heart attack and stroke symptomology knowledge question by Native American status was also analyzed. One complex samples logistic regression model was performed using low scores, on the combined heart attack and stroke symptomology knowledge questions, as the dependent variable. All of the study covariates were entered into the model. Alpha was set at 0.05 for all tests of statistical significance. SPSS version 25.0 (IBM, Chicago, IL) was used to complete the analyses. The Institutional Review Board (IRB) at the researchers&#x02019; institutions acknowledge that the analysis of de-identified and publicly available data does not constitute human subjects research as defined in federal regulations and thus does not require IRB review. As this was a de-identified data only study, IRB approval was not required.</p></sec><sec id="Sec3"><title>Results</title><p id="Par35">Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> describes the Native American population responding to the optional heart attack and stroke symptom module questions in 2005, 2007 and 2009 BRFSS. From the multiyear amalgamated database compiled for this study, a weighted population of 7,336,666 Native American adults &#x02265;18&#x02009;years of age from 25 states, the USVI and the District of Columbia were identified. Proportionately, this population was younger with 53.2% being 18&#x02013;44&#x02009;years of age. The majority reported having an annual median household income under $50,000 (68.6%). Geographically, in comparison to the overall US adult population, a higher proportion of Native American adults reported living in rural rather than non-rural areas (33.7% versus 18.0%). Almost a quarter of the respondents defined their health as fair to poor (24.2%). Over 20% of respondents reported that they had no health insurance (23.8%), no health care provider (25.8%) and deferred medical care because of cost (21.6%), all within the past 12&#x02009;months. Further, 35.1% reported not having had a routine medical check-up within the past 12&#x02009;months. Finally, slightly less than 50% of this population received a low, two-level composite heart attack and stroke symptom knowledge score.
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Description of Native American Population. Amalgamated 2005, 2007, 2009 BRFSS Database (weighted <italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x02009;7,336,666)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Variables and Factors</th><th>Percent</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Sex</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Male</td><td>51.9</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Female</td><td>48.1</td></tr><tr><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">Age</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;18&#x02013;44&#x02009;Years Of Age</td><td>53.2</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;45&#x02013;64&#x02009;Years Of Age</td><td>33.8</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;&#x0003e;&#x02009;=&#x02009;65&#x02009;Years Of Age</td><td>13.0</td></tr><tr><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">Annual Median Household Income</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;&#x0003c;$50,000</td><td>68.6</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;&#x0003e;&#x02009;=&#x02009;$50,000</td><td>31.4</td></tr><tr><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">Education Attained</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Did Not Graduate From HS</td><td>17.7</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;HS Graduate</td><td>61.4</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;University Graduate</td><td>20.9</td></tr><tr><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">Geographic Locale</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Non-Rural</td><td>66.3</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Rural</td><td>33.7</td></tr><tr><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">Health Status</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Good To Excellent Health</td><td>75.8</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Fair To Poor Health</td><td>24.2</td></tr><tr><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">Health Insurance Status</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Have Health Insurance</td><td>76.2</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Do Not Have Health Insurance</td><td>23.8</td></tr><tr><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">Have Health Care Provider</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Have HCP</td><td>74.2</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Do Not Have HCP</td><td>25.8</td></tr><tr><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">Medical Care Deferred</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Medical Care Deferred Because Of Cost</td><td>21.6</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Medical Care Not Deferred</td><td>78.4</td></tr><tr><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">Routine Medical Check Up</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Within Last 12&#x02009;Months</td><td>64.9</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Longer Than 12&#x02009;Months Ago</td><td>35.1</td></tr><tr><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">Three Level Composite Knowledge Score</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Low Composite Score</td><td>8.7</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Mid-Range Composite Score</td><td>40.9</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;High Composite Score</td><td>50.4</td></tr><tr><td char="." align="char" colspan="2">Two Level Composite Knowledge Score</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;High Score</td><td>50.4</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Low Score</td><td>49.6</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par36">Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> displays the complex samples stratified analysis of the three-level composite heart attack and stroke knowledge scores by the study covariates or predictor variables. Row percentages by variable factors are reported. Notably this analysis yielded statistically significant results by chi square (<italic>p</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x02009;&#x0003c;.05) for the variables age, education completed, household income, have personal healthcare provider, and routine medical checkup.
<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Composite Heart Attack and Stroke Symptomology Knowledge Score By Covariates for Native American Adults Complex Samples Analysis. Amalgamated 2005, 2007 and 2009 BRFSS Data</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Covariates and Factors</th><th colspan="3">Three Level Composite Score</th></tr><tr><th>% Low Composite Score</th><th>% Mid-Range Composite Score</th><th>% High Composite Score</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="4">Sex</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Male</td><td>9.1</td><td>41.7</td><td>49.2</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Female</td><td>8.2</td><td>40.1</td><td>51.7</td></tr><tr><td char="." align="char" colspan="4">Age*</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;18&#x02013;44&#x02009;Years</td><td>8.1</td><td>44.2</td><td>47.8</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;45&#x02013;64&#x02009;Years</td><td>6.9</td><td>35.7</td><td>57.5</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;&#x0003e;&#x02009;=&#x02009;65&#x02009;Years</td><td>16.8</td><td>40.5</td><td>42.7</td></tr><tr><td char="." align="char" colspan="4">Education Attained*</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Did Not Graduate From HS</td><td>16.1</td><td>48.2</td><td>35.7</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;HS Graduate</td><td>7.9</td><td>42.7</td><td>49.3</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;University Graduate</td><td>4.3</td><td>29.3</td><td>66.4</td></tr><tr><td char="." align="char" colspan="4">Household Income*</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;&#x0003c;$50,000</td><td>10.0</td><td>45.1</td><td>44.9</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;&#x0003e;&#x02009;=&#x02009;$50,000</td><td>3.7</td><td>30.4</td><td>65.9</td></tr><tr><td char="." align="char" colspan="4">Geographic Locale</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Non-Rural</td><td>8.3</td><td>40.1</td><td>51.6</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Rural</td><td>9.3</td><td>42.2</td><td>48.5</td></tr><tr><td char="." align="char" colspan="4">Health Status</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Good To Excellent Health</td><td>8.0</td><td>41.7</td><td>50.3</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Fair To Poor Health</td><td>10.8</td><td>38.2</td><td>51.0</td></tr><tr><td char="." align="char" colspan="4">Health Insurance Status*</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Have Health Insurance</td><td>8.1</td><td>39.2</td><td>52.8</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Do Not Have Health Insurance</td><td>10.5</td><td>46.4</td><td>43.1</td></tr><tr><td char="." align="char" colspan="4">Have Health Care Provider*</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Have HCP</td><td>8.3</td><td>38.3</td><td>53.3</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Do Not Have HCP</td><td>9.8</td><td>49.2</td><td>41.0</td></tr><tr><td char="." align="char" colspan="4">Medical Care Deferred</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Deferred Because Of Cost</td><td>7.8</td><td>38.3</td><td>53.9</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Care Not Deferred</td><td>8.8</td><td>41.7</td><td>49.5</td></tr><tr><td char="." align="char" colspan="4">Routine Medical Check Up*</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Within Last 12&#x02009;Months</td><td>7.7</td><td>39.0</td><td>53.3</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Longer Than 12&#x02009;Months Ago</td><td>10.4</td><td>44.4</td><td>45.2</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>*Significantly different by chi-square test of independence at the .05 level</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par37">A bivariate analysis of the percent correct and incorrect responses by symptom question and race/ethnicity status of respondents (Caucasian, African American, Native American, and Hispanic) is displayed in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>. For all of the questions on heart attack and stroke symptomology, Native American respondents had higher percentages of <italic>incorrect</italic> answers when compared to their Caucasian counterparts.
<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Heart Attack and Stroke Symptomology Knowledge Questions With Percent Incorrect and Correct Responses for US Adults By Race/Ethnicity. Amalgamated 2005, 2007 and 2009 BRFSS Data</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Survey Question (correct answer)</th><th colspan="4">Race Ethnicity</th><th rowspan="2">Total US</th></tr><tr><th>Caucasian</th><th>African American</th><th>Native American</th><th>Hispanic</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="6">Do you think pain or discomfort in the jaw, neck, or back are symptoms of a heart attack? (Yes)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Incorrect Answer</td><td>43.4</td><td>62.2</td><td>50.8</td><td>68.8</td><td>47.8</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Correct Answer</td><td>56.6</td><td>37.8</td><td>49.2</td><td>31.2</td><td>52.2</td></tr><tr><td char="." align="char" colspan="6">Do you think feeling weak, lightheaded, or faint are symptoms of a heart attack? (Yes)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Incorrect Answer</td><td>34.5</td><td>46.6</td><td>38.3</td><td>46.8</td><td>37.1</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Correct Answer</td><td>65.5</td><td>53.4</td><td>61.7</td><td>53.2</td><td>62.9</td></tr><tr><td char="." align="char" colspan="6">Do you think chest pain or discomfort are symptoms for a heart attack? (Yes)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Incorrect Answer</td><td>5.4</td><td>12.2</td><td>8.6</td><td>18.7</td><td>7.3</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Correct Answer</td><td>94.6</td><td>87.8</td><td>91.4</td><td>81.3</td><td>92.7</td></tr><tr><td char="." align="char" colspan="6">Do you think sudden trouble seeing in one or both eyes is a symptom of a heart attack? (No)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Incorrect Answer</td><td>56.6</td><td>59.5</td><td>60.9</td><td>61.6</td><td>57.4</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Correct Answer</td><td>43.4</td><td>40.5</td><td>39.1</td><td>38.4</td><td>42.6</td></tr><tr><td char="." align="char" colspan="6">Do you think pain or discomfort in the arms or shoulders are symptoms of a heart attack? (Yes)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Incorrect Answer</td><td>10.0</td><td>24.9</td><td>13.9</td><td>32.0</td><td>13.6</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Correct Answer</td><td>90.0</td><td>75.1</td><td>86.1</td><td>68.0</td><td>86.4</td></tr><tr><td char="." align="char" colspan="6">Do you think shortness of breath is a symptom of a heart attack? (Yes)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Incorrect Answer</td><td>13.0</td><td>20.3</td><td>18.5</td><td>25.8</td><td>14.9</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Correct Answer</td><td>87.0</td><td>79.7</td><td>81.5</td><td>74.2</td><td>85.1</td></tr><tr><td char="." align="char" colspan="6">Do you think sudden confusion or trouble speaking are symptoms of a stroke? (Yes)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Incorrect Answer</td><td>7.8</td><td>17.0</td><td>14.8</td><td>31.4</td><td>10.8</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Correct Answer</td><td>92.2</td><td>83.0</td><td>85.2</td><td>68.6</td><td>89.2</td></tr><tr><td char="." align="char" colspan="6">Do you think sudden numbness or weakness of face, arm, or leg, especially on one side are symptoms of a stroke? (Yes)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Incorrect Answer</td><td>4.5</td><td>9.6</td><td>7.8</td><td>19.8</td><td>6.3</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Correct Answer</td><td>95.5</td><td>90.4</td><td>92.2</td><td>80.2</td><td>93.7</td></tr><tr><td char="." align="char" colspan="6">Do you think sudden trouble seeing in one or both eyes is a symptom of a stroke? (Yes)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Incorrect Answer</td><td>25.9</td><td>36.7</td><td>32.2</td><td>44.0</td><td>28.7</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Correct Answer</td><td>74.1</td><td>63.3</td><td>67.8</td><td>56.0</td><td>71.3</td></tr><tr><td char="." align="char" colspan="6">Do you think sudden chest pain or discomfort are symptoms of a stroke? (No)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Incorrect Answer</td><td>57.3</td><td>70.1</td><td>64.8</td><td>63.9</td><td>59.6</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Correct Answer</td><td>42.7</td><td>29.9</td><td>35.2</td><td>36.1</td><td>40.4</td></tr><tr><td char="." align="char" colspan="6">Do you think sudden trouble walking, dizziness, or loss of balance are symptoms of a stroke? (Yes)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Incorrect Answer</td><td>12.4</td><td>20.8</td><td>19.4</td><td>29.7</td><td>14.8</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Correct Answer</td><td>87.6</td><td>79.2</td><td>80.6</td><td>70.3</td><td>85.2</td></tr><tr><td char="." align="char" colspan="6">Do you think severe headache with no known cause is a symptom of a stroke? (Yes)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Incorrect Answer</td><td>37.7</td><td>42.1</td><td>47.5</td><td>42.7</td><td>38.8</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Correct Answer</td><td>62.3</td><td>57.9</td><td>52.5</td><td>57.3</td><td>61.2</td></tr><tr><td char="." align="char" colspan="6">If you thought someone was having a heart attack or a stroke, what is the first thing you would do? (call 911)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Incorrect Answer</td><td>12.6</td><td>13.4</td><td>17.4</td><td>17.0</td><td>13.0</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Correct Answer</td><td>87.4</td><td>86.6</td><td>82.6</td><td>83.0</td><td>87.0</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par38">Complex samples logistic regression analysis, displayed in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>, showed that Native American adults who had low composite heart attack and stroke knowledge scores had greater odds of not being a university graduate but rather a high school graduate (OR 1.578, 95% CI 1.058&#x02013;2.352) or to not have graduated from high school (OR .283, 95% CI 1.443&#x02013;3.643). Further, low scoring Native American adults had greater odds of being &#x02265;65&#x02009;years of age (or lower odds of being 45&#x02013;64&#x02009;years of age rather than 18&#x02013;44&#x02009;years of age). Finally, low scoring Native American adults had greater odds of living in a household with an income &#x0003c; $50,000 (OR 1.938, 95% CI 1.378&#x02013;2.724).
<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Complex Samples Logistic Regression Analysis of US Native American Adults with Low Heart Attack and Stroke Symptom Knowledge Score. Amalgamated 2005, 2007, 2009 BRFSS Data</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Variables</th><th rowspan="2">Factors</th><th rowspan="2">Adjusted Odds Ratio</th><th colspan="2">95% Confidence Interval</th></tr><tr><th>Lower</th><th>Upper</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2">Age</td><td>45&#x02013;64&#x02009;Years Of Age vs. 18&#x02013;44&#x02009;Years Of Age</td><td>.756</td><td>.587</td><td>.973</td></tr><tr><td>&#x0003e;&#x02009;=&#x02009;65&#x02009;Years Of Age vs. 18&#x02013;44&#x02009;Years Of Age</td><td>1.130</td><td>.827</td><td>1.543</td></tr><tr><td>Sex</td><td>Male vs. Female</td><td>1.202</td><td>.930</td><td>1.554</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Education Completed</td><td>Did Not Graduate From HS vs. University Graduate</td><td>2.293</td><td>1.443</td><td>3.643</td></tr><tr><td>HS Graduate vs. University Graduate</td><td>1.578</td><td>1.058</td><td>2.352</td></tr><tr><td>Health Status</td><td>Fair To Poor Health vs. Good To Excellent Health</td><td>.867</td><td>.666</td><td>1.128</td></tr><tr><td>Health Insurance Status</td><td>Do Not Have Health Insurance vs. Have Health Insurance</td><td>1.250</td><td>.882</td><td>1.771</td></tr><tr><td>Have Health Care Provider</td><td>Do Not Have HCP vs. Have HCP</td><td>1.150</td><td>.818</td><td>1.615</td></tr><tr><td>Medical Care Deferred</td><td>Medical Care Deferred Because Of Cost vs. Medical Care Not Deferred</td><td>.699</td><td>.488</td><td>1.000</td></tr><tr><td>Routine Medical Check Up</td><td>Longer Than 12&#x02009;Months Ago vs. Within Last 12&#x02009;Months</td><td>1.138</td><td>.855</td><td>1.515</td></tr><tr><td>Geographic Locale</td><td>Rural vs. Non-Rural</td><td>1.022</td><td>.821</td><td>1.272</td></tr><tr><td>Household Income</td><td>&#x0003c;$50,000 vs. &#x0003e;&#x02009;=&#x02009;$50,000</td><td>1.938</td><td>1.378</td><td>2.724</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par39">This study identified the characteristics of Native American adults with low knowledge of heart attack and stroke symptomology. Among the significant characteristics identified, were that this population was older, poorer, less educated, and have health service deficits (no health insurance, no personal HCP, last routine medical check-up longer than 12&#x02009;months ago, and deferring medical care because of cost) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. This study was the first that we know of to specifically examine heart attack and stroke symptomology knowledge of the Native American adult population. Multiple studies have demonstrated a strong association between lower education completion and low knowledge of heart attack and stroke symptoms in various populations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>] and this was congruent with our findings.</p><p id="Par40">Our results suggest that overall Native American adults have a knowledge deficit regarding heart attack and stroke symptomology compared to the total US population. Racial disparities in knowledge of heart attack and stroke symptoms have been identified for non-Caucasian populations in previous studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>].</p><p id="Par41">Knowledge deficits regarding heart attack and stroke symptomology among the Native American population is particularly concerning for several reasons. Heart attack and stroke can lead to morbidity and are leading causes of death among Native Americans [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Furthermore, Native Americans die from heart disease at younger ages than other ethnic and racial groups in the US---over double the rate of the total US population under 65 who die from heart disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Moreover, this population is at a greater risk of being diagnosed with diabetes and hypertension, both of which are risk factors for heart attack and stroke [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. Prompt and proper recognition of symptoms are crucial to reducing debilitating effects and death related to heart attack and stroke [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>].</p><p id="Par42">Our findings have identified that Native American adults have health service deficits suggesting that this group has barriers to health care access. A 2006 regional study from Minnesota focusing on barriers to health care found that American Indians were more likely to report racial discrimination, cultural misunderstandings, family/work responsibilities, and transportation challenges [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. Specific barriers to health care access varied among racial groups as non-Hispanic Caucasians were more likely to report being unable to see their preferred provider as a barrier [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. Although this study included individuals who were enrolled in health care programs, access barriers were still encountered and significant differences were detected in challenges cited by American Indians and non-Hispanic Caucasians [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>].</p><p id="Par43">Despite the existence of the IHS, that theoretically provides universal health care services to Native Americans, there is a surprising number of Native Americans who report being uninsured. Previous research using BRFSS data noted that compared to non-Hispanic Caucasians, Native Americans had a lower prevalence of insurance coverage or access to a personal HCP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. A recent study analyzing the National Survey of America&#x02019;s Families investigated differences in insurance coverage, access, and health care utilization between Native Americans and non-Hispanic Caucasians. The researchers noted that Native Americans had lower rates of employer/other coverage and higher rates of public/state coverage. Sixteen percent of Native Americans reported IHS coverage only, and an additional 19% were uninsured and did not report the IHS as a source of coverage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. Native Americans have an uninsured rate almost three times that of non-Hispanic Caucasians and only about half of uninsured Native Americans reported having access to IHS care [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. Compared to non-Hispanic Caucasians, Native Americans reported challenges accessing health care, dissatisfaction with the quality of health care received and communication issues with providers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>].</p><p id="Par44">Knowledge is essential to recognizing the first signs of heart attack and stroke for timely and necessary care. We believe that pharmacists can play an important role in educating patients about the symptoms of heart attack and stroke because pharmacists are easily accessible HCPs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. Pharmacists have established positive roles in public health initiatives through providing education and interventions for a variety of disease states including hypertension, hyperlipidemia, and diabetes as well as smoking cessation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]. In dispensing settings, pharmacists can provide valuable education and information regarding stroke and heart attack symptoms as nearly 90% of all Americans live within 5&#x02009;miles of a community pharmacy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>]. Pharmacists are positioned as one of the most accessible HCPs, given that pharmacists see their patients between 1.5 to 10 times more frequently than primary care physicians see their patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>]. Clinical pharmacists and other health care professionals who provide care for Native American patients are also in positions which allow them to provide education about stroke and heart attack symptomology when providing direct patient care. Moreover, working as part of a health care team constituted of physicians, advanced practice clinicians (nurse practitioners and physician assistants), dietitians, pharmacists and others can enhance coordination of care by providing essential medication and health education that may lead to better health outcomes as well as a subsequent reduction in health care costs.</p><sec id="Sec5"><title>Limitations</title><p id="Par45">Although BRFSS provides a national database with a robust sample weighted to reflect the demographics of the US population, there are a few possible limitations to this study. First, those who could not be reached by telephone could not respond to BRFSS survey as data is collected in a random-digit dial fashion. This could cause data to be skewed as persons of lower socioeconomic status might not have not been included in the survey due to poorer phone access. However, few US residents live in households without telephones and US cell phone numbers are now included in the BRFSS call list, which lessens this bias. Secondly, people may passively refuse to participate in surveys like the BRFSS by filtering their phone calls through caller identification and answering machines. However, survey work sponsored by the government is exempted from the Do Not Call Register and any potential call filtering cannot be controlled by the survey administrators. A third limitation is that the BRFSS survey does not use open-ended questions. This limits the respondents&#x02019; opportunities to fully explain their answers; but the survey questions are worded so that the answer choices cover a broad range of responses. Additionally, there is the possibility of recall bias by the survey participant as all of the survey answers are self-reported. Finally, the survey is administered in the English and Spanish languages. Participants who did not speak either languages where excluded and a proportion of Native Americans are likely to not speak either language.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par46">The analysis in this study identified characteristics of Native American adults who had low knowledge levels regarding heart attack and stroke symptoms. The knowledge deficits were greater for Native Americans than for other racial and ethnic groups in the US. These characteristics of Native American adults with knowledge deficits or disparities should guide educational initiatives and programs targeted at patients with low knowledge of heart attack and stroke symptoms scores. Interprofessional health care teams, including pharmacists, should be used to develop and implement health education interventions.</p></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>AI</term><def><p id="Par5">American Indians</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>AN</term><def><p id="Par6">Alaskan Natives</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BRFSS</term><def><p id="Par7">Behavioral Risk Factor Surveillance System</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CABG</term><def><p id="Par8">Coronary Artery Bypass Graft</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CVD</term><def><p id="Par9">Cardiovascular disease</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HCP</term><def><p id="Par10">Health care provider</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IHS</term><def><p id="Par11">Indian Health Service</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IRB</term><def><p id="Par12">Institutional Review Board</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MSA</term><def><p id="Par13">Metropolitan Statistical Area</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PCI</term><def><p id="Par14">Percutaneous coronary intervention</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>US</term><def><p id="Par15">United States</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>USVI</term><def><p id="Par16">United States Virgin Islands</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><fn-group><fn><p>M. Nawal Lutfiyya is deceased. This paper is dedicated to her memory.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>Not applicable.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>All of the authors contributed equally to this research project and manuscript. JVH, KLR, MLM, AMS, BMF, EHB, SMS, MJD, and MNL all contributed to the conceptualization of the project and the design of the study. MNL extracted the data for analysis and JVH, KLR, MLM, AMS, BMF, EHB, SMS, and MJD all contributed to data analysis and interpretation of results. All of the authors contributed to the writing and editing of the final manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>Not applicable.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>Annual BRFSS data is publically available from the CDC at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/brfss/annual_data/annual_data.htm">https://www.cdc.gov/brfss/annual_data/annual_data.htm</ext-link></p></notes><notes><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par47">The Institutional Review Boards (IRBs) of the researchers&#x02019; institutions recognize that the analysis of de-identified, publicly available data does not constitute human subjects research as defined in federal regulations, and as such does not require IRB review.</p></notes><notes><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par48">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par49">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">World Health Organization (WHO). Cardiovascular diseases (CVDs). 2019. Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/cardiovascular-diseases-">https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/cardiovascular-diseases-</ext-link>(cvds).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benjamin</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Blaha</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiuve</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Cushman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Deo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Heart disease and stroke Statistics-2017 update: a report from the American Heart Association</article-title><source>Circulation</source><year>2017</year><volume>135</volume><fpage>e146</fpage><lpage>e603</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIR.0000000000000485</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28122885</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Indian Health Service</collab></person-group><source>Trends in Indian health, 2014</source><year>2014</year><publisher-loc>Rockville</publisher-loc><publisher-name>U.S. Department of Health and Human Services</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>U.S. Census Bureau</collab></person-group><source>American Indian and Alaska native heritage month</source><year>2018</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Barnes PM, Adams PF, Powell-Griner E (2010) Health characteristics of the American Indian or Alaska native adult population: United States, 2004&#x02013;2008. Natl health stat report: 1&#x02013;22.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jernigan</surname><given-names>VB</given-names></name><name><surname>Duran</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Winkleby</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Changing patterns in health behaviors and risk factors related to cardiovascular disease among American Indians and Alaska natives</article-title><source>Am J Public Health</source><year>2010</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>677</fpage><lpage>683</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2105/AJPH.2009.164285</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20220114</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>National Academies of Sciences, Engineering, and Medicine</collab></person-group><source>Communities in action: pathways to health equity</source><year>2017</year><publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc><publisher-name>The National Academies Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Disparities. Indian Health Service. Available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ihs.gov/newsroom/factsheets/disparities">http://www.ihs.gov/newsroom/factsheets/disparities</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">National Center for Health Statistics. Health, United States, 2013. With special feature on prescription drugs. Hyattsville. 2014.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Espey</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Jim</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cobb</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartholomew</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Haverkamp</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Plescia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Leading causes of death and all-cause mortality in American Indians and Alaska natives</article-title><source>Am J Public Health</source><year>2014</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>S303</fpage><lpage>S311</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2105/AJPH.2013.301798</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24754554</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Casper</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Denny</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Coolidge</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><source>Atlas of heart disease and stroke among American Indians and Alaska natives</source><year>2005</year><publisher-loc>Atlanta</publisher-loc><publisher-name>U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention and Indian Health Service</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Schiller JS, Lucas JW, Peregoy JA. Summary health statistics for U.S. adults: National Health Interview Survey, 2011. National Center for Health Statistics. Vital Health Stat. 2012;10(256).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>American Diabetes Association</collab></person-group><article-title>Economic Costs of Diabetes in the U.S. in 2017</article-title><source>Diabetes Care</source><year>2018</year><volume>41</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>917</fpage><lpage>928</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/dci18-0007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29567642</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sowers</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Epstein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Frohlich</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diabetes, hypertension, and cardiovascular disease: an update</article-title><source>Hypertension</source><year>2001</year><volume>37</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1053</fpage><lpage>1059</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/01.HYP.37.4.1053</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11304502</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Howard</surname><given-names>BV</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name><name><surname>Cowan</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Rising tide of cardiovascular disease in American Indians</article-title><source>Strong Heart Study Circulation</source><year>1999</year><volume>99</volume><issue>18</issue><fpage>2389</fpage><lpage>2395</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10318659</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</collab></person-group><source>National diabetes fact sheet: national estimates and general information on diabetes and prediabetes in the United States, 2011</source><year>2011</year><publisher-loc>Atlanta</publisher-loc><publisher-name>U.S. Department of Health and Human Services, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</collab></person-group><article-title>Disparities in premature deaths from heart disease: 50 states and the District of Columbia, 2001</article-title><source>MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep</source><year>2004</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>121</fpage><lpage>125</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14981360</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mcgruder</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenlund</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Malarcher</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Antoine</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Croft</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Racial and ethnic disparities associated with knowledge of symptoms of heart attack and use of 911: National Health Interview Survey, 2001</article-title><source>Ethn Dis</source><year>2008</year><volume>18</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>192</fpage><lpage>197</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18507273</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</collab></person-group><article-title>Disparities in adult awareness of heart attack warning signs and symptoms--14 states, 2005</article-title><source>MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep</source><year>2008</year><volume>57</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>175</fpage><lpage>179</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18288076</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Swanoski</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Lutfiyya</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Amaro</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Akers</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Huot</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Knowledge of heart attack and stroke symptomology: a cross-sectional comparison of rural and non-rural US adults</article-title><source>BMC Public Health</source><year>2012</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>283</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2458-12-283</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22490185</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lutfiyya</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Bardales</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bales</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Awareness of heart attack and stroke symptoms among Hispanic male adults living in the United States</article-title><source>J Immigr Minor Health</source><year>2010</year><volume>12</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>761</fpage><lpage>768</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10903-009-9250-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19365727</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lutfiyya</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Cumba</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Mccullough</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Barlow</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipsky</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Disparities in adult African American women's knowledge of heart attack and stroke symptomatology: an analysis of 2003-2005 behavioral risk factor surveillance survey data</article-title><source>J Women's Health (Larchmt)</source><year>2008</year><volume>17</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>805</fpage><lpage>813</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/jwh.2007.0599</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18479229</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lutfiyya</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipsky</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bales</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Cha</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Mcgrath</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Disparities in knowledge of heart attack and stroke symptoms among adult men: an analysis of behavioral risk factor surveillance survey data</article-title><source>J Natl Med Assoc</source><year>2008</year><volume>100</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1116</fpage><lpage>1124</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0027-9684(15)31483-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18942272</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oser</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Blades</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Strasheim</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Helgerson</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Gohdes</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Harwell</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Awareness of cardiovascular disease risk in American Indians</article-title><source>Ethn Dis</source><year>2006</year><volume>16</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>345</fpage><lpage>350</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17682234</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schweigman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Eichner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Welty</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cardiovascular disease risk factor awareness in American Indian communities: the strong heart study</article-title><source>Ethn Dis</source><year>2006</year><volume>16</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>647</fpage><lpage>652</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16937600</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brega</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Noe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Loudhawk-hedgepeth</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cardiovascular knowledge among urban American Indians and Alaska natives: first steps in addressing cardiovascular health</article-title><source>Prog Community Health Partnersh</source><year>2011</year><volume>5</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>273</fpage><lpage>279</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1353/cpr.2011.0042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22080775</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>GO</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosin</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name></person-group><source>Recognizing and surviving heart attacks and strokes: lifesaving advice you need now</source><year>2008</year><publisher-loc>Columbia, Missouri</publisher-loc><publisher-name>University of Missouri Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wall</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name><surname>Beagan</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>O'neill</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Foell</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Boddie-willis</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Addressing stroke signs and symptoms through public education: the stroke heroes act FAST campaign</article-title><source>Prev Chronic Dis</source><year>2008</year><volume>5</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>A49</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18341784</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lees</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Bluhmki</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Von Kummer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Time to treatment with intravenous alteplase and outcome in stroke: an updated pooled analysis of ECASS, ATLANTIS, NINDS, and EPITHET trials</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2010</year><volume>375</volume><issue>9727</issue><fpage>1695</fpage><lpage>1703</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(10)60491-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20472172</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fonarow</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name><name><surname>Saver</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Timeliness of tissue-type plasminogen activator therapy in acute ischemic stroke: patient characteristics, hospital factors, and outcomes associated with door-to-needle times within 60 minutes</article-title><source>Circulation</source><year>2011</year><volume>123</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>750</fpage><lpage>758</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.110.974675</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21311083</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O'gara</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name><surname>Kushner</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name><name><surname>Ascheim</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>2013 ACCF/AHA guideline for the management of ST-elevation myocardial infarction: executive summary: a report of the American College of Cardiology Foundation/American Heart Association task force on practice guidelines</article-title><source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source><year>2013</year><volume>61</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>485</fpage><lpage>510</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jacc.2012.11.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23256913</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name><name><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Blankenship</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>2011 ACCF/AHA/SCAI guideline for percutaneous coronary intervention: a report of the American College of Cardiology Foundation/American Heart Association task force on practice guidelines and the Society for Cardiovascular Angiography and Interventions</article-title><source>Circulation</source><year>2011</year><volume>124</volume><issue>23</issue><fpage>e574</fpage><lpage>e651</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22064601</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mokdad</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Stroup</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Giles</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Public health surveillance for behavioral risk factors in a changing environment. Recommendations from the Behavioral Risk Factor Surveillance Team</article-title><source>MMWR Recomm Rep</source><year>2003</year><volume>52</volume><issue>RR-9</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12817947</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</collab></person-group><source>2009 Behavioral Risk Factor Surveillance System Questionnaire</source><year>2008</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Camarata</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Heros</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Latchaw</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>"brain attack": the rationale for treating stroke as a medical emergency</article-title><source>Neurosurgery</source><year>1994</year><volume>34</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>144</fpage><lpage>157</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8121551</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chaturvedi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Should stroke be considered both a brain attack and a heart attack?</article-title><source>Stroke</source><year>2007</year><volume>38</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1713</fpage><lpage>1714</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/STROKEAHA.107.487223</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17431200</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saylor</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Friedmann</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Navigating complex sample analysis using national survey data</article-title><source>Nurs Res</source><year>2012</year><volume>61</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>231</fpage><lpage>237</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/NNR.0b013e3182533403</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22551998</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">St Hill CA, Swanoski MT, Lipsky MS, Lutfiyya MN. A population-based, cross-sectional study examining health services deficits of US veterans using 2014 behavioral risk factor surveillance system data: is rural residency an independent risk factor after controlling for multiple covariates? Healthcare (Basel). 2017;5(3).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lutfiyya</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Soffe</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipsky</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dental care utilization: examining the associations between health services deficits and not having a dental visit in past 12&#x02009;months</article-title><source>BMC Public Health</source><year>2019</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>265</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12889-019-6590-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30836954</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ratner</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Mackay</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tu</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Hossain</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Knowledge of &#x0201c;heart attack&#x0201d; symptoms in a Canadian urban community</article-title><source>Clin Med Insights Cardiol</source><year>2008</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>201</fpage><lpage>213</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mcneil</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Knowledge of heart attack symptoms in a community survey of Victoria</article-title><source>Emerg Med (Fremantle)</source><year>2002</year><volume>14</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>255</fpage><lpage>260</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1442-2026.2002.00340.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12487042</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schneider</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Pancioli</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Khoury</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Trends in community knowledge of the warning signs and risk factors for stroke</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2003</year><volume>289</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>343</fpage><lpage>346</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.289.3.343</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12525235</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reeves</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hogan</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Rafferty</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Knowledge of stroke risk factors and warning signs among Michigan adults</article-title><source>Neurology</source><year>2002</year><volume>59</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1547</fpage><lpage>1552</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/01.WNL.0000031796.52748.A5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12451195</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lutfiyya</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Asner</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipsky</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Disparities in stroke symptomology knowledge among US midlife women: an analysis of population survey data</article-title><source>J Stroke Cerebrovasc Dis</source><year>2009</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>150</fpage><lpage>157</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jstrokecerebrovasdis.2008.09.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19251192</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fussman</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Rafferty</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Reeves</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zackery</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lyon-callo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Racial disparities in knowledge of stroke and heart attack risk factors and warning signs among Michigan adults</article-title><source>Ethn Dis</source><year>2009</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>128</fpage><lpage>134</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19537222</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Call</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name><name><surname>Mcalpine</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Beebe</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mcrae</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Barriers to care among American Indians in public health care programs</article-title><source>Med Care</source><year>2006</year><volume>44</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>595</fpage><lpage>600</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/01.mlr.0000215901.37144.94</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16708009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Steele</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>Cardinez</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Tom-orme</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Surveillance for health behaviors of American Indians and Alaska natives-findings from the behavioral risk factor surveillance system, 2000-2006</article-title><source>Cancer</source><year>2008</year><volume>113</volume><issue>5 Suppl</issue><fpage>1131</fpage><lpage>1141</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cncr.23727</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18720374</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zuckerman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Haley</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Roubideaux</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Lillie-Blanton</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Health service access, use, and insurance coverage among American Indians/Alaska natives and whites: what role does the Indian Health Service play?</article-title><source>Am J Public Health</source><year>2004</year><volume>94</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>59</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2105/AJPH.94.1.53</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14713698</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>National Center for Chronic Disease Prevention and Health Promotion</collab></person-group><source>A program guide for public health: partnering with the pharmacist in the prevention and control of chronic diseases</source><year>2012</year><publisher-loc>Atlanta</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maguire</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>McElnay</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Drummond</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A randomized controlled trial of a smoking cessation intervention based in community pharmacies</article-title><source>Addiction</source><year>2001</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>325</fpage><lpage>331</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1360-0443.2001.96232516.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11182878</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsuyuki</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Teo</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ackman</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Biggs</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Cave</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name><surname>Dzavik</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Farris</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name><name><surname>Galvin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Semchuk</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A randomized trial of the effect of community pharmacist intervention on cholesterol risk management: the study of cardiovascular risk intervention by pharmacists (SCRIP)</article-title><source>Arch Intern Med</source><year>2002</year><volume>162</volume><fpage>1149</fpage><lpage>1155</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archinte.162.10.1149</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12020186</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zillich</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sutherland</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumbera</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hypertension outcomes through blood pressure monitoring and evaluation by pharmacists (HOME study)</article-title><source>JGIM</source><year>2005</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>1091</fpage><lpage>1096</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1525-1497.2005.0226.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16423096</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McLean</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>McAlister</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Makowsky</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsuyuki</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A randomized trial of the effect of community pharmacist and nurse care on improving blood pressure management in patients with diabetes mellitus: study of cardiovascular risk intervention by pharmacists-hypertension (SCRIPHTN)</article-title><source>Arch Intern Med</source><year>2008</year><volume>168</volume><fpage>2355</fpage><lpage>2361</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archinte.168.21.2355</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19029501</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sinclair</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name><surname>Bond</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lennox</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Silcock</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Winfield</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Knowledge of and attitudes to smoking cessation: the effect of stage of change training for community pharmacy staff</article-title><source>Health Bull</source><year>1998</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>526</fpage><lpage>539</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anderegg</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Gums</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name><surname>Uribe</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Coffey</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>James</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Physician-pharmacist collaborative management: narrowing the socioeconomic blood pressure gap</article-title><source>Hypertension</source><year>2016</year><volume>68</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1314</fpage><lpage>1320</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/HYPERTENSIONAHA.116.08043</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27600181</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bingham</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Mallette</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Federal Bureau of Prisons clinical pharmacy program improves patient A1C</article-title><source>J Am Pharm Assoc (2003)</source><year>2016</year><volume>56</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>173</fpage><lpage>177</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.japh.2016.01.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27000168</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dixon</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Sisson</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Parod</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Tassell</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name><name><surname>Nadpara</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Carl</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Dow A</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pharmacist-physician collaborative care model and time to goal blood pressure in the uninsured population</article-title><source>J Clin Hypertens (Greenwich)</source><year>2018</year><volume>20</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>88</fpage><lpage>95</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jch.13150</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29237095</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">National Association of Chain Drug Stores. Re: Health Care Workshop, Project No. P131207. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nacds.org/ceo/2014/0508/supplementa">http://www.nacds.org/ceo/2014/0508/supplementa</ext-link> l_comments.pdf.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsuyuki</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name><surname>Beahm</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name><name><surname>Okada</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Al Hamarneh</surname><given-names>YN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pharmacists as accessible primary health care providers: review of the evidence</article-title><source>Can Pharm J (Ott)</source><year>2018</year><volume>151</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>4</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1715163517745517</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29317929</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>