<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Open Access Maced J Med Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Open Access Maced J Med Sci</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Open Access Macedonian Journal of Medical Sciences</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1857-9655</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Republic of Macedonia</publisher-name><publisher-loc>ID Design 2012/DOOEL Skopje</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31949515</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6953944</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">OAMJMS-7-3195</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3889/oamjms.2019.795</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Clinical Science</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Comparison of Ondansetron and Granisetron Effects for Prevention of Nausea and Vomiting Following Strabismus Surgery</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Salajegheh</surname><given-names>Shirin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kuhestani</surname><given-names>Soodeh</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kermani</surname><given-names>Mahdieh Sharifzadeh</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Taheri</surname><given-names>Omid</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bafghi</surname><given-names>Naeimeh Naeimi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Anesthesiology, Shafa Hospital, Kerman University of Medical Sciences, Kerman, Iran</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Anesthesiology, Bahonar Hospital, Kerman University of Medical Sciences, Kerman, Iran</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label><bold>Correspondence:</bold> Soodeh Kuhestani. Department of Anesthesiology, Bahonar Hospital, Kerman University of Medical Sciences, Kerman, Iran. Tel: 00989131950629. Email: <email xlink:href="aeghmazi93@gmail.com">aeghmazi93@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><day>15</day><month>10</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>9</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>19</issue><fpage>3195</fpage><lpage>3200</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>25</day><month>7</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>10</day><month>8</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>8</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; 2019 Shirin Salajegheh, Soodeh Kuhestani, Mahdieh Sharifzadeh Kermani, Omid Taheri, Naeimeh Naeimi Bafghi.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/CC BY-NC/4.0"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License (CC BY-NC 4.0)</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec id="st1"><title>BACKGROUND:</title><p>Postoperative nausea and vomiting (PONV) is a common complaint after strabismus surgery that leads to unpleasantness, increased hospitalisation time and increased costs. In severe cases, it can lead to dehydration, electrolyte disturbances, aspiration, pneumonia, and even sutures opening.</p></sec><sec id="st2"><title>AIM:</title><p>This study was conducted to compare the effects of both ondansetron and granisetron on the reduction of PONV after strabismus surgery.</p></sec><sec id="st3"><title>METHODS:</title><p>This randomised, and the double-blind clinical study was conducted on patients with ASA I and II undergoing strabismus surgery with age over 3 years old in Shafa Hospital, Kerman University of Medical Sciences during 2017 under general anaesthesia. Patients with inclusion criteria were randomly assigned to one of three groups including Ondansetron (A), Granisetron (B) and control group (C). Matching cases and controls on drugs were fully completed. Furthermore, 100 &#x003bc;g/kg of Ondansetron was intravenously injected, followed by injection of 40 &#x003bc;g/kg Granisetron for another intervention group. All patients underwent the same anaesthetic procedure and intravenous injection of drugs during anaesthesia induction. The severity of nausea and vomiting in recovery, 6 and 18 hours after the operation were verified according to the Verbal Rating Scale (VRS). Our data were analysed by Chi-square, ANOVA and TUKEY tests via SPSS version 18.</p></sec><sec id="st4"><title>RESULTS:</title><p>There was no significant difference between the three groups in terms of age and sex. The incidence of postoperative nausea in recovery among three groups of A, B and C was determined to be 15, 7.5 and 37.5%, respectively. No significant difference was found between the two groups A and B (P = 0.68), although there was a significant difference between these two groups and group C (P &#x0003c; 0.05). The incidence of nausea at 6 hours after surgery in groups A, B and C was recorded as 40, 15 and 65% respectively, indicating that the incidence of nausea in group B was significantly lower than the other two groups, while showed a significant difference with group A (P = 0.039) and group C (P &#x0003c; 0.05). Also, the incident of nausea between groups was not statistically significant 18 hours after surgery (P &#x0003c; 0.05). Additionally, no significant difference was found in different groups in terms of vomiting incidence in recovery, 6 and 18 hours after surgery (P &#x0003c; 0.05).</p></sec><sec id="st5"><title>CONCLUSION:</title><p>Our study suggests that Granisetron is more effective in preventing PONV during 6 hours after the surgery in comparison with Ondansetron which makes it a favourable alternative for preventing PONV.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Nausea</kwd><kwd>Vomiting</kwd><kwd>Strabismus Surgery</kwd><kwd>Endonestrone</kwd><kwd>Granisetron</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Postoperative nausea and vomiting (PONV) are the second most adverse and complicated event following surgery [<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>], [<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. This usually occurs in the post-anaesthetic phase and ends within 24 hours, which its incidence ranged from 30 to 20% [<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Risk factors for postoperative nausea and vomiting include females, duration of anaesthesia for more than half an hour, age above 3 years, type of surgery, personal or familial history of postoperative nausea and vomiting, or motion sickness [<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], [<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].</p><p>The type of surgery is not necessarily the most important cause of PONV. The occurrence of PONV following various surgeries is more due to the factors related to the patient and anaesthesia than the self-surgery issue [<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], [<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. PONV is an unpleasant experience that patients often find worse than postoperative pain [<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Prevention of PONV in patients at high risk of this complication improves postoperative satisfaction [<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Although PONV is self-limiting, its occurrence following surgery can lead to multiple complications such as aspiration of stomach contents, suture opening, oesophagal rupture, subcutaneous emphysema and pneumothorax [<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], [<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. PONV delayed the patient&#x02019;s recovery and prolonged unexpected hospitalisation after an outpatient operation [<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. PONV prolongs the discharge time to 61-47 minutes. The annual impact of PONV on <italic>healthcare costs</italic> is estimated to be several hundred million dollars in the United States [<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. The reason for the lack of definitive prevention of PONV is the presence of multiple factors associated with this disorder, so the main solution to prevent this complication is still the use of anti-nausea drugs in clinical cases. <italic>Ondansetron</italic> is a serotonin receptor antagonist that is considered as the most effective anti-vomiting drug for preventing PONV [<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], [<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Granisetron is a serotonin 5-HT<sub>3</sub> receptor antagonist, with a half-life of about two times that of <italic>Ondansetron</italic> [<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], [<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>].</p><p>Strabismus surgery is among the operations with a high prevalence of PONV (75-40%), which causes long recovery, high costs, increased bleeding, increased eye pressure and patient dissatisfaction due to the nature of the strabismus surgery caused by the muscle tightening [<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Therefore, we compared the effect of two <italic>Ondansetron</italic> and Granisetron drugs on nausea and vomiting following strabismus surgery.</p></sec><sec sec-type="material|methods" id="sec1-2"><title>Material and methods</title><p>This randomised, and the double-blind clinical study was conducted on patients undergoing strabismus surgery with age over 3 years old in Shafa Hospital, Kerman University of Medical Sciences during 2017. Sampling was done based on purpose and field information was collected using a questionnaire.</p><p>Considering the maximum sample size, the standard deviation in similar studies, alpha coefficient of 5% and power of 80% [<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], [<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>], 120 patients with strabismus surgery were randomly assigned to 3 groups of 40 subjects in the placebo, <italic>Ondansetron</italic> and Granisetron.</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" width="100%"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Alpha</italic></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>=</italic></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>0.05</italic></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>(two-sided)</italic></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Z (1-&#x003b1;/2)</italic></th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>1.959964</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">power</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">=</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Z (1-&#x003b2;)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.841621</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">m1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">=</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">m2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">=</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">s<sup>2</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.69</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sd1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">=</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sd<sub>1</sub><sup>2</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.44</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sd2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">=</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sd<sub>2</sub><sup>2</sup></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.96</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.68619</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.68619</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p><graphic xlink:href="OAMJMS-7-3195-g001.jpg" position="float"/></p><p>Inclusion criteria: 1) Patients undergoing strabismus surgery over the age of 3 years And 2) Class 1 &#x00026; 2 American Society of Anaesthesiologists&#x02019; (ASA) classification of Physical Health. Exclusion criteria: 1) History of previous surgery and anaesthesia with postoperative nausea and vomiting; 2) History of M&#x000e9;ni&#x000e8;re&#x02019;s disease, motion sickness or migraine; 3) Dissatisfaction with surgery; 4) Use of drugs that affect nausea and vomiting within 24 hours of surgery; 5) Pregnancy or breastfeeding.</p><p>Patients with inclusion criteria were randomly assigned to one of three groups, including Ondansetron, Granisetron and placebo (normal saline administration). In a randomised clinical trial was blinded, in which neither the patient nor the evaluating person informed the type of drug used. Furthermore, matching cases and controls on drugs were fully completed.</p><p>Induction of all three groups was performed with midazolam 1 mg, fentanyl 100-50 micrograms, thiopental 5 mg/kg and atracurium 0.2 mg/kg. Maintenance of anaesthesia was carried out in all three groups with propofol infusion (100 &#x003bc;g/kg/min) and 50% N2O-O2 mixture.</p><p>After giving premed to the patient, 100 &#x003bc;g/kg of Ondansetron was intravenously injected, followed by injection of 40 &#x003bc;g/kg Granisetron for another intervention group.</p><p>All recovery personnel and section were unaware of the patient groups and the type of drug used. The severity of nausea and vomiting were evaluated by an anesthesiologist at the recovery and after transferring to the section during 6 hours following the operation and then after discharge from the hospital during the next 18 hours. A drug for the treatment of nausea and vomiting was not given to patients during anaesthesia. In case of severe nausea and vomiting, a dose of dimenhydrinate (mg) was administered to the patient. Additionally, patients who suffered from nausea and vomiting in recovery, received metoclopramide 0.1 mg/kg.</p><p>Because the two drugs used are both anti-nausea and -vomiting, and only their effect and potency are different, no additional drugs have been given to patients in recovery. Recording the age, height, weight and duration of anaesthesia, the severity of nausea and vomiting in recovery were done by anaesthesia technician. After transferring the patient to the section, the patients were evaluated by the anaesthesia resident within 6 hours after the operation and then after discharge from the hospital within the next 18 hours. The severity of nausea is measured according to the Verbal Rating Scale (VRS). By this method, an individual without nausea is assigned zero, in case of less than two nausea episode, mild nausea was considered, as followed twice or more (moderate nausea). The incidence of vomiting is considered to be the same as severe nausea.</p><p>Ethical considerations included: 1. Approval of the plan by the Research Council of the School of Medicine; 2. Informed consent was obtained from the patient to participate in the study, of mention, obtained by the legal parents for the children; and 3. Both anti-nausea drugs are used routinely without any complications if any unwanted side effects were observed, each treatment was followed by a withdrawal from the study, but no complication was observed.</p><sec id="sec2-1"><title>Data analysis</title><p>Information for each group was coded as 1, 2 and 3, and the recorded in the checklist for each drug or placebo, followed by statistical analysis through the SPSS version 18 software. Data analysis Information for each of the 3 groups, coded 1, 2 and 3, was recorded in the checklist for each drug or placebo, and then entered the SPSS version 18 software. Using the Kolmogorov-Smirnov test, the data were analysed for normal distribution. Depending on the distribution of data and quantitative or qualitative values, quantitative data such as age were analysed using one-way ANOVA test regarding their normalisation, while Non-parametric Kruskal-Wallis H test was used for data with skewed distribution. If parametric or parametric tests showed significant values, Dunn&#x02019;s multiple comparisons test and Tukey tests were employed to compare the groups. Chi-square test was applied to evaluate the qualitative variables. Regarding the lack of time assessment, repeated tests such as repeated measures ANOVA were not used. In all tests, a significant level of 0.05 was considered.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec1-3"><title>Results</title><p>Our study was conducted on 120 patients who referred to the operating room of the hospital for strabismus surgery and randomly divided into three groups: A (Ondansetron), B (Granisetron) and C (Placebo). Study population consisted of 76 male patients (63.3%) and 44 (36.7%) female. Among them, 26 patients received A, 21 drug B and 29 C, respectively. Among the female patients, 14 received A, 19 B and 11 C, respectively. Forty people were considered for each group A, B and C, without regarding gender.</p><p>The results of the chi-square test showed no significant relationship between nausea rate in all three groups and sex (P = 0.175). The mean age and standard deviation in each of groups A, B, C were determined as 43.68 &#x000b1; 19.3, 22.78 &#x000b1; 16.1 and 97.74 &#x000b1; 13.1.</p><p>The mean age of patients in Ondansetron, Granisetron and control groups was 19.43, 16.22 and 13.97, respectively. The mean age of the subjects was 16.49 years. Based on the ANOVA test, no significant difference was found between the groups in terms of age (P = 0.332).</p><p><xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> shows the magnitude and severity of nausea and vomiting in recovery. Of the 120 participants, 15% had a feeling of nausea in group A, followed by group B (7.5%) and group C (37.5%). The best possible status for lack of nausea episode was in group B with 92.5%, followed by group A (85%) and group C (62.5%). The highest vomiting (3 cases) was recorded in group C, followed by group A (one person) and group B (none), (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>The rate and severity of nausea and vomiting in recovery among three groups (A, B, C)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" width="100%"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="3">Variable</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">An (Endonestrone)</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">B (Granisetron)</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">C (control)</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Total</th></tr><tr><th align="center" colspan="8" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percent</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percent</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percent</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percent</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">Recovery</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No nausea</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mild nausea</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate nausea</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severity Nausea (Vomit)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p><xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> indicates the measurement of nausea episodes and severity in 6 hours after surgery. Of the 120 patients, 60% of the subjects did not feel nauseous, while 23.3% had mild nausea, followed by moderate nausea (7.5%) and severe nausea (vomiting: 9.2%).</p><table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>The rate and severity of nausea and vomiting in the first 6 hours after surgery in the three groups (A, B, C)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" width="100%"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="3">Variable</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">An (Endonestrone)</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">B (Granisetron)</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">C (control)</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Total</th></tr><tr><th align="center" colspan="8" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percent</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percent</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percent</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percent</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">6h after</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No nausea</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mild nausea</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate nausea</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severity Nausea (Vomit)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.2</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>The most common nausea episodes were observed in group C (placebo) with 65%, while episodes were 40% in group A and 15% in group B. In other words, the best possible situation was seen in Group B (85% without nausea). Vomiting in groups A, B and C was 7.5, 2.5 and 17.5%, with the lowest vomiting in group B and the highest in group C (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).</p><p>The incidence rate and severity of nausea and vomiting in 18 hours after surgery are listed in <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. After 18 hours of operation, 96.7% of the patients had no nausea episode One in group A, one in group B and two in group C patients, expressed the feeling, while vomiting was seen only in the group C (<xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T4" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Incidence and severity of nausea and vomiting 18 hours after operation in three groups (A, B, C)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" width="100%"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="3">Variable</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">An (Endonestrone)</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">B (Granisetron)</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">C (control)</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Total</th></tr><tr><th align="center" colspan="8" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percent</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percent</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percent</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percent</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4" colspan="1">18 h after</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No nausea</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">116</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mild nausea</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate nausea</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Severity Nausea (Vomit)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>The incidence of postoperative nausea in recovery in the three groups of Ondansetron, Granisetron and control was determined to be 15, 7.5 and 37.5%, respectively (<xref rid="T5" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). The result of the test demonstrated a significant general relationship between the groups. Based on the results of Tukey test, we found that despite the low nausea rate in the Granisetron group compared to the Ondansetron group, no significant difference was found between the two groups in terms of nausea (P = 0.658), although there was a significant difference between the two groups and the control group (P &#x0003c; 0.05) (<xref rid="T5" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T5" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Comparison of the three groups in terms of postoperative nausea in recovery</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" width="100%"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="3">Variable</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">An (Endonestrone)</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">B (Granisetron)</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">C (control)</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Total</th><th align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Results of the Chi-Square Test</th></tr><tr><th align="center" colspan="8" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percent</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percent</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percent</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percent</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recovery</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nausea</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Regarding the incidence of vomiting in recovery, although it was relatively reduced in the Granisetron group in comparison with Ondansetron and placebo, but no statistically significant difference was observed between the groups (P = 0.164) (<xref rid="T6" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T6" position="float"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Comparison of the three groups in terms of postoperative vomiting in recovery</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" width="100%"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="3">Variable</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">An (Endonestrone)</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">B (Granisetron)</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">C (control)</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Total</th><th align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Results of the Chi-Square Test</th></tr><tr><th align="center" colspan="8" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percent</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percent</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percent</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percent</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Recovery</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vomiting</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.164</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>The incidence of nausea in the 6 hours after strabismus surgery in the Ondansetron, Granisetron and control groups was 40, 15 and 65% respectively, indicating that the incidence of nausea was significantly lower in the Granisetron group when compared with the other two groups.</p><p>Although the incidence of vomiting demonstrated a decreasing trend in the granitic group at 6 hours after the operation as compared to placebo and indomethacin, there was no statistically significant difference between the groups (P = 0.061; <xref rid="T7" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref> and <xref rid="T8" ref-type="table">7</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T7" position="float"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Comparison of the three groups in terms of postoperative nausea in 6 hours after surgery</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" width="100%"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="3">Variable</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">An (Endonestrone)</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">B (Granisetron)</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">C (control)</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Total</th><th align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Results of the Chi-Square Test</th></tr><tr><th align="center" colspan="8" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percent</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percent</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percent</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percent</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6H after</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nausea</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0001</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T8" position="float"><label>Table 7</label><caption><p>Comparison of the three groups in terms of vomiting in 6 hours after surgery</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" width="100%"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="3">Variable</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">An (Endonestrone)</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">B (Granisetron)</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">C (control)</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Total</th><th align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Results of the Chi-Square Test</th></tr><tr><th align="center" colspan="8" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percent</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percent</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percent</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percent</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 h after</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vomiting</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.061</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>The incidence of nausea was not significantly different between the groups 18 hours after surgery (P = 0.772).</p><p>Also, there was no significant difference between the groups in terms of vomiting incidence 18 hours after the operation (P = 0.336; P &#x0003c; 0.05; <xref rid="T9" ref-type="table">Table 8</xref> and <xref rid="T10" ref-type="table">9</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T9" position="float"><label>Table 8</label><caption><p>Comparison of the three groups in terms of nausea 18 hours after surgery</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" width="100%"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="3">Variable</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">An (Endonestrone)</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">B (Granisetron)</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">C (control)</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Total</th><th align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Results of the Chi-Square Test</th></tr><tr><th align="center" colspan="8" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percent</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percent</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percent</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percent</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 h after</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nausea</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.772</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T10" position="float"><label>Table 9</label><caption><p>Comparison of the three groups in terms of vomiting 18 hours after surgery</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" width="100%"><thead><tr><th align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="3">Variable</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">An (Endonestrone)</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">B (Granisetron)</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">C (control)</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Total</th><th align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Results of the Chi-Square Test</th></tr><tr><th align="center" colspan="8" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percent</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percent</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percent</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percent</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18 h after</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vomiting</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.365</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec1-4"><title>Discussion</title><p>Today, the increasing number of surgeries has increased the desire for early release of patients from recovery. Decreasing the incidence of PONV has accelerated the discharge of patients, reduces the length of hospitalisation or re-admission, and leads to patient satisfaction [<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>], [<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. In this regard, we aimed to compare the effect of both Ondansetron, and Granisetron on nausea and vomiting following strabismus surgery.</p><p>The findings of the statistical tests showed that there was no significant difference between the level of nausea in all three groups and gender (p = 0.175). Furthermore, the mean age of patients in the three groups revealed no significant difference between the groups in terms of age (P = 0.332). The best possible status for lack of nausea was observed in group B (92.5%), followed by group A (85%) and group C (62.5%). Despite the low nausea rate in the Granisetron group in comparison with Ondansetron, there was no significant difference between them (P = 0.658);</p><p>The highest vomiting (3 cases) was recorded in group C, followed by group A (one person) and group B (none), (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). However, there was a significant difference between the two intervention groups and the control group (P &#x0003c; 0.05).</p><p>The highest vomiting (3 cases) was recorded in group C, followed by group A (one person) and group B (none). Although recovery vomiting was relatively reduced in the Granisetron group as compared to Ondansetron and placebo, but no statistically significant difference was found between the groups (P = 0.164).</p><p>Based on the results presented herein, 60% of the subjects did not feel nauseous, while 23.3% had mild nausea, followed by moderate nausea (7.5%) and severe nausea (vomiting: 9.2%).</p><p>The most common nausea episode was observed in group C (placebo) with 65%, while the episode was 40% in group A and 15% in group B. The best possible situation was seen in Group B (85% without nausea); Statistically, the incidence of nausea in the Granisetron group was significantly less than the other two groups, and this difference was significant in comparison with the Ondansetron group (P = 0.039) and the control group (P &#x0003c; 0.05).</p><p>In addition, vomiting in groups A, B and C was determined as 7.5, 2.5 and 17.5%, where the lowest vomiting was observed in group B and the highest in group C. Although, relative reduction of vomiting was observed in the Granisetron group as compared to placebo and Ondansetron, but no statistically significant difference was found between the groups (P = 0.061).</p><p>The incidence rate and severity of nausea and vomiting in 18 hours after surgery are listed in <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. After 18 hours of operation, 96.7% of the patients had no nausea episode. One in group A, one in group B and two in group C expressed episodes while vomiting was seen only in the group C.</p><p>The incidence of nausea was not statistically significant among the groups 18 hours after surgery (P = 0.772). Moreover, there was no significant difference between the groups in terms of vomiting18 hours after surgery (P = 0.365), (P &#x0003c; 0.05).</p><p>Very limited studies have been conducted on the effects of both Granisetron and Ondansetron on reducing the incidence of PONV in strabismus surgery, although more studies are available for other surgeries such as laparoscopy. Most studies have shown that Granisetron is more effective than Ondansetron which is consistent with our study, although some studies have also shown contradictory results.</p><p>A study assessed the effect of Granisetron, Ondansetron, Midazolam combination with Dexamethasone for reduction of PONV after strabismus surgery among 100 children ASA class I and II, where findings did not show significant differences between different groups [<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>].</p><p>Another study evaluated antiemetic effects of Ondansetron and Granisetron in preventing postoperative nausea and vomiting in subjects undergoing daycare laparoscopic tubal ligation where minimal emetic episodes in patients receiving intravenous granisetron when comparing with those receiving ondansetron and placebo. The study mentioned above indicated that emetic episodes were attributed to 7% of patients receiving intravenous granisetron, followed by 20% in the ondansetron group and 50% in placebo group C [<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>].</p><p>In a randomized double-blind investigation, 100 female patients were assessed for effect of Ondansetron and Granisetron in preventing PONV (intervals of 6-0, 12-6, 18-12 and 24-18 after surgery) in subjects undergoing elective laparoscopic cholecystectomy, where a significant was found in the incidence of PONV among two groups after 6 hours to 24 hours [<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>].</p><p>Gauchan et al. evaluated the antiemetic efficacy of Ondansetron and Granisetron in patients undergoing laparoscopic cholecystectomy during the first 24 hours after anaesthesia. They indicated that Granisetron was effectively capable of increasing incidence of PONV as compared to Ondansetron in the first 24 hours [<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>].</p><p>In another study by Savant et al., the effects of ondansetron (4 mg, 2 mL) and granisetron (2 mg, 2 mL) was assessed in preventing PONV in subjects undergoing oral and maxillofacial surgery.</p><p>Except for the headache side effect, it has been shown that the incidence of nausea and vomiting in the Granisetron group was significantly lower than that of Ondansetron [<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>].</p><p>In conclusion, our study suggests that Granisetron is more effective in preventing PONV for 6 hours after the surgery in comparison with Ondansetron which makes it a favourable alternative.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="supported-by"><p><bold>Funding:</bold> This research did not receive any financial support</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Competing Interests:</bold> The authors have declared that no competing interests exist</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Palazzo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Logistic regression analysis of fixed patient factors for postoperative sickness:a model for risk assessment</article-title><source>Br J Anaesth</source><year>1993</year><volume>70</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>135</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><comment>https://doi.org/10.1093/bja/70.2.135 PMid:8435254</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8435254</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Modir</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Moshiri</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamali</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Shokrpour</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shams</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prophylatic efficacy of dexamethasone, ketamine and dexmedetomidine against intra- and postoperative nausea and vomiting under spinal anesthesia</article-title><source>Formos J Surg</source><year>2019</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><comment>https://doi.org/10.4103/fjs.fjs_37_18</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dolin</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cashman</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Bland</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effectiveness of acute postoperative pain management:I. Evidence from published data</article-title><source>Br J Anaesth</source><year>2002</year><volume>89</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>409</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><comment>https://doi.org/10.1093/bja/89.3.409 PMid:12402719</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12402719</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodgers</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anesthetic management for pediatric strabismus surgery:Continuing professional development</article-title><source>Can J Anaesth</source><year>2010</year><volume>57</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>602</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><comment>https://doi.org/10.1007/s12630-010-9300-x PMid:20393822</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20393822</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eberhart</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Geldner</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kranke</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Morin</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sch&#x000e4;uffelen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Treiber</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The development and validation of a risk score to predict the probability of postoperative vomiting in pediatric patients</article-title><source>Anesth Analg</source><year>2004</year><volume>99</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1630</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><comment>https://doi.org/10.1213/01.ANE.0000135639.57715.6C PMid:15562045</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15562045</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koivuranta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>L&#x000e4;&#x000e4;r&#x000e4;</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Sn&#x000e5;re</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Alahuhta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A survey of postoperative nausea and vomiting</article-title><source>Anaesthesia</source><year>1997</year><volume>52</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>443</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><comment>https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2044.1997.117-az0113.x PMid:9165963</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9165963</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cario</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Weinger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Carney</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Which clinical anesthesia outcomes are important to avoid?The perspective of patients</article-title><source>Anesth Analg</source><year>1999</year><volume>89</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>652</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><comment>https://doi.org/10.1097/00000539-199909000-00022 PMid:10475299</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10475299</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Darkow</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Gora-Harper</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Goulson</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Record</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of antiemetic selection on postoperative nausea and vomiting and patient satisfaction</article-title><source>Pharmacotherapy</source><year>2001</year><volume>21</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>540</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><comment>https://doi.org/10.1592/phco.21.6.540.34543 PMid:11349743</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11349743</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bremner</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Delayed surgical emphysema, pneumomediastinum and bilateral pneumothoraces after postoperative vomiting</article-title><source>Br J Anaesth</source><year>1993</year><volume>71</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>296</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><comment>https://doi.org/10.1093/bja/71.2.296 PMid:8123411</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8123411</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schumann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Polaner</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Massive subcutaneous emphysema and sudden airway compromise after postoperative vomiting</article-title><source>Anesth Analg</source><year>1999</year><volume>89</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>796</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><comment>https://doi.org/10.1097/00000539-199909000-00050 PMid:10475327</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10475327</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gold</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitz</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lecky</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Neuhaus</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Unanticipated admission to the hospital ollowing ambulatory surgery</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>1989</year><volume>262</volume><issue>21</issue><fpage>3008</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><comment>https://doi.org/10.1001/jama.1989.03430210050028 PMid:2810644</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2810644</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Lubarsky</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Phillips-Bute</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Fortney</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Creed</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cost-effectiveness of prophylactic antiemetic therapy with ondansetron, droperidol, or placebo</article-title><source>Anesthesiology</source><year>2000</year><volume>92</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>958</fpage><lpage>67</lpage><comment>https://doi.org/10.1097/00000542-200004000-00012 PMid:10754614</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10754614</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pazoki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Modir</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamali</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zamani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Shahidani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ondansetron 8 mg and 4 mg with normal saline against post-operative headache and nausea/vomiting after spinal anesthesia:a randomized double-blind trial</article-title><source>Med Gas Res</source><year>2018</year><volume>8</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>48</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><comment>https://doi.org/10.4103/2045-9912.235125 PMid:30112165 PMCid:PMC6070840</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30112165</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Granisetron plus dexamethasone for prevention of postoperative nausea and vomiting in patients undergoing laparoscopic surgery:A meta-analysis</article-title><source>J Int Med Res</source><year>2017</year><volume>45</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>904</fpage><lpage>911</lpage><comment>https://doi.org/10.1177/0300060517703276 PMid:28436248 PMCid:PMC5536409</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28436248</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuhn</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheifler</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Wissing</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Incidence of nausea and vomiting in children after strabismus surgery following desflurane anaesthesia</article-title><source>Paediatr Anaesth</source><year>1999</year><volume>9</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>521</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><comment>https://doi.org/10.1046/j.1460-9592.1999.00418.x PMid:10597556</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10597556</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ommid</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jehan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Shiekh</surname><given-names>FI</given-names></name><name><surname>Nazir</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nissa</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative evaluation of ondansetron and granisetron in prevention of postoperative nausea and vomiting following laparoscopic cholecystectomy in females</article-title><source>IOSR</source><year>2013</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><comment>https://doi.org/10.9790/0853-0411520</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gauchan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Thapa</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Shakya</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhattarai</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Shakya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ondansetron and Granisetron for prevention of postoperative nausea and vomiting following laparoscopic cholecystectomy</article-title><source>Journal of Nepal Medical Association</source><year>2014</year><volume>52</volume><issue>193</issue><fpage>682</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><comment>https://doi.org/10.31729/jnma.2591</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shaikh</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagarekha</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hegade</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Marutheesh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Postoperative nausea and vomiting:A simple yet complex problem</article-title><source>Anesth Essays Res</source><year>2016</year><volume>10</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>388</fpage><lpage>396</lpage><comment>https://doi.org/10.4103/0259-1162.179310 PMid:27746521 PMCid:PMC5062207</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27746521</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Howard</surname><given-names>S. Smith</given-names></name><name><surname>Eric</surname><given-names>J. Smith</given-names></name><name><surname>Benjamin</surname><given-names>R. Smith</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Postoperative nausea and vomiting</article-title><source>Postoperative nausea and vomiting</source><year>2012</year><volume>1</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>94</fpage><lpage>102</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Riad</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Marouf</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Combination therapy in the prevention of PONV after strabismus surgery in children:granisetron, ondansetron, midazolam with dexamethasone</article-title><source>Middle East J Anesthesiol</source><year>2009</year><volume>20</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>431</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19950739</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhattacharya</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of ondansetron and granisetron for prevention of nausea and vomiting following day care gynaecological laparoscopy</article-title><source>Indian J Anaesth</source><year>2003</year><volume>47</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>279</fpage><lpage>282</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Savant</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Khandeparker</surname><given-names>RVS</given-names></name><name><surname>Berwal</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Khandeparker</surname><given-names>PV</given-names></name><name><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of ondansetron and granisetron for antiemetic prophylaxis in maxillofacial surgery patients receiving general anesthesia:a prospective, randomised, and double blind study</article-title><source>Journal of the Korean Association of Oral and Maxillofacial Surgeons</source><year>2016</year><volume>42</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>84</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><comment>https://doi.org/10.5125/jkaoms.2016.42.2.84 PMid:27162748 PMCid:PMC4&#x0219b;84</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27162748</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>