<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Vet Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Vet. Res</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Veterinary Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0928-4249</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1297-9716</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31924274</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6954585</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">730</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13567-019-0730-3</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A DIVA vaccine strain lacking RpoS and the secondary messenger c-di-GMP for protection against salmonellosis in pigs</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Gil</surname><given-names>Carmen</given-names></name><address><email>mariacarmen.gil@unavarra.es</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Latasa</surname><given-names>Cristina</given-names></name><address><email>cristina.latasa@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a-Ona</surname><given-names>Enrique</given-names></name><address><email>enrique@alecos.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>L&#x000e1;zaro</surname><given-names>Isidro</given-names></name><address><email>ilazaro@intiasa.es</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Labairu</surname><given-names>Javier</given-names></name><address><email>jlabairu@intiasa.es</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Echeverz</surname><given-names>Maite</given-names></name><address><email>maite.echeverz@unavarra.es</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Burgui</surname><given-names>Saioa</given-names></name><address><email>saioa.burgui@unavarra.es</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a</surname><given-names>Bego&#x000f1;a</given-names></name><address><email>begona.garcia@unavarra.es</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Lasa</surname><given-names>I&#x000f1;igo</given-names></name><address><email>ilasa@unavarra.es</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-6207-1766</contrib-id><name><surname>Solano</surname><given-names>Cristina</given-names></name><address><email>cristina.solano@unavarra.es</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2174 6440</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.410476.0</institution-id><institution>Laboratory of Microbial Pathogenesis, </institution><institution>Navarrabiomed-Universidad P&#x000fa;blica de Navarra (UPNA)-Complejo Hospitalario de Navarra (CHN), IdiSNA, </institution></institution-wrap>Irunlarrea 3, 31008 Pamplona, Navarra Spain </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Recombina S.L., 31192 Mutilva, Navarra Spain </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>Instituto Navarro de Tecnolog&#x000ed;as e Infraestructuras Agroalimentarias-INTIA, 31610 Villava, Navarra Spain </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>10</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>51</volume><elocation-id>3</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>7</day><month>10</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>9</day><month>12</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated in a credit line to the data.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Salmonellosis is the second most common food-borne zoonosis in the European Union, with pigs being a major reservoir of this pathogen. <italic>Salmonella</italic> control in pig production requires multiple measures amongst which vaccination may be used to reduce subclinical carriage and shedding of prevalent serovars, such as <italic>Salmonella enterica</italic> serovar Typhimurium. Live attenuated vaccine strains offer advantages in terms of enhancing cell mediated immunity and allowing inoculation by the oral route. However, main failures of these vaccines are the limited cross-protection achieved against heterologous serovars and interference with serological monitoring for infection. We have recently shown that an attenuated <italic>S.</italic> Enteritidis strain (&#x00394;XIII) is protective against <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium in a murine infection model. &#x00394;XIII strain harbours 13 chromosomal deletions that make it unable to produce the sigma factor RpoS and synthesize cyclic-di-GMP (c-di-GMP). In this study, our objectives were to test the protective effects of &#x00394;XIII strain in swine and to investigate if the use of &#x00394;XIII permits the discrimination of vaccinated from infected pigs. Results show that oral vaccination of pre-weaned piglets with &#x00394;XIII cross-protected against a challenge with <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium by reducing faecal shedding and ileocaecal lymph nodes colonization, both at the time of weaning and slaughter. Vaccinated pigs showed neither faecal shedding nor tissue persistence of the vaccine strain at weaning, ensuring the absence of &#x00394;XIII strain by the time of slaughter. Moreover, lack of the SEN4316 protein in &#x00394;XIII strain allowed the development of a serological test that enabled the differentiation of infected from vaccinated animals (DIVA).</p></abstract><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100003329</institution-id><institution>Ministerio de Econom&#x000ed;a y Competitividad</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>BIO2014-53530-R</award-id><award-id>BIO2017-83035-R</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Solano</surname><given-names>Cristina</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">Salmonellosis remains the second most common zoonosis in humans in the European Union (EU), with 91 662 confirmed cases in 2017. Despite national control programmes, in recent years, the declining trend of salmonellosis cases has levelled off and the number of reported cases in the EU has not shown any statistically significant decrease. Moreover, <italic>Salmonella</italic> is still responsible for the highest number of food-borne outbreaks in the EU, with eggs, pig meat and derived products being main sources of this pathogen [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. The European Commission set the criteria to control <italic>Salmonella</italic> infections within the poultry sector, resulting in a correlated reduction in the human cases associated with the consumption of eggs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. On the contrary, proposals concerning the monitoring and control of <italic>Salmonella</italic> in pigs have been dropped [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>], but still, regulations in the swine sector should follow to tackle <italic>Salmonella</italic> infection in pigs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. The most common serovar at EU level causing human food-borne infections from pork is <italic>Salmonella enterica</italic> serovar Typhimurium (<italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium), being widely prevalent along the entire pig chain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Therefore, it is assumed that control measures should be based on actions taken throughout the production chain, including a combination of measures aimed at preventing horizontal and vertical transmission, with the final objective of producing <italic>Salmonella</italic>-free animals. At the pre-harvest level, measures can be addressed to the prevention of introduction of <italic>Salmonella</italic> into the herd; the prevention of in-herd transmission; and the increase of resistance to infection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. In this regard, <italic>Salmonella</italic> vaccines are currently regarded as an adjunct to other on-farm control measures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>], by helping to prevent <italic>Salmonella</italic> colonization and the development of a carrier state, characteristic of pigs colonized by non-adapted serovars, such as <italic>S.</italic> Enteritidis and <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>].</p><p id="Par3">In recent years, increasing numbers of live <italic>Salmonella</italic> attenuated vaccines have been developed for pigs vaccination [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>], although most of them are not yet authorized. While this type of vaccines are claimed as the most effective means of immunoprophylaxis against <italic>Salmonella</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>], there are major drawbacks that must be taken into account. First, vaccines are usually serovar specific, providing limited protection against infections with <italic>Salmonella</italic> belonging to other serovars; second, vaccination may interfere with established serological monitoring programs, making it difficult to differentiate between vaccinated and infected animals; and third, attenuated vaccine strains may reverse to virulent, unsafe forms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>].</p><p id="Par4">We recently published a report detailing the analysis of an attenuated <italic>S.</italic> Enteritidis vaccine strain, referred to as &#x00394;XIII, that protected mice against a lethal oral challenge of a <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium virulent strain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. &#x00394;XIII strain is a multiple mutant in <italic>rpoS</italic>, the gene encoding the master sigma factor during stationary phase and under a variety of stress conditions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>] and also in the 12 genes encoding diguanylate cyclase proteins responsible for the synthesis of the second messenger bis-(3&#x02032;-5&#x02032;)-cyclic dimeric GMP (c-di-GMP) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Absence of c-di-GMP in &#x00394;XIII leads to a moderate attenuation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>] whilst the additional mutation in <italic>rpoS</italic> results in a highly attenuated strain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Moreover, the secondary messenger c-di-GMP is a key molecule in the transition from a planktonic to a biofilm lifestyle [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>] since it is required for the synthesis of cellulose, the main exopolysaccharide of the <italic>Salmonella</italic> biofilm matrix [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Hence, &#x00394;XIII strain is unable to form a biofilm and is sensitive to chlorine treatment, ultraviolet light irradiation, heavy metal stress and desiccation conditions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. In our previous report carried out in mice, the vaccine candidate showed several qualities of a promising veterinary <italic>Salmonella</italic> vaccine, such as the induction of a cellular/humoral balanced, long-lasting immune response; cross protection against the non-homologous serovar <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium; low environmental persistence; improbability of virulence reversal because of the complete deletion of 13 specific genes in its chromosome and also, DIVA features that allow differentiation of infected and vaccinated animals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>].</p><p id="Par5">In the current study, our objectives were to assess whether <italic>S.</italic> Enteritidis &#x00394;XIII is also able to cross-protect piglets from a challenge with the heterologous serovar <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium and to evaluate whether this vaccine strain can be used in swine without compromising the differentiation of infected from vaccinated animals. We demonstrate that vaccination of pre-weaned piglets with &#x00394;XIII strain conferred protection against subsequent challenge with a multi-antimicrobial resistant <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium strain, by reducing <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium gastrointestinal tissue colonization and faecal shedding, both at the time of weaning and slaughter. Importantly, vaccination resulted in the induction of a serological response lacking antibodies against the diguanylate cyclase SEN4316, enabling the development of an ELISA assay for the discrimination between vaccinated and infected pigs.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Bacterial strains and culture conditions</title><p id="Par6">The vaccine candidate, <italic>S.</italic> Enteritidis &#x00394;XIII, is a multiple mutant, derivative of the wild type clinical isolate <italic>S.</italic> Enteritidis 3934 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>], carrying deletions in all genes encoding GGDEF domain proteins and in <italic>rpoS</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium STM610T, a multi-antimicrobial resistant strain serologically identified and isolated from the mesenteric lymph nodes of a fattening pig at slaughter, was used as the challenge strain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. Bacteria were grown in LB broth and on LB agar. Media was supplemented with ampicillin (Am), 100&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL, to culture and isolate the challenge strain.</p><p id="Par7">To prepare the vaccine culture and the challenge strain for pig administration, a 100&#x000a0;mL culture (LB medium) was inoculated with 100&#x000a0;&#x000b5;L of an overnight culture in LB medium and was grown with shaking at 37&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 20&#x000a0;h. The culture was kept on ice until use for a maximum of 2&#x000a0;h before administration. Inoculum doses were determined immediately after infection via serial dilution and subsequent plating onto LB agar.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Ethics statement</title><p id="Par8">All procedures involving animals were performed in accordance with the European regulations regarding the protection of animals used for experimental and other scientific purposes (Directive 2010/63/EU of the Europe), under the supervision of the Ethical and Animal Welfare Committee of the Public University of Navarra, Spain (approved protocol PI-008/11).</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Sample collection from sows and processing</title><p id="Par9">In order to analyse the level of <italic>Salmonella</italic> seroprevalence in sows of the selected farm, a serological examination to evaluate the presence of <italic>Salmonella</italic> antibodies was conducted on five randomly selected pregnant sows. Sow blood was collected 1&#x000a0;week before farrowing. After coagulation, blood samples were centrifuged for 5&#x000a0;min at 1500&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;<italic>g</italic> to collect serum and kept frozen (&#x02212;20&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C) until serological analyses were carried out. Colostrum samples were collected from the sows on the day of farrowing. Colostrum was collected from sows immediately after the last piglet was born, when the contractions had stopped and after the expulsion of placenta. Colostrum was collected from three random teats located in the anterior, middle, and posterior part of the udder and pooled to 5 to 10&#x000a0;mL. The samples were centrifuged at 13 000&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;<italic>g</italic> for 1&#x000a0;h and the supernatants were collected and frozen at &#x02212;20&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Experimental design of the safety trial</title><p id="Par10">Three pregnant sows (Duroc) were randomly selected from a farrow-to-finish pig farm with high herd <italic>Salmonella</italic> seroprevalence (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) and relocated in a newly conditioned <italic>Salmonella</italic> free farm, 1&#x000a0;week before farrowing. G Power was used to calculate the number of piglets needed to obtain statistical significance (assuming an effect size of 0.50, a power level of 0.80, and a probability level for statistical significance of 0.05). Piglets were allocated at litter level to vaccinated (total number =&#x02009;21) or unvaccinated (total number =&#x02009;11) groups that were housed in separate isolation units at 25&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C under natural day&#x02013;night rhythm conditions.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p><bold>Serological results of samples from randomly selected sows. A</bold> Sera and <bold>B</bold> colostrum from five sows were analyzed by Western blot against a hot saline antigenic extract of <italic>Salmonella</italic> &#x00394;XIII strain and by an LPS based IDEXX test. An S/P ratio of &#x02265;&#x02009;0.25 is considered positive.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13567_2019_730_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par11">At 4&#x000a0;days of age, piglets were individually checked to be <italic>Salmonella</italic> free by stool culture.</p><p id="Par12">At 5&#x000a0;days of age, piglets were orally vaccinated using a bent-knob cannula and syringe to administer 1&#x000a0;mL of the vaccine (2.8&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>9</sup>&#x000a0;cfu/mL) or 1&#x000a0;mL of sterile LB broth to vaccinated or unvaccinated groups, respectively. At 28&#x000a0;days of age, all piglets were weaned and vaccinated groups were orally boosted with 1.3&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>9</sup>&#x000a0;cfu of &#x00394;XIII strain whilst the control group received 1&#x000a0;mL of sterile LB broth. Piglets were euthanized at 45&#x000a0;days of age. Surveillance of animals was carried out along the study by monitoring the body temperature and weight to calculate the daily weight gain (DWG).</p><p id="Par13">To investigate the immune response to <italic>Salmonella</italic> generated in vaccinated pigs, blood samples were collected at days 2, 7, 21, 35 and 42 of age and centrifuged for 5&#x000a0;min at 1500&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;<italic>g</italic> to collect serum. Sera from the control group were pooled into three samples per day whilst sera from the vaccinated group were pooled into four samples per day.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Experimental design of the vaccination and challenge trial</title><p id="Par14">Four pregnant sows (Duroc) were randomly selected from the same farm described above and relocated in a newly conditioned <italic>Salmonella</italic> free farm, 1&#x000a0;week before farrowing. G Power was used to calculate the number of piglets needed to obtain statistical significance (assuming an effect size of 0.50, a power level of 0.80, and a probability level for statistical significance of 0.05). Piglets were allocated at litter level to vaccinated (total number =&#x02009;24) or unvaccinated (total number =&#x02009;20) groups that were housed in separate isolation units at 25&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C under natural day&#x02013;night rhythm conditions. At 4&#x000a0;days of age, piglets were individually checked to be <italic>Salmonella</italic> free by stool culture.</p><p id="Par15">At day 12 of age, 24 piglets from 2 litters were orally vaccinated with 2.9&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>9</sup>&#x000a0;cfu of &#x00394;XIII strain. 20 control piglets from 2&#x000a0;litters received 1&#x000a0;mL of sterile LB broth. At 27&#x000a0;days of age, all piglets were challenged with 3.4&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>9</sup>&#x000a0;cfu of <italic>S</italic>. Typhimurium STM610T. Faecal samples were collected and analyzed at days 5, 13, 15, 19, 26, 28 and 32 of age. Blood samples were collected at days 5, 13, 19 and 26 of age and centrifuged for 5&#x000a0;min at 1500&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;<italic>g</italic> to collect serum. Sera from the control and vaccinated group were pooled into four samples per day.</p><p id="Par16">At 39&#x000a0;days of age, piglets were weaned, half of them were euthanized and faeces and ileocecal lymph nodes from each pig were collected. The other half remained until 180&#x000a0;days of age when they were slaughtered, after which faeces and ileocecal lymph nodes from each pig were collected.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Serological analyses</title><p id="Par17">Serum and colostrum IgG against <italic>Salmonella</italic> was detected by Western-Blot. For that, 15&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g of hot saline antigenic extract of &#x00394;XIII strain were separated by SDS-PAGE, transferred onto Hybond-ECL nitrocellulose membranes (GE Healthcare, Buckinghamshire, UK) by electroblotting, and blocked at room temperature for 2&#x000a0;h with 5% skimmed milk in PBS with 0.1% Tween 20 (PBS-T) under shaking conditions. Then, membranes were exposed to immune sera or to colostrum samples, diluted 1:1000 in PBS-T containing 5% skimmed milk at 4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C overnight. After five washes with PBS-T, membranes were incubated with rabbit anti-pig IgG HRP-conjugated secondary antibody (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, USA), diluted 1:1500 in PBS-T containing 5% skimmed milk at room temperature for 1&#x000a0;h and proteins were detected using Super Signal West Pico chemiluminescent substrate (Thermo Fisher Scientific).</p><p id="Par18">The hot saline antigenic extract was obtained as described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. Briefly, live cells were suspended in physiological saline (10&#x000a0;g of packed cells per 100&#x000a0;mL) and heat was applied in flowing steam for 15&#x000a0;min. After centrifugation at 12 000&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;<italic>g</italic> for 15&#x000a0;min, the supernatant was dialyzed for 2&#x000a0;days at 4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C against several changes of deionized water. The dialyzed material was centrifuged for 5&#x000a0;h at 100 000&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;<italic>g</italic>, and the pellet (hot extract) was resuspended in deionized water, lyophilized and stored at room temperature.</p><p id="Par19">Also, collected sera or colostrum samples were diluted 20-fold and analyzed for <italic>S. enterica</italic> specific antibodies with a commercial ELISA kit based on lipopolysaccharide (LPS) O-antigens of serogroups B, C1 and D (HerdChek Swine Salmonella, IDEXX Laboratories, Hoofddorp, The Netherlands). Results are expressed as a sample to positive ratio (S:P); samples with S:P ratios &#x02265;&#x02009;0.25 (OD%&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;10) were defined as positive.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Bacteriology and strain characterization</title><p id="Par20">Faeces and ileocecal lymph nodes from pigs were collected and analyzed using the standard International Organization for Standardization (ISO) 6579:2002/Amd 1:2007 method. Before the analyses, ileocaecal lymph nodes were externally decontaminated by dipping into absolute alcohol and further flaming.</p><p id="Par21">Distinction between challenge and the vaccine strains was carried out by transferring all individual colonies on agar plates without antibiotics or containing ampicillin (100&#x000a0;&#x003bc;g/mL), where only the challenge strain can grow. Further confirmation of strain identification was subsequently obtained by analyzing at least five colonies from each plate by PCR, exploiting the chromosomal differences between the two strains. Oligonucleotides sen4315 (cacgattacgccaactcgagttgt) and sen4317 (gtaagataactgtgcgaag) were used in order to amplify a 632&#x000a0;bp fragment exclusively from &#x00394;XIII DNA. Amplification of invA with oligonucleotides invA-fw (ggcgatattggtgtttatgg) and invA-rv (catattatcgctatcgccat) was used to amplify a 658&#x000a0;bp fragment from both the challenge strain and &#x00394;XIII DNA.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Production of recombinant SEN4316</title><p id="Par22">The <italic>sen4316</italic> gene was amplified from <italic>S.</italic> Enteritidis 3934 genomic DNA with primers sen4316 BamHI-fw (ggatccatgacaacaccatcctggcg) and sen4316 SalI-rv (gtcgactcatagggcgcgcatgtcgt), using Phusion High-Fidelity DNA Polymerase (Thermo Fisher Scientific). The PCR-amplified fragment was cloned in pJET 1.2 vector (Thermo Fisher Scientific), sequenced and digested with BamHI and SalI to clone it into the pET28a vector (Novagen, Merck, Darmstadt, Germany). The resulting plasmid pET28a::<italic>sen4316</italic> was electroporated into <italic>E. coli</italic> BL21 C43 (DE3) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. Cultures were grown at 37&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C, 250&#x000a0;rpm, to an optical density (OD<sub>600</sub>) of 0.5, and isopropyl-<sc>d</sc>-thiogalactopyranoside (IPTG) was added to a final concentration of 0.4&#x000a0;mM. Cells were then grown overnight at 23&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C. Harvested cells were lysed with BugBuster HT Protein Extraction Reagent (MilliporeSigma, Burlington, USA). SEN4316 accumulated in inclusion bodies was obtained by centrifugation at 16 000&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;<italic>g</italic> for 30&#x000a0;min at 4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C and suspension of insoluble material in CTAB 1%, incubation at room temperature for 10&#x000a0;min with vigorous agitation and overnight incubation at 4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C with mild agitation. The supernatant was recovered by centrifugation at 20 000&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;<italic>g</italic> and then dialyzed against binding buffer (20&#x000a0;mM sodium phosphate, 500&#x000a0;mM NaCl, 20&#x000a0;mM imidazole, pH 7.4). The recombinant protein was purified with a His GraviTrap affinity column according to standard protocols (GE Healthcare). Fractions containing the protein were pooled and concentrated using Amicon Ultra-4 filter units (MilliporeSigma) (3-kDa cutoff). The concentrate was resuspended with 2.5&#x000a0;mL carbonate&#x02013;bicarbonate buffer (pH 9.6) and the protein was further purified using a gel filtration column (PD10; GE Healthcare). Eluted protein was finally analysed by SDS-PAGE and Western-Blot and then stored in aliquots at &#x02212;80&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>SEN4316 based ELISA</title><p id="Par23">For the SEN4316 specific based ELISA, Nunc Maxisorp 96-well plates (Thermo Fisher Scientific) were coated with SEN4316 purified protein (1&#x000a0;&#x000b5;g/well) in carbonate&#x02013;bicarbonate buffer (pH 9.6) and incubated at 4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C overnight. Plates were then washed three times with PBS containing 0.05% Tween 20 (PBS-T; pH 7.4) and blocked with 2.5% bovine serum albumin (BSA) in PBS-T at room temperature for 2&#x000a0;h. After three washes with PBS-T, 100&#x000a0;&#x000b5;L of sera diluted 1:100 in PBS-T containing 2.5% of BSA were added to each well and incubated at 4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C overnight. Wells were washed three times with PBS-T and 100&#x000a0;&#x000b5;L of rabbit anti-pig IgG HRP-conjugated secondary antibody (Thermo Fisher Scientific) diluted 1:1000 were added to each well. The plates were incubated for 2&#x000a0;h at room temperature and then washed three times. One hundred microliters of ABTS (Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, USA) were added to each well and the absorbance at 420&#x000a0;nm was determined on an Epoch (BioTek) microplate spectrophotometer.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="Par24">Statistical analyses were performed using GraphPad Prism (version 5.01) software (GraphPad Inc., San Diego, CA, USA). A two-way analysis of variance combined with the Bonferroni test was used to analyze statistical significance in serology assays. The percentage of faeces and ileocaecal lymph nodes colonization among control and vaccinated groups was analyzed using Contingency tables for non-parametric data (Fisher&#x02019;s exact test).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec14"><title>Serological examination of sows</title><p id="Par25">Results of both the Western blot analysis that measures the levels of IgG against a <italic>Salmonella</italic> &#x00394;XIII strain antigenic extract and the IDEXX Test that determines the presence of serum antibody to <italic>Salmonella</italic> LPS antigen indicated that the five sows randomly selected were positive for antibodies to <italic>Salmonella</italic> (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>A). Importantly, analysis of faecal samples obtained from 7&#x000a0;days before to the day of parturition indicated that none of the sows shed <italic>Salmonella</italic> spp. To analyze the possibility that piglets might acquire maternal immunity against <italic>Salmonella</italic> through the ingestion of colostrum, colostrum samples were collected from the same sows on the day of farrowing and Western blot and IDEXX analyses were performed. All colostrum samples were also positive for antibodies to <italic>Salmonella</italic> (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>B). These results demonstrated a high seroprevalence of <italic>Salmonella</italic> and indicated that colostral immunity might be important in the context of piglet vaccination in the selected herd.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>&#x00394;XIII safety and immune response in vaccinated piglets</title><p id="Par26">With the final aim of evaluating &#x00394;XIII strain as a novel live attenuated vaccine candidate to reduce organ colonization and faecal excretion of <italic>S. enterica</italic> in infected pigs, we initially examined the safety of the vaccine. Results of animal surveillance showed that there were not any differences in the body temperature, weight and daily weight gain (DWG) between the vaccinated and the control groups, indicating that vaccine administration did not affect pigs health (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Concomitantly, and in order to investigate whether &#x00394;XIII vaccine might be able to induce a protective immune response against <italic>Salmonella</italic>, serum from each piglet was obtained at days 2 (preimmune), 7, 21, 35 and 42 of age and sera from each group were analyzed by Western-Blot against an antigenic extract of &#x00394;XIII strain and by ELISA (IDEXX test) (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). The presence of antibodies at an early time in sera from both control and vaccinated pigs can be explained by the fact that the three pregnant sows used in the study were serologically positive (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) and maternal immunity was therefore acquired through the ingestion of colostrum. Maternal immunity decreased along the study and disappeared after weaning (28&#x000a0;days of age) in control pigs. Notably, at days 35 and 42 of age, a marked seroconversion occurred in animals immunized with &#x00394;XIII strain. Thus, statistical analysis showed a significant difference in the antibody response against <italic>Salmonella</italic> LPS between pigs immunized with the &#x00394;XIII strain and control animals.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p><bold>Vaccination with &#x00394;XIII does not have any effect in body temperature and weight gain.</bold> Piglets from the vaccinated group (open squares) were orally vaccinated with 2.8&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>9</sup>&#x000a0;cfu of &#x00394;XIII at 5&#x000a0;days of age and boosted with 1.3&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>9</sup>&#x000a0;cfu at 28&#x000a0;days of age. The control group (black triangles) received sterile LB broth. From left to right, changes in mean temperature, weight and daily weight gain (DWG) of each group are shown. No significant difference in these parameters was found between groups. Statistical analysis was carried out using a two-way analysis of variance combined with the Bonferroni test.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13567_2019_730_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig>
<fig id="Fig3"><label>Figure&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p><bold>Serological results of pigs immunized with &#x00394;XIII strain and non-vaccinated pigs (control group).</bold> Sera from the control group were pooled into three samples per day whilst sera from the vaccinated group were pooled into four samples per day. <bold>A</bold> Sera were analyzed by Western blot against a hot saline antigenic extract of <italic>Salmonella</italic> &#x00394;XIII strain. In this case, an equal volume of each pool and group was mixed and the resulting samples were used for analysis. C: control; V: vaccinated. <bold>B</bold> Pooled sera were analyzed by an LPS based IDEXX test. An S/P ratio of &#x02265;&#x02009;0.25 is considered positive. Statistical analysis was carried out using a two-way analysis of variance combined with the Bonferroni test. *<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05; ***<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13567_2019_730_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Vaccination and challenge trial in pigs</title><p id="Par27">Once safety and immunogenicity of &#x00394;XIII strain were evidenced, a vaccination trial was performed. Based on the results presented above, showing passive immunity derived from the ingestion of colostrum, and in order to optimize &#x00394;XIII strain usefulness in vaccination field trials, piglet vaccination was delayed to day 12 of age so as to avoid interference with maternal immunity and also, vaccination was limited to a single dose. Analysis of sera obtained at days 5 (preimmune), 13, 19 and 26 of age by Western-Blot against an antigenic extract of &#x00394;XIII strain and by ELISA (IDEXX test) (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>) showed a significant seroconversion at day 26 of age in animals immunized with &#x00394;XIII strain. Also, evaluation of <italic>Salmonella</italic> faecal shedding confirmed that control piglets did not acquire <italic>Salmonella</italic> until challenge and that vaccinated animals stopped shedding &#x00394;XIII strain before challenge (two piglets were positive at 19&#x000a0;days of age; none were positive at 26&#x000a0;days of age). At 28&#x000a0;days of age, 1&#x000a0;day post-challenge, 45% and 62.5% of control and vaccinated pigs, respectively, were positive for faecal shedding of the challenge strain. These percentages increased to 100% and 87.5% in samples of control and vaccinated pigs, respectively, at 32&#x000a0;days of age.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Figure&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p><bold>Vaccinated piglets exhibited significant levels of serum IgG against</bold>
<bold><italic>Salmonella</italic></bold>
<bold>at the time of challenge.</bold> Sera from the control and vaccinated group were pooled into four samples per day. <bold>A</bold> Sera were analyzed by Western blot against a hot saline antigenic extract of <italic>Salmonella</italic> &#x00394;XIII strain. In this case, an equal volume of each pool and group was mixed and the resulting samples were used for analysis. C: control, V: vaccinated. <bold>B</bold> Pooled sera were analyzed by an LPS based IDEXX test. An S/P ratio of &#x02265;&#x02009;0.25 is considered positive. Statistical analysis was carried out using a two-way analysis of variance combined with the Bonferroni test. **<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13567_2019_730_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par28">At 39&#x000a0;days of age, immediately post weaning, half of the animals were sacrificed and results on <italic>Salmonella</italic> isolation showed that, 100% of control animals were colonized by <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium STM610T. In contrast, vaccinated animals showed a faecal shedding and prevalence in ileocaecal lymph nodes of 83.3% and 66.6% respectively (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). At slaughter age (180&#x000a0;days of age), 80% of control animals shed <italic>Salmonella</italic> and 40% of control ileocaecal lymph nodes were colonized. Vaccination with &#x00394;XIII decreased <italic>Salmonella</italic> prevalence on both samples by half (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Although due to the sample size, colonization differences in control and vaccinated animals were non-significant when data were analyzed by the Fisher&#x02019;s exact test, a trend towards significance was observed when the relative risk was calculated (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Also, sample analysis showed that none of the vaccinated pigs shed the vaccine strain or carried it in their lymph nodes at weaning and at slaughter age.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p><bold>Percentage of</bold>
<bold><italic>Salmonella</italic></bold>
<bold>positive ileocaecal lymph nodes and faecal samples of vaccinated and control pigs</bold></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="3"/><th align="left" colspan="2">Post weaning</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Slaughter age</th></tr><tr><th align="left">ILN</th><th align="left">Faeces</th><th align="left">ILN</th><th align="left">Faeces</th></tr><tr><th align="left">No. (%) positives<sup>a</sup></th><th align="left">No. (%) positives<sup>a</sup></th><th align="left">No. (%) positives<sup>a</sup></th><th align="left">No. (%) positives<sup>a</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Control pigs</td><td align="left">10/10 (100)</td><td align="left">10/10 (100)</td><td align="left">4/10 (40)</td><td align="left">8/10 (80)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Vaccinated pigs</td><td align="left">8/12 (66.6)</td><td align="left">10/12 (83.3)</td><td align="left">2/12 (16.6)</td><td align="left">5/12 (41.6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">P<sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">0.096</td><td align="left">0.480</td><td align="left">0.347</td><td align="left">0.099</td></tr><tr><td align="left">RR<sup>c</sup></td><td align="left">1.5</td><td align="left">1.2</td><td align="left">2.4</td><td align="left">1.9</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>No. and percentage of <italic>Salmonella</italic> positive samples.</p><p><sup>b</sup>Statistical significance (<italic>P</italic> values) between control vs vaccinated groups was analyzed using Contingency tables for non-parametric data (Fisher&#x02019;s exact test).</p><p><sup>c</sup>Relative risk.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par29">These findings demonstrated that vaccination of piglets with &#x00394;XIII strain reduces faecal shedding and ileocecal lymph nodes colonization, following infection with a virulent strain of <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium, both at post weaning and slaughter stages.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Evaluation of the absence of the <italic>sen4316</italic> gene in &#x00394;XIII strain as a DIVA marker</title><p id="Par30">We have previously demonstrated that &#x00394;XIII can be considered a DIVA vaccine since the diguanylate cyclase protein SEN4316, that is absent in &#x00394;XIII strain, enables discrimination of infected and vaccinated animals, after an oral administration of either a wild type or &#x00394;XIII strain to BALB/c mice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Specifically, antibodies directed against the SEN4316 protein were developed upon infection with a wild type strain and not upon vaccination with the &#x00394;XIII vaccine strain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. To investigate the functionality of the marker SEN4316 in field vaccination trials, we analysed all sera used along this study using a specific &#x0201c;in-house&#x0201d; ELISA assay in which a 6-His-tagged recombinant version of SEN4316 was used as the bound antigen. Firstly, sera obtained from sows were probed and, as expected, and since all five sows were positive for antibodies to <italic>Salmonella</italic> (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>A), they were also positive for antibodies directed against the SEN4316 protein (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>A). Then, pooled sera from control to vaccinated animals of the safety trial (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>) were examined. In this case, animals were never challenged with a wild type strain, and thus, neither control nor vaccinated pigs were serologically positive for SEN4316 at the end of the safety study (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>B). Finally, sera coming from the vaccination trial (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>) were tested. Taking into account that all sera corresponded to the pre-challenge stage, both control and vaccinated pigs showed titers of antibodies against SEN4316 that decreased gradually along time and never seroconverted (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>C). Note that high titers shown by sera obtained at an early time (Figures <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>B and C) correspond to maternal immunity acquired through the ingestion of colostrum.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Figure&#x000a0;5</label><caption><p><bold>Vaccination with &#x00394;XIII strain elicits a DIVA humoral immune response in pigs.</bold> SEN4316 based ELISA of sera from <bold>A</bold> the five randomly selected sows analysed in this study. Error bars represent standard deviation between triplicate wells; <bold>B</bold> control and vaccinated pigs of the present safety trial. The data represent the mean and standard deviation of duplicate measurements of every pool analysed; <bold>C</bold> control and vaccinated pigs of the present vaccination trial. The data represent the mean and standard deviation of duplicate measurements of every pool analysed. Statistical analysis in <bold>B</bold> and <bold>C</bold> was carried out using a two-way analysis of variance combined with the Bonferroni test.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13567_2019_730_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par31">It is nowadays widely accepted that vaccination for <italic>Salmonella</italic> in modern pig production can play an important role in the intervention in high prevalence herds [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. In a previous study, we constructed a novel live attenuated <italic>Salmonella</italic> Enteritidis vaccine candidate, named &#x00394;XIII, and showed its efficacy against <italic>Salmonella</italic> Typhimurium in a vaccination-challenge analysis carried out in BALBc mice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. The results presented herein extend these findings to pigs vaccination based on &#x00394;XIII qualities that make it a promising veterinary vaccine [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. There are few studies examining the outcome of vaccination of pre-weaned piglets [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>] and also, there is little information on candidate vaccines controlling <italic>Salmonella</italic> carriage and shedding by the time of slaughter, which is when <italic>Salmonella</italic> may lead to pig products contamination, resulting in human disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Thus, our study focused on vaccination of pre-weaned piglets from a farrow-to-finish pig herd with high <italic>Salmonella</italic> seroprevalence and extended sampling to slaughter age. As regards the study design, we focused on the oral administration of a single dose of the vaccine and also of a single high-dose challenge of a heterologous serovar, that is <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium, followed by sampling to assess vaccine effects. Piglets used in our study exhibited high <italic>Salmonella</italic> IgG titers derived from passive immunity of the sows. In this regard, there are previous studies demonstrating that suckling pigs with higher antibody titres show an improved resistance when challenged with <italic>Salmonella</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. On the contrary, De Ridder et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>] showed that amongst the herds analysed, a herd with the highest maternal <italic>Salmonella enterica</italic> antibody levels at vaccination was the only herd without significantly decreased <italic>Salmonella</italic> excretion at finishing state. Taking all this into account, we decided to delay vaccination to day 12 of age in order to avoid interference between maternal immunity and oral vaccination.</p><p id="Par32">Overall, our findings provide evidence that vaccination with &#x00394;XIII strain may be a suitable option for a <italic>Salmonella</italic> reduction strategy in farrow-to-finish pig herds. First, the candidate vaccine was safe and did not yield any adverse reactions in the vaccinated pigs. Second, after only one dose, &#x00394;XIII strain generated a response capable of reducing <italic>Salmonella</italic> prevalence in both mesenteric lymph nodes and faeces, suggesting that a fine balance between sufficient attenuation and sufficient immune response stimulation was achieved. It is very important to note that this candidate vaccine addresses the major hurdle of cross-protecting against heterologous serovars, by providing protection against the most prevalent serovar in pigs, <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium. Further trials are needed to evaluate cross-protection against other serovars such as the swine pathogen <italic>S.</italic> Cholerasuis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Third, reversion to the wild-type phenotype is extremely unlikely in &#x00394;XIII strain due to the complete deletion of 13 genes. Notably, these 13 deletions were carried out through a strategy that guarantees the lack of any trace of exogenous DNA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>] and therefore, &#x00394;XIII strain cannot be classified as a genetically modified organism. Fourth, vaccinated animals stopped shedding &#x00394;XIII strain 2&#x000a0;weeks after vaccination, and at weaning and slaughter age, none carried &#x00394;XIII in the lymph nodes. Moreover, &#x00394;XIII strain is sensitive to environmental hazards [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>], facilitating its elimination from the farm environment when excretion by vaccinated animals occurs.</p><p id="Par33">Since most of the control programs include surveillance of the herd status by monitoring <italic>Salmonella</italic> serological status in finishing pigs at market weight [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>], a very important additional aspect of &#x00394;XIII is that vaccination with this strain induces a response that is distinguishable from that produced by a natural <italic>Salmonella</italic> infection. Few <italic>Salmonella</italic> DIVA vaccines for pigs vaccination have been constructed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. The rationale behind this type of vaccines is that lack of specific antigens or epitopes allows the use of a serological test to discriminate infected from vaccinated animals. In the case of &#x00394;XIII strain, we already proposed the SEN4316 diguanylate cyclase as a negative selectable marker because it allows the serological discrimination of vaccinated from infected mice and also because SEN4316 is conserved in all <italic>S. enterica</italic> serovars and absent in <italic>E. coli</italic> and other gram negative bacteria [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. The present study confirms the use of a SEN4316 based ELISA to differentiate infected from &#x00394;XIII vaccinated pigs.</p><p id="Par34">Overall, our results indicate the efficacy of &#x00394;XIII strain as a candidate mucosal DIVA vaccine against salmonellosis in pigs. Nevertheless, a <italic>Salmonella</italic> &#x00394;XIII strain vaccination trial involving natural challenge with a large number of pigs is needed to assess vaccination relevance in field conditions. Also, future work might be conducted to assess &#x00394;XIII strain use as a carrier for recombinant antigens in order to exploit its potential as a mucosal multivalent vaccine candidate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>].</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher's Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn><fn><p>Carmen Gil and Cristina Latasa contributed equally to this work.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We express our gratitude to Dr M. J. Grill&#x000f3;, from the Animal Health Group of the Instituto de Agrobiotecnolog&#x000ed;a, Spain, for providing us the <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium STM610T strain.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>I&#x000f1;igo Lasa conceived this project, designed the experiments, coordinated all the activities of the project and reviewed the manuscript. CS designed the experiments, analyzed and interpreted the data and drafted and reviewed the manuscript. CG and CL designed and performed the experiments and interpreted the data. EGO, ME, SB and BG performed the experiments. Isidro L&#x000e1;zaro and JL provided expertise and contributed to design and sampling. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>SB was supported by a predoctoral contract from the Public University of Navarra. CG, ME and BG were recipients of postdoctoral contracts under Grant BIO2014-53530-R. This research was supported by grant IIM 13329.RI1 from the Departamento de Innovaci&#x000f3;n, Empresa y Empleo, Government of Navarra and grants BIO2014-53530-R and BIO2017-83035-R from the Spanish Ministry of Economy and Competitiveness (Agencia Espa&#x000f1;ola de Investigaci&#x000f3;n/Fondo Europeo de Desarrollo Regional, European Union).</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>All data generated or analysed during this study are included in this published article.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par35">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ecdc</surname><given-names>EFSA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The European Union summary report on trends and sources of zoonoses, zoonotic agents and food-borne outbreaks in 2017</article-title><source>EFSA J</source><year>2018</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>5500</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O&#x02019;Brien</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The &#x0201c;decline and fall&#x0201d; of nontyphoidal <italic>Salmonella</italic> in the United Kingdom</article-title><source>Clin Infect Dis</source><year>2013</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>705</fpage><lpage>710</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cid/cis967</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23166188</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>EFSA</collab></person-group><article-title>Opinion of the Scientific Panel on biological hazards (BIOHAZ) related to &#x0201c;<italic>Salmonella</italic> control in poultry flocks and its public health impact&#x0201d;</article-title><source>EFSA J</source><year>2019</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>5596</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">FCC Consortium (2010) Analysis of the costs and benefits of setting a target for the reduction of <italic>Salmonella</italic> in slaughter pigs. Report for European Commission Health and Consumers Directorate General SANCO/2008/E2/036 final report. 2010. p. 1&#x02013;198</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boyen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Haesebrouck</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Maes</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Immerseel</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ducatelle</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Pasmans</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Non-typhoidal <italic>Salmonella</italic> infections in pigs: a closer look at epidemiology, pathogenesis and control</article-title><source>Vet Microbiol</source><year>2008</year><volume>130</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetmic.2007.12.017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18243591</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>EFSA</collab></person-group><article-title>Opinion of the Scientific Panel on biological hazards (BIOHAZ) related to &#x0201c;Risk assessment and mitigation options of <italic>Salmonella</italic> in pig production&#x0201d;</article-title><source>EFSA J</source><year>2006</year><volume>341</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>131</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andres</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biosecurity measures to control <italic>Salmonella</italic> and other infectious agents in pig farms: a review</article-title><source>Compre Rev Food Sci Food Saf</source><year>2015</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>317</fpage><lpage>335</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1541-4337.12137</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Denagamage</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Connor</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sargeant</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajic</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>McKean</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efficacy of vaccination to reduce <italic>Salmonella</italic> prevalence in live and slaughtered swine: a systematic review of literature from 1979 to 2007</article-title><source>Foodborne Pathog Dis</source><year>2007</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>539</fpage><lpage>549</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/fpd.2007.0013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18041963</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wales</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Salmonella</italic> vaccination in pigs: a review</article-title><source>Zoonoses Public Health</source><year>2017</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/zph.12256</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26853216</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de la Cruz</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Conrado</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Nault</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Perez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dominguez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vaccination as a control strategy against <italic>Salmonella</italic> infection in pigs: a systematic review and meta-analysis of the literature</article-title><source>Res Vet Sci</source><year>2017</year><volume>114</volume><fpage>86</fpage><lpage>94</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rvsc.2017.03.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28340428</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haesebrouck</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Pasmans</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiers</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Maes</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ducatelle</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Decostere</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efficacy of vaccines against bacterial diseases in swine: what can we expect?</article-title><source>Vet Microbiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>255</fpage><lpage>268</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetmic.2004.03.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15145504</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bearson</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Bearson</surname><given-names>SMD</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunelle</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name><name><surname>Bayles</surname><given-names>DO</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kich</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Salmonella</italic> DIVA vaccine reduces disease, colonization and shedding due to virulent <italic>S.</italic> Typhimurium infection in swine</article-title><source>J Med Microbiol</source><year>2017</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>651</fpage><lpage>661</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/jmm.0.000482</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28516860</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Ridder</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Maes</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Dewulf</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Butaye</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Pasmans</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Haesebrouck</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Der Stede</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of a live attenuated <italic>Salmonella enterica</italic> serovar Typhimurium vaccine on farrow-to-finish pig farms</article-title><source>Vet J</source><year>2014</year><volume>202</volume><fpage>303</fpage><lpage>308</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tvjl.2014.09.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25278382</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruggeri</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pesciaroli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaetarelli</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Scaglione</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name><name><surname>Pregel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ammendola</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Battistoni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bollo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Alborali</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Pasquali</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Parenteral administration of attenuated <italic>Salmonella</italic> Typhimurium &#x02206;<italic>znuABC</italic> is protective against salmonellosis in piglets</article-title><source>Vaccine</source><year>2014</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>4032</fpage><lpage>4038</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vaccine.2014.05.066</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24907486</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gradassi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pesciaroli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinelli</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruggeri</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Petrucci</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hassan</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Raffatellu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Scaglione</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ammendola</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Battistoni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Alborali</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Pasquali</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Attenuated <italic>Salmonella enterica</italic> serovar Typhimurium lacking the ZnuABC transporter: an efficacious orally-administered mucosal vaccine against salmonellosis in pigs</article-title><source>Vaccine</source><year>2013</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>3695</fpage><lpage>3701</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vaccine.2013.05.105</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23770333</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leyman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Parys</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Verbrugghe</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Haesebrouck</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Pasmans</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tackling the issue of environmental survival of live <italic>Salmonella</italic> Typhimurium vaccines: deletion of the <italic>lon</italic> gene</article-title><source>Res Vet Sci</source><year>2012</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>1168</fpage><lpage>1172</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rvsc.2012.05.008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22683389</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Selke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Meens</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Springer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerlach</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immunization of pigs to prevent disease in humans: construction and protective efficacy of a <italic>Salmonella enterica</italic> serovar Typhimurium live negative-marker vaccine</article-title><source>Infect Immun</source><year>2007</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>2476</fpage><lpage>2483</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/IAI.01908-06</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17296750</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Latasa</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Echeverz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Gil</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a-Ona</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Burgui</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Casares</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Herv&#x000e1;s-Stubbs</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lasarte</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lasa</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Solano</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of a <italic>Salmonella</italic> strain lacking the secondary messenger c-di-GMP and RpoS as a live oral vaccine</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2016</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>e0161216</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0161216</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27537839</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Battesti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Majdalani</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Gottesman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The RpoS-mediated general stress response in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title><source>Annu Rev Microbiol</source><year>2011</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>189</fpage><lpage>213</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-micro-090110-102946</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21639793</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Solano</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Latasa</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Toledo-Arana</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zorraquino</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Valle</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Casals</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pedroso</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Lasa</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic reductionist approach for dissecting individual roles of GGDEF proteins within the c-di-GMP signaling network in <italic>Salmonella</italic></article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2009</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>7997</fpage><lpage>8002</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0812573106</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19416883</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zorraquino</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Latasa</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Echeverz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Toledo-Arana</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Valle</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lasa</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Solano</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coordinated cyclic-di-GMP repression of <italic>Salmonella</italic> motility through YcgR and cellulose</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>2013</year><volume>195</volume><fpage>417</fpage><lpage>428</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.01789-12</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23161026</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name><name><surname>Libby</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Buchmeier</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Loewen</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Switala</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Harwood</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Guiney</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The alternative sigma-Factor Katf (Rpos) regulates <italic>Salmonella</italic> virulence</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>1992</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>11978</fpage><lpage>11982</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.89.24.11978</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1465428</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>R&#x000f6;mling</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Galperin</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomelsky</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cyclic di-GMP: the first 25&#x000a0;years of a universal bacterial second messenger</article-title><source>Microbiol Mol Biol Rev</source><year>2013</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/MMBR.00043-12</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23471616</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Solano</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Valle</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Berasain</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghigo</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gamazo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lasa</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic analysis of <italic>Salmonella enteritidis</italic> biofilm formation: critical role of cellulose</article-title><source>Mol Microbiol</source><year>2002</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>793</fpage><lpage>808</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2958.2002.02802.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11929533</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Latasa</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Solano</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a-del Portillo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Gamazo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lasa</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of the GGDEF protein family in <italic>Salmonella</italic> cellulose biosynthesis and biofilm formation</article-title><source>Mol Microbiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>264</fpage><lpage>277</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2004.04269.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15458421</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zogaj</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Nimtz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rohde</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bokranz</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>R&#x000f6;mling</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The multicellular morphotypes of <italic>Salmonella</italic> Typhimurium and <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> produce cellulose as the second component of the extracellular matrix</article-title><source>Mol Microbiol</source><year>2001</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>1452</fpage><lpage>1463</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2958.2001.02337.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11260463</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Echeverz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Sabalza</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Valle</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gabald&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Solano</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lasa</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lack of the PGA exopolysaccharide in <italic>Salmonella</italic> as an adaptive trait for survival in the host</article-title><source>PLoS Genet</source><year>2017</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>e1006816</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1006816</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28542593</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Solano</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sesma</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Humphrey</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Thorns</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gamazo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Discrimination of strains of <italic>Salmonella enteritidis</italic> with differing levels of virulence by an in vitro glass adherence test</article-title><source>J Clin Microbiol</source><year>1998</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>674</fpage><lpage>678</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JCM.36.3.674-678.1998</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9508294</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>San Rom&#x000e1;n</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Garrido</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>S&#x000e1;nchez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez-Ballesteros</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Garaizar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mainar-Jaime</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Migura-Garcia</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Grill&#x000f3;</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Relationship between <italic>Salmonella</italic> infection, shedding and serology in fattening pigs in low-moderate prevalence areas</article-title><source>Zoonoses Public Health</source><year>2018</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>481</fpage><lpage>489</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/zph.12453</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29700976</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ochoa-Rep&#x000e1;raz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Solano</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lasa</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Irache</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gamazo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Protective ability of subcellular extracts from <italic>Salmonella</italic> enteritidis and from a rough isogenic mutant against salmonellosis in mice</article-title><source>Vaccine</source><year>2005</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>1491</fpage><lpage>1501</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vaccine.2004.09.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15670885</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miroux</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Over-production of proteins in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>: mutant hosts that allow synthesis of some membrane proteins and globular proteins at high levels</article-title><source>J Mol Biol</source><year>1996</year><volume>260</volume><fpage>289</fpage><lpage>298</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/jmbi.1996.0399</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8757792</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arguello</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubio</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Carvajal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Salmonella</italic> control measures at farm in swine production</article-title><source>Annous BA</source><year>2012</year><publisher-loc>Distribution, Adaptation, Control Measures and Molecular Technologies, InTech</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Gurtler JB Salmonella</publisher-name><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>122</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Salmonella</italic> vaccines for animals and birds and their future perspective</article-title><source>Open Vaccine J</source><year>2009</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>100</fpage><lpage>112</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/1875035400902010100</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hur</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>SO</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>IK</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efficacy of a novel virulence gene-deleted <italic>Salmonella</italic> Typhimurium vaccine for protection against <italic>Salmonella</italic> infections in growing piglets</article-title><source>Vet Immunol Immunopathol</source><year>2011</year><volume>139</volume><fpage>250</fpage><lpage>256</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetimm.2010.08.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20869776</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roesler</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Heller</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Waldmann</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Truyen</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Hensel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immunization of sows in an integrated pig-breeding herd using a homologous inactivated <italic>Salmonella</italic> vaccine decreases the prevalence of <italic>Salmonella</italic> Typhimurium infection in the offspring</article-title><source>J Vet Med B Infect Dis Vet Public Health</source><year>2006</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>224</fpage><lpage>228</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1439-0450.2006.00951.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16732880</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matiasovic</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kudlackova</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Babickova</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Stepanova</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Volf</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rychlik</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Babak</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Faldyna</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of maternally-derived antibodies against <italic>Salmonella enterica</italic> serovar Typhimurium on the bacterial load in suckling piglets</article-title><source>Vet J</source><year>2013</year><volume>196</volume><fpage>114</fpage><lpage>115</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tvjl.2012.08.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22967925</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hur</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immunization of pregnant sows with a novel virulence gene deleted live <italic>Salmonella</italic> vaccine and protection of their suckling piglets against salmonellosis</article-title><source>Vet Microbiol</source><year>2010</year><volume>143</volume><fpage>270</fpage><lpage>276</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vetmic.2009.11.034</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20031343</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bearson</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Bearson</surname><given-names>SMD</given-names></name><name><surname>Kich</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A DIVA vaccine for cross-protection against <italic>Salmonella</italic></article-title><source>Vaccine</source><year>2016</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>1241</fpage><lpage>1246</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vaccine.2016.01.036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26836212</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leyman</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Parys</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Verbrugghe</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Haesebrouck</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Pasmans</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Salmonella</italic> Typhimurium LPS mutations for use in vaccines allowing differentiation of infected and vaccinated pigs</article-title><source>Vaccine</source><year>2011</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>3679</fpage><lpage>3685</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vaccine.2011.03.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21419163</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>