<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="brief-report"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Bioinformatics</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Bioinformatics</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bioinformatics</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Bioinformatics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1367-4803</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1367-4811</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31240309</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6954642</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btz517</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">btz517</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Applications Notes</subject><subj-group subj-group-type="category-toc-heading"><subject>Structural Bioinformatics</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>TCR3d: The T cell receptor structural repertoire database</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gowthaman</surname><given-names>Ragul</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="btz517-aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="btz517-aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="btz517-aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pierce</surname><given-names>Brian G</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="btz517-cor1"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="btz517-aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="btz517-aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="btz517-aff3">3</xref><!--<email>pierce@umd.edu</email>--></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Wren</surname><given-names>Jonathan</given-names></name><role>Associate Editor</role></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="btz517-aff1"><label>1</label>
<institution>University of Maryland Institute for Bioscience and Biotechnology Research</institution>, Rockville, MD, <country country="US">USA</country></aff><aff id="btz517-aff2"><label>2</label>
<institution>Department of Cell Biology and Molecular Genetics, University of Maryland</institution>, College Park, MD, <country country="US">USA</country></aff><aff id="btz517-aff3"><label>3</label>
<institution>University of Maryland Marlene and Stewart Greenebaum Comprehensive Cancer Center</institution>, Baltimore, MD, <country country="US">USA</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="btz517-cor1">To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: <email>pierce@umd.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>15</day><month>12</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2019-06-26"><day>26</day><month>6</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>26</day><month>6</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>35</volume><issue>24</issue><fpage>5323</fpage><lpage>5325</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>01</day><month>3</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>31</day><month>5</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>20</day><month>6</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019. Published by Oxford University Press.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><license license-type="cc-by-nc" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="btz517.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><sec id="s1"><title>Summary</title><p>T cell receptors (TCRs) are critical molecules of the adaptive immune system, capable of recognizing diverse antigens, including peptides, lipids and small molecules, and represent a rapidly growing class of therapeutics. Determining the structural and mechanistic basis of TCR targeting of antigens is a major challenge, as each individual has a vast and diverse repertoire of TCRs. Despite shared general recognition modes, diversity in TCR sequence and recognition represents a challenge to predictive modeling and computational techniques being developed to predict antigen specificity and mechanistic basis of TCR targeting. To this end, we have developed the TCR3d database, a resource containing all known TCR structures, with a particular focus on antigen recognition. TCR3d provides key information on antigen binding mode, interface features, loop sequences and germline gene usage. Users can interactively view TCR complex structures, search sequences of interest against known structures and sequences, and download curated datasets of structurally characterized TCR complexes. This database is updated on a weekly basis, and can serve the community as a centralized resource for those studying T cell receptors and their recognition.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Availability and implementation</title><p>The TCR3d database is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://tcr3d.ibbr.umd.edu/">https://tcr3d.ibbr.umd.edu/</ext-link>.</p></sec></abstract><funding-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source><named-content content-type="funder-name">National Institutes of Health</named-content><named-content content-type="funder-identifier">10.13039/100000002</named-content></funding-source><award-id>GM126299</award-id></award-group></funding-group><counts><page-count count="3"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>1 Introduction</title><p>T cell receptors (TCRs) are a critical component of the adaptive immune response, mediating the specific recognition of foreign peptide and small molecule antigens presented on the surfaces of cells. To enable their recognition of an immense array of foreign antigens, a large and diverse repertoire of unique TCRs is present in each individual. Accurate and potent TCR targeting of viral and tumor antigens is critical for TCR-based therapeutics and vaccine design, while aberrant TCR targeting is linked to autoimmune diseases such as diabetes, celiac disease and multiple sclerosis (<xref rid="btz517-B15" ref-type="bibr">Yin <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012</xref>). The 3D structures of these interfaces provide unparalleled views of these interactions, and can lead to better therapeutics, vaccines, and understanding of the molecular basis of many diseases. As noted in several reviews (<xref rid="btz517-B10" ref-type="bibr">Rossjohn <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015</xref>; <xref rid="btz517-B11" ref-type="bibr">Rudolph <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>), a number of experimentally determined TCR structures are available that collectively provide insights into the basis of TCR structure and targeting. This has led to identification of key residues and TCR features underlying specific binding of antigens and antigen-presenting molecules (<xref rid="btz517-B1" ref-type="bibr">Blevins <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>; <xref rid="btz517-B4" ref-type="bibr">DeWitt <italic>et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>; <xref rid="btz517-B13" ref-type="bibr">Stadinski <italic>et al.</italic>, 2016</xref>). To provide a central resource and interface for all known TCR structures, we have developed the TCR3d database. This complements recently developed databases focused on TCR sequences (<xref rid="btz517-B12" ref-type="bibr">Shugay <italic>et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>; <xref rid="btz517-B14" ref-type="bibr">Tickotsky <italic>et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>), and with a focus on TCR targeting and antigen interactions, in addition to other notable features described below, it is distinguished from a previously developed database, STCRDab (<xref rid="btz517-B7" ref-type="bibr">Leem <italic>et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>2 Materials and methods</title><p>TCR complex structures are automatically identified from the Protein Data Bank (PDB) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.rcsb.org">https://www.rcsb.org</ext-link>) on a weekly basis, through searching of all protein sequences from the PDB using hidden Markov models representing TCR variable domain sequences. A custom C++ program was developed to calculate TCR docking angles, based on the approach of Rudolph et al. (<xref rid="btz517-B11" ref-type="bibr">Rudolph <italic>et al.</italic>, 2006</xref>) (available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/piercelab/tcr_docking_angle">https://github.com/piercelab/tcr_docking_angle</ext-link>), while the NACCESS (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://wolf.bms.umist.ac.uk/naccess/">http://wolf.bms.umist.ac.uk/naccess/</ext-link>) and S<sub>c</sub> (from CCP4 suite; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ccp4.ac.uk">http://www.ccp4.ac.uk</ext-link>) programs are used to calculate interface buried surface area and shape complementarity, respectively. TCR variable germline genes are identified based on comparison with IMGT reference protein sequences (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.imgt.org">http://www.imgt.org</ext-link>). TCR complementarity determining region (CDR) loop clustering is performed using backbone &#x003c6;&#x003c8; conformational distances and affinity propagation, as previously described for the classification of antibody CDR loops (<xref rid="btz517-B8" ref-type="bibr">North <italic>et al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). The database and interface are implemented in SQLite and the Flask web framework, data plots are generated using plotly (https//plot.ly), and JSmol is used for structural visualization (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jmol.org">http://www.jmol.org</ext-link>). Sequence searches against the database are performed using ungapped pairwise global or semi-global alignment (CDR3 and peptide sequences) or BLAST (<xref rid="btz517-B3" ref-type="bibr">Camacho <italic>et al.</italic>, 2009</xref>) (variable domain sequences).</p></sec><sec><title>3 Features and usage</title><p>TCR3d is designed to provide comprehensive and up-to-date information on all known TCR structures in the PDB, and a reference for key features of their antigen recognition. This includes:
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p><bold>TCR complex sets</bold>: comprehensive tables of all known TCR complexes, organized by Major Histocompatibility Complex (MHC) class or MHC-like molecule, complex visualization</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>TCR complex analysis</bold>: TCR docking angles, binding interface parameters, unbound structures and binding conformational changes</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>TCR structures</bold>: germline gene coverage, CDR loop sequences, CDR loop structure clustering</p></list-item><list-item><p><bold>TCR sequences</bold>: sets of cancer-specific and virus-specific TCR sequences of interest, search sequences against known structures and an external database of TCR sequences (<xref rid="btz517-B12" ref-type="bibr">Shugay <italic>et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>)</p></list-item></list></p><p>A primary interface of the TCR3d database consists of browsable tables of all TCR-antigen complexes classified by TCR restriction (Class I MHC, Class II MHC, CD1d, MR1), as well as &#x003b3;&#x003b4; TCRs, containing key features of the TCRs and targeting. Links to measured wild-type and mutant binding affinities in the ATLAS database (<xref rid="btz517-B2" ref-type="bibr">Borrman <italic>et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>) are provided for each complex, if values are available. Clicking the PDB codes in these tables gives a dedicated viewing window of complex structures and binding axes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="btz517-F1">Fig.&#x000a0;1A</xref>). Interactive plots provide summaries of distribution of TCR docking angles and interface parameters (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="btz517-F1">Fig.&#x000a0;1B</xref>), as well as germline gene representation from experimentally determined TCR structures (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="btz517-F1">Fig.&#x000a0;1C</xref>). For those studying or predicting TCR binding, TCR3d includes a curated set of unbound TCR and peptide-MHC structures, corresponding to an updated version of a previously reported benchmark (<xref rid="btz517-B9" ref-type="bibr">Pierce and Weng, 2013</xref>). Users can download complex structures individually from the complex viewing page, and can download sets of all TCR complex structures from the Downloads page. CDR loop sequences from all known TCR structures, and clusters of CDR loop structures, are also available to users.
</p><fig id="btz517-F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p>TCR structural and complex data in TCR3d. (<bold>A</bold>) The tables of TCR complexes (top) link to interactive TCR complex structure viewers, which show the structure of the selected TCR (green, blue) bound to peptide or antigen (gray sticks) and MHC or MHC-like molecule (red), along with MHC-peptide plane (magenta grid) and TCR inter-domain axis and vector (dashed magenta lines), to indicate twist (crossing angle) and tilt (incident angle). (<bold>B</bold>) The set of calculated docking orientation angles (incident angle, crossing angle) for TCRs, classified according to TCR restriction and type. (<bold>C</bold>) Human TRAV gene representation in experimentally determined TCR structures (Color version of this figure is available at <italic>Bioinformatics</italic> online.)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="btz517f1"/></fig><p>Though its primary focus is TCR structures and interfaces, TCR3d also contains sets of published TCR sequences, particularly those that target neoantigens and viral antigens. Users have the option to search any of those sequences against sequences of experimentally determined TCR structures, and a link is provided to submit sequences directly to the TCRmodel server (<xref rid="btz517-B6" ref-type="bibr">Gowthaman and Pierce, 2018</xref>) to generate a 3D model. TCR3d also allows users to search their own CDR3, peptide, or variable domain sequences against known structures, with the option to search using subsequence motifs for CDR3 or peptide sequences. Recent studies have demonstrated that sequence-based analysis can lead to insights into TCR targeting (<xref rid="btz517-B4" ref-type="bibr">DeWitt <italic>et al.</italic>, 2018</xref>; <xref rid="btz517-B5" ref-type="bibr">Glanville <italic>et al.</italic>, 2017</xref>), and by providing a simple and easily accessible interface on TCRs and their interactions through TCR3d, we hope to enable further advances incorporating structural and molecular data, leading to a predictive and mechanistic understanding of TCR structures, antigen recognition and specificity.</p></sec></body><back><ack id="ack1"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Johnathan Guest and Philip Bradley for helpful input, as well as Zhiping Weng, Sydney Blevins and Brian Baker, whose input and discussions spurred the initial development of the database. Tyler Borrman provided assistance with linking TCR complex entries to the ATLAS database, while Mikhail Shugay provided assistance with the VDJdb API. Christian Presley and the IBBR computing services team supported server and web site setup. We also express our thanks and appreciation to the x-ray crystallographers whose efforts produced the structures that provided the basis for this database.</p><sec><title>Funding</title><p>This work was supported by the National Institutes of Health [GM126299 to B.G.P.].</p><p>
<italic>Conflict of Interest</italic>: none declared.</p></sec></ack><ref-list id="ref1"><title>References</title><ref id="btz517-B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blevins</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal>et al</etal> (<year>2016</year>) 
<article-title>How structural adaptability exists alongside HLA-A2 bias in the human alphabeta TCR repertoire</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source>, <volume>113</volume>, <fpage>E1276</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1285</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26884163</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="btz517-B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Borrman</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal>et al</etal> (<year>2017</year>) 
<article-title>ATLAS: a database linking binding affinities with structures for wild-type and mutant TCR-pMHC complexes</article-title>. <source>Proteins</source>, <volume>85</volume>, <fpage>908</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>916</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28160322</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="btz517-B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Camacho</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) 
<article-title>BLAST+: architecture and applications</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>10</volume>, <fpage>421</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20003500</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="btz517-B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>DeWitt</surname><given-names>W.S.</given-names><suffix>3rd</suffix></name></person-group>
<etal>et al</etal> (<year>2018</year>) 
<article-title>Human T cell receptor occurrence patterns encode immune history, genetic background, and receptor specificity</article-title>. <source>eLife</source>, <volume>7</volume>, e38358.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="btz517-B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Glanville</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal>et al</etal> (<year>2017</year>) 
<article-title>Identifying specificity groups in the T cell receptor repertoire</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>, <volume>547</volume>, <fpage>94</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>98</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28636589</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="btz517-B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gowthaman</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pierce</surname><given-names>B.G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>) 
<article-title>TCRmodel: high resolution modeling of T cell receptors from sequence</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>., <volume>46</volume>, <fpage>W396</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>W401</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29790966</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="btz517-B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leem</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal>et al</etal> (<year>2018</year>) 
<article-title>STCRDab: the structural T-cell receptor database</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>., <volume>46</volume>, <fpage>D406</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>D412</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29087479</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="btz517-B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>North</surname><given-names>B.</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name></person-group>
<etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) 
<article-title>A new clustering of antibody CDR loop conformations</article-title>. <source>J. Mol. Biol</source>., <volume>406</volume>, <fpage>228</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>256</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21035459</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="btz517-B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pierce</surname><given-names>B.G.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weng</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) 
<article-title>A flexible docking approach for prediction of T cell receptor-peptide-MHC complexes</article-title>. <source>Protein Sci</source>., <volume>22</volume>, <fpage>35</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>46</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23109003</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="btz517-B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rossjohn</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal>et al</etal> (<year>2015</year>) 
<article-title>T cell antigen receptor recognition of antigen-presenting molecules</article-title>. <source>Annu. Rev. Immunol</source>., <volume>33</volume>, <fpage>169</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>200</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25493333</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="btz517-B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rudolph</surname><given-names>M.G.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) 
<article-title>How TCRs bind MHCs, peptides, and coreceptors</article-title>. <source>Annu. Rev. Immunol</source>., <volume>24</volume>, <fpage>419</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>466</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16551255</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="btz517-B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shugay</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal>et al</etal> (<year>2018</year>) 
<article-title>VDJdb: a curated database of T-cell receptor sequences with known antigen specificity</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>., <volume>46</volume>, <fpage>D419</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>D427</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28977646</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="btz517-B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stadinski</surname><given-names>B.D.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal>et al</etal> (<year>2016</year>) 
<article-title>Hydrophobic CDR3 residues promote the development of self-reactive T cells</article-title>. <source>Nat. Immunol</source>., <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>946</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>955</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27348411</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="btz517-B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tickotsky</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal>et al</etal> (<year>2017</year>) 
<article-title>McPAS-TCR: a manually curated catalogue of pathology-associated T cell receptor sequences</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>33</volume>, <fpage>2924</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2929</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28481982</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="btz517-B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) 
<article-title>Structural basis for self-recognition by autoimmune T-cell receptors</article-title>. <source>Immunol. Rev</source>., <volume>250</volume>, <fpage>32</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>48</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23046121</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>