<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="case-report"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Cardiothorac Surg</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Cardiothorac Surg</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Cardiothoracic Surgery</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1749-8090</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31924238</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6954628</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1065</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13019-020-1065-x</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A surgical case of mediastinal hematoma caused by a minor traffic injury</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>Katsuyuki</given-names></name><address><email>k-suzuki@ypch.gr.jp</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-4087-635X</contrib-id><name><surname>Shiono</surname><given-names>Satoshi</given-names></name><address><email>sshiono@ypch.gr.jp</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hayasaka</surname><given-names>Kazuki</given-names></name><address><email>kzkhayasaka@ypch.gr.jp</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Endoh</surname><given-names>Makoto</given-names></name><address><email>m-endoh@ypch.gr.jp</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1773 9434</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.417323.0</institution-id><institution>Department of Thoracic Surgery, </institution><institution>Yamagata Prefectural Central Hospital, </institution></institution-wrap>1800, Ooazaaoyagi, Yamagata, 990-2292 Japan </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>10</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>12</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>16</day><month>1</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>6</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s). 2020</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Mediastinal hematoma rarely occurs after a minor traffic injury.</p></sec><sec><title>Case presentation</title><p id="Par2">A woman in her forties was transferred to the emergency room by ambulance due to a traffic accident. Computed tomography (CT) revealed no abnormal findings, and she went home. Two days after the accident, the contrast-enhanced CT was repeated, which revealed cervical and mediastinal hematomas. Because it was possible that there was active bleeding from the right inferior thyroid artery, embolization of the right inferior thyroid artery was performed; however, her condition further deteriorated, so we performed emergency surgery to achieve hemostasis and remove the hematoma. Because of oozing from the right thyroid lobe, we performed right hemithyroidectomy and drainage of mediastinal space and right thoracic cavity. Since there was no bleeding site in the mediastinum, we thought that the mediastinal hematoma was due to bleeding from the thyroid gland. Her postoperative course was uneventful, and she is doing well at 9&#x02009;months of follow-up after surgery.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par3">It is possible that mediastinal hematoma might be caused by a minor traffic injury<bold>.</bold></p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Mediastinal hematoma</kwd><kwd>Thyroid bleeding</kwd><kwd>Minor traffic injury</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par5">Most massive mediastinal hematomas are associated with great vessel disruption or major injury [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. There are a few reports of mediastinal hematoma not associated with great vessel disruption or major injury. Additionally, there have been no reports of massive mediastinal hemorrhage after a minor traffic injury. Because massive mediastinal hematoma due to minor injury is very rare, the indication for surgical intervention is controversial [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. We herein report a very rare surgical case of mediastinal hematoma caused by a minor traffic injury.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Case presentation</title><p id="Par6">A woman in her forties was transferred to the emergency room by an ambulance due to a traffic accident. While sitting in the driver&#x02019;s seat of an automobile traveling at 40&#x02009;km per hour, a lightweight truck traveling at 30&#x02009;km per hour crashed into the right side of her vehicle. Because of the location of the impact, the front air bag did not deploy. Just after the accident, she complained of left posterior neck pain and slight left chest pain. Since computed tomography (CT) revealed no abnormal findings, she went home. Ten hours after the accident, when she bent back, she felt a sudden sore throat and dyspnea, and the pain continued. On the next day, she visited an orthopedic surgery department, and her condition was diagnosed as cervical sprain. Two days after the traffic accident, she visited the emergency room again due to cervical swelling, dysphagia, chest pain, and severe fatigue. Repeated contrast-enhanced CT revealed a massive retropharyngeal and mediastinal hematoma compressing the trachea, esophagus, and superior vena cava. The CT findings suggested extravasation from the right inferior thyroid artery (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). To confirm and embolize the site of bleeding, angiography was performed. However, angiography could not identify the active bleeding point, and we performed the embolization of the right inferior thyroid artery according to the CT findings. Despite embolization, her condition further deteriorated. We decided to perform surgery to obtain hemostasis and drain the mediastinal hematoma. First, we performed surgery of the neck and ligated the right inferior thyroid artery and vein. To stop the oozing from the thyroid gland, a right hemithyroidectomy was performed (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Subsequently, mediastinal drainage and hemostasis was performed through a posterolateral thoracotomy. There was a hematoma mainly at the prevertebral lesion, and mediastinal drainage was carried out (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). The mediastinal pleura was fully opened, and the azygos and vagus nerves were secured. The hematoma between the pre-vertebral lesion and the dorsal aspect of the esophagus was removed. Since a site of bleeding in the mediastinum could not be identified, we believed the mediastinal hematoma was due to bleeding from the thyroid gland. Total blood loss was 255&#x02009;g, and the operative time was 106&#x02009;min. Because of laryngeal edema, she was extubated on postoperative day 2. After leaving the intensive care unit, her clinical course was uneventful, and she was discharged on postoperative day 14. She is doing well at 9&#x02009;months of follow-up after surgery.
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>CT findings. <bold>a</bold> A cervical hematoma in the retropharyngeal space. <bold>b</bold> Mediastinal hematoma. <bold>c</bold> A mediastinal hematoma compressing the trachea, esophagus, and superior vena cava. <bold>d</bold> Extravasation of contrast medium (arrow)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13019_2020_1065_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig>
<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Cervical surgical view. Ligation of the right inferior thyroid artery and vein (arrow) Right lobe of the thyroid gland (arrowhead). In Fig. 2, H: Head, F: Foot, R: Right, L: Left</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13019_2020_1065_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig>
<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Thoracic surgical view. <bold>a</bold> The hematoma extended from the cervical pleura to the surface of the diaphragm, and there was marked swelling of the mediastinum. <bold>b</bold> The mediastinal pleura was fully opened, and the azygos (arrow) and vagus nerves (arrowhead) were secured. <bold>c</bold> The hematoma between the pre-vertebral lesion and dorsal aspect of the esophagus was removed. Vagus nerves (arrow), Esophagus (arrowhead)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13019_2020_1065_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec3"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par7">Mediastinal hematoma without major thoracic injury is reported to be extremely rare [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. According to previous reports, various causes have been reported: thyroid gland rupture by blunt neck trauma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>], rupture of the inferior thyroid artery by repetitive Valsalva maneuver [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>], violent coughing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>], spontaneous rupture of an inferior thyroid artery aneurysm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>], and hemorrhage in a parathyroid adenoma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. The thyroid gland has a rich blood supply, and we could not find bleeding from the inferior thyroid artery and mediastinum. Thus, we speculated this patient&#x02019;s bleeding could have been caused by neck bleeding from the thyroid gland due to increased venous pressure resulting from the traffic injury. Moreover, it is thought that the blood passed through the retropharyngeal prevertebral space, which is the same root as a deep neck infection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>].</p><p id="Par8">Lemke et al. reviewed 34 cases of thyroid gland hemorrhage after blunt neck trauma and reported the delayed onset of symptoms due to bleeding from the thyroid gland, even 24&#x02009;h after neck trauma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. In this case, the patient showed remarkable symptoms 2&#x02009;days after the traffic accident. At first, we did not suspect that the mediastinal hematoma was due to the minor accident. We subsequently realized that the minor traffic injury may have caused massive mediastinal bleeding. Even after a minor traffic injury, patients who complain of a sore throat or chest pain could have mediastinal bleeding. Such patients should be observed to assure that their condition is stable.</p><p id="Par9">The treatment of mediastinal hematoma depends on the cardiorespiratory conditions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Angiography and embolization are less invasive, and embolization is regarded as an option for treatment. On the other hand, if a patient has severe cardiorespiratory problems due to active bleeding, massive hematoma and tracheal compression, surgical intervention and drainage of the mediastinal hematoma may be necessary. If a patient&#x02019;s general condition is stable, close monitoring and conservative treatment may be appropriate. In this case, although we adopted a wait-and-see strategy after embolization of the right inferior thyroid artery, her general condition was deteriorating, and CT revealed compression of mediastinal organs including the trachea due to the hematoma; therefore, we decided to perform emergent surgery. As a result, she had a good clinical course. The treatment of mediastinal hematoma should be based on the patient&#x02019;s status.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par10">We described a rare case of mediastinal hematoma following a minor traffic injury. Even though such a case is very rare, it should be kept in mind that a minor traffic injury could cause a mediastinal hematoma due to thyroid bleeding.</p></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviation</title><def-list><def-item><term>CT</term><def><p id="Par4">Computed tomography</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We would like to thank Dr. S. Kurabe for angiography and embolization, and Dr. S. Koike, F. Saito, S. Okazaki, and A. Yosida for the surgical procedure of the cervical region.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>All authors (KS, SS, KH, ME) performed the surgery and post-operative treatment. KS wrote the manuscript, and SS was correspondence. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>No funding has been received.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>Not applicable.</p></notes><notes><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par11">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par12">Informed consent was obtained from the patient for publication of this case report.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par13">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoetzenecker</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>T&#x000f6;pker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Klepetko</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Ankersmit</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spontaneous rupture of the inferior thyroid artery resulting in mediastinal hematoma</article-title><source>Interact Cardiovasc Thorac Surg</source><year>2010</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>209</fpage><lpage>210</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1510/icvts.2010.232553</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20442206</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hara</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirose</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamashita</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Thyroid gland rupture caused by blunt trauma to the neck</article-title><source>BMC Res Notes</source><year>2016</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>114</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13104-016-1932-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26892467</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lemke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Schreiber</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Henne-Bruns</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Cammerer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Hillenbrand</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Thyroid gland hemorrhage after blunt neck trauma: case report and review of the literature</article-title><source>BMC Surg</source><year>2017</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>115</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12893-017-0322-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29183351</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bageacu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Prades</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaczmarek</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Porcheron</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spontaneous rupture of the inferior thyroid artery leading to life-threatening mediastinal hematoma</article-title><source>Ann Thorac Surg</source><year>2005</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>e20</fpage><lpage>e21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.athoracsur.2005.05.020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16242417</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heckenkamp</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Aleksic</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gawenda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Krueger</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Reichert</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunkwall</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Endovascular treatment of a ruptured aneurysm of the inferior thyroid artery. Case report and literature review</article-title><source>J Cardiovasc Surg</source><year>2007</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>193</fpage><lpage>196</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17410066</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ilyicheva</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spontaneous cervical-mediastinal hematoma caused by hemorrhage into parathyroid adenoma: a clinical case</article-title><source>Int J Surg Case Rep</source><year>2015</year><volume>6C</volume><fpage>214</fpage><lpage>217</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijscr.2014.10.029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25553526</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>