<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Infect Drug Resist</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Infect Drug Resist</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IDR</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">idr</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Infection and Drug Resistance</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1178-6973</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">32021315</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6954848</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">234292</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/IDR.S234292</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Species Diversity, Molecular Characterization, and Antimicrobial Susceptibility of Opportunistic Actinomycetes Isolated from Immunocompromised and Healthy Patients of Markazi Province of Iran</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Azadi et al</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Azadi et al</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-7641-7035</contrib-id><name><surname>Azadi</surname><given-names>Davood</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="AN0001"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0001">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0002">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-3061-7987</contrib-id><name><surname>Motallebirad</surname><given-names>Tahereh</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0001">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ghaffari</surname><given-names>Kazem</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0001">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shokri</surname><given-names>Dariuosh</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0003">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-2945-2436</contrib-id><name><surname>Rezaei</surname><given-names>Fatemeh</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0001">1</xref></contrib><aff id="AFF0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Laboratory Sciences, Khomein University of Medical Sciences</institution>, <addr-line>Khomein</addr-line>, <country>Iran</country></aff><aff id="AFF0002"><label>2</label><institution>Molecular Medicine Research Center, Faculty of Medicine, Arak University of Medical Sciences</institution>, <addr-line>Arak</addr-line>, <country>Iran</country></aff><aff id="AFF0003"><label>3</label><institution>Department of Biology and Microbiology, Shahid Ashrafi Isfahani University</institution>, <addr-line>Isfahan</addr-line>, <country>Iran</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="AN0001">Correspondence: Davood Azadi <institution>Khomein University of Medical Sciences</institution>, <addr-line>Gods Street</addr-line>, <addr-line>Khomein</addr-line>, <country>Iran</country><phone>Tel +98-8646224143</phone> Email Davood.azadi@gmail.com</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>07</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>13</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>11</day><month>10</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>13</day><month>12</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2020 Azadi et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Azadi et al.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/"><license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution &#x02013; Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec id="S2001"><title>Background</title><p>Actinomycetes widely exist in nature and these species cause infections in immunocompromised and healthy patients, although they are frequently found as members of the normal microbiota of humans and animals. These subsequent infections are often misdiagnosed as malignancy and tuberculosis. Due to this issue, the present study aimed to determine the presence and diversity of actinomycetes species causing infections in Iranian patients.</p></sec><sec id="S2002"><title>Materials and Methods</title><p>A total of 79 clinical samples collected from five hospitals in Markazi province were analyzed for the existence of actinomycetes using standard protocols for isolation and characterization of the isolates. The conventional tests were used for preliminary identification, the PCR amplification of <italic>hsp</italic>65 gene, the specific region of the 16S rRNA, and sequence analyses of 16S rRNA were applied for the genus and species identification. MICs of the antimicrobial agent were determined by the broth microdilution method and interpreted according to the NCCLS guidelines.</p></sec><sec id="S2003"><title>Results</title><p>A total of 17 (21.51%) actinomycetes isolates were recovered from clinical samples. In other analyzed samples, eight (10.12%) gram-positive, 12 (15.18) gram-negative bacteria, and six (7.6) fungi isolates were recovered. The most prevalent actinomycetes species were <italic>M. fortuitum</italic> (17.64%), <italic>N. Mexicana</italic> and <italic>S. heliomycini</italic> (11.76% each), and 10 species, ie, <italic>N. farcinica, M</italic>. &#x0feff;<italic>lehmannii</italic>,<italic> M. flavescens, Arthrobacter crystalopoetis, N. neocaledoniensis, M. phocaicum, M. abscessus, M. arupense</italic>,<italic> M. setense</italic>, and<italic> N. cyriacigeorgica</italic> made up the single isolates. Results of DST illustrated that all of the isolates were susceptible to Amikacin, Levofloxacin, Ofloxacin, and Ciprofloxacin, whereas all of them were resistant to Rifampicin and Doxycycline.</p></sec><sec id="S2004"><title>Conclusion</title><p>In conclusion, increasing isolation of actinomycetes found in various clinical cases merits special attention by health authorities in developing countries. In health centers, action should be taken to increase awareness of appropriate diagnostic criteria and management guidelines for actinomycetes diseases. Furthermore, an increase in the number as well as the quality of national and regional reference laboratories may facilitate more accurate diagnosis of actinomycetes diseases.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>actinomycetes</kwd><kwd>16SrRNA</kwd><kwd>drug susceptibility pattern</kwd><kwd>immunocompromised</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="1"/><table-count count="2"/><ref-count count="55"/><page-count count="10"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="S0001"><title>Introduction</title><p>Actinomycetes are the general term for a heterogeneous group of gram-positive bacteria that grow as anaerobic facultative or aerobic rods with various degrees of branching.<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> Actinomycetes species are widely distributed in nature and are found in soil, water, and decaying vegetation,<xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> and also frequently found as members of the normal microbiota in open cavities, especially the oropharynx, upper respiratory tract, gastrointestinal tract, and female genital tract.<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></p><p>To date, the group actinomycetes comprise over eight genera and 500 species. Although <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> is one of the most common species, the major genera of the actinomycetes group are the mycobacterium, corynebactenium, nocardioform actinomycetes, actinomyces, and streptomyces. Among the different species of actinomycetes identified, only a few lead to diseases such as mycobacterium, n ocardia, and actinomyces, moreover nowadays several other species are being increasingly recognized as significant human pathogens.<xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref> These species have been cited as responsible pathogens for opportunistic infections in immunocompromised patients such as those with neoplastic diseases, diabetic patients, patients on immunosuppressive therapy, and those with autoimmune disorders.<xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> However, several recent reports indicated that nocardia and actinomyces can produce infections in patients with no preexisting illness, trauma, or immunosuppressive therapy.<xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> The major pathologic appearance of the disease by these bacteria is a granulomatous inflammatory reaction, which may progress to abscess formation.<xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></p><p>The conventional diagnosis of actinomycetes infections has been done by a combination of clinical and microbiological methods, however they are often non-specific and require invasive diagnostic biopsy procedures, though isolation and accurate characterization of isolates are difficult.<xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> Recent advances in microbiological and molecular methods in disease diagnosis and identification of bacterial isolates improve the outcomes of infected patients, helping clinicians and clinical microbiology personnel with the earliest possible diagnosis; and the evaluation of newer effective drug therapies for these patients.<xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> Due to this issue nowadays for isolation and identification of actinomycetes species used the various molecular method such as sequence analysis of housekeeping gene included 16SrRNA and <italic>rpo</italic>B gene etc, DNA&#x02013;DNA hybridization and direct amplification of specific gene such as <italic>hsp</italic>65 and ITS gene.<xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></p><p>Despite the abundance of reports in the scientific literature regarding the isolation of actinomycetes from both clinical samples and non-hospitalized patients around the world,<xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> few studies have investigated the isolation and identification of actinomycetes species in clinical samples from Iran.<xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></p><p>Drug susceptibility testing results among the actinomycetes species is very different. For example, some mycobacterium, nocardia, and other actinomycetes species are sensitive to macrolides, aminoglycosides, and tigecycline, while some of them are resistant to this antibiotic.<xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> Due to this issue, antibiotic susceptibility testing should be performed In order to determine the susceptibility of the infectious strains for proper treatment of patients.</p><p>The aim of the current study was to assess the frequency, diversity, and drug susceptibility testing (DST) of actinomycetes species causing infection in hospitalized and non-hospitalized patients, by applying molecular and conventional microbiologic approaches in order to provide a deeper insight into their role in pathogenesis, nosocomial infections, and achieve a better diagnosis and effective drug therapies for infected patients.</p></sec><sec id="S0002"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="S0002-S2001"><title>Sampling and Isolation</title><p>From April 2018 to September 2019, there were a total of 79 clinical samples, including 10 sputum samples, 10 pleural fluid/pus samples, eight dental abscess samples, eight bronchial wash samples, 22 wound samples, nine blood samples, and 12 abscesses were collected from immunocompromised (patients with underlying disease such as malignancy, diabetes mellitus, HIV, organ transplantation, inherent immune deficiency, etc.) and immunocompetent patients (patients with no underlying disease) from five hospitals in Markazi province of Iran. The sources and clinical details of the isolates were summarized (<xref rid="T0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The sampling and pretreatment were carried out based on standard methods for isolation and identification of actinomycetes.<xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> In summary, each sample was transported at 4&#x000b0;C to the laboratory and processed within a maximum period of 24 hours. Initially non-sterile samples such as wound, pus, and sputum processed by NaOH 4% and HCL 1% and other sterile samples include blood, tracheal fluid, and pleural fluid condensed with centrifugation in 3,000 &#x000d7;g, then inoculated in Lowenstein Jensen (LJ) (Merk, Germany), carbon free broth, blood agar (Merk, Germany), and Sauton&#x02019;s media supplemented with antifungal and antibacterial antibiotics [kanamycin, nalidixic, and nystatin acid (each at 50 &#x003bc;g/mL)] and incubated for 8 weeks at 25, 32, and 37&#x000b0;C.<xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref><table-wrap id="T0001" orientation="landscape" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Isolation Source, Underlying Disease of Patients, and Phenotypic and Biochemical Features of Actinomycetes Isolated from Clinical Samples</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="5" rowspan="1">Sample Profile</th><th colspan="11" rowspan="1">Biochemical Features</th><th colspan="3" rowspan="1">16S rRNA Analysis</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Isolates</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Location (City)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Origin</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Immune Defect</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poly Microbial</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Opt. Tm</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urease</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Catalase</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pigment Production</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tween 80 Hydrolysis</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nitrate Reduction Ne</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Growth Rate (Days)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lysozyme Resistance</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Decomposition of Tyrosine</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Decomposition of Xanthene</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Decomposition of Hypoxanthine</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Similarity (%)<sup>a</sup></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Base Pair Differences</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Identification</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Khomein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lung/Skin abscess</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cancer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/860</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>M. fortuitum</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Khomein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abscess</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diabetic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/878</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>M. fortuitum</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arak</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wound</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cancer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/712</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>M. fortuitum</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arak</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abscess</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AIDS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yellow</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/689</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>M. lehmannii</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arak</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wound</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cancer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Orange</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.97</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2/951</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>M. flavescens</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Khomein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Foot wound</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diabetic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Orange</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/1240</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>M. phocaicum</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arak</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Skin abscess</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Organ transplant</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;/+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/920</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>M. abscessus</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Khomein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dental abscess</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cancer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/980</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>M. arupense</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Khomein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Foot wound</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/860</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>M. setense</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Khomein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abscess</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Surgery</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">White</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/648</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>N. neocaledoniensis</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Khomein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Brain abscess</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cancer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">White</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/912</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>N. cyriacigeorgica</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arak</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wound</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">AIDS</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">White</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/1010</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>N. mexicana</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Khomein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Breast abscess</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cancer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">White</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/912</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>N. mexicana</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Khomein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Breast abscess</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cancer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Red</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/745</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>S. heliomycini</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arak</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Foot wound</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diabetic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Red</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/745</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>S. heliomycini</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Khomein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Breast abscess</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cancer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">White</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/800</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>N. farcinica</italic></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Khomein</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Foot wound</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Diabetic</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">+</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yellow</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0/745</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>A. crystalopoetis</italic></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p><p>This study was approved by the ethics committee of Arak University of Medical Sciences and Social Welfare Organization under which the private and public daycare nurseries or kindergartens are organized and operate (Grant No. 3005). Any patient&#x02019;s participant provided an informed consent on their behalf.</p></sec><sec id="S0002-S2002"><title>Conventional Bacterial Identification</title><p>The clinical isolates were identified primarily as actinomycetes such as mycobacterium, nocardia, and streptomyces by conventional phenotypic and biochemical tests including acid-fast staining, semi-quantitative, and heat-stable (68&#x000b0;C) catalase production, tween opacity, nitrate reduction, urease activity, tellurite reduction, niacin accumulation, growth at 25, 32, 37, and 42&#x000b0;C, pigment production, resistance to lysozyme, hydrolysis of tyrosine, xanthine, and hypoxanthine tests.<xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> The recognition was further pursued by molecular tests as follows.</p></sec><sec id="S0002-S2003"><title>Molecular Identification</title><p>The method of Pitcher et al<xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> was used for DNA extraction with some modifications. In brief, for the lysis of actinomycetes cells, a pretreatment with lipase (2 mg/mL) and sonication was carried out followed by cell wall disruption with a high concentrations of lysozyme (200 mg/mL final concentration) and proteinase K (300 mg/mL final concentration) in the presence of sodium dodecyl sulfate (SDS) and additional treatment with guanidium isothiocyanate solution. The extracted DNA was purified with phenol-chloroform-isoamyl alcohol (25:24:1, vol/vol/vol) and chloroform-isoamyl alcohol (24:1, vol/vol) and precipitated with sodium acetate and ethanol at 20&#x000b0;C. Precipitated DNA was then washed with 70% ethanol and resuspended in 200 mL of Milli-Q water.</p><p>The isolates identified phenotypically as actinomycetes were further analyzed in terms of genus and species levels using a panel of molecular tests that included a genus-specific PCR based on a 596 bp region of the 16S rRNA for Nocardia and Streptomyces, as recommended by Laurent et al,<xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> and a genus-specific PCR based on a 618-bp fragment of the 65-kDa heat shock protein for mycobacterium, as recommended by Khan and Yadav,<xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> followed by the amplification and direct analysis of almost complete 16SrRNA sequencing for species identification, as described by Shojaei et al.<xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> Sequencing was performed by the Bioneer Company (South Korea), and the sequence data received were aligned manually with existing sequences of actinomycetes retrieved from the GenBank database and analyzed using the Blast program in GenBank and the jPhydit program.<xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></p></sec><sec id="S0002-S2004"><title>Drug Susceptibility Testing (DST)</title><p>To perform DST for clinical actinomycetes isolates, we selected amikacin, ciprofloxacin, cefoxitin, rifampicin, doxycycline, Imipenem, linezolid, and streptomycin based on Clinical &#x00026; Laboratory Standards Institute (CLSI) 2017.<xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref> The stock solutions of each agent were prepared by dissolving pure powder of individual drugs in sterile distilled water or another suitable solvent. All isolates were subcultured in Sauton&#x02019;s media with 0.5% Tween 80 and subsequently incubated at 37&#x000b0;C for 7 days. For each isolate, a suspension in broth was prepared from isolates grown in agar medium and the inoculum was standardized for susceptibility testing to a turbidity equivalent to a 0.5 McFarland standard. Suspensions were then diluted and inoculated into 96-well microtiter plates.</p><p>Minimum inhibitory concentrations (MICs) of the antimicrobial agents were determined by the broth microdilution method and interpreted based on the guidelines established by the NCCLS.<xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> Microdilution plates were prepared manually for each antibiotic. Serial double dilutions of antimicrobial agents were prepared ranging from 0.06&#x02013;512 mg/L, added to Mueller&#x02013;Hinton broth plus 10% tween 80, and then 0.1 mL was dispensed into the wells of microdilution plates. Following inoculation, all cultures were incubated at 37&#x000b0;C. Growth was examined up to 7 days. The MIC was defined as the lowest concentration of the antibiotic that inhibited bacterial growth. Susceptible and resistant breakpoints were defined according to the NCCLS recommendations.<xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref> Quality control of MICs was performed by testing NCCLS recommended reference strains, including <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> ATCC 29213, <italic>Enterococcus faecalis</italic> ATCC 29212, and <italic>Mycobacterium peregrinum</italic> ATCC 700686.</p></sec><sec id="S0002-S2005"><title>Nucleotide Sequence Accession Numbers</title><p>The GenBank accession numbers for the 16S rRNA sequencing of clinical isolates of Iranian actinomycetes determined in this study are; <italic>N. farcinica</italic> MK478806, <italic>M. lehmannii</italic> MK478802, <italic>M. flavescens</italic> MK478804, <italic>M. fortuitum</italic> MK478942, <italic>N. mexicana</italic> MK478947, <italic>S. heliomycini</italic> MK478949, <italic>A. crystalopoetis</italic> MK483330, <italic>N. neocaledoniensis</italic> MK483335, <italic>M. phocaicum</italic> MK483337, <italic>M. arupense</italic> MK493306, <italic>M. setense</italic> KF019693, and <italic>N. cyriacigeorgica</italic> MF437315.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S0003"><title>Result</title><p>In this study of the 79 patients referred to our laboratory, 32 (40.5%) were female and 47 (59.5%) were male, 18 (22.78%) were between the ages of 30 and 40 years, 16 (20.25%) were between the ages of 50 and 60 years, 14 (17.72%) were between the ages of 40 and 50 years, 12 (15.2%) were over the age of 70 years, 10 (12.65%) were between the ages of 20 and 30 years, five (6.32%) were between the ages of 60 and 70 years, and four (5%) were between the ages of 10 and 20 years. Forty-five patients were found to have various immunosuppressive syndromes, including malignancy (14 cases), diabetes mellitus (10 cases), HIV infection (5 cases), chronic obstructive pulmonary diseases (6 cases), hepatitis (6 cases), and autoimmune diseases (4 case), while the remainder of the patients had no apparent history of immune disorder.</p><p>In the present study, a total of 17 (21.51%) actinomycetes isolates were recovered from 79 clinical samples collected from immunocompromised and immunocompetent patients from Markazi province hospitals. Among all actinomycetes isolates, a total of 14 isolates were recovered from immunocompromised patients and three isolates were recovered from immunocompetent patients. In other analyzed samples, eight (10.12%) gram-positive, 12 (15.18%) gram-negative bacteria, and six (7.6%) fungi isolates were recovered. Of the total isolates, five isolates were from an abscess, four from a wound, three from a bronchial wash, two from a dental abscess and blood of each, and one isolate was from sputum.</p><p>On the basis of morphological, culture, and biochemical properties, and the genus specific marker, ie, presence of a 596 bp fragment of the 16S rRNA and a 618-bp fragment of the <italic>hsp</italic>65, all 17 isolates were identified as actinomycetes (nocardia, Streptomyces, and mycobacterium), of which nine isolates were identified as mycobacterium, five isolates were identified as Nocardia, two isolates were identified as Streptomyces, and one isolate was identified as Arthrobacter.</p><p>16S rRNA gene sequences&#x02019; analysis of the isolates revealed that all isolates had nucleotide signatures of actinomycetes, at positions 70&#x02013;98 (U-A), 139&#x02013;224 (G-C), 843 (C), 1008&#x02013;1021 (C-G), 1189 (C), 1244&#x02013;129 (C-G), and 1308&#x02013;1329 (C-G) for mycobacterium and at positions 70&#x02013;98 (A-T), 293&#x02013;304 (G-T), 307 (C), 328 (T), 614&#x02013;626 (A-T), 631(G), 661&#x02013;744 (G-C), 824e876 (T-A), 825&#x02013;875 (A-T), 843 (C), and 1122&#x02013;1151 (A-T) for Nocardia and Streptomyces.<xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref></p><p>The most prevalent actinomycetes species isolated from Iranian clinical samples were <italic>M. fortuitum</italic> (3 isolates, 17.64%), <italic>N. Mexicana</italic> and <italic>Streptomyces heliomycini</italic> (2 isolates, 11.76%) each and 10 species, ie, <italic>N. farcinica, M. lehma</italic>n<italic>nii, M. flavescens, Arthrobacter crystalopoetis, N. neocaledoniensis, M. phocaicum, M. abscessus, M. arupense</italic>,<italic> M. setense</italic>, and<italic> N. cyriacigeorgica</italic>, made up the single isolates. The almost complete 16S rRNA gene sequences obtained for the species&#x02019; accurate identification of clinical isolates showed that all isolates had 100% similarity with the nearest standard type strain of actinomycetes.</p><p>The phylogenic relationship between our isolates and the validated actinomycetes species was supported by a phylogenetic tree of 16S rRNA and by the high bootstrap value obtained using the neighbor-joining method with arithmetic mean using the matrix of pairwise differences (<xref rid="F0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>).<fig id="F0001" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>16SrRNA sequence based phylogenetic tree for Iranian actinomycetes isolates and nearest validated species of actinomycetes by using the neighbor-joining method. The figures at each node represent bootstrapping values. The tree was rooted with <italic>Gordonia terrae</italic>.</p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="IDR-13-1-g0001"/></fig></p><sec id="S0003-S2001"><title>Drug Susceptibility Pattern</title><p><xref rid="T0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> shows that the MIC of the tested isolates and the interpretation of activity of 10 antimicrobial agents against the 17 actinomycetes isolates. MIC lowest rates of antimicrobial agents against tested isolates belonged to Levofloxacin, Ofloxacin, and Ciprofloxacin, respectively, with a MIC rate of 0.25&#x02013;2 &#x000b5;g/mL and the highest rates of MIC of antimicrobial agents belonged to Doxycycline and Isoniazid with MIC rate 4 (<xref rid="T0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).<table-wrap id="T0002" orientation="landscape" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>MIC Range and Susceptibility Pattern of Iranian Actinomycetes Using the Broth Microdilution Method</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Isolates</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rifampicin</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Imipenem</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Streptomycin</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amikacin</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kanamycin</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ciprofloxacin</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ofloxacin</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Levofloxacin</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cefoxitin</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Doxycycline</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>N. farcinica</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;128</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;256</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;256</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;0.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;256</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>M. lehmannii</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;256</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;128</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;0.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;256</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>M. flavescens</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;128</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;256</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;128</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;0.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;256</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>M. fortuitum</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;256</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;128</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;256</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;128</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>N. mexicana</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;256</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;256</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>S. heliomycini</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;256</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;128</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;0.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;128</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>M. fortuitum</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;128</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;256</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;128</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;0.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;128</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>A. crystalopoetis</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;128</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;256</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;128</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;0.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;256</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>M. fortuitum</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;256</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;256</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>N. neocaledoniensis</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;128</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;256</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>M. phocaicum</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;128</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;256</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>M. abscessus</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;128</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;0.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;128</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;128</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;256</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>M. arupense</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;0.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;256</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>N. mexicana</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;0.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;128</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>M. setense</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264; 3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;128</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;256</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>N. cyriacigeorgica</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;128</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;256</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;256</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;0.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;256</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>S. heliomycini</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;256</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;128</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;0.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265;128</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p><p>Actinomycetes isolates recovered from immunocompromised patients had a higher MIC rate to Rifampicin, Doxycycline, Streptomycin, and Imipenem; however they had a low MIC rate to Ciprofloxacin, Ofloxacin, and Cefoxitin. Actinomycetes isolates recovered from immunocompetent patients had a higher MIC rate to Amikacin, Doxycycline, and Cefoxitin, but also had a low MIC rate to Streptomycin, Levofloxacin, and Kanamycin.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S0004"><title>Discussion</title><p>Many species of actinomycetes such as nocardia, mycobacterium, and ie, are increasingly being recognized as important human pathogens in both immunocompetent and immunocompromised patients.<xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref> The clinical presentation and severity of disease and the prognosis in an infected patient are extremely variable and may be determined by several factors such as the route of infection and the functioning level of the immune system.<xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> Likewise, accurate identification and DST of actinomycetes clinical isolates is a significant decision support tool which may help clinicians in order to select more appropriate therapy and, thus, improve the management and outcomes of some important actinomycetes diseases.</p><p>In low-income countries like Iran, where the microbiological diagnosis of infection agents relies mostly on microscopy, and also where access to culture and drug susceptibility testing is virtually non-existent, a clinician may neglect to consider the possibility that infections found in patients.<xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> Isolation and identification of actinomycetes species from clinical samples can often require specific preparatory procedures, while extensive microbial identification of this group of bacteria comprises a minimum of 10 phenotypic tests used to identify the entire spectrum of actinomycetes. These tests are difficult to interpret and generally lead to inconclusive results.<xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> Consequently, attempts to isolate and identify actinomycetes species by conventional phenotypic tests alone may result in erroneous or incomplete identification if a sufficient number of discriminative tests are not available.<xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> However, in response to the need for a more rapid and accurate identification of clinically relevant actinomycetes, appropriate use of molecular tests, in conjunction with the key phenotypic tests, has shown significant promise.<xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref> Increasing recovery of actinomycetes species from environmental and clinical sources in different parts of the world<xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref> prompted us to design the present study to determine the extent of the actinomycetes diversity in clinical samples of Markazi province of Iran. We envisaged that optimization of methods in isolation and accurate characterization of actinomycetes species from clinical samples by application of conventional microbiologic and molecular approaches is a key step towards the description of the emerging infections that they cause but are often ignored or missed.</p><p>In the current study, we isolated and characterized 17 (21.51%) actinomycetes species from 79 clinical samples collected from five educational hospitals. The actinomycetes species recovered from clinical samples in our studies included nine mycobacterial species, including <italic>M. fortuitum</italic>,<italic> M. phocaicum, M. lehma</italic><italic>n</italic><italic>nii, M. abscessus, M. arupense</italic>, and <italic>M. setense</italic>, four nocardia species, <italic>N. Mexicana, N. farcinica, N. neocaledoniensis</italic>, and <italic>N. cyriacigeorgica</italic>, two <italic>Streptomyces heliomycini</italic>, and one <italic>Arthrobacter crystalopoetis</italic>. However, there are no comprehensive reports about isolation of actinomycetes from clinical samples. The results of this study compared with other reports showed that the <italic>M. fortuitum, N. farcinica</italic>, and <italic>N. cyriacigeorgica</italic> are the most common actinomycetes species isolated from the clinical samples in Iran and various parts of the world.<xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref> In the current study we reported the first isolation of <italic>M. lehma</italic>n<italic>nii, N. neocaledoniensis</italic>,<italic> S. heliomycini</italic>, and <italic>A. crystalopoetis</italic> from clinical samples.</p><p>In our study <italic>M. fortuitum</italic> was the most encountered actinomycete, including three isolates (17.64%). This organism is a rapidly growing mycobacteria initially isolated and characterized in 1938 from a stomach lavage specimen.<xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref> These findings are in accordance with another report from various parts of the world, which showed the <italic>M. fortuitum</italic> is one of the most common actinomycetes species isolated from clinical samples.<xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref> In the current study, <italic>M. fortuitum</italic> was isolated from lung secretion, abscess, and wound of cancerous patients.</p><p><italic>N. Mexicana</italic> and <italic>S. heliomycini</italic> ranked second, which included 11.76% of the isolates. Based on literature, <italic>N. mexicana</italic> is a human opportunistic pathogen isolated from various clinical samples including bronchial secretions, mycetoma, and cutaneous botryomycosis, pulmonary, and cerebral abscess in humans and tenosynovitis and arthritis in animals.<xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref> In the present study <italic>N. mexicana</italic> was isolated from a breast wound in immunocompetent patients. <italic>S. heliomycini</italic> is an antibiotics producer of bacteria that was first isolated and characterized in 1958 from soil.<xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref> Based on the literature, there are no reports about isolation of <italic>S. heliomycini</italic> from clinical samples, nevertheless in the present study we reported the first isolation and characterization of <italic>S. heliomycini</italic> from a breast abscess of cancerous patient and a foot wound of diabetic patients.</p><p>In this study, ten species, ie, <italic>N. cyriacigeorgica, N. neocaledoniensis, N. farcinica, M. lehma</italic>n<italic>nii, M. flavescens, A. crystalopoetis, M. phocaicum, M. abscessus, M. arupense</italic>, and<italic> M. setense</italic> consisted of the single isolates recovered from immunocompromised patients.</p><p><italic>N. cyriacigeorgica</italic> is a human opportunistic pathogen that was first isolated from the bronchial secretions of a patient with chronic bronchitis in 2001.<xref rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref> In our study, this organism was isolated from a brain abscess of a malignancy patient. <italic>N. farcinica</italic> is one of the first historically identified Nocardia species and has been the most commonly reported isolate from clinical and environmental samples worldwide.<xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref> In the current study, <italic>N. farcinica</italic> was isolated from the breast abscess of a cancerous patient.</p><p>In this study <italic>M. setense, M. abscessus, M. phocaicum, M. flavescens</italic>, and <italic>M. arupense</italic> were recovered from foot wounds of immunocompetent patients, skin abscesses of organ recipient patients, foot wounds of diabetic patients, wounds of malignancy patients, and dental abscesses of malignancy patients, respectively. These mycobacteria are rare emerging organisms originally isolated from clinical specimens.<xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref> Our study reports the first isolation of this organism from clinical samples in Iran.</p><p>In the present study <italic>N. neocaledoniensis, M. lehma</italic>n<italic>nii</italic>, and <italic>A. crystalopoetis</italic> were recovered from surgery wounds of immunocompetent patients, abscesses of AIDS patients, and foot wounds of diabetic patients, respectively. These organisms were originally isolated from environmental resources of actinomycetes and there were no reports on the isolation of these bacteria from clinical samples.<xref rid="CIT0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref> Here, we reported the first isolation and characterization of <italic>N. neocaledoniensis, M. lehma</italic>n<italic>nii</italic>, and <italic>A. crystalopoetis</italic> from clinical specimens.</p><p>DST of actinomycetes clinical isolates may be even more critical in our region due to use of a traditional method for identification, leading to misdiagnosis with tuberculosis, mycetoma, mycosis, etc.<xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref> In developing countries, for example, all smear positive patients are automatically given first line anti-TB agents, and the majority of NTM diseases in Iran are resistant to this treatment regimen.<xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref> Likewise, DST of actinomycetes clinical isolates is an important decision tool which may help clinicians in order to select a suitable and efficient therapy and, thus, improve the management and outcomes of some actinomycetes diseases. Due to this issue in the present study DST for all actinomycetes isolates were done by applying the broth microdilution methods.</p><p>According to an antimicrobial susceptibility test of actinomycetes, clinical isolates <italic>N. neocaledoniensis</italic> and <italic>N. mexicana</italic> had low resistance, whiles <italic>S. heliomycini</italic> and <italic>N. cyriacigeorgica</italic> had a high resistance profile to our selected antibiotics. All of the isolates were susceptible to Amikacin, Levofloxacin, Ofloxacin, and Ciprofloxacin, whereas all of them were resistant to Rifampicin and Doxycycline.</p></sec><sec id="S0005"><title>Conclusion</title><p>In conclusion, increasing isolation of actinomycetes found in various clinical cases of healthy and immunocompromised patients and the high diversity of species of isolated actinomycetes merit special attention by health authorities, microbiologists, and clinicians in developing countries. In health centers, action should be taken to increase awareness of appropriate diagnostic criteria and management guidelines for actinomycetes diseases. Furthermore, an increase in the number as well as the quality of national and regional reference laboratories may cause more accurate diagnosis of actinomycetes diseases. Although the role of in vitro DST in the treatment of the majority of actinomycetes species has not been evaluated, it may play an essential role in the management of patients suffering from actinomycetes-related disease.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgment</title><p>The authors are grateful to the Office of Vice-chancellor for Research of Khomein University of Medical Sciences for financial support of the current study (Grant No. 3005).</p></ack><sec id="S0006" sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Disclosure</title><p>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="CIT0001"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pierre</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zarrouk</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Noussair</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Molina</surname>
<given-names>J-M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fantin</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Invasive actinomycosis: surrogate marker of a poor prognosis in immunocompromised patients</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Infect Dis</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>29</volume>:<fpage>74</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>79</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijid.2014.06.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25449239</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0002"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Saubolle</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>. <chapter-title>Aerobic actinomycetes</chapter-title> In: <source>Diagnostic Microbiology of the Immunocompromised Host</source>. <publisher-name>American Society of Microbiology</publisher-name>; <italic>ASM Press, Washington DC,</italic>
<year>2009</year>:<fpage>269</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>281</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0003"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Dilip</surname>
<given-names>CV</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mulaje</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mohalkar</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A review on actinomycetes and their biotechnological application</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Pharm Sci Res</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1730</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0004"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="data"><collab>from GM-BNU-t-D&#x02013;r</collab>. <year>2019</year>
<comment>Available from:</comment>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dsmz.de/bacterial-diversity/prokaryotic-nomenclature-up-to-date/prokariotic-nomenclature-up-to-date.html">https://www.dsmz.de/bacterial-diversity/prokaryotic-nomenclature-up-to-date/prokariotic-nomenclature-up-to-date.html</ext-link>. <date-in-citation>Accessed <month>12</month><day>16</day>, 2019</date-in-citation>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0005"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Conville</surname>
<given-names>PS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Witebsky</surname>
<given-names>FG</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nocardia, Rhodococcus, Gordonia, Actinomadura, Streptomyces, and Other Aerobic Actinomycetes.</italic> Manual of Clinical Microbiology, <italic toggle="yes">10th Edition</italic></source>. <publisher-name>American Society of Microbiology</publisher-name>; <year>2011</year>:<fpage>443</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>471</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0006"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Carr</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hagan</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Guest</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gompertz</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A &#x0201c;not so superficial&#x0201d; skin infection in a patient with diabetes</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMJ Case Rep</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>2012</volume>:. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bcr-2012-007062</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0007"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bang</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Herlin</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stegger</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title><italic>Mycobacterium arosiense</italic> sp. nov., a slowly growing, scotochromogenic species causing osteomyelitis in an immunocompromised child</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Syst Evol Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>58</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>2398</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2402</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/ijs.0.65503-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18842863</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0008"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Corti</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fioti</surname>
<given-names>MEV</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Nocardiosis: a review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Infect Dis</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>243</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>250</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1201-9712(03)90102-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14656414</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0009"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wong</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Turmezei</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Weston</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Actinomycosis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMJ</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>343</volume>:<fpage>d6099</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.d6099</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21990282</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0010"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ahmed</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>van de Sande</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fahal</surname>
<given-names>AH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Mycetoma laboratory diagnosis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS Negl Trop Dis</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>e0005638</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0005638</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28837657</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0011"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mencarini</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Antonelli</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Scoccianti</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Madura foot in Europe: diagnosis of an autochthonous case by molecular approach and review of the literature</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">New Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>156</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>159</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27196558</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0012"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rajivgandhi</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ramachandran</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Maruthupandy</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vaseeharan</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Manoharan</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Molecular identification and structural characterization of marine endophytic actinomycetes <italic>Nocardiopsis</italic> sp. GRG 2 (KT 235641) and its antibacterial efficacy against isolated ESBL producing bacteria</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Microb Pathog</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>126</volume>:<fpage>138</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>148</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.micpath.2018.10.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30316902</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0013"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Betr&#x000e1;n</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Villuendas</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rezusta</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pereira</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Revillo</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez-Nava</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Clinical significance, antimicrobial susceptibility and molecular identification of Nocardia species isolated from children with cystic fibrosis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Braz J Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>47</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>531</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>535</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bjm.2016.01.029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27155949</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0014"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Madhaiyan</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Poonguzhali</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Saravanan</surname>
<given-names>VS</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title><italic>Streptomyces pini</italic> sp. nov., an actinomycete isolated from phylloplane of pine (Pinus sylvestris L.) needle-like leaves</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Syst Evol Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>66</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>4204</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4210</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/ijsem.0.001336</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27469580</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0015"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Huttenhower</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gevers</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Knight</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Structure, function and diversity of the healthy human microbiome</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nature</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>486</volume>(<issue>7402</issue>):<fpage>207</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22699609</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0016"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Fong</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Francis</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hamblin</surname>
<given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Korman</surname>
<given-names>TM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Graham</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Identification and diversity of Actinomyces species in a clinical microbiology laboratory in the MALDI-TOF MS era</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Anaerobe</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>54</volume>:<fpage>151</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>158</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.anaerobe.2018.09.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30261272</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0017"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Boyanova</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kolarov</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mateva</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Markovska</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mitov</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Actinomycosis: a frequently forgotten disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Future Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>613</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>628</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2217/fmb.14.130</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25865197</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0018"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Irandoost</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ghanbari</surname>
<given-names>MZ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sakhaee</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>High rates of Mycobacterium fortuitum isolation in respiratory samples from Iranian patients with suspected tuberculosis: is it clinically important?</article-title>
<source><italic toggle="yes">J Med Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>67</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1243</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1248</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/jmm.0.000814</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30052175</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0019"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hashemi-Shahraki</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Heidarieh</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bostanabad</surname>
<given-names>SZ</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Genetic diversity and antimicrobial susceptibility of Nocardia species among patients with nocardiosis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Sci Rep</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>17862</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep17862</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26638771</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0020"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cowman</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Burns</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Benson</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wilson</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Loebinger</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The antimicrobial susceptibility of non-tuberculous mycobacteria</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Infect</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>72</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>324</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>331</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jinf.2015.12.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26723913</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0021"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>McTaggart</surname>
<given-names>LR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Doucet</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Witkowska</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Richardson</surname>
<given-names>SE</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Antimicrobial susceptibility among clinical Nocardia species identified by multilocus sequence analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Antimicrob Agents Chemother</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>59</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>269</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>275</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.02770-14</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25348540</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0022"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Njeru</surname>
<given-names>FM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ndungu</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bii</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Characterization and antimicrobial susceptibility of actinomycetes from TB smear negative and retreatment patients in Nairobi, Kenya</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Biosci Med (Irvine)</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4236/jbm.2019.78001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0023"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Saubolle</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sussland</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Nocardiosis review of clinical and laboratory experience</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>4497</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4501</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JCM.41.10.4497-4501.2003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14532173</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0024"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Azadi</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shojaei</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mobasherizadeh</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Naser</surname>
<given-names>AD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Screening, isolation and molecular identification of biodegrading mycobacteria from Iranian ecosystems and analysis of their biodegradation activity</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">AMB Express</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>180</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13568-017-0472-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28933031</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0025"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Pitcher</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Saunders</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Owen</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Rapid extraction of bacterial genomic DNA with guanidium thiocyanate</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lett Appl Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>151</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>156</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1472-765X.1989.tb00262.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0026"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Laurent</surname>
<given-names>FJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Provost</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Boiron</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Rapid identification of clinically relevant Nocardia species to genus level by 16S rRNA gene PCR</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>2805</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0027"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Khan</surname>
<given-names>IU</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yadav</surname>
<given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Development of a single-tube, cell lysis-based, genus-specific PCR method for rapid identification of mycobacteria: optimization of cell lysis, PCR primers and conditions, and restriction pattern analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>453</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>457</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JCM.42.1.453-457.2004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14715804</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0028"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Shojaei</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Heidarieh</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hashemi</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Feizabadi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Daei</surname>
<given-names>NA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Species identification of neglected nontuberculous mycobacteria in a developing country</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Jpn J Infect Dis</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>64</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>265</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>271</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21788699</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0029"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Jeon</surname>
<given-names>Y-S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chung</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Park</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hur</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>J-H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chun</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>jPHYDIT: a JAVA-based integrated environment for molecular phylogeny of ribosomal RNA sequences</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Bioinformatics</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>14</issue>):<fpage>3171</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3173</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/bti463</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15855247</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0030"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Wayne</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Performance Standards for Antimicrobial Susceptibility Testing</italic></source>. <publisher-name>Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute (CLSI)</publisher-name>; <year>2017</year>:<fpage>20</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0031"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Woods</surname>
<given-names>GL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brown-Elliott</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Desmond</surname>
<given-names>EP</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Susceptibility testing of mycobacteria, Nocardia, and other aerobic actinomycetes; approved standard</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">NCCLS Document M24-A</italic></source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>18</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0032"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Stackebrandt</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rainey</surname>
<given-names>FA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ward-Rainey</surname>
<given-names>NL</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Proposal for a new hierarchic classification system, Actinobacteria classis nov</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Sys Evol Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>47</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>479</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>491</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0033"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Cortez-Escalante</surname>
<given-names>JJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Santos</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Garnica</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sarmento</surname>
<given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Castro</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Romero</surname>
<given-names>GAS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Mediastinitis and pericardial effusion in a patient with AIDS and disseminated <italic>Mycobacterium avium</italic> infection: a case report</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Rev Soc Bras Med Trop</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>407</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>409</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0037-86822012000300027</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0034"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ambrosioni</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lew</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Garbino</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Nocardiosis: updated clinical review and experience at a tertiary center</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Infection</italic></source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>38</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>89</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>97</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s15010-009-9193-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20306281</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0035"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Prevots</surname>
<given-names>DR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marras</surname>
<given-names>TK</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Epidemiology of human pulmonary infection with nontuberculous mycobacteria: a review</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Clin Chest Med</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>13</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>34</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ccm.2014.10.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25676516</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0036"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Azadi</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Motallebirad</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ghaffari</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shojaei</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Mycobacteriosis and tuberculosis: laboratory diagnosis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Open Microbiol J</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>41</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/1874285801812010041</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29785215</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0037"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>DeWitt</surname>
<given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stetson</surname>
<given-names>CL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thomas</surname>
<given-names>KL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carroll</surname>
<given-names>BJ</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Extensive cutaneous botryomycosis with subsequent development of nocardia-positive wound cultures</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Cutan Med Surg</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>344</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>346</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1203475418755762</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29366337</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0038"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kim</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>KL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lee</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Nocardia brain abscess in an immunocompetent patient</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Infect Chemother</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>46</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>45</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>49</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3947/ic.2014.46.1.45</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24693470</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0039"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Raby</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hiew</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Arthur</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>A case of <italic>Nocardia mexicana</italic> cerebral abscess highlights deficiencies in susceptibility testing and the utility of direct molecular identification</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Pathology</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>48</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>508</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>510</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pathol.2016.03.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27311866</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0040"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Bhargava</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kombade</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dash</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jain</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Disseminated nocardiasis by <italic>Nocardia farcinica</italic>: review and first case report from Central India</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Med J Armed Forces India</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>75</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>106</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>111</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mjafi.2018.11.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30705489</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0041"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kandi</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Human Nocardia infections: a review of pulmonary nocardiosis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Cureus</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>8</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7759/cureus.268</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0042"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Okamori</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Asakura</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nishimura</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Natural history of <italic>Mycobacterium fortuitum</italic> pulmonary infection presenting with migratory infiltrates: a case report with microbiological analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">BMC Infect Dis</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12879-017-2892-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29291713</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0043"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Rodriguez-Nava</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Couble</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Molinard</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sandoval</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Boiron</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Laurent</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>. <article-title><italic>Nocardia mexicana</italic> sp. nov., a new pathogen isolated from human mycetomas</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Microbiol.</italic></source>
<year>2004</year>;<volume>42</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>4530</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4535</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15472305</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0044"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ikeda</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nakanishi</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Morishita</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Houdai</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ito</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gonoi</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>First case report of pulmonary nocardiosis caused by <italic>Nocardia mexicana</italic></article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">JMM Case Rep</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>e005054</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28348776</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0045"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Owen</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Buckle</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Olm</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Isolation of <italic>Nocardia mexicana</italic> from focal proliferative tenosynovitis and arthritis in a steer</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Aust Vet J</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>93</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>170</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>173</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/avj.v93.5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25939264</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0046"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Avila-Flores</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Medellin</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Ecological, taxonomic, and physiological correlates of cave use by mexican bats</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Mammal</italic></source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>85</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>675</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>687</lpage>. (). doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1644/BOS-127</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0047"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yassin</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rainey</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Steiner</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Nocardia cyriacigeorgici sp. nov</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Syst Evol Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>51</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1419</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1423</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/00207713-51-4-1419</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11491341</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0048"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Elsayed</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kealey</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Coffin</surname>
<given-names>CS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Read</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Megran</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title><italic>Nocardia cyriacigeorgica</italic> septicemia</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Clin Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>44</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>280</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>282</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JCM.44.1.280-282.2006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16390991</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0049"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kageyama</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hoshino</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yazawa</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title><italic>Nocardia cyriacigeorgica</italic> is a significant pathogen responsible for nocardiosis in Japan and Thailand</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mycopathologia</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>160</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>15</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>19</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11046-005-3050-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16160763</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0050"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Nasiri</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dabiri</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Darban-Sarokhalil</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shahraki</surname>
<given-names>AH</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Prevalence of non-tuberculosis mycobacterial infections among tuberculosis suspects in Iran: systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">PLoS One</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>e0129073</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0129073</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26052701</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0051"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Saintpierre-Bonaccio</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Maldonado</surname>
<given-names>LA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Amir</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pineau</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Goodfellow</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title><italic>Nocardia neocaledoniensis</italic> sp. nov., a novel actinomycete isolated from a new-caledonian brown hypermagnesian ultramafic soil</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Syst Evol Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>54</volume>(<issue>Pt 2</issue>):<fpage>599</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>603</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/ijs.0.02881-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15023981</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0052"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Nouioui</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sangal</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carro</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Two novel species of rapidly growing mycobacteria: <italic>mycobacterium lehmannii</italic> sp. nov. and <italic>Mycobacterium neumannii</italic> sp. nov</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Syst Evol Microbiol</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>67</volume>:<fpage>4948</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4955</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/ijsem.0.002350</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29058645</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0053"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Busse</surname>
<given-names>HJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wieser</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Buczolits</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>. <chapter-title>Arthrobacter</chapter-title> In: <source><italic toggle="yes">Bergey&#x02019;s Manual of Systematics of Archaea and Bacteria</italic></source>. 2nd ed., vol. 1, Springer-Verlag, New York, NY, <year>2015</year>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>70</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0054"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Nai-Yang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Qi</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Canalicular inflammatory etiology and the common misdiagnosis study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int Eye Sci</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>2154</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2156</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0055"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mirsaeidi</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tabarsi</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Khoshnood</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Treatment of multiple drug-resistant tuberculosis (MDR-TB) in Iran</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Int J Infect Dis</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>317</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>322</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijid.2004.09.012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16183321</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>