<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Chron Obstruct Pulmon Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Int J Chron Obstruct Pulmon Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">COPD</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">copd</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>International Journal of Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1176-9106</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1178-2005</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Dove</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">32021140</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6954103</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">234634</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/COPD.S234634</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The Protective Effect of HBO1 on Cigarette Smoke Extract-Induced Apoptosis in Airway Epithelial Cells</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">Chen et al</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">Chen et al</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Lin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0001">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0002">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0003">3</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="FT0001"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Lijuan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0001">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0002">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0003">3</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="FT0001"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>Naixin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0001">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0002">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0003">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Xue</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0001">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0002">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0003">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Tiao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0001">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0002">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0003">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-7713-6913</contrib-id><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Yan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="AN0001"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0001">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0002">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0003">3</xref></contrib><aff id="AFF0001"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Pulmonary and Critical Care Medicine, The Second Xiangya Hospital, Central South University</institution>, <addr-line>Changsha</addr-line>
<addr-line>410011</addr-line>, <addr-line>Hunan</addr-line>, <country>People&#x02019;s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="AFF0002"><label>2</label><institution>Research Unit of Respiratory Disease, Central South University</institution>, <addr-line>Changsha</addr-line>
<addr-line>410011</addr-line>, <addr-line>Hunan</addr-line>, <country>People&#x02019;s Republic of China</country></aff><aff id="AFF0003"><label>3</label><institution>Diagnosis and Treatment Center of Respiratory Disease, Central South University</institution>, <addr-line>Changsha</addr-line>
<addr-line>410011</addr-line>, <addr-line>Hunan</addr-line>, <country>People&#x02019;s Republic of China</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="AN0001">Correspondence: Yan Chen <institution>Department of Pulmonary and Critical Care Medicine, The Second Xiangya Hospital, Central South University</institution>, <addr-line>139 Renmin Middle Road</addr-line>, <addr-line>Changsha</addr-line><addr-line>410011</addr-line>, <addr-line>Hunan</addr-line>, <country>People&#x02019;s Republic of China</country><phone>Tel +86 731 85295148</phone> Email chenyan99727@csu.edu.cn</corresp><fn id="FT0001"><label>*</label><p>These authors contributed equally to this work</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>06</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>14</day><month>10</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>12</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2020 Chen et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Chen et al.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/"><license-p>This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited. The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution &#x02013; Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed. For permission for commercial use of this work, please see paragraphs 4.2 and 5 of our Terms (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec id="S2001"><title>Purpose</title><p>Epigenetic modification is one of most important mechanisms underlying the pathogenesis of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD). The purpose of this study was to determine whether histone acetyltransferase binding to ORC1 (HBO1) can protect against cigarette smoke (CS)-induced cell apoptosis and sustain normal histone acetylation in COPD.</p></sec><sec id="S2002"><title>Methods</title><p>Human lung tissue samples were obtained from patients who underwent lung resection. The emphysema mouse model and HBO1 overexpressing mice were each established by intraperitoneal injection with cigarette smoke extract (CSE) or intratracheal lentiviral vectors instillation. TUNEL (terminal deoxynucleotidyl transferase dUTP nick end labeling) assays were used to assess apoptotic ratio in mice. The apoptosis of human bronchial epithelial cells (HBECs) was assayed by flow cytometry. HBO1, B-cell lymphoma-2 (BCL-2), and H3K14ac protein expression were detected by Western blotting. HBO1 mRNA expression was measured by quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction.</p></sec><sec id="S2003"><title>Results</title><p>Protein expression of HBO1 was decreased significantly in lung tissue from COPD patients and CSE-treated emphysema mouse models. Overexpression of HBO1 attenuated CSE-induced emphysematous changes, as well as apoptosis in the lungs of COPD mice. In vitro, the HBO1 protein degraded in a time- and dose-dependent course with CSE treatment. With flow cytometry, we proved that HBO1 could reverse the apoptosis of HBECs induced by CSE. Furthermore, HBO1 overexpression promoted the expression of anti-apoptotic&#x000a0;BCL-2 protein and enhanced H3K14 acetylation in airway epithelial cells.</p></sec><sec id="S2004"><title>Conclusion</title><p>These findings demonstrate that the key histone modulator HBO1 plays a protective role in COPD pathogenesis that may shed light on potential therapeutic targets to inhibit the progress of COPD.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</kwd><kwd>apoptosis</kwd><kwd>HBO1</kwd><kwd>emphysema</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (No. 81400032, No. 81600031, and No. 81873410) and the Fundamental Research Funds for the Central Universities of Central South University (2019zzts1047).</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="6"/><table-count count="1"/><ref-count count="28"/><page-count count="10"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="S0001"><title>Introduction</title><p>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) is a heterogeneous disease characterized by persistent respiratory symptoms and irreversible airflow limitation. It has become the fourth leading cause of death worldwide,<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref> and in the coming decades, further increases in COPD morbidity and mortality are expected.<xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref> Epidemiological data has proved that cigarette smoking is the most common risk factor for COPD development and progression throughout the world. The airway epithelium is the first line of defense against noxious particles or gases entering the lungs. Increasing evidence has demonstrated that airway epithelial cell dysfunction plays a critical role in COPD pathogenesis.<xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></p><p>Epigenetic alternations including DNA methylation, post-modifications of histone modification, and non-coding RNAs are increasingly studied in the context of COPD. In eukaryotic cells, histone acetylation is related to chromatin structure and gene expression.<xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref> Histone acetyltransferases (HATs) and deacetylases (HDACs) are responsible for the acetylation status of a given chromatin locus.<xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> HATs can provide transcriptional machinery access to the DNA template by catalyzing the acetylation of histones. Conversely, HDACs are responsible for the removal of acetyl groups from the lysine residues of histones, resulting in transcriptional repression.<xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> HBO1 (histone acetyltransferase binding to ORC1) is a member of the HAT family that possesses a highly conserved MYST domain.<xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> The MYST domain contains an acetyl-CoA binding motif and a zinc finger and is responsible for the catalytic activity of HBO1.<xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> HBO1 acts on histones H3 and H4 and engages in a variety of biological processes including DNA replication and transcriptional regulation.<xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref> During the G1 phase of the cell cycle, HBO1 can interact with Cdt1 and be recruited to perform the replication functions required for loading the minichromosome maintenance (MCM) complex onto origin DNA and the assembly of pre-replicative complexes (pre-RCs).<xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref> During the S phase, HBO1 is required for the acetylation of H3K14, which is necessary for CDC45 recruitment and activation of DNA replication.<xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> Deleting HBO1 from embryonic cells causes a reduction of global H3K14 acetylation and decreases the expression of genes that regulate embryonic development.<xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> Conversely, HBO1 can lead to excessive cell replication and proliferation in tumors.<xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></p><p>In the present study, we assessed the involvement of HBO1 in COPD pathogenesis.</p></sec><sec id="S0002"><title>Materials And Methods</title><sec id="S0002-S2001"><title>Subjects</title><p>Peripheral lung tissue specimens were obtained from patients who underwent resection for lung cancers. The tissue specimens were resected at least 5 cm away from the cancerous tissue. We included 32 subjects: nonsmokers (n=15), and smokers with COPD (n=5) and without COPD (n=12). The diagnosis of COPD was followed by the guidelines of the Global Initiative for Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease (GOLD) (<underline><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.goldcopd.com">http://www.goldcopd.com</ext-link></underline>). The patients with COPD had airflow limitation (forced expiratory volume in 1 s/forced vital capacity [FEV1/FVC] &#x0003c;0.7). Subject age, sex, smoking history, and lung function (FEV1<sub>pred</sub> and FEV1/FVC) are listed in <xref rid="T0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. Exclusion criteria consisted of lung diseases other than COPD and lung tumors, other systemic diseases, pulmonary infection and antibiotic exposure up to 4 weeks before surgery, use of inhaled or oral glucocorticoids up to 3 months before surgery, a history of chemotherapy or radiotherapy, and a history of occupational exposure. The study was approved by the Clinical Trial and Ethics Committee of the Second Xiangya Hospital of Central South University. Written informed consent was obtained from all human subjects before their enrollment into the study, which was conducted in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki.<table-wrap id="T0001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Clinical Characteristics of the Study Subjects</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristic</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nonsmokers (n=15)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smokers Without COPD(n=12)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smokers with COPD (n=5)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Age, years</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.60&#x000b1;7.48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.92&#x000b1;12.29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.00&#x000b1;5.61</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male, n, (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1(6.67%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11(91.67%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5(100%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoking, (pack-year)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 (10, 30)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.00&#x000b1;19.24</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FEV1pred, %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.72&#x000b1;11.95</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">94.73&#x000b1;15.60</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.78&#x000b1;12.95*<sup>#</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">FEV1/FVC, %</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.49(73.74, 78.23)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.54&#x000b1;5.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.21&#x000b1;8.42*<sup>#</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p><bold>Notes:</bold> Values are presented as mean&#x000b1;SEM for normally distributed data or median (25th, 75th percentiles) for non-normally distributed data. P-values were calculated by Kruskal&#x02013;Wallis tests. *<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.01 compared with nonsmokers; <sup>#</sup><italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.01 compared with smokers without COPD.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Abbreviations:</bold> COPD, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease; FEV1, forced expiratory volume in 1 s; FVC, forced vital capacity.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="S0002-S2002"><title>Animals</title><p>The emphysema mouse model was built according to the protocol of previous study.<xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref> with slight modifications. Six-week-old, specific pathogen-free, BALB/c mice (21&#x02013;23 g each) (Slyke Jingda, Hunan, China) were injected intraperitoneally with cigarette smoke extract (CSE) or phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) at days 0, 11, and 22 (0.3 mL per injection). Lentivirus (10<sup>9</sup> ifu/mL) (GeneChem, Shanghai, China) or PBS (0.1 mL) was injected intratracheally at day 14. The animals were sacrificed on day 28. All animal care and experimental protocols were approved by the Animal Care and Use Committee of Hunan Provincial People&#x02019;s Hospital and were conducted in accordance with the committee&#x02019;s animal care and use guidelines.</p></sec><sec id="S0002-S2003"><title>CSE Preparation</title><p>Cigarettes (Furong, Changde Cigarette Company, Hunan, China) were combusted using a modified syringe-driven apparatus (products of 5 cigarettes were collected in 10 mL PBS for animal experiments, and products of 1 cigarette were collected in 20 mL Dulbecco&#x02019;s minimum essential media [DMEM] for cell experiments). Each cigarette contained 12 mg tar, 1.1 mg nicotine, and 14 mg carbon monoxide. The smoke was bubbled through DMEM/PBS then filtered through a 0.2-&#x003bc;m pore-size filter. The 100% CSE sample was titrated to a pH of 7.2&#x02013;7.4 and diluted with DMEM/PBS to obtain the required concentration. CSE was freshly prepared for every experiment.</p></sec><sec id="S0002-S2004"><title>Cell Lines and Culture</title><p>HBECs were purchased from the Chinese Academy of Sciences (Shanghai, China) and cultured in DMEM (Hyclone, Logan, UT, USA) supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum and 50 U/mL penicillin and streptomycin (Gibco,Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA) at 37&#x000b0;C in a 5% CO<sub>2</sub> culture chamber. Starvation for 24 h was performed before exposure to CSE, siRNA, and/or lentivirus.</p></sec><sec id="S0002-S2005"><title>Small-Interfering RNA Preparation and Transfection</title><p>HBECs were cultured in a 12-well plate for 24 h to 40&#x02013;60% confluence in complete medium without antibiotics. Then, non-targeting negative control siRNA or HBO1 siRNA (RiboBio, Guangzhou, China) were transfected at 50 nM for 48&#x000a0;hours following the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions.</p></sec><sec id="S0002-S2006"><title>Lentivirus HBO1 Preparation and Transfection</title><p>HBO1 and the vector lentivirus were transfected into HBECs following the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. Lentivirus was transfected into the HBECs at a multiplicity of infection of 10. Cells positive for green fluorescent protein were considered infected.</p></sec><sec id="S0002-S2007"><title>Isolation of RNA and Real-Time Polymerase Chain Reaction (PCR)</title><p>The total RNA was isolated from HBECs using TRIzol reagent (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA) and then treated with DNase I (Invitrogen) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. Total RNA was then reverse-transcribed using the RevertAid First Strand cDNA Synthesis Kit (Thermo Fisher Scientific). Subsequently, real-time PCR was performed using a StepOne Plus real-time PCR system (Life Technologies, Carlsbad, CA, USA). Glyceraldehyde 3-phosphate dehydrogenase (GAPDH) was used as an internal control. The sequences of all primers used were:</p><p>HBO1-F: 5&#x02032;-AAAAGTTGGCTCCCCAGAAC-3&#x02032;</p><p>HBO1-R: 5&#x02032;-GCCGTCTCCTGACTGATTTC-3&#x02032;</p><p>GAPDH-F: 5&#x02032;-TCAAGAAGGTGGTGAAGCAG-3&#x02032;</p><p>GAPDH-R: 5&#x02032;-CGTCAAAGGTGGAGGAGTG-3&#x02032;</p></sec><sec id="S0002-S2008"><title>Western Blot Analysis</title><p>The total isolated soluble proteins were measured using bicinchoninic acid assay kits, separated by polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis, transferred onto polyvinylidene fluoride membranes, then incubated with antibodies to HBO1 (ab190908, Abcam, Cambridge, UK), BCL-2 (ab196495, Abcam), and H3K14ac (#7627s, Cell Signaling Technology, Danvers, MA, USA). After washing, membranes were incubated with goat anti-mouse and goat anti-rabbit IgG horseradish peroxidase-conjugated secondary antibodies (Proteintech Group, Inc., Rosemont, IL, USA). The bound complexes were detected using enhanced chemiluminescence (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Dallas, TX, USA). The data were normalized to &#x003b2;-actin or H3 levels.</p></sec><sec id="S0002-S2009"><title>Lung Tissue Morphometry</title><p>Lung tissue samples were fixed in 4% formaldehyde, cut into 3.5-mm-thick sections, and stained with hematoxylin and eosin (HE). Morphometry was quantified by the values of mean linear intercept (MLI) and destructive index (DI) at a magnification of 100&#x000d7; as previously described.<xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></p></sec><sec id="S0002-S2010"><title>Lung Immunohistochemistry (IHC)</title><p>Sections were incubated with anti-HBO1 (ab190908, Abcam) to detect HBO1 expression. Scoring was performed according to the method of Chiappara et al<xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref> with slight modification. The results were blindly evaluated by two investigators. HBO1 expression was classified according to the staining intensity: no staining (0), weak staining (1), moderate staining (2), or strong staining (3). The staining areas were scored as 0 (0%), 1 (1&#x02013;10%), 2 (11&#x02013;50%), and 3 (51&#x02013;100%). The staining index was calculated as the product of the proportion of positive cells and the staining intensity score. High-power fields of bronchial tissues were randomly sampled, and calculations were performed on five images per section. The average score of five images from each tissue section was used for statistical analyses.</p></sec><sec id="S0002-S2011"><title>TUNEL Analysis</title><p>Terminal deoxynucleotidyl transferase-mediated dUTP nick end labeling (TUNEL) assays were performed with an in situ Apoptosis Detection Kit (Hoffman-La Roche Ltd., Basel, Switzerland). We randomly selected 5/9 areas to measure the apoptotic index (AI). Fields containing non-parenchymal structures such as large airways or vessels were excluded.</p></sec><sec id="S0002-S2012"><title>Flow Cytometry (FCM) Analysis</title><p>HBECs were harvested from 6-well plates and washed with PBS twice, centrifuged (800 rpm, 5 min), then mixed with 500 &#x000b5;L binding buffer. After resuspension, 10 &#x000b5;L propidium iodide (PI) and Annexin V-fluorescein isothiocyanate (FITC) were added, following the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions (KGA108, KeyGen, Nanjing, China). Finally, the HBECs were examined with the flow cytometer (A00-1-1102, Beckman, USA).</p></sec><sec id="S0002-S2013"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>The data are presented as mean &#x000b1; SEM. Statistical significance was calculated using one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) or Kruskal&#x02013;Wallis tests.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S0003"><title>Results</title><sec id="S0003-S2001"><title>HBO1 Protein Decreased Significantly in COPD Airway Epithelium</title><p>The study subjects&#x02019; baseline characteristics are presented in <xref rid="T0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. Age, FEV1<sub>pred</sub>, and FEV1/FVC did not differ between groups. The numbers of pack-years between smoking groups were not significantly different. The values of FEV1<sub>pred</sub> and FEV1/FVC in the smokers with COPD group was significantly decreased compared to the nonsmokers and smokers without COPD groups.</p><p>HE staining was performed to detect the degree of emphysema in peripheral lung tissue specimens. The results showed that the degree of emphysema in smokers with and without COPD was much more severe than in nonsmokers (<xref rid="F0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1A</xref>). By Western blot, HBO1 protein levels were significantly downregulated in smokers with and without COPD compared to nonsmokers (<xref rid="F0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1D</xref> and <xref rid="F0001" ref-type="fig">E</xref>). Next, IHC analysis demonstrated that HBO1 was distributed in the airway epithelium, and its abundance was significantly downregulated in smokers compared with nonsmokers. (<xref rid="F0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1B</xref> and <xref rid="F0001" ref-type="fig">C</xref>). These results indicated that HBO1 protein levels were significantly decreased in the airway epithelium of COPD patients.<fig id="F0001" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>HBO1 expression in peripheral lung tissue. (<bold>A</bold>) HE staining of peripheral lung tissue. (<bold>B</bold>) IHC staining of HBO1 in peripheral lung tissue. (<bold>C</bold>) The mean IOD of HBO1 in the airway epithelium. (<bold>D</bold> and <bold>E</bold>) The levels of total HBO1 and H3K14ac protein in specimens were measured by Western blot. P-values were calculated by analysis of variance (ANOVA). *<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05.</p><p><bold>Abbreviation:</bold> HBO1, histone acetyltransferase binding to ORC1.</p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="COPD-15-15-g0001"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="S0003-S2002"><title>HBO1 Attenuates Cell Apoptosis and Emphysema in the Mouse Model</title><p>In mice exposed to CSE, HBO1 protein levels detected by Western blot and IHC were significantly decreased (<xref rid="F0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2A</xref> and <xref rid="F0002" ref-type="fig">B</xref>). The MLI and DI values were significantly increased in the CSE group compared with the control group, and the values were decreased in Lenti-HBO1 groups compared with Lenti-NC groups (<xref rid="F0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2C</xref>). Furthermore, HBO1 protein levels negatively correlated with the MLI and DI (<xref rid="F0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2D</xref>). We performed TUNEL assays to clarify whether decreased HBO1 was associated with apoptosis in the CSE-exposed mouse model. The results showed significantly fewer TUNEL-positive cells in the control and Lenti-HBO1 groups compared to the CSE and Lenti-NC groups, respectively (<xref rid="F0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3A</xref> and <xref rid="F0003" ref-type="fig">B</xref>). These results indicate that HBO1 could attenuate CSE-induced cell apoptosis and emphysema in mouse models.<fig id="F0002" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>HBO1 expression in mice. (<bold>A</bold>) IHC staining of HBO1 in lung tissues of mice in each group. Control: mice exposed to PBS. CSE: mice exposed to CSE. CSE+Lenti-NC: mice exposed to CSE and negative control virus. CSE+Lenti-HBO1: mice exposed to CSE and HBO1 virus. (<bold>B</bold>) The levels of total HBO1 and H3K14ac protein in specimens were measured by Western blot. (<bold>C</bold>) Morphometric measurements of MLI (&#x003bc;m) and DI (%) were performed in each group. (<bold>D</bold>) Correlation analysis of MLI and DI with HBO1 expression in mice. Results are expressed as mean&#x000b1;SD. *<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05.</p><p><bold>Abbreviations:</bold> CSE, cigarette smoke extract; DI, destructive index; HBO1, histone acetyltransferase binding to ORC1; MLI, mean linear intercept.</p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="COPD-15-15-g0002"/></fig><fig id="F0003" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>TUNEL staining in lung tissue of mice. (<bold>A</bold>) Green cells are TUNEL-positive. (<bold>B</bold>) Statistical analysis of the AI in different groups. Results are expressed as mean&#x000b1;SD. *<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05.</p><p><bold>Abbreviations:</bold> AI, apoptosis index; TUNEL, terminal deoxynucleotidyl transferase dUTP nick end labeling.</p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="COPD-15-15-g0003"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="S0003-S2003"><title>HBO1 Prevents CSE-Induced Apoptosis in HBECs</title><p>We sought to determine whether HBO1 could prevent the apoptosis of HBECs exposed to CSE. FCM analysis with Annexin V-FITC/PI staining showed HBEC apoptosis was significantly upregulated in the CSE and Si-HBO1 groups when compared with the control and Si-vector groups, respectively. HBO1 overexpression in the Lenti-HBO1 group reduced the apoptosis of HBECs exposed to CSE compared with the Lenti-NC group (<xref rid="F0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>). These results illustrate that HBO1 can prevent CSE-induced apoptosis in HBECs.<fig id="F0004" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Apoptosis of HBECs exposed to CSE/siRNA/virus. (<bold>A</bold>) Apoptosis analysis using Annexin V-FITC/PI staining and FCM. Control: HBECs exposed to DMEM. CSE: HBECs exposed to CSE (5% CSE at 24 h). Si-vector: HBECs exposed to non-targeting negative control siRNA. Si-HBO1: HBECs exposed to siHBO1. Lenti-NC: HBECs exposed to negative control lentivirus and CSE (5% CSE at 24 h). Lenti-HBO1: HBECs exposed to HBO1 lentivirus and CSE (5% CSE at 24 h). (<bold>B</bold>) Apoptosis index of HBECs in the different groups. Results are expressed as mean&#x000b1;SD. *<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05.</p><p><bold>Abbreviations:</bold> CSE, cigarette smoke extract; HBECs, human bronchial epithelial cells; HBO1, histone acetyltransferase binding to ORC1.</p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="COPD-15-15-g0004"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="S0003-S2004"><title>CSE Decreases HBO1 Protein Expression in HBECs</title><p>Next, we sought to elucidate the possible mechanism by HBO1 prevents CSE-induced apoptosis in HBECs. We detected HBO1 expression in HBECs exposed to CSE. Dose- and time-dependence were observed for HBEC expression of HBO1 protein (<xref rid="F0005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5A</xref> and <xref rid="F0005" ref-type="fig">B</xref>). However, mRNA levels did not differ in HBECs exposed to different concentrations of CSE (<xref rid="F0005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5C</xref>). These results indicate that CSE decreases HBO1 protein levels but not mRNA levels.<fig id="F0005" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Effect of HBO1 expression in HBECs exposed to CSE. (<bold>A</bold>) HBO1 protein levels in HBECs were measured by Western blot. (<bold>B</bold>) Densitometry was performed to measure HBO1 protein levels, which were normalized to &#x003b2;-actin levels. (<bold>C</bold>) HBO1 mRNA levels in HBECs exposed to CSE for 24 h were measured by real-time PCR. Results are expressed as mean&#x000b1;SD. *<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05 compared with the control group.</p><p><bold>Abbreviations:</bold> CSE, cigarette smoke extract; HBECs, human bronchial epithelial cells; HBO1, histone acetyltransferase binding to ORC1.</p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="COPD-15-15-g0005"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="S0003-S2005"><title>HBO1 Is Required for H3K14 Acetylation</title><p>To detect the possible mechanism by which HBO1 prevents CSE-induced apoptosis in HBECs, we measured the expression of H3K14ac in lung specimens and HBECs. H3K14ac protein was significantly decreased in the human specimens (<xref rid="F0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1D</xref>), lung tissues of mice (<xref rid="F0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2B</xref>), and HBECs (<xref rid="F0006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>). The protein levels of BCL-2 and H3K14ac were significantly decreased in the Si-HBO1 group compared with the Si-vector group. HBO1 overexpression in the Lenti-HBO1 group led to upregulated H3K14ac and BCL-2 protein levels (<xref rid="F0006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>). These results indicate that HBO1 is required for H3K14 acetylation and BCL-2 protein expression in HBECs exposed to CSE.<fig id="F0006" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>The protein levels of HBO1, H3K14ac, and BCL-2. (<bold>A</bold> and <bold>B</bold>) The protein levels of HBO1, BCL-2, and H3K14ac in HBECs were measured by Western blot. (<bold>C</bold> and <bold>D</bold>) The relative expressions of HBO1, BCL-2, and H3K14ac in HBECs. Results are expressed as mean&#x000b1;SD. *<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05 compared with the control group. <sup>#</sup><italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05 compared with the Si-vector group. <sup>&#x00394;</sup><italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05 compared with the CSE+Lenti-NC group.</p><p><bold>Abbreviations:</bold> BCL-2, B-cell lymphoma-2; CSE, cigarette smoke extract; HBECs, human bronchial epithelial cells; HBO1, histone acetyltransferase binding to ORC1.</p></caption><graphic content-type="print-only" xlink:href="COPD-15-15-g0006"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="S0004"><title>Discussion</title><p>Our results showed that HBO1 protein levels were significantly downregulated in the airway epithelium of patients with COPD, and HBO1 overexpression can attenuate CSE-induced cell apoptosis and emphysema in mice. In vitro, HBO1 can prevent the apoptosis of CSE-exposed HBECs. Moreover, HBO1 is required for H3K14 acetylation and BCL-2 protein expression. These findings illustrate that HBO1 is required for H3K14 acetylation and the survival of HBECs exposed to CSE.</p><p>Histone acetylation has been well documented in the pathogenesis of COPD.<xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref> The levels of H4 acetylation in smokers and H3 acetylation in ex-smokers were significantly increased compared with nonsmokers.<xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref> Significant decreases in HDAC activity and protein levels, attributed to histone hyperacetylation, were also reported in COPD.<xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref> The hyperacetylation of histones is associated with pro-inflammatory cytokine expression, which is an important mechanism for the chronic inflammation in COPD. An imbalance of HATs and HDACs may affect the acetylation status of H3/H4. However, HAT activity was not significantly different in patients with or without COPD.<xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></p><p>HBO1 protein levels in CSE-exposed HBECs were significantly decreased, but mRNA levels were not significantly different. It seems that the effect of CSE on HBO1 expression is at the level of its stability, rather than its transcription. As a possible mechanism, HBO1 is phosphorylated by MeK1 and then targeted by the ubiquitin E3 ligase subunit FBXW15 for recognition, site-specific ubiquitination, and degradation.<xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></p><p>HBO1 is a member of the HAT family and exerts acetyltransferase activity towards H3 and H4 chromatin substrates by forming HBO1 complexes, including ING4/5, and scaffold proteins (JADE or BRPF).<xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref> In our study, HBO1 was required for H3K14 acetylation in vivo and in vitro. The acetylation of H3K14 is associated with multiple physiological processes including cell proliferation,<xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref> embryonic development,<xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> and fetal liver erythropoiesis.<xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref> The H3 and H4 lysine residues acetylated by HBO1 were determined by the scaffold proteins, including JADE1/2/3 and BRPF1/2/3, but how HBO1 complexes modulate the acetylation of lysine 14 of H3 is still unknown.</p><p>Apoptosis of epithelial and endothelial cells is one of the most important mechanisms in COPD development.<xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref> We observed a clear effect of HBO1 on the regulation of apoptosis in CSE-exposed HBECs, which may be a reasonable explanation for the role of HBO1 in COPD development. Kueh and colleagues demonstrated that the development of HBO1-deficient embryos was arrested at the 10-somite stage.<xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> The decrease in HBO1 or H3K14ac protein levels could be a useful biomarker of CSE-induced apoptosis in HBECs.</p><p>HBO1 is involved in multiple molecular processes including DNA replication origin binding and DNA-binding transcriptional factor activity.<xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref> HBO1 acetylates both H3 and H4, which is important in DNA replication licensing and the completion of DNA replication. HBO1 interacts with Cdt1, associating MCM2-7 with chromatin to trigger DNA replication during the G1 phase; in the S phase, DNA replication is terminated by Cdt1 degradation and geminin recruitment.<xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref> Cell cycle arrest in the G1 phase was reported in A549 cells with HBO1 silencing.<xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref> The abnormalities of DNA replication and cell cycle arrest caused by HBO1 degradation may explain the apoptosis of HBECs exposed to CSE. However, the connection between H3K14 acetylation and BCL-2 expression is still unknown, and the precise molecular mechanism requires further research. Understanding the mechanism of HBO1 in modulating CSE-exposed HBEC apoptosis will help clarify the pathogenesis of COPD.</p><p>Although HBO1 plays a critical role in the pathogenesis of COPD, especially in airway epithelial cell apoptosis, the specific molecular mechanism of HBO1 on regulating histone acetylation and apoptosis needs to be further explored.</p></sec><sec id="S0005"><title>Conclusions</title><p>In summary, HBO1 protein levels were downregulated significantly in the airway epithelium of patients with COPD. HBO1 can attenuate CSE-induced cell apoptosis and emphysema in mice. In vitro, HBO1 can prevent the apoptosis of HBECs exposed to CSE. The results might be related with the level of H3K14 acetylation. These findings demonstrate that HBO1 plays a protective role in COPD pathogenesis, and enhancing its expression may be a new therapy to prevent COPD.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>The authors would like to thank all the participants involved in this study.</p></ack><sec id="S0006"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>All authors contributed to data analysis, drafting and revising the article, gave final approval of the version to be published, and agree to be accountable for all aspects of the work.</p></sec><sec id="S0007" sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Disclosure</title><p>The authors declare that there are no competing interests in this work.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="CIT0001"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lozano</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Naghavi</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Foreman</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Global and regional mortality from 235 causes of death for 20 age groups in 1990 and 2010: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2010</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>380</volume>(<issue>9859</issue>):<fpage>2095</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2128</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(12)61728-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23245604</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0002"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Prevalence and risk factors of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease in China (the China Pulmonary Health [CPH] study): a national cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Lancet</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>391</volume>(<issue>10131</issue>):<fpage>1706</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1717</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(18)30841-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29650248</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0003"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Hiemstra</surname>
<given-names>PS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McCray</surname>
<given-names>PB</given-names>
<suffix>Jr</suffix></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bals</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>The innate immune function of airway epithelial cells in inflammatory lung disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Eur Respir J</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1150</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1162</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/09031936.00141514</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25700381</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0004"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Brody</surname>
<given-names>JS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Steiling</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Interaction of cigarette exposure and airway epithelial cell gene expression</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Annu Rev Physiol</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>73</volume>:<fpage>437</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>456</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-physiol-012110-142219</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21090967</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0005"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Shen</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wei</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>DX</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Histone acetylation enzymes coordinate metabolism and gene expression</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Trends Plant Sci</italic></source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>614</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>621</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tplants.2015.07.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26440431</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0006"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Shahbazian</surname>
<given-names>MD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grunstein</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Functions of site-specific histone acetylation and deacetylation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Annu Rev Biochem</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>76</volume>:<fpage>75</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>100</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.biochem.76.052705.162114</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17362198</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0007"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Avvakumov</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lalonde</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Saksouk</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Conserved molecular interactions within the HBO1 acetyltransferase complexes regulate cell proliferation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mol Cell Biol</italic></source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>689</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>703</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/MCB.06455-11</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22144582</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0008"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Tao</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhong</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ding</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Structural and mechanistic insights into regulation of HBO1 histone acetyltransferase activity by BRPF2</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nucleic Acids Res</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>45</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>5707</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5719</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkx142</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28334966</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0009"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Doyon</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cayrou</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ullah</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>ING tumor suppressor proteins are critical regulators of chromatin acetylation required for genome expression and perpetuation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mol Cell</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>51</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>64</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2005.12.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16387653</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0010"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Iizuka</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stillman</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Histone acetyltransferase HBO1 interacts with the ORC1 subunit of the human initiator protein</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Biol Chem</italic></source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>274</volume>(<issue>33</issue>):<fpage>23027</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>23034</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.274.33.23027</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10438470</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0011"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Feng</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vlassis</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Roques</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>BRPF3-HBO1 regulates replication origin activation and histone H3K14 acetylation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">EMBO J</italic></source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>176</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>192</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15252/embj.201591293</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26620551</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0012"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Kueh</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dixon</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Voss</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thomas</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>HBO1 is required for H3K14 acetylation and normal transcriptional activity during embryonic development</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mol Cell Biol</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>31</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>845</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>860</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/MCB.00159-10</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21149574</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0013"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tian</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>High-expression HBO1 predicts poor prognosis in gastric cancer</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Clin Pathol</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>152</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>517</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>526</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ajcp/aqz065</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31247063</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0014"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Li</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhou</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Function of PM2.5 in the pathogenesis of lung cancer and chronic airway inflammatory diseases</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Oncol Lett</italic></source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>7506</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7514</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3892/ol.2018.8355</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29725457</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0015"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Quintela</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sieglaff</surname>
<given-names>DH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gazze</surname>
<given-names>AS</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>HBO1 directs histone H4 specific acetylation, potentiating mechano-transduction pathways and membrane elasticity in ovarian cancer cells</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nanomedicine</italic></source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>254</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>265</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nano.2019.01.017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30759370</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0016"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zhang</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cao</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Intraperitoneal injection of cigarette smoke extract induced emphysema, and injury of cardiac and skeletal muscles in BALB/C mice</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Exp Lung Res</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>18</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>31</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/01902148.2012.745910</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23216006</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0017"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Chiappara</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gjomarkaj</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Virz&#x000ec;</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The role of p21 Waf1/Cip1 in large airway epithelium in smokers with and without COPD</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Biochim Biophys Acta</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>1832</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1473</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1481</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbadis.2013.04.022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23639631</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0018"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Sundar</surname>
<given-names>IK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yao</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rahman</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Oxidative stress and chromatin remodeling in chronic obstructive pulmonary disease and smoking-related diseases</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Antioxid Redox Signal</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>15</issue>):<fpage>1956</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1971</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/ars.2012.4863</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22978694</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0019"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Szulakowski</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Crowther</surname>
<given-names>AJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jim&#x000e9;nez</surname>
<given-names>LA</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The effect of smoking on the transcriptional regulation of lung inflammation in patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Am J Respir Crit Care Med</italic></source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>174</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>41</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>50</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1164/rccm.200505-725OC</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16574938</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0020"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Ito</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ito</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Elliott</surname>
<given-names>WM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Decreased histone deacetylase activity in chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">N Engl J Med</italic></source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>352</volume>(<issue>19</issue>):<fpage>1967</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1976</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa041892</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15888697</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0021"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Zou</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>RM</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>SCF(Fbxw15) mediates histone acetyltransferase binding to origin recognition complex (HBO1) ubiquitin-proteasomal degradation to regulate cell proliferation</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Biol Chem</italic></source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>288</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>6306</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6316</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M112.426882</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23319590</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0022"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mishima</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Miyagi</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Saraya</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>The Hbo1-Brd1/Brpf2 complex is responsible for global acetylation of H3K14 and required for fetal liver erythropoiesis</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Blood</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>118</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>2443</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2453</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1182/blood-2011-01-331892</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21753189</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0023"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Lalonde</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cheng</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>C&#x000f4;t&#x000e9;</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Histone target selection within chromatin: an exemplary case of teamwork</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Genes Dev</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>28</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1029</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1041</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gad.236331.113</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24831698</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0024"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Newman</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Voss</surname>
<given-names>AK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thomas</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Allan</surname>
<given-names>RS</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Essential role for the histone acetyltransferase KAT7 in T cell development, fitness, and survival</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">J Leukoc Biol</italic></source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>101</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>887</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>892</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1189/jlb.1MA0816-338R</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27733580</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0025"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Mishima</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Miyagi</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al. <article-title>Histone acetylation mediated by Brd1 is crucial for Cd8 gene activation during early thymocyte development</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Nat Commun</italic></source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>5872</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms6872</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25519988</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0026"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Yoshida</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tuder</surname>
<given-names>RM</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Pathobiology of cigarette smoke-induced chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Physiol Rev</italic></source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>87</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>1047</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1082</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/physrev.00048.2006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17615396</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0027"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Miotto</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Struhl</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>JNK1 phosphorylation of Cdt1 inhibits recruitment of HBO1 histone acetylase and blocks replication licensing in response to stress</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Mol Cell</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>44</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>62</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>71</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2011.06.021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21856198</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0028"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><string-name><surname>Gaudet</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Livstone</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lewis</surname>
<given-names>SE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Thomas</surname>
<given-names>PD</given-names></string-name>. <article-title>Phylogenetic-based propagation of functional annotations within the gene ontology consortium</article-title>. <source><italic toggle="yes">Brief Bioinform</italic></source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>449</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>462</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bib/bbr042</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21873635</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>