<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="editorial"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31924808</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6954192</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">56278</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-56278-1</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Editorial</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Guest Edited Collection: Radioisotopes and radiochemistry in health science</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Fassbender</surname><given-names>Michael E.</given-names></name><address><email>mifa@lanl.gov</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0428 3079</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.148313.c</institution-id><institution>Chemistry Division, Los Alamos National Laboratory, </institution></institution-wrap>Los Alamos, NM 87545 United States </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>10</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>340</elocation-id><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1" abstract-type="Standfirst"><p id="Par1">Radioisotopes can be produced artificially from stable nuclei through the interaction with particles or highly energetic photons. In combination with modern detection and counting techniques, radioisotopes and radiochemical methods uniquely contribute to the health sciences. This Collection showcases salient aspects of medical radioisotope science ranging from the production, recovery and purification of radioisotopes to the methods used to attach them to biomolecules. The Collection also presents studies that highlight the importance of radiochemistry in the assessment of environmental radioactivity.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Nuclear chemistry</kwd><kwd>Analytical chemistry</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">The discovery of radioactivity dates back to the year 1896, when Antoine Henri Becquerel, now the eponym of the SI unit to quantify radioactive decay rate, first described the phenomenon of a mysterious penetrating radiation originating from uranium salt<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. This radiation was able to produce an image on a photographic plate. Radioactivity is a process where an unstable nucleus undergoes conversion to a different -energetically more favorable- nucleus, accompanied by the release of energy in the form of particles and photons.</p><p id="Par3">The relationship between radioactivity and human health perception has been a bumpy ride. The radioactive element radium (<sup>226</sup>Ra half-life 1600 y) that was discovered in the year 1898<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup> by Polish-French radiochemist Marie Sklodowska-Curie, the graduate student of Becquerel who would later earn herself the honour of becoming the first female Nobel prize laureate, was initially regarded as a harmless, even health-boosting natural agent. A few milligrams of radium chloride <sup>226</sup>RaCl<sub>2</sub> could be recovered from one metric ton of uranium ore<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup> through tedious radiochemical efforts. Grossly underestimating the hazards, radium was made a component of self-luminous paints<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>; it was also the subject of flourishing radioactive quackery<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par4">A later discovery, for which German radiochemist Otto Hahn received the Nobel Prize in the year 1944, ushered civilization into the &#x0201c;nuclear age&#x0201d;. Hahn &#x02013;initially unknowingly- provided the radiochemical proof of barium as a product of neutron bombardment of uranium<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>, which signalled the existence of a thitherto-unknown phenomenon: nuclear fission. Nuclear fission could be harnessed as a source of energy, but the wide range of unstable fission products associate it with quasi everlasting environmental impact -highly geochemically mobile<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>
<sup>99</sup>Tc (half-life 2.1&#x000b7;10<sup>5</sup>&#x02009;y) to mention here- and dangerous levels of radioactivity.</p><p id="Par5">Decades later there was the &#x0201c;Chernobyl disaster&#x0201d;<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>. Still a high schooler in Cold-War era West Germany, I vividly recall the news streaming in that stoked the populace&#x02019;s fears of radioactivity like no other event before. And the event on April 26<sup>th</sup>, 1986, made us Europeans think twice about what produce to eat and to better ask where it came from. Children were barred from entering playgrounds; the time span &#x0201c;eight days&#x0201d;, the half-life of volatile fission product <sup>131</sup>I, kept circulating in people&#x02019;s heads. The &#x0201c;Chernobyl&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;Fukushima&#x0201d;<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup> disasters are certainly entries in the history annals of nuclear science and technology that bear witness to the blight of radioactivity.</p><p id="Par6">The blessings of radioactivity, on the other hand, became apparent from the work of another radiochemist and Nobel Prize laureate, George de Hevesy. Hevesy pioneered the concept of radioactive tracers to study biological processes <italic>in vivo</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>, and he is widely regarded as the &#x0201c;father of modern nuclear medicine&#x0201d;<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. Other sources<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup> name the Donner Laboratory at the University of California, Berkley, the &#x0201c;birthplace of nuclear medicine&#x0201d; and rather ascribe nuclear fatherhood to John Lawrence. The discovery of several well-known medical isotopes was claimed by the Donner Laboratory, including <sup>14</sup>C, <sup>18</sup>F, <sup>15</sup>O and <sup>201</sup>Tl. Also among them was &#x0201c;an isotope with a half-life of about one week&#x0201d;<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>, as personally requested by Joseph G. Hamilton from Glenn T. Seaborg (1951 Chemistry Nobelist) for use in certain thyroid studies. Iodine-131 (half-life 8.0 d) was Seaborg&#x02019;s legendary answer to his request, produced at Berkeley via deuteron irradiation of tellurium. The first use of <sup>131</sup>I to treat hypothyroidism in humans was reported by Saul Hertz on January 1<sup>st</sup>, 1941<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>, and a series of treatment studies was published in May 1946<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. Ironically, the later &#x0201c;Chernobyl scare&#x0201d; <sup>131</sup>I had become the first U.S. Food and Drug Administration approved radiopharmaceutical in 1951<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>. Seaborg &#x02013;along with Emilio Segr&#x000e9; - also isolated metastable <sup>99m</sup>Tc (half-life 6.0&#x02009;h) for the first time<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. This isotope has become an invaluable tool for single photon computer tomography (SPECT). The last radioisotopes to mention in my almost chiastic introductory narrative are alpha emitters <sup>223</sup>Ra and <sup>224</sup>Ra<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup> (half-lives 11.4 d and 3.7 d), thereby taking the reader&#x02019;s attention back to the element that Madame Curie discovered. One of them, <sup>223</sup>Ra, has recently become a U.S. FDA approved pharmaceutical for the treatment of bone metastases.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Collection Overview</title><p id="Par7">As the &#x02018;Radioisotopes and radiochemistry in health science&#x02019; Collection launches, applications of short-lived positron emitter fluorine-18 (half-life 109.8&#x02009;min) naturally find the strongest representation. Certainly due to fluorine&#x02019;s ability to rapidly form extremely stable F-C bonds via nucleophilic or electrophilic fluorination of organic molecules, <sup>18</sup>F is undisputedly the most widely used positron emission tomography (PET) labelling agent. Advances in <sup>18</sup>F labelling chemistry also shed light on the more fundamental chemistry of this most reactive halogen. For instance, a new route to [<sup>18</sup>F]fluoroform has been demonstrated<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>, where the trifluoromethyl synthon is formed in the gas phase by passing [<sup>18</sup>F]fluoromethane over heated CoF<sub>3</sub>, one of the few binary phases that release elemental fluorine (F<sub>2</sub>) upon heating. The introduction of new <sup>18</sup>F-labelled triazolyl-linked argininamides to target neuropeptides for the imaging of mammary carcinoma<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup> serves as an apt example of click chemistry-based <sup>18</sup>F-labelling, and a Design of Experiments (DoE) approach has been reported to optimize copper-mediated radiofluorination<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. The evaluation of new <sup>18</sup>F-labelled melanoma xenograft targeting peptides is the subject of an imaging study<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup> that is also published as part of this Collection.</p><p id="Par8">While the lightest halogen has become the workhorse of PET imaging, the heaviest (natural) halogen, astatine, has been advancing as a therapy agent. This Collection includes reports on optimized <sup>209</sup>Bi(&#x003b1;,2n) cyclotron production and recovery of targeted alpha therapy (TAT) isotope <sup>211</sup>At (7.2&#x02009;h)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup> and an investigation into astatine&#x02019;s solvent extraction behaviour<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. Radioiodine still plays an important role; beyond historic <sup>131</sup>I, other iodine isotopes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup> are now utilized for SPECT imaging (<sup>123</sup>I, 13.3&#x02009;h) and treatment (Auger emitter <sup>125</sup>I, 59.4 d).</p><p id="Par9">Radiometals have their deserved place in the toolbox of nuclear medicine: cobalt (<sup>57</sup>Co, 271.8 d; as a surrogate for <sup>55</sup>Co, 17.5&#x02009;h) and indium (<sup>111</sup>In, 2.8 d) were used as labels for affibody monomers targeting tumours in BxPC-3 xenografted mice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. A further contribution broaches the application of nanospheres labelled with <sup>89</sup>Zr (78.4&#x02009;h)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>, a positron emitter with a half-life roughly matching the <italic>in vivo</italic> circulation of antibodies.</p><p id="Par10">Lanthanides are represented, as many of their easily accessible chemically similar -and thus interchangeable- radioisotopes constitute versatile agents for diagnostics and therapy. The purification of SPECT isotope <sup>155</sup>Tb (5.3 d) is featured<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>, and a method for the production and recovery of the theranostic pair <sup>132,135</sup>La (4.8&#x02009;h and 19.5&#x02009;h) with initial imaging and biodistribution evaluation is reported<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. Alpha emitter <sup>225</sup>Ac (10.0 d) has emerged as a TAT isotope: one contribution looks into the <italic>in-vivo</italic> redistribution of <sup>225</sup>Ac daughter isotopes in a mouse model<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>; another study reports the purification of accelerator produced <sup>225</sup>Ac using a silicotitanate sorbent<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par11">Surveys into the distribution and detection of naturally occurring radioactivity are an important part of the Collection as well, as they demonstrate how radioisotope science helps assess radiation doses from natural radioactivity; the &#x0201c;isodose&#x0201d; concept to Swedish residential buildings was applied to optimize topsoil removal concepts<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par12">As the Collection is still open for submissions on a rolling basis, this is only the beginning! May the interested colleague find in this &#x0201c;living&#x0201d; Collection a one-stop overview of the current research that puts radioactivity and radiochemistry to work for the sake of human health.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s note</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>I would like to extend my thanks to all colleagues for submitting their cutting edge contributions. My gratitude is also due to all peer reviewers who donated a share of their valuable time to assess and help improve these contributions, and to Nature Research as well as the staff editors of <italic>Scientific Reports</italic> for their kind invitation to propose and lead this Collection.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>M.E.F. wrote the invited editorial.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par13">The author declares no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Becquerel</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sur les radiations invisibles &#x000e9;mises par les sels d&#x02019;uranium</article-title><source>C R Acad Sci Paris</source><year>1896</year><volume>122</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>420</fpage><lpage>421</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Curie, P., Curie, M., B&#x000e9;mont, G. Sur une nouvelle substance fortement radio-active, contenue dans la pechblende. <italic>C R Acad Sci Paris</italic><bold>127</bold>, 1215&#x02013;1217, (1898). (note of 26 December 1898).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>Fernando P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Marie Curie and the Discovery of Radium</article-title><source>The New Uranium Mining Boom</source><year>2011</year><publisher-loc>Berlin, Heidelberg</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer Berlin Heidelberg</publisher-name><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>13</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pratt</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Review of radium hazards and regulation of radium in industry</article-title><source>Environment International</source><year>1993</year><volume>19</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>475</fpage><lpage>489</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0160-4120(93)90273-K</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Macklis</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Great Radium Scandal</article-title><source>Sci Am</source><year>1993</year><volume>269</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>94</fpage><lpage>99</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/scientificamerican0893-94</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8351514</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hahn</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Strassmann</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ueber den Nachweis und das Verhalten der bei der Bestrahlung des Urans mittels Neutronen entstehenden Erdalkalimetalle</article-title><source>Naturwiss</source><year>1939</year><volume>27</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF01488241</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Impeding <sup>99</sup>Tc(IV) mobility in novel waste forms</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2016</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>12067</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms12067</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27357121</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Smith, J. T., Beresford, N. A. Chernobyl-Catastrophe and Consequences. Springer-Verlag Berlin Heidelberg New York. ISBN 3-540-23866-2 (2005).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grech</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Chernobyl Accident, the Male to Female Ratio at Birth and Birth Rates</article-title><source>Acta Medica</source><year>2014</year><volume>57</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>62</fpage><lpage>67</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14712/18059694.2014.41</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25257152</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of the Fukushima nuclear disaster on global public acceptance of nuclear energy</article-title><source>Energy Policy</source><year>2013</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>822</fpage><lpage>828</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.enpol.2013.06.107</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chiewitz</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Hevesy</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Radioactive Indicators in the Study of Phosphorus Metabolism in Rats</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1935</year><volume>136</volume><fpage>754</fpage><lpage>755</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/136754a0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Georg Charles de Hevesy: the father of nuclear medicine</article-title><source>J Nucl Med</source><year>1979</year><volume>20</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>590</fpage><lpage>594</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">395289</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Donner Laboratory: the birthplace of nuclear medicine</article-title><source>J Nucl Med</source><year>1999</year><volume>40</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>16N</fpage><lpage>20N</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9935047</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCready</surname><given-names>VR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Radioiodine &#x02013; the success story of Nuclear Medicine</article-title><source>Eur J Nucl Med Mol Imaging</source><year>2017</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>179</fpage><lpage>182</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00259-016-3548-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27761621</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hertz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Radioactive iodine in the study of thyroid physiology; the use of radioactive iodine therapy in hyperthyroidism</article-title><source>J Am Med Assoc.</source><year>1946</year><volume>131</volume><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.1946.02870190005002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21025609</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stabin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nuclear Medicine dosimetry</article-title><source>Phys Med Biol</source><year>2006</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>R187</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1088/0031-9155/51/13/R12</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16790903</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hoffman, D. C., Ghiorso, A. &#x00026; Seaborg, G. T. The Transuranium People: The Inside Story, https://doi.org/10.1142/p074.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mastren</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Simultaneous Separation of Actinium and Radium Isotopes from a Proton Irradiated Thorium Matrix</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2017</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>8216</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-08506-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28811573</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>BY</given-names></name><name><surname>Gas Phase</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Route to [18F]fluoroform with Limited Molar Activity Dilution</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2019</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>14835</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-50747-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31619702</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maschauer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title><sup>18</sup>F-labelled triazolyl-linked argininamides targeting the neuropeptide Y Y1R for PET imaging of mammary carcinoma</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2019</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>12990</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-49399-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31506520</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bowden</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A Design of Experiments (DoE) Approach Accelerates the Optimization of Copper-Mediated <sup>18</sup>F-Fluorination Reactions of Arylstannanes</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2019</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>11370</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-47846-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31388076</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title><sup>18</sup>F-Labeled Cyclized &#x003b1;-Melanocyte-Stimulating Hormone Derivatives for Imaging Human Melanoma Xenograft with Positron Emission Tomography</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2019</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>13575</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-50014-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31537869</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O&#x02019;Hara</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Development of an autonomous solvent extraction system to isolate astatine-211 from dissolved cyclotron bombarded bismuth targets</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2019</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>20318</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-56272-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31889075</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Investigation of a tellurium-packed column for isolation of astatine-211 from irradiated bismuth targets and demonstration of a semi-automated system</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2019</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>16960</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-53385-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31740701</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aneheim</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Towards elucidating the radiochemistry of astatine &#x02013; Behavior in chloroform</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2019</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>15900</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-52365-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31685874</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Glaser</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>One-Pot Radiosynthesis and Biological Evaluation of a Caspase-3 Selective 5-[123,125I]iodo-1,2,3-triazole derived Isatin SPECT Tracer</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2019</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>19299</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-55992-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31848442</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosestedt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Improved contrast of affibody-mediated imaging of HER3 expression in mouse xenograft model through co-injection of a trivalent affibody for <italic>in vivo</italic> blocking of hepatic uptake</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2019</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>6779</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-43145-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31043683</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Red Blood Cell Membrane Bioengineered Zr-89 Labelled Hollow Mesoporous Silica Nanosphere for Overcoming Phagocytosis</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2019</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>7419</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-43969-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31092899</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Webster</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Chemical Purification of Terbium-155 from Pseudo-Isobaric Impurities in a Mass Separated Source Produced at CERN</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2019</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>10884</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-47463-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31350422</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aluicio-Sarduy</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Production and <italic>in vivo</italic> PET/CT imaging of the theranostic pair <sup>132/135</sup>La</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2019</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>10658</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-47137-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31337833</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Kruijff</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The <italic>in vivo</italic> fate of 225Ac daughter nuclides using polymersomes as a model carrier</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2019</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>11671</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-48298-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31406320</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fitzsimmons</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The application of poorly crystalline silicotitanate in production of <sup>225</sup>Ac</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2019</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>11808</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-48021-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31413268</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hinrichsen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Influence of the migration of radioactive contaminants in soil, resident occupancy, and variability in contamination on isodose lines for typical Northern European houses</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2019</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>7876</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-44392-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31133735</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>