<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Open Access Maced J Med Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Open Access Maced J Med Sci</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Open Access Macedonian Journal of Medical Sciences</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1857-9655</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Republic of Macedonia</publisher-name><publisher-loc>ID Design 2012/DOOEL Skopje</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31949533</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6953951</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">OAMJMS-7-3294</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3889/oamjms.2019.714</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Public Health</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Incentives Motivating Mentors and Criteria for Selecting Mentors in the Pre-Graduation Traineeship of Future Registered Nurses</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dragusheva</surname><given-names>Snezhana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Petleshkova</surname><given-names>Penka</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Panova</surname><given-names>Gordana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Nursing, Faculty of Public Health, Medical University - Plovdiv, Plovdiv, Bulgaria</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Department Obstetrics and Gynaecology, Medical Faculty, Medical University - Plovdiv, Bulgaria</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Faculty of Medical Sciences, University Goce Delchev, Stip, Republic of Macedonia</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label><bold>Correspondence:</bold> Snezhana Dragusheva. Department of Nursing, Faculty of Public Health, Medical University - Plovdiv, Plovdiv, Bulgaria. E-mail: <email xlink:href="sdragusheva68@gmail.com">sdragusheva68@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><day>15</day><month>10</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>11</day><month>9</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>19</issue><fpage>3294</fpage><lpage>3297</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>04</day><month>8</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>21</day><month>8</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>8</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; 2019 Snezhana Dragusheva, Penka Petleshkova, Gordana Panova.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/CC BY-NC/4.0"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License (CC BY-NC 4.0)</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec id="st1"><title>BACKGROUND:</title><p>Modern education in the field of healthcare is faced with the challenge of coping with one of the most important tasks &#x02013; to develop in students a set of competencies which serve as a sound basis for mastering a series of job-specific knowledge, skills and abilities, and which constitute a guarantee for coping successfully with all everyday tasks. The attention of the mentor is focused on finding the most reasonable solution to the various situations that the trainee may find him/herself in, and ensuring emotional comfort.</p></sec><sec id="st2"><title>AIM:</title><p>To identify the grounds and criteria for selecting mentors for the pre-graduation traineeships of the future registered nurses.</p></sec><sec id="st3"><title>METHODS:</title><p>To determine the opinion of the mentors, we surveyed 106 mentors in several university hospitals: &#x02018;St. Georgi&#x02019; University Hospital &#x02013; Plovdiv, MPHAT AD &#x02013; Haskovo, &#x02018;Dr. At. Dafovski&#x02019; University Hospital &#x02013; Kardzhali, University Hospital &#x02013; Stara Zagora.</p></sec><sec id="st4"><title>RESULTS:</title><p>During the pre-graduation traineeship in a real-life environment, students have the opportunity to develop and consolidate a series of skills, competences and qualities which are an integral part of the modern image of the registered nurse. Logically, the mentor should be the leading factor in the pre-graduation traineeship, yet the tutor has organisational and control functions.</p></sec><sec id="st5"><title>CONCLUSION:</title><p>Mentors are expected to ensure patient safety, as well to create suitable working conditions for students.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Mentors</kwd><kwd>Pre-graduation traineeship</kwd><kwd>Trainee-nurses</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-1"><title>Introduction</title><p>The modern world is changing at an unprecedented rate. One of the areas with tangible dynamic transformations in medical education, which has to meet the growing current and future health needs of society. Most urgent among those needs are the processes of demographic ageing which have affected Bulgaria to an alarming extent. Life expectancy is increasing, and so is the proportion of older adults. In this regard, the need for well-trained medical specialists is unquestionable [<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>].</p><p>On the other hand, new technologies have a strong impact on medical education. These new technologies affect every aspect of our lives and cause a fundamental change in the way students communicate, establish and maintain relationships, and study [<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>], [<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>], [<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Lecturers and tutors are expected to make the processes of learning more interesting, challenging and thought-provoking [<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. This applies to both theoretical and practical training of medical specialists.</p><p>Modern education in the field of health care is faced with the challenge of coping with one of the most important tasks &#x02013; the task to develop in students a set of competencies which serve as a sound basis for mastering a series of job-specific knowledge, skills and abilities, and which constitute a guarantee for coping successfully with all everyday tasks. They are of vital importance as they include competencies needed not only for the moment but also for the future. Improving and keeping up the qualifications of registered nurses means striving after improving the quality of their professional work by developing and realising their potential as both personalities and professionals [<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>].</p><p>In this context, the professional competence of registered nurses is a necessary prerequisite for achieving higher quality healthcare and improving the health status of the population.</p><p>During their pre-graduation training, students work independently in the respective hospital ward without the presence of a tutor. Therefore, the traineeship has to be very well organised and controlled by the mentor, who should strictly and closely monitor, support and assess the independent work of the trainees.</p><p>The attention of the mentor is focused on finding sensible and efficient solutions to various situations the trainee may find him/herself in, as well as on ensuring emotional comfort.</p><p>According to the Dictionary of the Bulgarian Language, a mentor is a person who &#x0201c;tutors and monitors someone, and gives them advice &#x0201e;&#x0041b;&#x00438;&#x00446;&#x00435;, and synonyms of &#x02018;mentor&#x02019; are &#x02018;teacher&#x02019;, &#x02018;educator&#x02019;, &#x02018;guide&#x02019; (Dictionary of the Bulgarian Language, 2004). In a broad sense, the mentor is a qualified specialist with sufficient experience in his / her work. The idea of mentorship is widely popular in vocational training in Western Europe, Russia and the USA.</p><p>Mentorship is a valuable and popular vocational training method. It is one of the oldest forms of mastering professional skills and enables the trainee to have confidence in his / her skills, to develop the qualities and competencies needed for their future or current profession [<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>].</p><p>Mentorship is a mechanism of sharing experience between two parties, one of whom has a higher status based on knowledge and skills in a certain area. The knowledgeable, competent, capable, established specialists pass on the professional and personal knowledge and skills they have acquired to the newcomers to the profession.</p><p>Bulgarian medical education also has traditions in the field of mentorship. Mentors are registered nurses with a Bachelor&#x02019;s or Master&#x02019;s degree in Healthcare Management, working in university hospitals and clinics. They have the required pedagogical training acquired in the respective courses and degrees, and they have also mastered the specific knowledge and skills needed in the process of training [<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. These changes have brought forward mentors alongside tutors.</p><p>The international nursing standard defines 8 competences distinguishing the responsibilities of mentors: 1. Mentors are expected to facilitate the progress of the students towards achieving results; 2. Establish efficient working relationships; 3. Facilitate learning; 4. Assess and evaluate the student learning experience; 5. Create a suitable environment for learning; 6. Apply theory into practice, implement scientifically proven practices; 7. Assist in the identification and achievement of the learning objectives of the students; and 8. Participation in the formation of an overall evaluation of the students trained in the conditions of clinical practises guaranteeing the mastering of clinical competences [<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].</p><p>In the training of Healthcare students, in addition to the necessary qualification and practical experience of the mentor, the latter&#x02019;s personal qualities and teaching skills also play a very important role.</p><p>S. Toncheva points out that &#x0201c;the mentor has to be included in the continuous training and improvement system of the healthcare establishment where the mentor works, to keep up his / her professional qualifications up-to-date and to develop his/her personal and professional competences&#x0201d; [<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>].</p><p>Objective: To identify and establish grounds and criteria for the selection of mentors during the pre-graduation traineeship of future registered nurses.</p></sec><sec sec-type="material|methods" id="sec1-2"><title>Material and Methods</title><p>To determine the opinion of the mentors, we surveyed 106 mentors in several university hospitals: &#x02018;St. Georgi&#x02019; University Hospital &#x02013; Plovdiv, MPHAT AD &#x02013; Haskovo, &#x02018;Dr. At. Dafovski&#x02019; University Hospital &#x02013; Kardzhali, University Hospital &#x02013; Stara Zagora.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec1-3"><title>Results</title><p>The average age of the surveyed mentors is 41.88 &#x000b1; 1.04 y., and their average work experience is 18.74 &#x000b1; 1.15 y.</p><p>According to their position: 1% are head nurses, 16% are nurse managers, and 83% are ordinary registered nurses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>).</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Distribution of the mentors according to the position held</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="OAMJMS-7-3294-g001"/></fig><p>The distribution of the mentors according to their level of education is as follows: the highest percentage is that of the holders of Specialist&#x02019;s degrees &#x02013; 31.0%, followed by those with Bachelor&#x02019;s degrees &#x02013; 29.0%, with Master&#x02019;s degrees in Healthcare Management-27.0%, and Bachelor&#x02019;s degrees in Healthcare management-13.0% (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>).</p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Distribution of the mentors according to their level of education</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="OAMJMS-7-3294-g002"/></fig><p>It is of note that only 40.0% of the mentors have Bachelor&#x02019;s or Master&#x02019;s degrees in Healthcare Management, and are therefore trained and qualified to conduct the practical training of students based on their pedagogical qualifications and aptitude.</p><p>Over half of the participants in the survey (55%) believe that pre-graduation traineeships have to be conducted under the supervision of a mentor, 16% think these traineeships have to be conducted under the supervision of a tutor, 15%-by both a tutor and a mentor, and 14% cannot decide.</p><p>During the pre-graduation traineeship in a real-life environment, students develop and consolidate a series of skills, competences and qualities which are an integral part of the modern image of the registered nurse. Logically, the mentor should be the leading factor in the pre-graduation traineeship, yet the tutor has organisational and control functions. What is important is that the traineeship has to be very well planned and organised, and this constitutes the managerial role of the tutor in the pre-graduation traineeship process.</p><p>Since the mentor is a central figure in this process, the professional and personal qualities, as well as the incentives of the mentor, are of vital importance. Therefore, we decided to identify the leading incentives for the respondents to become mentors. The analysis of the results shows that for 61.3% of the surveyed, the driving force is the opportunity to pass their personal experience to their future colleagues. Three-point eight percent consider it prestigious to be mentors. Twenty-one-point seven percent believe their work as mentors is a way of personal and professional improvement. Sixteen percent of the find their work as mentors personally rewarding and consider it an opportunity to prove their competences, 19.00 % state other incentives. The opportunity to work with students motivate Three-point eight percent of the surveyed, and the remuneration motivates only 12.4%. The total exceeds 100% because the respondents were allowed multiple answers (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>).</p><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Motivation of the mentors for working as such</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="OAMJMS-7-3294-g003"/></fig><p>It is immediately apparent from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref> that the remuneration is not a driving factor for the majority of the mentors. According to the criterion of the position held, the findings show that head nurses and nurse managers are mainly motivated by the opportunity to pass their experience on to the students A &#x0003c; 0.05 (&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup> = 5.67). The role of a mentor invariably adds to the workload of the registered nurse, so in selecting mentors, their willingness and consent also have to be taken into consideration. This logically raises the question of the remuneration even though in some European country&#x02019;s mentorship is voluntary. Mentorship is considered professional recognition, honour and prestige. In those countries, nurses apply for mentorship, and their selection is based on certain criteria. The successful applicants attend regulated training before commencing their work as mentors.</p><p>Accordingly, the mentors were allowed to outline specific professional requirements that registered nurses conducting students&#x02019; pre-graduation traineeships have to meet. The highest percentage of the mentors (82.10%) believe that a Bachelor&#x02019;s or Master&#x02019;s degree in Healthcare Management should be a prerequisite; 57.50% consider a certain number of years of work experience an important condition; according to 50.90% of the respondents professional competences are of vital importance; 42.55% share the opinion that the position held should be a requirement; however, only 13.44% state that nurse managers are suitable mentors.</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec1-4"><title>Discussion</title><p>The analysis shows that the suggestions for a certain number of years of work experience vary widely. According to 53.00% of the respondents, mentors should have at least 5 years&#x02019; experience, 39.00% believe this period should be 6-10 years, while 8.00% of the surveyed mentors the required work experience should be over 11 years.</p><p>In the responses to this question, the following dependencies were established: in terms of &#x0201c;age&#x0201d;, respondents aged 51+ believe mentors should have over 10 years of work experience, while younger respondents aged &#x0003c; / = 30 believe 5 years of work experience to be sufficient A &#x0003c; 0.05 (F = 3.32). In terms of &#x0201c;position held&#x0201d;, most head nurses and nurse managers believe the level of education should be an important criterion in selecting mentors A &#x0003c; 0.05 (&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup> = 4.37). These results show that in developing criteria for selecting mentors, work experience and level of education should be taken into account.</p><p>The conducted survey among mentors provides grounds for the following conclusions:</p><p>
<list list-type="order"><list-item><p>The main factors motivating mentors to work with trainees include the opportunity to pass their personal experience on to their young future colleagues, personal satisfaction, and the opportunity for self-improvement.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The mentors agree that they should fulfil certain requirements.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Since the mentor is a key figure in pre-graduation traineeships, the following aspects have to be taken into account in developing the selection criteria for mentors: - Work experience; - Level of education of the applicant for a mentor; - A list of mentors should be compiled.</p></list-item></list>
</p><p>In conclusion, the performed analysis explicitly shows that in the students&#x02019; practical training in Healthcare, in addition to the required educational qualifications and work experience of the mentor, his / her personal qualities and teaching skills also play a very important role. Mentors are expected not only to ensure the safety of the patient but also to create suitable working conditions for their trainees.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="supported-by"><p><bold>Funding:</bold> This survey was supported by the National scientific program &#x0201c;Young scientists and post-graduates&#x0201d; of the Medical University of Plovdiv, Bulgaria</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Competing Interests:</bold> The authors have declared that no competing interests exist</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paskaleva</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Current issues and healthcare possibilities for prophylaxis of premature ageing, author's summary of dissertation</article-title><year>2018</year><fpage>6</fpage><lpage>7</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Torniova</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Paskaleva</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Innovative technologies in the training of medical specialists</article-title><source>Management &#x00026;Education magazine</source><year>2015</year><volume>11</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>66</fpage><lpage>71</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paskaleva</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A new-generation educational solution to the benefit of the training of specialists in Healthcare</article-title><source>Varna Medical Forum magazine</source><year>2015</year><volume>4</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>27</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paskaleva</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Possibilities for applying Students Response Systems in the process of training specialists in Healthcare, Collection, Stara Zagora</article-title><year>2016</year><fpage>207</fpage><lpage>211</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><comment><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://uni-sz.bg/wp-content/uploads/truni/file/Med_laborant_spisanie_Dokladi.pdf">http://uni-sz.bg/wp-content/uploads/truni/file/Med_laborant_spisanie_Dokladi.pdf</uri></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Torniova</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Paskaleva</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Didactic means in the training of healthcare specialists in the light of the contemporary educational paradigm</article-title><source>ARTTE</source><year>2014</year><volume>2</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>434</fpage><lpage>440</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Doynovska</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hospital healthcare management</article-title><source>Nursing magazine</source><year>2013</year><issue>2</issue><fpage>42</fpage><lpage>44</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Doynovska</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bacheva</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Velichkova-Hadzhieva</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The expectations of Porfessional strand 7.5 Healthcare students of their mentors during their clinical practice</article-title><source>Management &#x00026;Education magazine</source><year>2019</year><volume>15</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>225</fpage><lpage>229</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Doynovska</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Krasteva</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Antova</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Importance of nursing documentation in the training of patients with chronic pulmonary diseases</article-title><source>Preventive Medicine magazine</source><year>2012</year><issue>2</issue><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>29</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Georgieva</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><source>Project &#x0201c;mENTERing&#x0201d;</source><year>2013</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Toncheva</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><source>author's summary of dissertation for acquiring a Doctoral Degree, Varna</source><year>2018</year></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>