<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Bone Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Bone Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Bone Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2352-1872</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31938717</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6953598</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S2352-1872(20)30001-2</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bonr.2020.100242</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100242</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Generation of an immunodeficient mouse model of tcirg1-deficient autosomal recessive osteopetrosis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0005"><name><surname>Palagano</surname><given-names>Eleonora</given-names></name><xref rid="af0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="af0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="fn0005" ref-type="fn">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0010"><name><surname>Muggeo</surname><given-names>Sharon</given-names></name><xref rid="af0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="af0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="fn0005" ref-type="fn">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0015"><name><surname>Crisafulli</surname><given-names>Laura</given-names></name><xref rid="af0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="af0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0020"><name><surname>Tourkova</surname><given-names>Irina L.</given-names></name><xref rid="af0015" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0025"><name><surname>Strina</surname><given-names>Dario</given-names></name><xref rid="af0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="af0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0030"><name><surname>Mantero</surname><given-names>Stefano</given-names></name><xref rid="af0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="af0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0035"><name><surname>Fontana</surname><given-names>Elena</given-names></name><xref rid="af0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="af0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0040"><name><surname>Locatelli</surname><given-names>Silvia L.</given-names></name><xref rid="af0020" ref-type="aff">d</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0045"><name><surname>Monari</surname><given-names>Marta</given-names></name><xref rid="af0025" ref-type="aff">e</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0050"><name><surname>Morenghi</surname><given-names>Emanuela</given-names></name><xref rid="af0030" ref-type="aff">f</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0055"><name><surname>Carlo-Stella</surname><given-names>Carmelo</given-names></name><xref rid="af0020" ref-type="aff">d</xref><xref rid="af0035" ref-type="aff">g</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0060"><name><surname>Barnett</surname><given-names>John B.</given-names></name><xref rid="af0040" ref-type="aff">h</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0065"><name><surname>Blair</surname><given-names>Harry C.</given-names></name><xref rid="af0015" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0070"><name><surname>Vezzoni</surname><given-names>Paolo</given-names></name><xref rid="af0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="af0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0075"><name><surname>Villa</surname><given-names>Anna</given-names></name><xref rid="af0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="af0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0080"><name><surname>Sobacchi</surname><given-names>Cristina</given-names></name><email>cristina.sobacchi@humanitasresearch.it</email><xref rid="af0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="af0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="cr0005" ref-type="corresp">&#x0204e;</xref><xref rid="fn0010" ref-type="fn">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0085"><name><surname>Ficara</surname><given-names>Francesca</given-names></name><xref rid="af0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="af0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="fn0010" ref-type="fn">2</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="af0005"><label>a</label>CNR-IRGB, Milan Unit, via Fantoli 16/15, 20138 Milan, Italy</aff><aff id="af0010"><label>b</label>Humanitas Clinical and Research Center IRCCS, via Manzoni 56, 20089 Rozzano, MI, Italy</aff><aff id="af0015"><label>c</label>Veteran's Affairs Medical Center and Department of Pathology, University of Pittsburgh, 4200 Fifth Avenue, Pittsburgh, PA 15260, USA</aff><aff id="af0020"><label>d</label>Department of Oncology and Hematology, Humanitas Clinical and Research Center IRCCS, via Manzoni 56, 20089 Rozzano, MI, Italy</aff><aff id="af0025"><label>e</label>Clinical Investigation Laboratory, Humanitas Clinical and Research Center IRCCS, via Manzoni 56, 20089 Rozzano, MI, Italy</aff><aff id="af0030"><label>f</label>Biostatistics Unit, Humanitas University, Rozzano, MI, Italy</aff><aff id="af0035"><label>g</label>Department of Biomedical Sciences, Humanitas University, Rozzano, MI, Italy</aff><aff id="af0040"><label>h</label>Department of Microbiology, Immunology, and Cell Biology, West Virginia University School of Medicine, Morgantown, WV 26505, USA</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cr0005"><label>&#x0204e;</label>Corresponding author at: Humanitas Clinical and Research Center &#x02013; IRCCS, via Manzoni 56, 20089 Rozzano, Italy. <email>cristina.sobacchi@humanitasresearch.it</email></corresp><fn id="fn0005"><label>1</label><p id="np0005">Co-first authorship.</p></fn><fn id="fn0010"><label>2</label><p id="np0010">Co-last authorship.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>07</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>6</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>07</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>12</volume><elocation-id>100242</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>9</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>23</day><month>12</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>4</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2020 Published by Elsevier Inc.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder/><license license-type="CC BY-NC-ND" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="ab0005"><sec><title>Background</title><p>Autosomal recessive osteopetrosis is a rare skeletal disorder with increased bone density due to a failure in osteoclast bone resorption. In most cases, the defect is cell-autonomous, and &#x0003e;50% of patients bear mutations in the <italic>TCIRG1</italic> gene, encoding for a subunit of the vacuolar proton pump essential for osteoclast resorptive activity. The only cure is hematopoietic stem cell transplantation, which corrects the bone pathology by allowing the formation of donor-derived functional osteoclasts. Therapeutic approaches using patient-derived cells corrected <italic>ex vivo</italic> through viral transduction or gene editing can be considered, but to date functional rescue cannot be demonstrated <italic>in vivo</italic> because a relevant animal model for xenotransplant is missing.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>We generated a new mouse model, which we named NSG oc/oc, presenting severe autosomal recessive osteopetrosis owing to the <italic>Tcirg1</italic><sup><italic>oc</italic></sup> mutation, and profound immunodeficiency caused by the NSG background. We performed neonatal murine bone marrow transplantation and xenotransplantation with human CD34<sup>+</sup> cells.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>We demonstrated that neonatal murine bone marrow transplantation rescued NSG oc/oc mice, in line with previous findings in the oc/oc parental strain and with evidence from clinical practice in humans. Importantly, we also demonstrated human cell chimerism in the bone marrow of NSG oc/oc mice transplanted with human CD34<sup>+</sup> cells. The severity and rapid progression of the disease in the mouse model prevented amelioration of the bone pathology; nevertheless, we cannot completely exclude that minor early modifications of the bone tissue might have occurred.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Our work paves the way to generating an improved xenograft model for <italic>in vivo</italic> evaluation of functional rescue of patient-derived corrected cells. Further refinement of the newly generated mouse model will allow capitalizing on it for an optimized exploitation in the path to novel cell therapies.</p></sec></abstract><abstract abstract-type="author-highlights" id="ab0010"><title>Highlights</title><p><list list-type="simple" id="l0005"><list-item id="li0005"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0005"><italic>Ex vivo</italic> corrected autologous HSCs might cure Autosomal Recessive Osteopetrosis (ARO).</p></list-item><list-item id="li0010"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0010">There is no animal model to prove <italic>in vivo</italic> functional rescue of corrected human cells.</p></list-item><list-item id="li0015"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0015">NSG oc/oc mice display osteoclast-rich cell-autonomous ARO and immunodeficiency.</p></list-item><list-item id="li0020"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0020">Human CD34<sup>+</sup> cell-transplanted NSG oc/oc mice show human cell chimerism in the BM.</p></list-item><list-item id="li0025"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0025">Further improvements will allow <italic>in vivo</italic> evaluating corrected patient-derived cells.</p></list-item></list></p></abstract><kwd-group id="ks0005"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Osteopetrosis</kwd><kwd>Mouse model</kwd><kwd>Transplantation</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s0005"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0030">Osteopetrosis is a heterogeneous group of rare skeletal diseases, characterized by an increase in bone density due to defective bone resorption resulting from an alteration in osteoclast formation or function (<xref rid="bb0225" ref-type="bibr">Sobacchi et al., 2013</xref>). The autosomal recessive form (<xref rid="dt0005" ref-type="term">ARO</xref>) is the most severe, affecting children in early life and often leading to death if left untreated. The main clinical features of ARO are high bone density, reduced medullary space leading to pancytopenia, compression of cranial nerves, blindness and/or deafness; in addition, other multi-systemic defects (<italic>e.g.</italic> severe neurological defects) may be present (<xref rid="bb0225" ref-type="bibr">Sobacchi et al., 2013</xref>).</p><p id="p0035">To date, hematopoietic stem cell transplantation (<xref rid="dt0070" ref-type="term">HSCT</xref>) is the only therapy (<xref rid="bb0185" ref-type="bibr">Penna et al., 2019</xref>). The outcome of this procedure is influenced by several factors: the age at the time of transplantation, the presence of secondary defects, the genetic defect and the availability of a compatible <xref rid="dt0065" ref-type="term">HLA</xref> donor. Regarding specifically this latter issue, in the absence of an HLA-matched donor, the probability of a successful transplant is variable and, despite substantial enhancement, HLA-haploidentical transplantation remains a procedure to be undertaken only in experienced centers (<xref rid="bb0020" ref-type="bibr">Bahr et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bb0190" ref-type="bibr">Pronk et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="bb0165" ref-type="bibr">Neven et al., 2019</xref>; <xref rid="bb0240" ref-type="bibr">Stepensky et al., 2019</xref>). In recent years, an increasing number of ARO patients surviving until adulthood without a cure (hence classified as intermediate) have been reported (<xref rid="bb0230" ref-type="bibr">Sobacchi et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="bb0170" ref-type="bibr">Palagano et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="bb0220" ref-type="bibr">Sobacchi et al., 1993</xref>; <xref rid="bb0235" ref-type="bibr">Stattin et al., 2017</xref>). Despite a milder presentation as compared to &#x0201c;classical ARO&#x0201d;, they accumulate debilitating skeletal (and extra-skeletal, as well) complications over time, thus prompting to consider the set-up of personalized therapeutic interventions (<xref rid="bb0240" ref-type="bibr">Stepensky et al., 2019</xref>; <xref rid="bb0160" ref-type="bibr">Neri et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="bb0250" ref-type="bibr">Teti and Econs, 2017</xref>). In particular, transplantation of <italic>ex vivo</italic> corrected autologous HSCs might represent a valid therapeutic option (<xref rid="bb0010" ref-type="bibr">Askmyr et al., 2009a</xref>). In 2007, the feasibility and efficacy of this approach was demonstrated in the oc/oc mouse model (<xref rid="bb0100" ref-type="bibr">Johansson et al., 2007</xref>), bearing a spontaneous homozygous genomic deletion in the <italic>Tcirg1</italic> gene (<xref rid="bb0070" ref-type="bibr">Frattini et al., 2005</xref>; <xref rid="bb0205" ref-type="bibr">Scimeca et al., 2000</xref>), which is also the most frequently mutated gene in ARO patients (<xref rid="bb0175" ref-type="bibr">Palagano et al., 2018</xref>). The <italic>Tcirg1</italic> gene encodes the a3 subunit of the osteoclast ATP-dependent vacuolar proton pump V-ATPase, essential for the acidification of the resorption lacuna and for osteoclast resorptive function (<xref rid="bb0065" ref-type="bibr">Frattini et al., 2000</xref>). Johansson and colleagues demonstrated that neonatal intraperitoneal infusion of oc/oc fetal liver cells transduced with a retroviral vector expressing TCIRG1 and <xref rid="dt0055" ref-type="term">GFP</xref>. This improved the survival of transplanted oc/oc mice, ameliorated their skeletal phenotype at 8&#x000a0;weeks and almost completely normalized it after 18&#x000a0;weeks (<xref rid="bb0100" ref-type="bibr">Johansson et al., 2007</xref>). Based on these encouraging results, lentiviral-mediated correction of the genetic defect in human cells was undertaken; their functional rescue was demonstrated <italic>in vitro</italic> after differentiation in bone-resorbing osteoclasts (<xref rid="bb0145" ref-type="bibr">Moscatelli et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bb0255" ref-type="bibr">Thudium et al., 2016</xref>), while <italic>in vivo</italic> transplant in immunodeficient <xref rid="dt0090" ref-type="term">NSG</xref> mice proved their capacity to engraft (<xref rid="bb0150" ref-type="bibr">Moscatelli et al., 2018</xref>). Overall, these observations further fueled efforts towards the development of gene therapy for ARO. At the same time, the demonstration of <italic>in vivo</italic> functional rescue and amelioration of the disease by gene-corrected human cells could not be provided due to lack of a suitable animal model.</p><p id="p0040">Immunodeficient animal models are largely used in human stem cell research as they can be engrafted with human cells thus allowing the assessment of human stem cell function <italic>in vivo</italic> (<xref rid="bb0125" ref-type="bibr">Manz and Di Santo, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="bb0075" ref-type="bibr">Fujiwara, 2018</xref>). In particular, the non-obese diabetic (NOD) SCID Il2r&#x003b3;<sup>&#x02212;</sup><sup>/</sup><sup>&#x02212;</sup> (NSG) mice lack the adaptive immune response due to the defect in the <italic>Prkdc</italic> gene as well as the innate immune response (NK cells) due to the disruption of the <italic>Il2r&#x003b3;</italic> gene (<xref rid="bb0050" ref-type="bibr">DiSanto et al., 1995</xref>), and express a <italic>Sirp&#x003b1;</italic> polymorphism that enhances the binding of mouse Sirp&#x003b1; to human CD47, thus preventing macrophage-mediated rejection of human cells (<xref rid="bb0245" ref-type="bibr">Takenaka et al., 2007</xref>).</p><p id="p0045">We took advantage of this mouse model and, through an appropriate mating strategy, introduced the <italic>Tcirg1</italic><sup><italic>oc</italic></sup> mutation in the NSG background, eventually generating a new mouse model that we called NSG oc/oc, displaying osteopetrosis with immunodeficiency. Our findings set the bases for an improved xenograft model to evaluate <italic>in vivo</italic>, in a relevant murine condition, the efficacy of gene-corrected cells from ARO patients.</p></sec><sec id="s0010"><label>2</label><title>Methods</title><sec id="s0015"><label>2.1</label><title>Animals</title><p id="p0050">NOD.Cg-Prkdc<sup>scid</sup> Il2rg<sup>tm1Wjl</sup>/SzJ (NSG) (<xref rid="bb0215" ref-type="bibr">Shultz et al., 2005</xref>) and B6C3Fe a/a Tcirg1 oc/J-Ly5.2 (oc/+) mice were purchased from The Jackson Laboratory (Bar Harbor, ME); of note, prior to the present work, we had fully backcrossed the oc/+ mice on the C57BL/6J background.</p><p id="p0055">Animals were group-housed in a specific-pathogen-free animal facility, under a 12-hour dark/light cycle, with water and food provided <italic>ad libitum</italic>. All the procedures involving mice were performed in accordance with ethical rules of the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee of Humanitas Clinical and Research Center and with international laws (Italian Ministry of Health, protocol n.473/2017-PR).</p></sec><sec id="s0020"><label>2.2</label><title>Mouse genotyping</title><p id="p0060">Mice were genotyped by <xref rid="dt0100" ref-type="term">PCR</xref> using DNA extracted from a tail biopsy. The PCR conditions for the <italic>Prkdc</italic> mutation were: 95&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 2&#x000a0;min, then 35&#x000a0;cycles, 95&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 30&#x000a0;s, 58&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 30&#x000a0;s and 72&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 1&#x000a0;min, then 72&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 5&#x000a0;min, with forward primer 5&#x02032;-TTGAGCAGACAATGCTGAGAA-3&#x02032; and reverse primer 5&#x02032;-TTCTGCATTCACAAGTCTTACCA-3&#x02032;. The 157 base pair (bp) amplicon obtained was sequenced with the forward primer to identify the T-to-A transversion point mutation at position c.12138 in the <italic>Prkdc</italic> gene (ENSMUST00000023352.8).</p><p id="p0065">For the <italic>Il2r&#x003b3;</italic> gene, the targeted allele was identified by the presence of the Neomycin cassette, using the following PCR conditions: 95&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 2&#x000a0;min, then 35&#x000a0;cycles, 95&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 30&#x000a0;s, 55&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 30&#x000a0;s and 72&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 1&#x000a0;min, then 72&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 5&#x000a0;min, with forward primer 5&#x02032;-GATGCTCTTCGTCCAGATCA-3&#x02032; and reverse primer 5&#x02032;-CTCCTGCCGAGAAAGTATCC-3&#x02032;, producing a 150&#x000a0;bp amplicon in the presence of the Neo cassette; the wild type allele was detected through the same protocol using forward primer 5&#x02032;-TCATGGGATGCATTGTCAGT-3&#x02032; and reverse primer 5&#x02032;-CCTGGAGCTGGACAACAAAT-3&#x02032;, producing a 234&#x000a0;bp amplicon (ENSMUST00000033664.13) in the absence of the Neo cassette.</p><p id="p0070">For the <italic>Tcirg1</italic> gene, which in the oc/oc model carries a 1579&#x000a0;bp genomic deletion spanning from intron 1 to the 5&#x02032; of exon 3, genotyping was performed as previously described (<xref rid="bb0265" ref-type="bibr">Tondelli et al., 2009</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s0025"><label>2.3</label><title>Tissue preparation and histology</title><p id="p0075">Mice were sacrificed by CO<sub>2</sub> asphyxiation; tissues were harvested and either fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde (<xref rid="dt0105" ref-type="term">PFA</xref>) or processed to obtain cell suspensions for further analysis (see below). Selected bones were decalcified in an Ion Exchange Decal Unit (Biocare Medical, LLC, Pacheco, CA), dehydrated and embedded in paraffin for Hematoxylin and Eosin (<xref rid="dt0060" ref-type="term">H/E</xref>) staining. Other bones, after fixation, were decalcified in 14% ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid (<xref rid="dt0045" ref-type="term">EDTA</xref>), pH&#x000a0;7.4 with Acetic Acid, then dehydrated and embedded in paraffin for <xref rid="dt0140" ref-type="term">TRAP</xref> staining (Sigma-Aldrich, Saint Louis, MO). Von Kossa/Van Gieson staining was performed on plastic-embedded spine, according to standard procedures. Images were acquired with an Olympus BX51 Microscope (Olympus Optical Co., Ltd., Shinjuku, Tokyo, Japan).</p><p id="p0080">For immunohistochemical staining, 3&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m thick longitudinal serial sections of formalin-fixed paraffin-embedded tissue were collected on glass slides, deparaffinized and treated for antigen retrieval, according to standard procedures. Tissue sections were incubated with 2% H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> for 15&#x000a0;min in the dark, washed with water and blocked with Rodent Block M (Biocare Medical) for 40&#x000a0;min at RT. Then, they were incubated overnight at 4&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C or 1&#x000a0;h at RT with the following primary antibodies: anti-mouse CD3 (SP7, 1:100; Thermo Fisher Scientific, Inc., Waltham, MA), anti-mouse B220 (1:300; eBioscience, Inc., San Diego, CA), anti-human CD45 (1:100; DAKO, Glostrup, Denmark), diluted in <xref rid="dt0095" ref-type="term">PBS</xref> 0.05% Tween 20 (PBST) (GIBCO&#x000ae;, Grand Island, NY, and Merck Millipore, Burlington, MA, respectively). Sections were then rinsed in PBST and incubated with Mach 1 Polymer (Biocare Medical) for 30&#x000a0;min at RT, rinsed in PBST, developed with 3-3'-Diaminobenzidine (<xref rid="dt0040" ref-type="term">DAB</xref>) and counterstained with Hematoxylin. Images were acquired by an Olympus BX51 Microscope (Olympus Optical Co., Ltd).</p></sec><sec id="s0030"><label>2.4</label><title>Flow cytometry</title><p id="p0085">Cell suspensions from spleens were prepared by meshing tissues in PBS with 2% fetal bovine serum (<xref rid="dt0050" ref-type="term">FBS</xref>) and 1&#x000a0;mM EDTA (FACS buffer) on a 40&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m filter followed by red blood cell lysis, and then incubated with the following monoclonal anti-mouse fluorescent-conjugated antibodies: TER-119 (TER-119), CD335 (29A1.4), CD11b (M1/70), CD8 (53-6.7), CD4 (RM4-5), B220 (RA3-6B2), IgM (II/41), IgD (<xref rid="bb0160" ref-type="bibr">Neri et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="bb0250" ref-type="bibr">Teti and Econs, 2017</xref>; <xref rid="bb0010" ref-type="bibr">Askmyr et al., 2009a</xref>; <xref rid="bb0100" ref-type="bibr">Johansson et al., 2007</xref>; <xref rid="bb0070" ref-type="bibr">Frattini et al., 2005</xref>; <xref rid="bb0205" ref-type="bibr">Scimeca et al., 2000</xref>; <xref rid="bb0175" ref-type="bibr">Palagano et al., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="bb0065" ref-type="bibr">Frattini et al., 2000</xref>; <xref rid="bb0145" ref-type="bibr">Moscatelli et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bb0255" ref-type="bibr">Thudium et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bb0150" ref-type="bibr">Moscatelli et al., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="bb0125" ref-type="bibr">Manz and Di Santo, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="bb0075" ref-type="bibr">Fujiwara, 2018</xref>; <xref rid="bb0050" ref-type="bibr">DiSanto et al., 1995</xref>; <xref rid="bb0245" ref-type="bibr">Takenaka et al., 2007</xref>; <xref rid="bb0215" ref-type="bibr">Shultz et al., 2005</xref>), F4/80 (BM8), Ly6C (AL-21), Ly6-G (1A8). Cell suspensions from thymuses were prepared by meshing tissues in FACS buffer on a 40&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m filter and then stained with the following monoclonal anti-mouse fluorescent-conjugated antibodies: CD45 (30-F11), CD8 (53-6.7), CD4 (RM4-5).</p><p id="p0090">Bone marrow (<xref rid="dt0010" ref-type="term">BM</xref>) cell suspensions were prepared by crushing of multiple bones as described (<xref rid="bb0040" ref-type="bibr">Crisafulli et al., 2019</xref>); in general, we had already optimized this procedure to obtain enough cells for the analysis from osteopetrotic mice, in which BM encroachment and severe growth retardation dramatically reduce the total number of BM cells (<xref rid="bb0110" ref-type="bibr">Lo Iacono et al., 2012</xref>). Staining was performed as above, using monoclonal anti-human CD45 (2D1) and CD14 (61D3) fluorescent-conjugated antibodies. The same antibody cocktail was used for splenocytes obtained from transplanted mice.</p><p id="p0095">For all described tissues, dead cell discrimination was performed with LIVE/DEAD&#x02122; Fixable Dead Cell Stain Kit (Thermo Fisher Scientific), following the manufacturer's instructions.</p><p id="p0100">All samples were acquired on a BD FACSCanto II or an LSR Fortessa flow cytometer (BD Biosciences, Franklin Lakes, NJ) equipped with BD FACSDIVA&#x02122; software (BD Biosciences) and analyzed with FlowJo software v10.5.3 (FlowJo LLC, BD Biosciences). Antibodies were purchased from either BD Biosciences or eBioscience, Inc.</p></sec><sec id="s0035"><label>2.5</label><title>Serological analysis</title><p id="p0105">Blood was collected at necropsy by cardiac puncture in the absence of anticoagulants, according to standard procedures. After few hours, serum was separated by low-speed centrifugation and samples were stored at &#x02212;20&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C until use. Total calcium and phosphorus levels were determined using a Ci16200 Architect Abbott instrument (Abbott Park, IL, USA).</p></sec><sec id="s0040"><label>2.6</label><title><italic>In vitro</italic> osteoclast differentiation and resorption assay</title><p id="p0110"><italic>In vitro</italic> osteoclastogenesis was induced following standard protocols, as previously reported (<xref rid="bb0135" ref-type="bibr">Menale et al., 2019</xref>). Briefly, 4&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>5</sup> splenocytes/well from NSG and NSG oc/oc littermates were cultured in 96-well plate in &#x003b1;MEM medium (Sigma-Aldrich) supplemented with 10% FBS, 1% penicillin/streptomycin (<xref rid="dt0110" ref-type="term">P/S</xref>) and 1% glutamine in the presence of 25&#x000a0;ng/ml murine Macrophage-Colony Stimulating Factor (<xref rid="dt0080" ref-type="term">M-CSF</xref>), 5&#x000a0;ng/ml human Transforming Growth Factor &#x003b2;1 (TGF&#x003b2;1; both reagents from Peprotech, London, UK), 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M Dexamethasone (Sigma-Aldrich) and with or without 100&#x000a0;ng/ml murine Receptor Activator of Nf-kB Ligand (<xref rid="dt0115" ref-type="term">RANKL</xref>) for 6&#x000a0;days. Mature osteoclasts were stained using the Tartrate Resistant Acid Phosphatase (TRAP) Kit (Sigma-Aldrich) following the manufacturer's instruction.</p><p id="p0115">The same culture conditions were applied to achieve osteoclast formation on dentin discs (Immunodiagnostic Systems, Ltd., Scottsdale, AZ) and evaluate their resorptive capacity. After 3&#x000a0;weeks, dentin discs were rinsed with water, scraped to remove attached cells, stained with 1% Toluidine blue solution for 3&#x000a0;min and then washed with water to visualize resorption pits. Images were acquired on an EVOS XL Inverted Microscope (Thermo Fisher Scientific) for both TRAP<sup>+</sup> mature osteoclasts and Toluidine blue-stained dentin discs.</p></sec><sec id="s0045"><label>2.7</label><title>Transplantation</title><p id="p0120">For murine cell transplantation, 2&#x02013;4&#x000a0;day old pups were irradiated with 100 centiGray (<xref rid="dt0030" ref-type="term">cGy</xref>) administered from a <sup>137</sup>Caesium (<sup>137</sup>Cs) source. Four hours later, 10<sup>7</sup> total BM cells from 10&#x000a0;week old C57BL/6J donor mice were suspended in 30&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l PBS and injected into the temporal vein of recipient irradiated mice. After injection, the pups were returned to their cages. Mice were sacrificed by CO<sub>2</sub> inhalation at 2 time-points: 3&#x000a0;weeks and 12&#x000a0;weeks post-transplantation.</p><p id="p0125">For human cell transplantation, the radiation dose was 200&#x000a0;cGy, aiming at further favoring human cell engraftment. 1&#x02013;2.6&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>6</sup> CD34<sup>+</sup> cells from mobilized peripheral blood of consenting lymphoma patients (82&#x02013;92% purity), were injected into NSG and NSG oc/oc recipient mice as above described. These CD34<sup>+</sup> cells are notoriously regarded as normal and in fact autologous hematopoietic stem cell transplantation is an established treatment for patients with hematologic malignancies (<xref rid="bb0035" ref-type="bibr">Castagna et al., 2015</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s0050"><label>2.8</label><title>Micro-computed tomography (&#x003bc;CT)</title><p id="p0130">MicroCT was performed using a Skyscan 1172 instrument (Bruker) at 6&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m resolution with 0.5&#x000a0;mm aluminum filter, source voltage 80&#x000a0;kV and current 100 uA. A 255&#x000a0;mg/ml cutoff was used for bone. Images were reconstructed using the NRecon and InstaRecon software (Bruker). Cross sectional images were obtained using Dataviewer software and three-dimensional images using the CTvox software (Bruker). Quantitative histomorphometric analysis of lumbar vertebrae and femoral bone were performed using the Bruker CTanalyser software.</p></sec><sec id="s0055"><label>2.9</label><title>Statistics</title><p id="p0135">Statistical analysis was performed using Mann-Whitney test when comparing two groups. Kruskall-Wallis test was used for multiple comparisons (GraphPad Prism 6.0, GraphPad Softwares, Inc., La Jolla, CA). Statistical significance was considered when p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05. All data are presented as mean&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;SEM unless otherwise stated.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0060"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><sec id="s0065"><label>3.1</label><title>Generation of the NSG oc/oc mouse model</title><p id="p0140">In order to generate NSG oc/oc mice, first we bred NSG female mice with C57BL/6J oc/+ male mice. Fifty percent of the mice in the litters carried the mutations of the parental strains in the heterozygous state, on a NSG/C57BL/6J mixed background. These heterozygous mice were bred with NSG mice. In the generated litter, we selected individuals carrying the <italic>Prkdc</italic> and <italic>Il2r&#x003b3;</italic> mutations in the homozygous state (hemizygous state for the <italic>Il2r&#x003b3;</italic> mutation in male mice) and the <italic>Tcirg1</italic><sup><italic>oc</italic></sup> mutation in the heterozygous state (hereafter indicated as NSG oc/+ on a mixed background). These were crossed with NSG mice and the same breeding scheme was applied in the following four generations. Specifically, according to the Marker-Assisted Accelerated Backcrossing (MAX-BAX&#x000ae;) technology (Charles River Laboratories International, Inc., Wilmington, MA), which genotypes 384 carefully selected strain-specific single nucleotide polymorphisms, mice with allelic profiles most closely matching the profile of the recipient NSG strain, were mated to NSG mice to complete backcrossing for two additional generations. At the end, the NSG oc/+ colony was maintained in the heterozygous state due to early lethality of the NSG oc/oc mice, as further detailed below.</p></sec><sec id="s0070"><label>3.2</label><title>The NSG oc/oc mouse displays immunodeficiency and severe recessive osteopetrosis</title><p id="p0145">Characteristic features of the parental strains used to generate the NSG oc/oc mouse are on one hand immunodeficiency with complete lack of B, T, and NK cells (<xref rid="bb0215" ref-type="bibr">Shultz et al., 2005</xref>), and on the other osteoclast rich-osteopetrosis with severe growth retardation, defective tooth eruption and extramedullary hematopoiesis (<xref rid="bb0070" ref-type="bibr">Frattini et al., 2005</xref>). Thus, we verified that the newly generated mouse model displayed these phenotypes.</p><p id="p0150">NSG oc/oc mice were born at Mendelian ratio from NSG oc/+ breeding pairs; in total, litters comprised on average 8 pups each, as expected for the NSG strain in optimal housing conditions, and were regularly nursed, differently from what occurs with the parental oc/oc strain according to our experience. NSG oc/oc mice did not display an overt phenotype at birth, but around post-natal day 14 (P14) difference in body weight became apparent as compared to NSG and NSC oc/+ littermates (<xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>a), and tooth eruption failed to occur (<xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>b). In the following days, NSG oc/oc mice started displaying the so-called &#x0201c;circling behavior&#x0201d; typical of oc/oc mice, possibly due to worsening of the skull bone defect; moreover, they gradually lost weight, likely owing to poor nutrition. The severity of the disease importantly reduced their life span: in fact, 50% of NSG oc/oc mice died before weaning, and the remaining shortly after; none of them survived longer than 4&#x000a0;weeks (<xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>c). NSG oc/+ had a normal life span and were completely indistinguishable from NSG littermates, as expected based on the recessive nature of the <italic>Tcirg1</italic><sup><italic>oc</italic></sup> mutation; therefore, they were not further investigated.<fig id="f0005"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>The NSG oc/oc mouse model presents failure to thrive, lack of tooth eruption and reduced life span. a Left: body weight of NSG, NSG oc/+ and NSG oc/oc mice from post-natal day 11 (P11) to P20. NSG oc/+: n&#x000a0;&#x02265;&#x000a0;3; NSG and NSG oc/oc: n&#x000a0;&#x02265;&#x000a0;6. *p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05; **p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.01. Right: representative photographs of NSG and NSG oc/oc littermates showing apparent reduced size in the latter. b Representative photographs of NSG and NSG oc/oc littermates showing lack of tooth eruption in the latter. c Kaplan-Mayer survival curves of NSG and NSG oc/oc mice (Log-rank test, ***p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.0001).</p></caption><alt-text id="al0005">Fig. 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig></p><p id="p0155">To perform a deep characterization, we sacrificed NSG oc/oc and NSG littermates at P16-18; age matched C57BL/6J wild type (WT) mice were also included as positive controls for histology (<xref rid="f0030" ref-type="graphic">Supplementary Fig. 1</xref>) and FACS analysis of the spleen (<xref rid="f0035" ref-type="graphic">Supplementary Fig. 2</xref>a). At necropsy, the spleen was significantly enlarged in NSG oc/oc mice as compared to controls, and, considering the marked reduction of body weight in NSG oc/oc animals, the spleen weight/body weight ratio was even more strikingly increased (<xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>a). Tissue histology revealed that splenic architecture was completely disrupted in both NSG and NSG oc/oc mice: Hematoxilin/Eosin (H/E) staining showed absence of separation between red and white pulp and abundance of megakaryocytes, suggestive of intense extramedullary hematopoiesis, while immunohistochemical (IHC) staining with anti-CD3 and anti-B220 antibodies did not detect any T and B cells, respectively (<xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>b). Accordingly, total splenic cellularity was significantly higher in NSG oc/oc mice as compared to controls (<xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>c). Cytofluorimetric analysis of splenic cell suspensions showed that lymphocytes were virtually absent in NSG oc/oc and NSG littermates, with negligible numbers of T, B, and NK cells, as expected (<xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>c). The observed higher splenic cellularity in NSG oc/oc compared to NSG mice was accounted for by increased numbers of both myeloid and erythroid cells, with a 2- and 21-fold difference, respectively, resulting in a relative expansion of the erythroid compartment over the myeloid one, as likely expected during extramedullary hematopoiesis (<xref rid="f0035" ref-type="graphic">Supplementary Fig. 2</xref>b). The thymus was almost undetectable in NSG oc/oc and NSG littermates, in accordance with the genetic defects in the <italic>Prkdc</italic> and <italic>Il2r&#x003b3;</italic> genes. Moreover, in both groups FACS analysis showed only few residual double-negative thymocytes, with almost complete absence of immature double-positive and mature single-positive T cells (<xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>d and <xref rid="f0040" ref-type="graphic">Supplementary Fig. 3</xref>).</p><p id="p0165">Serological analysis revealed significantly reduced calcium and phosphate levels in NSG oc/oc mice as compared to controls (<xref rid="f0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>a). Derangements in calcium homeostasis point to altered bone metabolism. Indeed, H/E staining of decalcified paraffin-embedded bone sections showed very dense tissue containing cartilage remnants, loss of corticomedullary differentiation and extremely limited marrow space in NSG oc/oc mice as compared to controls, demonstrating a typical osteopetrotic appearance (<xref rid="f0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>b). TRAP staining was increased in NSG oc/oc mice, indicating that they displayed an osteoclast-rich form of osteopetrosis. Finally, von Kossa staining on non-decalcified resin-embedded tissue sections demonstrated an abnormal pattern of mineralization typical of rickets (<xref rid="f0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>b); this peculiar feature was previously described in the oc/oc mouse model and ascribed to defective gastric acidification in the absence of <italic>Tcirg1</italic> gene expression in gastric parietal cells, and reduced dietary calcium absorption (<xref rid="bb0200" ref-type="bibr">Schinke et al., 2009</xref>). Overall, the findings in NSG oc/oc mice mirrored those described in the oc/oc model (<xref rid="bb0205" ref-type="bibr">Scimeca et al., 2000</xref>; <xref rid="bb0200" ref-type="bibr">Schinke et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="bb0130" ref-type="bibr">Marks Jr. et al., 1985</xref>).<fig id="f0010"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>The NSG oc/oc mouse model displays marked splenomegaly and severe immunodeficiency. a Spleen weight, body weight and spleen weight over body weight ratio in NSG and NSG oc/oc mice (n&#x000a0;&#x02265;&#x000a0;7 per genotype). b Representative images of formalin-fixed paraffin-embedded spleen sections from NSG and NSG oc/oc mice, stained with Hematoxylin/Eosin (H/E), anti-mouse CD3 or anti-mouse B220 antibody; positive controls are shown in <xref rid="f0030" ref-type="fig">Supplementary Fig. 1</xref>. Scale bar: 500&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m in the low magnification images, 100&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m in the inset. c Left: number of total splenocytes in NSG and NSG oc/oc mice (n&#x000a0;&#x02265;&#x000a0;8 per genotype). Right: number of cells of all main splenic cell subpopulations (CD11b<sup>+</sup> myeloid cells, TER119<sup>+</sup> erythroid cells, B220<sup>+</sup> B cells, CD4<sup>+</sup> and CD8<sup>+</sup> T lymphocytes, NKp46<sup>+</sup> NK cells) as determined by FACS analysis, following the gating strategy depicted in <xref rid="f0035" ref-type="fig">Supplementary Fig. 2</xref> (n&#x000a0;&#x02265;&#x000a0;5 per genotype). d Number of double negative (DN), double positive (DP) and CD8, CD4 single-positive (SP8 and SP4) thymocytes after gating on CD45<sup>+</sup> hematopoietic cells, as described in <xref rid="f0040" ref-type="fig">Supplementary Fig. 3</xref> (n&#x000a0;&#x02265;&#x000a0;3 per genotype). **p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;0.01; ***p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001.</p><p>The NSG oc/oc mouse model displays marked splenomegaly and severe immunodeficiency. a Spleen weight, body weight and spleen weight over body weight ratio in NSG and NSG oc/oc mice (n&#x000a0;&#x02265;&#x000a0;7 per genotype). b Representative images of formalin-fixed paraffin-embedded spleen sections from NSG and NSG oc/oc mice, stained with Hematoxylin/Eosin (H/E), anti-mouse CD3 or anti-mouse B220 antibody; positive controls are shown in Supplementary Fig. 1. Scale bar: 500&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m in the low magnification images, 100&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m in the inset. c Left: number of total splenocytes in NSG and NSG oc/oc mice (n&#x000a0;&#x02265;&#x000a0;8 per genotype). Right: number of cells of all main splenic cell subpopulations (CD11b<sup>+</sup> myeloid cells, TER119<sup>+</sup> erythroid cells, B220<sup>+</sup> B cells, CD4<sup>+</sup> and CD8<sup>+</sup> T lymphocytes, NKp46<sup>+</sup> NK cells) as determined by FACS analysis, following the gating strategy depicted in Supplementary Fig. 2 (n&#x000a0;&#x02265;&#x000a0;5 per genotype). d Number of double negative (DN), double positive (DP) and CD8, CD4 single-positive (SP8 and SP4) thymocytes after gating on CD45<sup>+</sup> hematopoietic cells, as described in Supplementary Fig. 3 (n&#x000a0;&#x02265;&#x000a0;3 per genotype). **p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;0.01; ***p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0010">Fig. 2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig><fig id="f0015"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>NSG oc/oc mice present osteoclast-rich osteopetrosis. a Calcium and phosphorus serum levels in NSG and NSG oc/oc mice (n&#x000a0;&#x02265;&#x000a0;8 per genotype). **p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.01, ****p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.0001. b Representative images of decalcified formalin-fixed paraffin-embedded vertebral sections of NSG and NSG oc/oc mice stained with H/E (upper panels) and TRAP (middle panels); undecalcified formalin-fixed resin-embedded vertebral sections stained with von Kossa/van Gieson staining (lower panels). Scale bar: 500&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m. c <italic>In vitro</italic> osteoclastogenesis from splenic precursors of NSG and NSG oc/oc mice: representative images of TRAP staining on plastic (upper panels) and of Toluidine blue staining of resorption pits on dentin discs (lower panels). Scale bars: 400&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0015">Fig. 3</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr3"/></fig></p><p id="p0170">Finally, we evaluated <italic>in vitro</italic> osteoclast formation and bone resorption from NSG oc/oc and NSG splenic precursors according to standard protocols. In both cases, osteoclasts formed, but those generated from NSG oc/oc mice were mostly smaller and irregularly shaped (<xref rid="f0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>c), as previously observed in oc/oc osteoclasts (<xref rid="bb0155" ref-type="bibr">Nakamura et al., 1997</xref>), in line with the involvement of the V-ATPase in vesicle trafficking, in addition to its essential proton-pumping activity (<xref rid="bb0225" ref-type="bibr">Sobacchi et al., 2013</xref>). When differentiated on dentin, NSG osteoclasts generated well-developed resorption pits, while no sign of resorption was found in the presence of NSG oc/oc differentiated cells, thus demonstrating a complete functional impairment (<xref rid="f0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>c).</p><p id="p0175">In conclusion, the NSG oc/oc mouse model displayed immunodeficiency and severe recessive osteoclast-rich osteopetrosis.</p></sec><sec id="s0075"><label>3.3</label><title>Neonatal murine bone marrow transplantation corrects the pathology in NSG oc/oc mice</title><p id="p0180">Osteopetrosis in the oc/oc mouse derives from an osteoclast cell-autonomous defect, and in fact can be corrected by WT bone marrow transplantation (<xref rid="dt0015" ref-type="term">BMT</xref>) (<xref rid="bb0070" ref-type="bibr">Frattini et al., 2005</xref>; <xref rid="bb0095" ref-type="bibr">Johansson et al., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="bb0015" ref-type="bibr">Askmyr et al., 2009b</xref>; <xref rid="bb0060" ref-type="bibr">Flores et al., 2010</xref>). Therefore, we verified whether the same occurred in our NSG oc/oc mouse. In detail, NSG oc/oc and NSG neonates (P2-P4, n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;6 per group) were transplanted with BM cells from adult C57BL/6J WT mice after receiving a radiation dose of 100&#x000a0;cGy, and were sacrificed 3 or 12&#x000a0;weeks after transplant. In particular, the first time-point (<italic>i.e.</italic> 3&#x000a0;weeks post-BMT) allowed comparing the bone and spleen phenotype with that of untreated NSG oc/oc mice, which did not survive further, as mentioned above.</p><p id="p0185">As early as 3&#x000a0;weeks after-BMT, <xref rid="dt0085" ref-type="term">&#x003bc;CT</xref> analysis of long bones showed complete normalization of the skeletal phenotype in transplanted NSG oc/oc mice (<xref rid="f0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>a). Of note, most of the measurements (<italic>i.e.</italic> bone volume over total volume ratio, <xref rid="dt0025" ref-type="term">BV/TV</xref>; bone surface over total volume ratio, <xref rid="dt0020" ref-type="term">BS/TV</xref>; trabecular number, <xref rid="dt0120" ref-type="term">Tb.N</xref>, and trabecular spacing, <xref rid="dt0125" ref-type="term">Tb.Sp</xref>) in transplanted NSG oc/oc mice overlapped those of untreated NSG and transplanted NSG mice. On the other hand, trabecular thickness (<xref rid="dt0130" ref-type="term">Tb.Th</xref>) did not differ among the different genotype and treatment groups (<xref rid="f0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>a). In parallel, axial bone histology showed substantial improvement of the bone defect in transplanted NSG oc/oc mice, with clear enlargement of the BM cavity and increase in BM cellularity (<xref rid="f0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>b). Accordingly, serological analysis showed no difference in calcium and phosphate levels in transplanted NSG oc/oc as compared to transplanted NSG mice (<xref rid="f0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>c), and normalization of these parameters in the former group as compared to untreated NSG oc/oc mice (see <xref rid="f0015" ref-type="fig">Fig. 3</xref>a). Finally, H/E staining of the spleen demonstrated an initial attempt to restore red and white pulp separation, and IHC staining with specific antibodies documented the presence of partially compartmentalized T and B cells, both in NSG oc/oc and in NSG mice (<xref rid="f0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>d).<fig id="f0020"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Neonatal murine bone marrow transplantation corrects the pathology in NSG oc/oc mice. a MicroCT analysis of the femur of untreated NSG and NSG oc/oc mice, and murine BM-transplanted NSG and NSG oc/oc mice (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;3 in all groups but transplanted NSG, where n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;2). b Representative images of decalcified formalin-fixed paraffin-embedded vertebral sections of transplanted (tx) NSG and NSG oc/oc mice 3&#x000a0;weeks after transplantation, stained with H/E. Scale bar: 500&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m. c Calcium and phosphorus serum levels in NSG and NSG oc/oc mice 3&#x000a0;weeks after transplantation (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;2 per genotype; bars indicate the range). d Representative images of spleen of tx NSG and tx NSG oc/oc mice 3&#x000a0;weeks after transplantation, stained with H/E, anti-mouse CD3 or anti-mouse B220 antibody. Scale bar: 500&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m. e Growth curve of NSG and NSG oc/oc mice after transplantation, during the 3-month follow-up. f Representative images of decalcified formalin-fixed paraffin-embedded vertebral sections of transplanted (tx) NSG and NSG oc/oc mice 3&#x000a0;months after transplantation, stained with H/E. Scale bar: 500&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m. g Representative images of spleen of tx NSG and tx NSG oc/oc mice 3&#x000a0;months after transplantation, stained with H/E, anti-mouse CD3 or anti-mouse B220 antibody. Scale bar: 500&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m. h Histograms from FACS analysis of bone marrow (BM) and spleen (SP) cell suspensions from NSG and NSG oc/oc mice 3&#x000a0;months after transplantation (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;3 per genotype).</p></caption><alt-text id="al0020">Fig. 4</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr4"/></fig></p><p id="p0190">Mice that were kept under observation for 3&#x000a0;months after transplantation, gained weight over time, despite remaining smaller than control littermates (<xref rid="f0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>e) and in good health; of note, none of the transplanted NSG oc/oc mice showed the &#x0201c;circling behavior&#x0201d;. At this time point, histological analysis showed no difference between transplanted NSG and NSG oc/oc mice neither in the bone (<xref rid="f0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>f) nor in the spleen structure (<xref rid="f0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>g), which acquired a canonical pattern of tissue organization and cell distribution. Accordingly, cytofluorimetric analysis confirmed similar proportion of B and T cells in BM and spleen cell suspensions, in NSG and NSG oc/oc transplanted mice (<xref rid="f0020" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>h).</p><p id="p0195">Overall, these data demonstrated that all the cell-autonomous defects (and specifically, osteoclast resorptive function) of the new mouse model could be rescued by BM transplantation, as previously observed for the oc/oc mouse (<xref rid="bb0070" ref-type="bibr">Frattini et al., 2005</xref>; <xref rid="bb0095" ref-type="bibr">Johansson et al., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="bb0015" ref-type="bibr">Askmyr et al., 2009b</xref>; <xref rid="bb0060" ref-type="bibr">Flores et al., 2010</xref>), highlighting the potential usefulness of our model to test novel cell therapy approaches for curing osteopetrosis, including preclinical studies with transduced murine progenitors.</p></sec><sec id="s0080"><label>3.4</label><title>NSG oc/oc mice are able to host human cells in their bone</title><p id="p0200">NSG mice are widely used as models for xenotransplants, based on the capacity to support engraftment and development of human cells, conferred by their specific genetic background that prevents rejection. We speculated our new mouse model might serve as a xenograft model for the functional evaluation of gene-corrected human cells. To test this hypothesis, we performed human cell transplantation in neonate NSG oc/oc mice, owing to their severe phenotype impeding survival into adulthood. As donor cells, we exploited human CD34<sup>+</sup> cells from mobilized peripheral blood, as these are a relevant source for cell and gene therapy approaches to human osteopetrosis (<xref rid="bb0185" ref-type="bibr">Penna et al., 2019</xref>). In line with the above described experiments, here we irradiated NSG oc/oc mice and NSG controls (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;7 and 2, respectively; age: P2-P4) sublethally with 100&#x000a0;cGy dose and infused CD34<sup>+</sup> cells in the temporal vein. Necropsy was performed on average 2&#x000a0;weeks later, after appearance of signs of suffering typical for the pathology (<italic>i.e.</italic> circling behavior and weight loss). Cytofluorimetric analysis of BM cell suspensions showed the presence of human CD45<sup>+</sup> cells in the NSG oc/oc (data not shown), indicating that, despite their severely compromised bone microenvironment, NSG oc/oc mice were able in principle to host human cells. However, the very low chimerism detected in the BM at this early time point (mean 1.65%&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.04 of human CD45<sup>+</sup> cells, median 0.6%; for the NSG controls, mean 2.46%&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;3.46, median 2.46% for the NSG oc/oc) was not sufficient for affecting the bone phenotype in such a short timeframe.<fig id="f0025"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Analysis of mice transplanted with human CD34<sup>+</sup> cells. a FACS analysis of the BM of a representative NSG oc/oc mouse 2&#x000a0;weeks after transplantation. Human CD45<sup>+</sup> leukocytes derived from transplanted CD34<sup>+</sup> cells were gated (left pseudocolor plot) and analyzed for the expression of the human CD14 monocyte marker (histogram on the right, blue line; gray line represents the Fluorescent-Minus-One control). b Scatter plots showing (left) the percentage of human CD45<sup>+</sup> leukocytes within the BM and the spleen of NSG and NSG oc/oc mice, and (right) the percentage of human CD14<sup>+</sup> cells within the BM. c Representative immunohistochemical staining of vertebral bone of transplanted mice two weeks after transplantation, showing the presence of human CD45<sup>+</sup> cells. Scale bar: 200&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m. d MicroCT analysis of the femur of NSG and NSG oc/oc mice (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;3 per group) and NSG oc/oc mice transplanted with human cells (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;5).</p></caption><alt-text id="al0025">Fig. 5</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr5"/></fig></p><p id="p0205">Thus, we decided to raise the radiation dose to 200&#x000a0;cGy in order to favor human cell engraftment by further depleting residual host cells occupying the BM or spleen stem cell niches. Nine NSG oc/oc and 6 NSG littermates were treated with this protocol; each mouse received on average 2&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>6</sup> CD34<sup>+</sup> cells (range: 10<sup>6</sup>&#x02013;2.6&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;10<sup>6</sup> cells). Actually, also in this setting NSG oc/oc mice started displaying the pathology at about 2&#x000a0;weeks of age; sacrifice was performed 2&#x02013;3&#x000a0;weeks after transplantation. FACS analysis of the BM revealed an increased chimerism as compared to the previous experimental setting (human CD45<sup>+</sup> cells in NSG oc/oc BM: mean 4.01%&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.31, median 3.46%; in NSG BM: mean 7.45%&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;3.1, median 5%), with some NSG oc/oc recipient mice showing up to 9&#x02013;11% of human cells in their BM (<xref rid="f0025" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>a and b). Human cells were also present in the spleen (<xref rid="f0025" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>b). Importantly, human CD14<sup>+</sup> cells were detected in the BM of both NSG and NSG oc/oc mice (<xref rid="f0025" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>a and b), suggesting differentiation of human cells towards the myeloid lineage in the murine bone microenvironment, which is relevant in our disease model. Human CD45<sup>+</sup> cells could be detected also by IHC staining on bone (<xref rid="f0025" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>c; relevant controls for the IHC are shown in <xref rid="f0045" ref-type="graphic">Supplementary Fig. 4</xref>). On the other hand, &#x003bc;CT analysis of bone demonstrated that the bone of transplanted NSG oc/oc mice remained osteopetrotic with no amelioration as compared to untreated NSG oc/oc mice (<xref rid="f0025" ref-type="fig">Fig. 5</xref>d), even though we cannot exclude that minor early modifications of the bone tissue might have occurred.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0085"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0215">Here we described the generation of a new mouse model of autosomal recessive osteopetrosis, which we named NSG oc/oc. This model carried the same genetic mutation as the well-known oc/oc mouse, since it was generated through a specific breeding strategy, and faithfully reproduced the key pathologic features of the parental strain. In addition, the NSG oc/oc mice displayed a complete lack of T, B and NK cells, which was the distinctive characteristic of the NSG strain.</p><p id="p0220">To the best of our knowledge, there are no reports in literature of the very same approach (<italic>i.e.</italic> backcross of a disease-causing mutation into the NSG background for human hematopoietic stem cell transfer) carried out in the context of other disease models. For the sake of completeness, here we mention Brehm and colleagues, which generated the spontaneously diabetic NRG-Akita mouse model by backcrossing the Ins2<sup>Akita</sup> mutation into the NOD-Rag1<sup>null</sup> IL2r&#x003b3;<sup>null</sup> background (<xref rid="bb0030" ref-type="bibr">Brehm et al., 2010</xref>). However, owing to the rapid disease course and short life-span of mice homozygous for the Ins2<sup>Akita</sup> mutation, the authors performed all studies in mice heterozygous for the Ins2<sup>Akita</sup> allele.</p><p id="p0225">The original purpose of our work was to provide the scientific community with an osteopetrotic mouse that might be used as a xenotransplant model to test <italic>in vivo</italic> the functional rescue of gene-edited patient-derived cells. In fact, since several years, studies are ongoing to develop a gene therapy approach to human osteopetrosis, with particular respect to the TCIRG1-deficient form that is the most common one (<xref rid="bb0100" ref-type="bibr">Johansson et al., 2007</xref>; <xref rid="bb0145" ref-type="bibr">Moscatelli et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bb0255" ref-type="bibr">Thudium et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bb0150" ref-type="bibr">Moscatelli et al., 2018</xref>); moreover, in recent years other tools for gene editing and cell therapy have been implemented (<xref rid="bb0115" ref-type="bibr">Maeder and Gersbach, 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bb0055" ref-type="bibr">Doss and Sachinidis, 2019</xref>). On the other hand, at a preclinical level demonstration of a functional rescue has been limited to <italic>in vitro</italic> assays (<xref rid="bb0145" ref-type="bibr">Moscatelli et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bb0255" ref-type="bibr">Thudium et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bb0150" ref-type="bibr">Moscatelli et al., 2018</xref>), while <italic>in vivo</italic> studies could demonstrate only the capacity of human corrected cells to engraft and differentiate in the host, not their resorbing capacity. Therefore, we intended to provide a missing tool in preclinical research.</p><p id="p0230">Since the rapid and fatal progression of the disease impeded survival of transplanted NSG oc/oc mice, correction of the skeletal pathology could not be tested in the framework of the present work. Indeed, the major obstacle was represented by the severity of the disease: all NSG oc/oc mice generated in the framework of this study became very sick and had a rapid progression of their pathology, similarly to what observed in oc/oc mice (<xref rid="bb0205" ref-type="bibr">Scimeca et al., 2000</xref>). In this respect, the <italic>Tcirg1</italic><sup><italic>oc</italic></sup> mutation was invariably associated with a severe phenotype in the two different genetic backgrounds. Interestingly, in a previous work, oc/oc mice on a mixed (B6xC3x129) background were generated and, while the vast majority died at a mean age of 25&#x000a0;days, some of them survived up to 90&#x000a0;days (<xref rid="bb0025" ref-type="bibr">Blin-Wakkach et al., 2006</xref>). It is possible that, if our mouse model had had an extended life span, this could have been more compatible with the timing of human cell differentiation, which notoriously takes more time than murine cell differentiation (<xref rid="bb0005" ref-type="bibr">Abkowitz et al., 2000</xref>), and thus it could have possibly allowed achieving a benefit to the mouse from the transplanted human cells. However, by anticipating the xenotransplantation to the prenatal period, it could be possible to give transplanted cells more time to differentiate into functional osteoclasts, or at least into myeloid mature cells able to fuse with resident osteoclasts thereby rescuing their functional defect (<xref rid="bb0270" ref-type="bibr">Wakkach et al., 2008</xref>; <xref rid="bb0090" ref-type="bibr">Jacome-Galarza et al., 2019</xref>). In this regard, by performing <italic>in utero</italic> HSCT, we were able to rescue the osteopetrotic phenotype of oc/oc mice (<xref rid="bb0070" ref-type="bibr">Frattini et al., 2005</xref>; <xref rid="bb0265" ref-type="bibr">Tondelli et al., 2009</xref>); on the other hand, this kind of approach with human cells would be technically more challenging than with murine cells, requiring some refinement of the published protocol.</p><p id="p0235">The transplant conditions we used, specifically the conditioning regimen, might raise some concern. Actually, despite being completely immunodeficient, NSG mice usually undergo myeloablative protocols prior to human cell transplantation, both when treated at the adult age and at the neonatal stage (<xref rid="bb0085" ref-type="bibr">Ishikawa et al., 2007</xref>; <xref rid="bb0045" ref-type="bibr">Cuddihy et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="bb0105" ref-type="bibr">Ko et al., 2017</xref>; <xref rid="bb0180" ref-type="bibr">Pang et al., 2019</xref>), and the radiation doses we used were in those ranges. In addition, the osteopetrotic bone is known to be a poorly permissive environment for cell engraftment, due to the lack of a proper niche, therefore a stronger host cell depletion is likely required to allow donor cell engraftment (<xref rid="bb0120" ref-type="bibr">Mansour et al., 2012</xref>). Accordingly, osteopetrotic patients are usually subjected to strong pretransplant conditioning, and only recent papers reported encouraging results in terms of outcome using reduced intensity conditioning (<xref rid="bb0020" ref-type="bibr">Bahr et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bb0260" ref-type="bibr">Tolar et al., 2006</xref>; <xref rid="bb0210" ref-type="bibr">Shadur et al., 2018</xref>).</p><p id="p0240">Last, osteoclast differentiation is known to crucially depend on the presence of RANKL and M-CSF. Indeed, mouse RANKL is known to be effective both on mouse and on human progenitors, at variance with mouse M-CSF which has been reported to be species specific (<xref rid="bb0080" ref-type="bibr">Gow et al., 2012</xref>). Therefore, it could be hypothesized that, if NSG oc/oc mice had survived longer, lack of human M-CSF might have anyway impeded human osteoclast formation in the murine bone. We considered this concern and conducted a pilot experiment in which together with xenotransplantation mice received repeated doses of human M-CSF; no improvement was observed in this experiment (data not shown), so this approach was not further pursued. Of note, other authors evaluated the possibility to induce ectopic expression of human M-CSF in CD34<sup>+</sup> cells, but this strategy blunted osteoclastogenesis, at least <italic>in vitro</italic> (<xref rid="bb0140" ref-type="bibr">Montano Almendras et al., 2017</xref>).</p><p id="p0245">Humanized mice expressing human M-CSF are reported in the literature (<xref rid="bb0195" ref-type="bibr">Rathinam et al., 2011</xref>) and we might have considered the possibility to use that strain instead of NSG to generate our xenograft osteopetrotic mouse model. We did not undertake this strategy, so we do not know whether in that case the short lifespan of the model and severity of the disease might have still constituted an insuperable hurdle.</p></sec><sec id="s0090"><label>5</label><title>Conclusion</title><p id="p0250">In summary, this work describes the generation and characterization of the NSG oc/oc mouse model of osteoclast-rich cell-autonomous Autosomal Recessive Osteopetrosis together with immunodeficiency. We show human cell chimerism in the bone marrow of NSG oc/oc mice transplanted with human CD34<sup>+</sup> cells. Exploitation of this new mouse model in the context of xenotransplants will likely require more attempts to set up experimental conditions, starting from our results, including for example infusion of human cytokines to foster differentiation, or further crossing with another genetic background. This notwithstanding, efforts would be likely worth the case, based on the importance of testing the functionality of human corrected cells in a relevant, live organism.</p><p id="p0255">The following are the supplementary data related to this article.<fig id="f0030"><label>Supplementary Fig 1</label><caption><p>Representative images of spleen of C57BL/6J mice stained with H/E, anti-mouse CD3 or anti-mouse B220 antibody, as technical control of the same stainings in NSG and NSG oc/oc mice. Scale bar: 500 &#x003bc;m.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0030">Supplementary Fig 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr6"/></fig><fig id="f0035"><label>Supplementary Fig 2</label><caption><p>Immunophenotypic analysis of splenocytes from NSG oc/oc and control mice. a Representative FACS analysis of splenocytes from C57BL/6J adult WT mice, serving as technical control (top panels), from NSG mice (middle panels) and from NSG oc/oc mice (bottom panels), after red blood cells lysis. Erythroid cells are defined as TER119<sup>+</sup>NKp46<sup>-</sup>CD11b<sup>-</sup>B220<sup>-</sup>CD4<sup>-</sup>CD8<sup>-</sup> (highlighted in red); NK cells as TER119<sup>-</sup>NKp46<sup>+</sup>CD11b<sup>-</sup>B220<sup>-</sup>CD4<sup>-</sup>CD8<sup>-</sup> (light blue); myeloid cells as TER119<sup>-</sup>NKp46<sup>-</sup>CD11b<sup>+</sup>B220<sup>-</sup>CD4<sup>-</sup>CD8<sup>-</sup> (green); B cells as TER119<sup>-</sup>NKp46<sup>-</sup>CD11b<sup>-</sup>B220<sup>+</sup>CD4<sup>-</sup>CD8<sup>-</sup> (orange); CD4 and CD8 T lymphocytes as TER119<sup>-</sup>NKp46<sup>-</sup>CD11b<sup>-</sup>B220<sup>-</sup>, CD4<sup>+</sup>CD8<sup>-</sup> or CD4<sup>-</sup>CD8<sup>+</sup>, respectively (dark blue). b Histogram showing mean percentage of splenic subpopulations depicted in a in the spleen of NSG and NSG-oc/oc mice. *p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05; **p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.01.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0035">Supplementary Fig 2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr7"/></fig><fig id="f0040"><label>Supplementary Fig 3</label><caption><p>Immunophenotypic analysis of thymocytes from NSG oc/oc and control mice.</p><p>Representative FACS analysis of thymocytes from C57BL/6J adult WT mice, serving as technical control (top panels), from NSG mice (middle panels) and from NSG oc/oc mice (bottom panels). After gating on the hematopoietic cell fraction based on the expression of the pan-leukocyte marker CD45, the four main thymus subpopulation are defined as follows: DP: double positive CD4<sup>+</sup>CD8<sup>+</sup>; SP4: single positive CD4<sup>+</sup>CD8<sup>-</sup>; SP8: single positive CD4<sup>-</sup>CD8<sup>+</sup>; DN: double negative CD4<sup>-</sup>CD8<sup>-</sup>.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0040">Supplementary Fig 3</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr8"/></fig><fig id="f0045"><label>Supplementary Fig 4</label><caption><p>Immunohistochemical staining with anti-human CD45 antibody. Left: negative control. Representative section of formalin-fixed paraffin-embedded decalcified bone from a wild type untreated C57BL/6J mouse stained with anti-human CD45 antibody; as expected, no positive cells are found. Right: positive control. Representative section of a formalin-fixed paraffin-embedded decalcified human osteomedullary biopsy. Scale bars: 200&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0045">Supplementary Fig 4</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr9"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0095"><title>Abbreviations</title><p id="p0265"><def-list><def-item><term id="dt0005"><xref rid="p0030" ref-type="p">ARO</xref></term><def><p id="p0270">Autosomal Recessive Osteopetrosis</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="dt0010"><xref rid="p0090" ref-type="p">BM</xref></term><def><p id="p0275">Bone Marrow</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="dt0015"><xref rid="p0180" ref-type="p">BMT</xref></term><def><p id="p0280">Bone Marrow Transplantation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="dt0020"><xref rid="p0185" ref-type="p">BS/TV</xref></term><def><p id="p0285">Bone Surface/Total Volume</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="dt0025"><xref rid="p0185" ref-type="p">BV/TV</xref></term><def><p id="p0290">Bone Volume/Total Volume</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="dt0030"><xref rid="p0120" ref-type="p">cGy</xref></term><def><p id="p0295">centiGray</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="dt0035">Cs</term><def><p id="p0300">Caesium</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="dt0040"><xref rid="p0080" ref-type="p">DAB</xref></term><def><p id="p0305">3-3'-Diaminobenzidine</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="dt0045"><xref rid="p0075" ref-type="p">EDTA</xref></term><def><p id="p0310">ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="dt0050"><xref rid="p0085" ref-type="p">FBS</xref></term><def><p id="p0315">Fetal Bovine Serum</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="dt0055"><xref rid="p0035" ref-type="p">GFP</xref></term><def><p id="p0320">Green Fluorescent Protein</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="dt0060"><xref rid="p0075" ref-type="p">H/E</xref></term><def><p id="p0325">Hematoxylin/Eosin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="dt0065"><xref rid="p0035" ref-type="p">HLA</xref></term><def><p id="p0330">Human Leukocyte Antigen</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="dt0070"><xref rid="p0035" ref-type="p">HSCT</xref></term><def><p id="p0335">Hematopoietic Stem Cell Transplantation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="dt0075">IHC</term><def><p id="p0340">immunohistochemical</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="dt0080"><xref rid="p0110" ref-type="p">M-CSF</xref></term><def><p id="p0345">Macrophage-Colony Stimulating Factor</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="dt0085"><xref rid="p0185" ref-type="p">&#x003bc;CT</xref></term><def><p id="p0350">Micro-computed tomography</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="dt0090"><xref rid="p0035" ref-type="p">NSG</xref></term><def><p id="p0355">NOD Scid Gamma common chain</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="dt0095"><xref rid="p0080" ref-type="p">PBS</xref></term><def><p id="p0360">Phosphate-buffered saline</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="dt0100"><xref rid="p0060" ref-type="p">PCR</xref></term><def><p id="p0365">Polymerase chain reaction</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="dt0105"><xref rid="p0075" ref-type="p">PFA</xref></term><def><p id="p0370">paraformaldehyde</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="dt0110"><xref rid="p0110" ref-type="p">P/S</xref></term><def><p id="p0375">penicillin/streptomycin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="dt0115"><xref rid="p0110" ref-type="p">RANKL</xref></term><def><p id="p0380">Receptor Activator of Nf-kB Ligand</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="dt0120"><xref rid="p0185" ref-type="p">Tb.N</xref></term><def><p id="p0385">Trabecular Number</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="dt0125"><xref rid="p0185" ref-type="p">Tb.Sp</xref></term><def><p id="p0390">Trabecular Spacing</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="dt0130"><xref rid="p0185" ref-type="p">Tb.Th</xref></term><def><p id="p0395">Trabecular Thickness</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="dt0135">TGF&#x003b2;</term><def><p id="p0400">Transforming Growth Factor &#x003b2;</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="dt0140"><xref rid="p0075" ref-type="p">TRAP</xref></term><def><p id="p0405">Tartrate Resistant Acid Phosphatase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="dt0145">WT</term><def><p id="p0410">wild type</p></def></def-item></def-list></p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="bi0005"><title>References</title><ref id="bb0005"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0005"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abkowitz</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Golinelli</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Harrison</surname><given-names>D.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guttorp</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vivo kinetics of murine hemopoietic stem cells</article-title><source>Blood</source><volume>96</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2000</year><fpage>3399</fpage><lpage>3405</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11071634</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0010"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0010"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Askmyr</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Flores</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fasth</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Richter</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prospects for gene therapy of osteopetrosis</article-title><source>Current Gene Therapy</source><volume>9</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>150</fpage><lpage>159</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19519360</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0015"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0015"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Askmyr</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Holmberg</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Flores</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehinger</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hjalt</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Richter</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Low-dose busulphan conditioning and neonatal stem cell transplantation preserves vision and restores hematopoiesis in severe murine osteopetrosis</article-title><source>Exp. Hematol.</source><volume>37</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>302</fpage><lpage>308</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19100677</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0020"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0020"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bahr</surname><given-names>T.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lund</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sando</surname><given-names>N.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Orchard</surname><given-names>P.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>W.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Haploidentical transplantation with post-transplant cyclophosphamide following reduced-intensity conditioning for osteopetrosis: outcomes in three children</article-title><source>Bone Marrow Transplant.</source><volume>51</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>1546</fpage><lpage>1548</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27376448</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0025"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0025"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blin-Wakkach</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Breuil</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Quincey</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bagnis</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carle</surname><given-names>G.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Establishment and characterization of new osteoclast progenitor cell lines derived from osteopetrotic and wild type mice</article-title><source>Bone</source><volume>39</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2006</year><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16503212</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0030"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0030"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brehm</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bortell</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Diiorio</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leif</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Laning</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cuthbert</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Human immune system development and rejection of human islet allografts in spontaneously diabetic NOD-Rag1null IL2rgammanull Ins2Akita mice</article-title><source>Diabetes</source><volume>59</volume><issue>9</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>2265</fpage><lpage>2270</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20570944</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0035"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0035"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Castagna</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carlo-Stella</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mazza</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Santoro</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Current role of autologous and allogeneic stem cell transplantation for relapsed and refractory hodgkin lymphoma</article-title><source>Mediterranean Journal of Hematology and Infectious Diseases</source><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2015</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e2015015</object-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0040"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0040"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crisafulli</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Muggeo</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Uva</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwasaki</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Locatelli</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MicroRNA-127-3p controls murine hematopoietic stem cell maintenance by limiting differentiation</article-title><source>Haematologica</source><volume>104</volume><issue>9</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>1744</fpage><lpage>1755</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30792210</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0045"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0045"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cuddihy</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Suterwala</surname><given-names>B.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kohn</surname><given-names>L.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Andrade</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rapid thymic reconstitution following bone marrow transplantation in neonatal mice is VEGF-dependent</article-title><source>Biology of Blood and Marrow Transplantation: Journal of the American Society for Blood and Marrow Transplantation</source><volume>18</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>683</fpage><lpage>689</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0050"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0050"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>DiSanto</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guy-Grand</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajewsky</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lymphoid development in mice with a targeted deletion of the interleukin 2 receptor gamma chain</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A.</source><volume>92</volume><issue>2</issue><year>1995</year><fpage>377</fpage><lpage>381</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7831294</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0055"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0055"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Doss</surname><given-names>M.X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sachinidis</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Current challenges of iPSC-based disease modeling and therapeutic implications</article-title><source>Cells</source><volume>8</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2019</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0060"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0060"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Flores</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Vries</surname><given-names>T.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moscatelli</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Askmyr</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schoenmaker</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Langenbach</surname><given-names>G.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nonablative neonatal bone marrow transplantation rapidly reverses severe murine osteopetrosis despite low-level engraftment and lack of selective expansion of the osteoclastic lineage</article-title><source>Journal of Bone and Mineral Research: The Official Journal of the American Society for Bone and Mineral Research</source><volume>25</volume><issue>9</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>2069</fpage><lpage>2077</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0065"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0065"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frattini</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Orchard</surname><given-names>P.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sobacchi</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giliani</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abinun</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mattsson</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Defects in TCIRG1 subunit of the vacuolar proton pump are responsible for a subset of human autosomal recessive osteopetrosis</article-title><source>Nat. Genet.</source><volume>25</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2000</year><fpage>343</fpage><lpage>346</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10888887</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0070"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0070"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frattini</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Blair</surname><given-names>H.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sacco</surname><given-names>M.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cerisoli</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Faggioli</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cato</surname><given-names>E.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rescue of ATPa3-deficient murine malignant osteopetrosis by hematopoietic stem cell transplantation in utero</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A.</source><volume>102</volume><issue>41</issue><year>2005</year><fpage>14629</fpage><lpage>14634</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16195375</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0075"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0075"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fujiwara</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Humanized mice: a brief overview on their diverse applications in biomedical research</article-title><source>J. Cell. Physiol.</source><volume>233</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>2889</fpage><lpage>2901</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28543438</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0080"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0080"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gow</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Garceau</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kapetanovic</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sester</surname><given-names>D.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fici</surname><given-names>G.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shelly</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cloning and expression of porcine Colony Stimulating Factor-1 (CSF-1) and Colony Stimulating Factor-1 Receptor (CSF-1R) and analysis of the species specificity of stimulation by CSF-1 and Interleukin 34</article-title><source>Cytokine</source><volume>60</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>793</fpage><lpage>805</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22974529</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0085"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0085"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ishikawa</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hijikata</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitamura</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemotherapy-resistant human AML stem cells home to and engraft within the bone-marrow endosteal region</article-title><source>Nat. Biotechnol.</source><volume>25</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2007</year><fpage>1315</fpage><lpage>1321</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17952057</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0090"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0090"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jacome-Galarza</surname><given-names>C.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Percin</surname><given-names>G.I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>J.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mass</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lazarov</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eitler</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Developmental origin, functional maintenance and genetic rescue of osteoclasts</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>568</volume><issue>7753</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>541</fpage><lpage>545</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30971820</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0095"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0095"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jansson</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehinger</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fasth</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Karlsson</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Richter</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neonatal hematopoietic stem cell transplantation cures oc/oc mice from osteopetrosis</article-title><source>Exp. Hematol.</source><volume>34</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2006</year><fpage>242</fpage><lpage>249</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16459192</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0100"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0100"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Vries</surname><given-names>T.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schoenmaker</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehinger</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brun</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fasth</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hematopoietic stem cell-targeted neonatal gene therapy reverses lethally progressive osteopetrosis in oc/oc mice</article-title><source>Blood</source><volume>109</volume><issue>12</issue><year>2007</year><fpage>5178</fpage><lpage>5185</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17332244</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0105"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0105"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeong</surname><given-names>Y.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transplantation of human umbilical cord blood CD34(+) cells into the liver of newborn NOD/SCID/IL-2Rgamma null (NSG) mice after busulfan conditioning</article-title><source>Blood Research</source><volume>52</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>316</fpage><lpage>319</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29333410</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0110"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0110"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lo Iacono</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Blair</surname><given-names>H.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Poliani</surname><given-names>P.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marrella</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ficara</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cassani</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Osteopetrosis rescue upon RANKL administration to Rankl(&#x02212;/&#x02212;) mice: a new therapy for human RANKL-dependent ARO</article-title><source>Journal of Bone and Mineral Research: The Official Journal of the American Society for Bone and Mineral Research</source><volume>27</volume><issue>12</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>2501</fpage><lpage>2510</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0115"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0115"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maeder</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gersbach</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-editing technologies for gene and cell therapy</article-title><source>Molecular Therapy: The Journal of the American Society of Gene Therapy</source><volume>24</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>430</fpage><lpage>446</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26755333</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0120"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0120"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mansour</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abou-Ezzi</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sitnicka</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobsen</surname><given-names>S.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wakkach</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Blin-Wakkach</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Osteoclasts promote the formation of hematopoietic stem cell niches in the bone marrow</article-title><source>J. Exp. Med.</source><volume>209</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>537</fpage><lpage>549</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22351931</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0125"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0125"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manz</surname><given-names>M.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Santo</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Renaissance for mouse models of human hematopoiesis and immunobiology</article-title><source>Nat. Immunol.</source><volume>10</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>1039</fpage><lpage>1042</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19767720</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0130"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0130"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marks</surname><given-names>S.C.</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name><name><surname>Seifert</surname><given-names>M.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>P.W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Osteosclerosis, a recessive skeletal mutation on chromosome 19 in the mouse</article-title><source>The Journal of Heredity</source><volume>76</volume><issue>3</issue><year>1985</year><fpage>171</fpage><lpage>176</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3998439</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0135"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0135"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Menale</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Campodoni</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Palagano</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mantero</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Erreni</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Inforzato</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MSC-seeded biomimetic scaffolds as a factory of soluble RANKL in Rankl-deficient osteopetrosis</article-title><source>Stem Cells Transl. Med.</source><volume>8</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>22</fpage><lpage>34</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30184340</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0140"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0140"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Montano Almendras</surname><given-names>C.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thudium</surname><given-names>C.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lofvall</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moscatelli</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schambach</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Henriksen</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Forced expression of human macrophage colony-stimulating factor in CD34(+) cells promotes monocyte differentiation in vitro and in vivo but blunts osteoclastogenesis in vitro</article-title><source>Eur. J. Haematol.</source><volume>98</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>517</fpage><lpage>526</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28160330</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0145"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0145"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moscatelli</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thudium</surname><given-names>C.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Flores</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Askmyr</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gudmann</surname><given-names>N.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lentiviral gene transfer of TCIRG1 into peripheral blood CD34(+) cells restores osteoclast function in infantile malignant osteopetrosis</article-title><source>Bone</source><volume>57</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23907031</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0150"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0150"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moscatelli</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lofvall</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schneider Thudium</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rothe</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Montano</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kertesz</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Targeting NSG mice engrafting cells with a clinically applicable lentiviral vector corrects osteoclasts in infantile malignant osteopetrosis</article-title><source>Hum. Gene Ther.</source><volume>29</volume><issue>8</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>938</fpage><lpage>949</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28726516</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0155"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0155"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Udagawa</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moriyama</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurokawa</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jimi</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lack of vacuolar proton ATPase association with the cytoskeleton in osteoclasts of osteosclerotic (oc/oc) mice</article-title><source>FEBS Lett.</source><volume>401</volume><issue>2&#x02013;3</issue><year>1997</year><fpage>207</fpage><lpage>212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9013888</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0160"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0160"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neri</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Muggeo</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Paulis</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Caldana</surname><given-names>M.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Crisafulli</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Strina</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Targeted gene correction in osteopetrotic-induced pluripotent stem cells for the generation of functional osteoclasts</article-title><source>Stem Cell Reports</source><volume>5</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>558</fpage><lpage>568</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26344905</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0165"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0165"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neven</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Diana</surname><given-names>J.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Castelle</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Magnani</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosain</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Touzot</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Haploidentical HSCT with post-transplant CY for primary immunodeficiencies and inherited disorders in children</article-title><source>Biology of Blood and Marrow Transplantation: Journal of the American Society for Blood and Marrow Transplantation</source><volume>25</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>1363</fpage><lpage>1373</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0170"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0170"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Palagano</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Blair</surname><given-names>H.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pangrazio</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tourkova</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Strina</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Angius</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Buried in the middle but guilty: intronic mutations in the TCIRG1 gene cause human autosomal recessive osteopetrosis</article-title><source>Journal of Bone and Mineral Research: The Official Journal of the American Society for Bone and Mineral Research</source><volume>30</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>1814</fpage><lpage>1821</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0175"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0175"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Palagano</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Menale</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sobacchi</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Villa</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetics of osteopetrosis</article-title><source>Current Osteoporosis Reports</source><volume>16</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29335834</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0180"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0180"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pang</surname><given-names>W.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Czechowicz</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Logan</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhardwaj</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Poyser</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>C.Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anti-CD117 antibody depletes normal and myelodysplastic syndrome human hematopoietic stem cells in xenografted mice</article-title><source>Blood</source><volume>133</volume><issue>19</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>2069</fpage><lpage>2078</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30745302</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0185"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0185"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Penna</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Capo</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Palagano</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sobacchi</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Villa</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>One disease, many genes: implications for the treatment of osteopetroses</article-title><source>Front. Endocrinol.</source><volume>10</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>85</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0190"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0190"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pronk</surname><given-names>C.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Turkiewicz</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vult von Steyern</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehinger</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dykes</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Toporski</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transplantation of haploidentical TcRass-depleted hematopoietic cells allows for optimal timing and sustained correction of the metabolic defect in children with infantile osteopetrosis</article-title><source>Journal of Bone and Mineral Research: The Official Journal of the American Society for Bone and Mineral Research</source><volume>32</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>82</fpage><lpage>85</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0195"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0195"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rathinam</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Poueymirou</surname><given-names>W.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rojas</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Valenzuela</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yancopoulos</surname><given-names>G.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efficient differentiation and function of human macrophages in humanized CSF-1 mice</article-title><source>Blood</source><volume>118</volume><issue>11</issue><year>2011</year><fpage>3119</fpage><lpage>3128</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21791433</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0200"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0200"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schinke</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schilling</surname><given-names>A.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baranowsky</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seitz</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>R.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Linn</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impaired gastric acidification negatively affects calcium homeostasis and bone mass</article-title><source>Nat. Med.</source><volume>15</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>674</fpage><lpage>681</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19448635</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0205"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0205"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scimeca</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Franchi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Trojani</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parrinello</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grosgeorge</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Robert</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The gene encoding the mouse homologue of the human osteoclast-specific 116-kDa V-ATPase subunit bears a deletion in osteosclerotic (oc/oc) mutants</article-title><source>Bone</source><volume>26</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2000</year><fpage>207</fpage><lpage>213</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10709991</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0210"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0210"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shadur</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zaidman</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>NaserEddin</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lokshin</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hussein</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oron</surname><given-names>H.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Successful hematopoietic stem cell transplantation for osteopetrosis using reduced intensity conditioning</article-title><source>Pediatr. Blood Cancer</source><volume>65</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2018</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e27010</object-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0215"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0215"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shultz</surname><given-names>L.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lyons</surname><given-names>B.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Burzenski</surname><given-names>L.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gott</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaleff</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Human lymphoid and myeloid cell development in NOD/LtSz-scid IL2R gamma null mice engrafted with mobilized human hemopoietic stem cells</article-title><source>J. Immunol.</source><volume>174</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2005</year><fpage>6477</fpage><lpage>6489</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15879151</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0220"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="rf0220"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sobacchi</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Villa</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kornak</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Adam</surname><given-names>M.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ardinger</surname><given-names>H.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pagon</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>S.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bean</surname><given-names>L.J.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stephens</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><source>CLCN7-Related Osteopetrosis</source><year>1993</year><publisher-name>GeneReviews((R))</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Seattle (WA)</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0225"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0225"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sobacchi</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coxon</surname><given-names>F.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Villa</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Helfrich</surname><given-names>M.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Osteopetrosis: genetics, treatment and new insights into osteoclast function</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Endocrinol.</source><volume>9</volume><issue>9</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>522</fpage><lpage>536</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23877423</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0230"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0230"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sobacchi</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pangrazio</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>A.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomez</surname><given-names>D.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Caldana</surname><given-names>M.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Susani</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>As little as needed: the extraordinary case of a mild recessive osteopetrosis owing to a novel splicing hypomorphic mutation in the TCIRG1 gene</article-title><source>Journal of Bone and Mineral Research: The Official Journal of the American Society for Bone and Mineral Research</source><volume>29</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2014</year><fpage>1646</fpage><lpage>1650</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0235"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0235"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stattin</surname><given-names>E.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Henning</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Klar</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>McDermott</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stecksen-Blicks</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sandstrom</surname><given-names>P.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>SNX10 gene mutation leading to osteopetrosis with dysfunctional osteoclasts</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><volume>7</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2017</year><fpage>3012</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28592808</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0240"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0240"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stepensky</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grisariu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Avni</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zaidman</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shadur</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Elpeleg</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stem cell transplantation for osteopetrosis in patients beyond the age of 5 years</article-title><source>Blood Advances</source><volume>3</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>862</fpage><lpage>868</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30885997</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0245"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0245"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takenaka</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prasolava</surname><given-names>T.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mortin-Toth</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Khalouei</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gan</surname><given-names>O.I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Polymorphism in Sirpa modulates engraftment of human hematopoietic stem cells</article-title><source>Nat. Immunol.</source><volume>8</volume><issue>12</issue><year>2007</year><fpage>1313</fpage><lpage>1323</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17982459</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0250"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0250"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Teti</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Econs</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Osteopetroses, emphasizing potential approaches to treatment</article-title><source>Bone</source><volume>102</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>50</fpage><lpage>59</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28167345</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0255"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0255"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thudium</surname><given-names>C.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moscatelli</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lofvall</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kertesz</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Montano</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bjurstrom</surname><given-names>C.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation and function of lentiviral vector-mediated TCIRG1 expression in osteoclasts from patients with infantile malignant osteopetrosis: implications for gene therapy</article-title><source>Calcif. Tissue Int.</source><volume>99</volume><issue>6</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>638</fpage><lpage>648</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27541021</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0260"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0260"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tolar</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonfim</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grewal</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Orchard</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Engraftment and survival following hematopoietic stem cell transplantation for osteopetrosis using a reduced intensity conditioning regimen</article-title><source>Bone Marrow Transplant.</source><volume>38</volume><issue>12</issue><year>2006</year><fpage>783</fpage><lpage>787</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17086207</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0265"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0265"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tondelli</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Blair</surname><given-names>H.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guerrini</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Patrene</surname><given-names>K.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cassani</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vezzoni</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fetal liver cells transplanted in utero rescue the osteopetrotic phenotype in the oc/oc mouse</article-title><source>Am. J. Pathol.</source><volume>174</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>727</fpage><lpage>735</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19218349</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0270"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf0270"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wakkach</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mansour</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dacquin</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coste</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jurdic</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carle</surname><given-names>G.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bone marrow microenvironment controls the in vivo differentiation of murine dendritic cells into osteoclasts</article-title><source>Blood</source><volume>112</volume><issue>13</issue><year>2008</year><fpage>5074</fpage><lpage>5083</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18768394</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><ack id="ac0005"><sec id="s0100"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p id="p0415">We thank Fondazione Damiano per l'Ematologia and Fondazione Nicola del Roscio for their support to SM and LC, respectively (both, fellowship's assignees). We thank Dr. Ambra Rizzo (Laboratory of Clinical Pathology and Medical Genetics, Fondazione IRCCS Istituto Neurologico Carlo Besta) for the technical assistance.</p></sec><sec id="s0105"><title>Authors' contributions</title><p id="p0420">PV conceived the project. PV, AV and HCB provided financial support. CS and FF designed and supervised the experiments. EP, SM, LC, ILT, DS, SM, EF and MM performed the experiments and measurements. SLL and CCS collected the human samples. EM, HCB, CS and FF analyzed the data. CS and FF wrote the manuscript. All authors reviewed and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="s0110"><title>Funding</title><p id="p0425">This work was partially supported by the <funding-source id="gts0005">EC Seventh Framework Programme</funding-source> (FP7/2007-2013, SYBIL Project, n. 602300) to AV, by the <funding-source id="gts0010">Ministry of Health, Italy</funding-source> (Grant n. PE-2011-02347329) to PV, and by the <funding-source id="gts0015">Department of Veterans Affairs</funding-source> (USA) grant I01BX002490 and the <funding-source id="gts0020">National Institutes of Health</funding-source> (USA) grant AR065407 to HCB.</p></sec><sec id="s0115"><title>Ethics approval</title><p id="p0430">The study was approved by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee of Humanitas Clinical and Research Center and by the Italian Ministry of Health, protocol n.473/2017-PR.</p></sec><sec id="s0120"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="p0435">Not applicable.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s0125"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p id="p0440">The data that support the findings of this study are included in this article or available from the corresponding author upon request.</p></sec><sec id="s0130"><title>Declaration of competing interest</title><p id="p0445">The authors declare that they have no known competing financial interests or personal relationships that could have appeared to influence the work reported in this paper.</p></sec></ack></back></article>