<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="brief-report"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Intensive Care Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Intensive Care Med</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Intensive Care Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0342-4642</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1432-1238</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer Berlin Heidelberg</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Berlin/Heidelberg</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31650184</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6954141</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">5831</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00134-019-05831-7</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Less is more in Intensive Care</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Less is more, but are we doing enough?</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-3862-169X</contrib-id><name><surname>&#x000d1;amendys-Silva</surname><given-names>Silvio A.</given-names></name><address><email>snamendyss@medicasur.org.mx</email><email>snamendys@incan.edu.mx</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.414741.3</institution-id><institution>Department of Critical Care Medicine, </institution><institution>Hospital Medica Sur, </institution></institution-wrap>Mexico City, Mexico </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.419167.c</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1777 1207</institution-id><institution>Department of Critical Care Medicine, </institution><institution>Instituto Nacional de Cancerologia, </institution></institution-wrap>Mexico City, Mexico </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.416850.e</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0698 4037</institution-id><institution>Division of Pulmonary, Anesthesia and Critical Care Medicine, </institution><institution>Instituto Nacional de Ciencias Medicas y Nutricion Salvador Zubiran, </institution></institution-wrap>Mexico City, Mexico </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>24</day><month>10</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>24</day><month>10</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>46</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>113</fpage><lpage>115</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>8</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>10</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits any noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made.</license-p></license></permissions><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Springer-Verlag GmbH Germany, part of Springer Nature 2020</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p id="Par1">Knox and Pickkers proposed that the concept &#x0201c;less is more&#x0201d; applies to the treatment of critically ill patients in the intensive care unit (ICU) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. As intensivists, we need to focus on the quality of care for our critically ill patients and on reducing health care costs by eliminating waste in our health care systems. &#x0201c;Less is more&#x0201d;, but we should ensure that sufficient health care services are provided to critically ill patients to improve patient outcomes. Doing less must not be confounded with doing nothing. Because each patient&#x02019;s clinical scenario is unique, &#x0201c;less is more&#x0201d; is not equivalent to stopping diagnostic or therapeutic interventions to reduce expenses or closing the doors of ICUs to critically ill patients and sending them home.</p><p id="Par2">The distinction between cost and value is critical. High-cost interventions may provide good value because these interventions are highly beneficial; conversely, low-cost interventions may have little or no value if they provide little benefit [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Interventions that provide minimal or no health benefit typically have low value regardless of the cost. The elimination of these ineffective interventions and procedures would reduce both potential harm to patients and excess costs without adversely affecting the hard outcomes (safety) while providing substantial health care cost savings.</p><p id="Par3">High-value care is backed by evidence that the interventions confer benefit for patients and that the likelihood of benefits exceeds that of probable harm or, more broadly, that the added costs of the intervention provide proportional added benefits relative to the alternatives [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Physicians often have a poor understanding of patients&#x02019; values and incorrectly assume that some patients would prefer to avoid aggressive or invasive interventions while other patients would favor more care rather than less care [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Critical care clinicians working in the ICU must minimize both risks and harm to critically ill patients. At the end of the twentieth century, Chassin and Galvin defined overuse as the provision of medical services when the potential for harm exceeds the potential for benefits [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. <italic>Primum non nocere</italic>-first, do no harm-prohibits any risk and therefore effectively prevents any meaningful therapeutic endeavor [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. This motto represents the ethical and professional responsibility of health care professionals to avoid overusing and misusing care that does not benefit patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>].</p><p id="Par4">Courtright and colleagues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>] proposed that fellowship programs focus on four major educational domains: fostering a value-based culture, providing a robust didactic experience, engaging trainees in process improvement projects, and encouraging scholarship&#x000a0;[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Adequate financial investment in human resources and talent development (sufficient education, research, quality and quantity of ICU nurses or physicians) is lacking in low- and middle-income countries (LMICs). ICUs in LMICs should implement strategies that allow the establishment of an empowered nurses&#x02019; team that can influence productivity, resources, information, and opportunities to learn and grow professionally. Nurse&#x000a0;or physicians retention strategies to reduce turnover will have a positive effect on professional satisfaction, associated costs, patient care, quality, and patient safety.</p><p id="Par5">Critically ill patients are heterogeneous, and few interventions can be applied equally to all patients. In many ICUs of LMICs, some clinical practices depend on the availability of medical devices and supplies. They are often based on anecdotes, individual experiences or local practices (&#x0201c;that is the way it is done here&#x0201d;) and have been passed down from generation to generation without academic support suggesting positive clinical impacts on patients; these approaches should be abandoned [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Data on the treatment outcomes of critically ill patients generated by clinical trials in LMICs are rare. Therefore, intensivists in resource-limited settings must treat their patients based on the literature from high-income countries (HICs).</p><p id="Par6">Sometimes &#x0201c;less is more&#x0201d;, and sometimes &#x0201c;more is more&#x0201d;. We need &#x0201c;less&#x0201d; aerospace medicine for LMICs, and &#x0201c;more&#x0201d; interventions are needed to improve the care and outcomes of ICU patients (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The intensivists of LMICs should actively participate in the development of recommendations for the treatment of critically ill patients in resource-limited settings such as those developed by the Global Intensive Care Working Group of the European Society of Intensive Care Medicine (ESICM) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. In addition, we must improve the decision-making processes and procedures used in our ICUs.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Examples of interventions to improve the care and outcomes of critically ill patients in low- and middle-income countries</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td align="left">Change organizational culture to improve critical care performance</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Strategies for improving knowledge of the epidemiology and outcomes of critically ill patients in our countries</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Continuous quality improvement; redesign processes to facilitate appropriate and efficient utilization of critical care services</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Development of a management algorithm to guide intensive care unit (ICU) admission</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Implement preventive measures to avoid potentially inappropriate treatments in the ICU</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Incorporate a high-value care curriculum into critical care fellowship training [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">In-service training for healthcare workforce (e.g., physicians, nurses, allied health professionals) to improve the care of critically ill patients</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Local consensus processes aimed at promoting the implementation of and adherence to guidelines (e.g., guidelines on the management of sepsis and acute respiratory distress syndrome) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><p>Strategies for decreasing ICU-acquired healthcare-associated infections [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]:</p><p>&#x000a0;a. Interventions to improve hand hygiene compliance in the ICU</p><p>&#x000a0;b. Strategies to enhance rational use of antibiotics in the ICU</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Development of strategies to improve prescribing practices (e.g., crystalloids and/or colloids, antibiotics, vasoactive agents, corticosteroids) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Strategies for improving the care of critically ill obstetric patients</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Strategies for improving the care of critically ill trauma patients</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Strategies for improving the care of critically ill patients during natural disasters (e.g., hurricanes, earthquakes) and epidemics (e.g., influenza, cholera, dengue shock syndrome)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p id="Par7">The implementation of less invasive procedures in the ICU that are quicker and simpler or those that avoid high-cost pharmacological treatments may actually mean &#x0201c;more&#x0201d; for ICU patients. Recently, several studies have presented the results of interventions that were not associated with better outcomes or clinical impacts for critically ill patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Regardless of how many well-conducted studies indicate the advantages of changes in clinical practices, the culture of the ICU, customs (traditions) and medical beliefs drive practices in critical and intensive care settings.</p><p id="Par8">Less is more, but are we doing enough? That is the question. As intensivists in LMICs, we must know and understand the epidemiological characteristics of the patients we treat, and we need to create knowledge and &#x0201c;innovations&#x0201d; for in-house standardized clinical decisions, such as diagnoses, tests, or treatment selection. This information can be applied to other patients in our countries. There are some ways to guide the ongoing development of critical care in resource-limited settings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]:<list list-type="order"><list-item><p id="Par9">Develop hospital-based needs assessments with plans for stepwise interventions;</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par10">Focus on training to leverage available human resources, emphasizing standardized protocols;</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par11">Prioritize the development of relevant technology that is affordable and maintainable;</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par12">Use what is appropriate from HICs;</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par13">Stimulate interorganizational collaboration, networking and sharing of best practices.</p></list-item></list></p><p id="Par14">&#x0201c;Innovation in intensive care is not new&#x0201d; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. There is currently a great need to improve the quality of ICU patients&#x02019; management in resource-poor settings to provide effective and efficient intensive care services directed at improving outcomes in critically ill patients. Intensive care medicine research agendas from LMICs and HICs could reflect an excellent symbiosis (a win&#x02013;win strategy) to achieve that goal.</p></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher's Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Author's Note</bold></p><p>The views expressed by author reflect his personal views and do not necessarily reflect the official position or policy of his institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><notes notes-type="ethics"><title>Compliance with ethical standards</title><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflicts of interest</title><p id="Par15">The author declares that he has no conflicts of interest.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kox</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pickkers</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>&#x0201c;Less is more&#x0201d; in critically ill patients: not too intensive</article-title><source>JAMA Intern Med</source><year>2013</year><volume>173</volume><fpage>1369</fpage><lpage>1372</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamainternmed.2013.6702</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23752755</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Owens</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Qaseem</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Shekelle</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical Guidelines Committee of the American College of Physicians. High-value, cost-conscious health care: concepts for clinicians to evaluate the benefits, harms, and costs of medical interventions</article-title><source>Ann Intern Med</source><year>2011</year><volume>154</volume><fpage>174</fpage><lpage>180</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7326/0003-4819-154-3-201102010-00007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21282697</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elshaug</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenthal</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Lavis</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Levers for addressing medical underuse and overuse: achieving high-value health care</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2017</year><volume>390</volume><fpage>191</fpage><lpage>202</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(16)32586-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28077228</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>&#x000d1;amendys-Silva</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>High value care in critical care medicine</article-title><source>Med Crit</source><year>2019</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>97</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brownlee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chalkidou</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Doust</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Evidence for overuse of medical services around the world</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2017</year><volume>390</volume><fpage>156</fpage><lpage>168</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(16)32585-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28077234</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chassin</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Galvin</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The urgent need to improve health care quality. Institute of Medicine National Roundtable on Health Care Quality</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>1998</year><volume>280</volume><fpage>1000</fpage><lpage>1005</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.280.11.1000</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9749483</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gifford</surname><given-names>RW</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name></person-group><article-title>Primum non nocere</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>1977</year><volume>238</volume><fpage>589</fpage><lpage>590</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.1977.03280070029018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">577959</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hood</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name><name><surname>Weinberger</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>High value, cost-conscious care: an international imperative</article-title><source>Eur J Intern Med</source><year>2012</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>495</fpage><lpage>498</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejim.2012.03.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22863424</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Courtright</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Weinberger</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Meeting the milestones. Strategies for including high-value care education in pulmonary and critical care fellowship training</article-title><source>Ann Am Thorac Soc</source><year>2015</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>574</fpage><lpage>578</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1513/AnnalsATS.201501-035OI</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25714122</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dunser</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Festic</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Dondorp</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Global Intensive Care Working Group of European Society of Intensive Care Medicine. Recommendations for sepsis management in resource-limited settings</article-title><source>Intensiv Care Med</source><year>2012</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>557</fpage><lpage>574</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00134-012-2468-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Serpa Neto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Festic</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ventilatory support of patients with sepsis or septic shock in resource-limited settings</article-title><source>Intensiv Care Med</source><year>2016</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>100</fpage><lpage>103</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00134-015-4070-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Musa</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Murthy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kissoon</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pediatric sepsis and septic shock management in resource-limited settings</article-title><source>Intensiv Care Med</source><year>2016</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>2037</fpage><lpage>2039</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00134-016-4382-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Combes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hajage</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Capellier</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Extracorporeal membrane oxygenation for severe acute respiratory distress syndrome</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2018</year><volume>378</volume><fpage>1965</fpage><lpage>1975</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa1800385</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29791822</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barbar</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Clere-Jehl</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bourredjem</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Timing of renal-replacement therapy in patients with acute kidney injury and sepsis</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2018</year><volume>379</volume><fpage>1431</fpage><lpage>1442</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa1803213</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30304656</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beitler</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarge</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Banner-Goodspeed</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effect of titrating positive end-expiratory pressure (peep) with an esophageal pressure-guided strategy vs an empirical high peep-fio2 strategy on death and days free from mechanical ventilation among patients with acute respiratory distress syndrome: a randomized clinical trial</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2019</year><volume>321</volume><fpage>846</fpage><lpage>857</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.2019.0555</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30776290</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shehabi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Howe</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name><surname>Bellomo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Early sedation with dexmedetomidine in critically ill patients</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2019</year><volume>380</volume><fpage>2506</fpage><lpage>2517</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa1904710</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31112380</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Brower</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Early neuromuscular blockade in the acute respiratory distress syndrome</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2019</year><volume>380</volume><fpage>1997</fpage><lpage>2008</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMoa1901686</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31112383</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dondorp</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Limmathurotsakul</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashley</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>What&#x02019;s wrong in the control of antimicrobial resistance in critically ill patients from low- and middle-income countries?</article-title><source>Intensiv Care Med</source><year>2018</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>79</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00134-017-4795-z</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Backer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Cecconi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Challenges in the management of septic shock: a narrative review</article-title><source>Intensiv Care Med</source><year>2019</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>420</fpage><lpage>433</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00134-019-05544-x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Riviello</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><name><surname>Letchford</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Achieng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Newton</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Critical care in resource-poor settings: lessons learned and future directions</article-title><source>Crit Care Med</source><year>2011</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>860</fpage><lpage>867</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/CCM.0b013e318206d6d5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21297458</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>