<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="case-report"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Med Case Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Med Case Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Medical Case Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1752-1947</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31924259</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6954518</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2318</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13256-019-2318-y</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Occurrence of abscesses during treatment with pazopanib in metastatic renal cancer: a case report</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Puliafito</surname><given-names>Ivana</given-names></name><address><email>dott.ssapuliafito@mail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Russo</surname><given-names>Alessio</given-names></name><address><email>alessio.russo@grupposamed.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sciacca</surname><given-names>Dorotea</given-names></name><address><email>dorotea.sciacca@grupposame.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Puglisi</surname><given-names>Caterina</given-names></name><address><email>caterina.puglisi@gruposamed.com</email><email>caterina.puglisi@grupposamed.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Giuffrida</surname><given-names>Dario</given-names></name><address><email>dario.giuffrida@grupposamed.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Experimental Oncology, Mediterranean Institute of Oncology, via Penninazzo 7, Viagrande, I-95029 Catania, Italy </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>IOM Ricerca srl, via Penninazzo 11, Viagrande, I-95029 Catania, Italy </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>11</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>11</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>7</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>5</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>18</day><month>11</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s). 2020</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Pazopanib is a multitarget tyrosine kinase inhibitor used in the treatment of renal cancer and soft tissue sarcoma. Its use is commonly associated with a number of side effects, such as hemorrhagic diathesis, neutropenia, leukopenia, thrombocytopenia, nausea, vomiting, abdominal pain, increased serum aspartate aminotransferase, increased serum alanine aminotransferase, decreased serum glucose, increased serum bilirubin, decreased serum phosphate and magnesium, fatigue, hypertension, diarrhea, anorexia, proteinuria, and hypothyroidism. Abscesses of metastases caused by pazopanib administration are rarely reported in the literature.</p></sec><sec><title>Case presentation</title><p id="Par2">We report a case of abscesses of lung metastases related to pazopanib in a patient with metastatic renal cancer. The patient was a 53-year-old Caucasian man who developed abscesses of lung metastases during the first 3 months of treatment with pazopanib. The abscesses resolved after 1 month by stopping pazopanib and administering adequate antibiotic therapy.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par3">We conclude that abscesses of metastases could be a rare side effect occurring during treatment with pazopanib in patients with renal cancer.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Pazopanib</kwd><kwd>Abscesses of lung metastases</kwd><kwd>Drug-related adverse effects</kwd><kwd>Metastatic renal cancer</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par7">Pazopanib (Votrient; Novartis, East Hanover, NJ, USA) is a tyrosine kinase inhibitor used to treat kidney cancer and soft tissue sarcoma (STS). This drug is a multikinase inhibitor that has been demonstrated to inhibit vascular endothelial growth factor receptors (VEGFR-1, -2, and&#x000a0;-3), platelet-derived growth factor receptor-&#x003b1; and -&#x003b2;, fibroblast growth factor receptor-1 and -3, and c-KIT. This inhibition affects tumor growth and inhibits angiogenesis, thereby slowing or stopping cancer cell proliferation and spread of malignancies. Furthermore, pazopanib binds to various physiological receptors and ion channels, such as histamine, opioid, serotonergic, dopaminergic, cholinergic, glutamate, adenosine, and adrenergic receptors and calcium, potassium, and sodium ion channels. Common adverse effects of pazopanib include headache, loss of appetite, weight loss, nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, erythrodysesthesia, changes in hair or skin color, and joint or muscle pain.</p><p id="Par8">The efficacy and safety of pazopanib were evaluated in a phase III randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>] that enrolled 435 patients with locally advanced or metastatic renal cell carcinoma. The study results indicated that Votrient significantly prolonged progression-free survival in comparison with placebo, both in the overall study population and in the cytokine-pretreated patients. The median progression-free survival was 9.2&#x02009;months for patients who received Votrient and 4.2&#x02009;months for patients in the placebo arm. Regarding safety, the study highlighted that most of the treatment-emergent adverse events were grade 1 or 2, even though grade 3/4 hypertension and diarrhea were observed with appreciable incidence and four pazopanib-treated patients had fatal adverse effects.</p><p id="Par9">The efficacy and safety of pazopanib were evaluated also in patients with metastatic soft tissue sarcoma (STS) that achieved progression despite previous standard chemotherapy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>].</p><p id="Par10">In this report, we describe a case of abscesses of lung metastases related to pazopanib in a patient with metastatic renal cancer.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Case presentation</title><p id="Par11">A 53-year-old Caucasian man was admitted to our hospital with&#x000a0;back pain in March 2016. He was a heavy smoker with a 30-pack-year smoking history. He had had hypertension for 2&#x02009;years. Regarding his medical history, there was nothing in particular to note apart from metastatic renal cancer and its complications. Indeed, on physical examination, the patient appeared well.</p><p id="Par12">The patient underwent computed tomography (CT), which showed a mass in the left kidney (75&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;53&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;105 mm), as well as lung and liver metastases, confirmed by magnetic resonance imaging examination.</p><p id="Par13">He underwent hepatic biopsy with a negative result because of exiguity of the sample. The patient received left radical nephrectomy and splenectomy in April 2016, and postoperative histopathology revealed clear cell carcinoma of the kidney. In May 2016, the patient was admitted to our hospital again&#x000a0;because of kidney failure and electrolyte alterations.</p><p id="Par14">A CT scan at that time confirmed lung and hepatic metastases, and the patient received supportive care with resolution of metabolic alterations (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a).
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p><bold>a</bold> Basal computed tomography. <bold>b</bold> Computed tomography slice showing necrotizing metastases with cavitation on lung similar to abscesses after 3 months of treatment. <bold>c</bold> Computed tomography slice showing resolution of abscesses 1 month after stopping treatment with pazopanib</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13256_2019_2318_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p><p id="Par15">In June 2016, he started treatment with pazopanib 800&#x02009;mg daily for metastatic renal cancer.</p><p id="Par16">After 3 months, he had a repeat CT scan (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>b), which revealed evidence of necrotizing metastases with cavitation on the lung similar to abscesses in the absence of fever. He stopped pazopanib and started therapy with antibiotics as suggested by a pneumologist.</p><p id="Par17">One month after starting antibiotics, a CT scan showed resolution of the patient&#x02019;s abscesses but progressive disease (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>c).</p></sec><sec id="Sec3"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par18">Pazopanib is a multitargeted tyrosine kinase inhibitor that principally inhibits VEGFR, producing block of tumor angiogenesis and growth. Pazopanib is currently approved for the treatment of renal cell carcinoma and advanced STS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>].</p><p id="Par19">Our patient had a rare case of necrotizing lung metastases with cavitation induced by pazopanib.</p><p id="Par20">Cases of abscesses have been reported in patients with STS treated with pazopanib [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>].</p><p id="Par21">Pulmonary abscess is a cavitation containing pus and products of necrosis with perilesional inflammatory area of variable dimensions. Common bacteria detectable in pus include <italic>Streptococcus</italic> spp.</p><p id="Par22">In our patient, a possible mechanism of abscess origin could be necrosis of metastases because pazopanib works by decreasing the blood supply to the cancer. Suppuration of lung metastases could be secondary to bronchial obstruction or to superinfection of the central area of metastases not receiving blood. This process causes necrosis.</p><p id="Par23">Another possibility is immunodepression in patients with malignancy.</p><p id="Par24">The adverse event in our patient required interruption of pazopanib because consequences could be severe, including creation of communicating cavitations, pleural empyema, hemoptysis, diffusion of infection with migration of septic embolus, and chronicity of abscess.</p><p id="Par25">In 2014, a single-center case series by Verschoor and Gelderblom was published [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. They reported 6 cases of pneumothorax among over 43 patients with STS treated with pazopanib in their center. Pneumothorax was reported as an adverse event with a percentage of 3.3% in the phase III registered trial&#x000a0;[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>] supporting use of pazopanib for locally advanced or metastatic nonliposarcoma STS after prior treatment with doxorubicin and/or ifosfamide. In that study, the percentage of pneumothorax was 14%, superior to that reported in a registered trial. The six patients who developed pneumothorax during or after pazopanib therapy had subpleural lung metastases or pleural metastases. After the start of pazopanib treatment, patients had necrotizing lung metastases with cavitation or malignant pleural effusion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. No case of pneumothorax was reported in patients with renal cell carcinoma receiving pazopanib.</p><p id="Par26">Pazopanib was tolerated in most clinical studies. The most commonly reported adverse events in patients with renal cancer treated with pazopanib were fatigue, diarrhea, and hypertension [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>].</p><p id="Par27">The relationship between pazopanib treatment and pulmonary abscesses can be supported by regression of the abscesses after interruption of treatment and antibiotic therapy.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par28">We suggest that abscesses that develop after pazopanib administration should be considered a rare toxicity after excluding other causes. Pazopanib should be stopped according to the severity of the clinical situation.</p></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>CT</term><def><p id="Par4">Computed tomography</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>STS</term><def><p id="Par5">Soft tissue sarcoma</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>VEGFR</term><def><p id="Par6">Vascular endothelial growth factor receptor</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors gratefully acknowledge the patient involved in the study.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>GD coordinated the study. PI and PC wrote the manuscript. RA and SD were involved in the diagnosis and management of the patient. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>No source of funding.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>The datasets created during and/or analyzed during this case are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></notes><notes><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par29">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par30">Written informed consent was obtained from the patient for publication of this case report and any accompanying images. A copy of the written consent is available for review by the Editor-in-Chief of this journal.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par31">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sternberg</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>ID</given-names></name><name><surname>Mardiak</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Szczylik</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagstaff</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Barrios</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Salman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gladkov</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kavina</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zarb&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>McCann</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Pandite</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Roychowdhury</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawkins</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pazopanib in locally advanced or metastatic renal cell carcinoma: result of randomized phase III trial</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>2010</year><volume>28</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1061</fpage><lpage>1068</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/JCO.2009.23.9764</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20100962</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van der Graaf</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name><name><surname>Blay</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Chawla</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Bui-Nguyen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Casali</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>Sch&#x000f6;ffski</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Aglietta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Staddon</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Beppu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Cesne</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gelderblom</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Judson</surname><given-names>IR</given-names></name><name><surname>Araki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ouali</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Marreaud</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hodge</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Dewji</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Coens</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Demetri</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name><surname>Fletcher</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Dei Tos</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Hohenberger</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>EORTC Soft Tissue and Bone Sarcoma Group; PALETTE study group. Pazopanib for metastatic soft-tissue sarcoma (PALETTE): a randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled phase 3 trial</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2012</year><volume>379</volume><fpage>1879</fpage><lpage>1886</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(12)60651-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22595799</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miyamoto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kakutani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanashi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kinoshita</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishikawa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Drug review: pazopanib</article-title><source>Jpn J Clin Oncol</source><year>2018</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>503</fpage><lpage>513</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jjco/hyy053</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29684209</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Dowlati</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Infante</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishioka</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hodge</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Gainer</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Arumugham</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Suttle</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Dar</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lager</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Burris</surname><given-names>HA</given-names><suffix>3rd</suffix></name></person-group><article-title>Phase I study of pazopanib in combination with weekly paclitaxel in patients with advanced solid tumors</article-title><source>Oncologist</source><year>2010</year><volume>15</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1253</fpage><lpage>1261</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1634/theoncologist.2010-0095</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21147873</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Verschoor</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gelderblom</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pneumothorax as adverse event in patients with lung metastases of soft tissue sarcoma treated with pazopanib: a single reference centre case series</article-title><source>Clin Sarcoma Res</source><year>2014</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>14</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/2045-3329-4-14</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25302110</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matrana</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Baiomy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Alamri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Shetty</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Teegavarapu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalra</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Atkinson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Corn</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Jonasch</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Elsayes</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Tannir</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Outcomes of patients with metastatic non-clear-cell renal cell carcinoma treated with pazopanib</article-title><source>Clin Genitourin Cancer</source><year>2017</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>e205</fpage><lpage>e208</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clgc.2016.07.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27568124</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bersanelli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Maines</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Facchini</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Gelsomino</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Zustovich</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Santoni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Verri</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>De Giorgi</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Masini</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Morelli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Vitale</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Sava</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Prati</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Librici</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fraccon</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Fornarini</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Maruzzo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Leonardi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Caffo</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>First-line pazopanib in non-clear-cell renal carcinoma: the Italian retrospective multicenter PANORAMA study</article-title><source>Clin Genitourin Cancer</source><year>2017</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>e609</fpage><lpage>e614</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clgc.2016.12.024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28108284</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rha</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pazopanib for the treatment of non-clear cell renal cell carcinoma: a single-arm, open-label, multicenter, phase II study</article-title><source>Cancer Res Treat</source><year>2018</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>488</fpage><lpage>494</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4143/crt.2016.584</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28546525</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Agarwala</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramaswamy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Patil</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name><name><surname>Noronha</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Menon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Popat</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><name><surname>Sable</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Prabhash</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Treatment outcomes of metastatic nonclear cell renal cell carcinoma: a single institution retrospective analysis</article-title><source>South Asian J Cancer</source><year>2018</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>226</fpage><lpage>230</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/sajc.sajc_22_18</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30430089</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Srinivas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Stein</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Teltsch</surname><given-names>DY</given-names></name><name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cisar</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramaswamy</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Real-world chart review study of adverse events management in patients taking tyrosine kinase inhibitors to treat metastatic renal cell carcinoma</article-title><source>J Oncol Pharm Pract</source><year>2018</year><volume>24</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>574</fpage><lpage>583</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1078155217719583</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28732453</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>