<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="review-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Support Care Cancer</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Support Care Cancer</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Supportive Care in Cancer</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0941-4355</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1433-7339</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer Berlin Heidelberg</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Berlin/Heidelberg</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31792879</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6954134</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">5136</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00520-019-05136-x</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Review Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Health-related quality of life in adult patients with brain metastases after stereotactic radiosurgery: a systematic, narrative review</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-1801-9845</contrib-id><name><surname>Verhaak</surname><given-names>Eline</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-6989-1855</contrib-id><name><surname>Gehring</surname><given-names>Karin</given-names></name><address><email>k.gehring@tilburguniversity.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hanssens</surname><given-names>Patrick E. J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-2574-4850</contrib-id><name><surname>Aaronson</surname><given-names>Neil K.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sitskoorn</surname><given-names>Margriet M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.416373.4</institution-id><institution>Gamma Knife Center, </institution><institution>Elisabeth-TweeSteden Hospital, </institution></institution-wrap>Hilvarenbeekseweg 60, 5022 GC Tilburg, The Netherlands </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.416373.4</institution-id><institution>Department of Neurosurgery, </institution><institution>Elisabeth-TweeSteden Hospital, </institution></institution-wrap>Hilvarenbeekseweg 60, 5022 GC Tilburg, The Netherlands </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.12295.3d</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0943 3265</institution-id><institution>Department of Cognitive Neuropsychology, </institution><institution>Tilburg University, </institution></institution-wrap>Warandelaan 2, 5037 AB Tilburg, The Netherlands </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.430814.a</institution-id><institution>Division of Psychosocial Research and Epidemiology, </institution><institution>Netherlands Cancer Institute, </institution></institution-wrap>Plesmanlaan 121, 1066 CX Amsterdam, The Netherlands </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>2</day><month>12</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>2</day><month>12</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>28</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>473</fpage><lpage>484</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>18</day><month>1</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>10</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Purpose</title><p id="Par1">A growing number of patients with brain metastases (BM) are being treated with stereotactic radiosurgery (SRS), and the importance of evaluating the impact of SRS on the health-related quality of life (HRQoL) in these patients has been increasingly acknowledged. This systematic review summarizes the current knowledge about the HRQoL of patients with BM after SRS.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">We searched EMBASE, Medline Ovid, Web-of-Science, the Cochrane Database, PsycINFO Ovid, and Google Scholar up to November 15, 2018. Studies in patients with BM in which HRQoL was assessed before and after SRS and analyzed over time were included. Studies including populations of several types of brain cancer and/or several types of treatments were included if the results for patients with BM and treatment with SRS alone were described separately.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">Out of 3638 published articles, 9 studies met the eligibility criteria and were included. In 4 out of 7 studies on group results, overall HRQoL of patients with BM remained stable after SRS. In small study samples of longer-term survivors, overall HRQoL remained stable up to 12 months post-SRS. Contradictory results were reported for physical and general/global HRQoL, which might be explained by the different questionnaires that were used.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par4">In general, SRS does not have significant negative effects on patients&#x02019; overall HRQoL over time. Future research is needed to analyze different aspects of HRQoL, differences in individual changes in HRQoL after SRS, and factors that influence these changes. These studies should take into account several methodological issues as discussed in this review.</p></sec><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>The online version of this article (10.1007/s00520-019-05136-x) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Brain metastases</kwd><kwd>Cancer</kwd><kwd>Health-related quality of life</kwd><kwd>Neoplasm metastasis</kwd><kwd>Patient-reported outcome measures</kwd><kwd>Radiosurgery</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100001826</institution-id><institution>ZonMw</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>842003006 and 842003008</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Springer-Verlag GmbH Germany, part of Springer Nature 2020</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par5">Brain metastases (BM) originate from a malignancy outside the central nervous system. Most patients diagnosed with BM have primary lung cancer, breast cancer, or melanoma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Partly due to improved imaging such as MRI and improved systemic treatment of the primary cancer, the number of patients with BM is increasing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>].</p><p id="Par6">Traditionally, most patients with BM have been treated with whole brain radiation therapy (WBRT) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. However, due to advances in the technology, and the increased availability, of stereotactic radiosurgery (SRS) and concerns about the long-term side effects of WBRT, radiation treatment is shifting toward SRS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. The high precision of SRS spares healthy brain tissue, reducing the risks of long-term side effects [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Although SRS is usually delivered in one fraction, it can be delivered in up to five fractions using a linear accelerator, particle beam accelerator or multisource Cobalt-60 unit [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>].</p><p id="Par7">Although the prognosis still remains poor [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>], life expectancy in patients with BM is increasing due to improvements in systemic treatments of the primary tumor [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. Therefore, maintaining a good health-related quality of life (HRQoL) as long as possible is an important [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>] primary objective in this patient group [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Consequently, management of BM is no longer focused solely on survival, but also on HRQoL and cognitive functioning of patients with BM after treatment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>].</p><p id="Par8">Authors of previous clinical studies and reviews concluded that future trials that include patients with BM should assess HRQoL as outcome measure, to inform clinical practice (e.g., make informed treatment decisions, assess the efficacy of treatment, and inform patients about HRQoL over time) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. In addition, HRQoL is important to evaluate as patients with BM rated HRQoL as the most important factor to be considered in choosing among available treatment options [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>], as results from standard assessment of HRQoL in clinical practice may help communication between patients and clinicians [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>], and as HRQoL appears to be an independent prognostic factor for survival [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>].</p><p id="Par9">To our knowledge, no systematic review has been conducted that focuses primarily on HRQoL outcomes after treatment with SRS alone in patients with BM. A synthesis of the available research findings can help to better understand patients&#x02019; HRQoL over time after SRS and can provide directions for future clinical trials. Ultimately, patients and physicians can be better informed on what to expect after SRS in terms of HRQoL. This systematic review summarizes the current knowledge on (changes in) the HRQoL of this patient group after SRS.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Literature search</title><p id="Par10">A systematic literature search was conducted to identify studies in which adult patients with BM were treated with SRS, and HRQoL was assessed by means of a self-report questionnaire. EMBASE, Medline Ovid, Web-of-Science, the Cochrane Database, PsycINFO Ovid, and Google Scholar were searched up to November 15, 2018. Search terms were verified, and search strategies were built and performed by a biomedical information specialist of the library service of the Erasmus Medical Center, The Netherlands. Studies had to be published as empirical research articles in peer-reviewed journals and written in English, German, or Dutch. Case-report studies were excluded. Studies with an HRQoL assessment before and at least one HRQoL assessment after SRS alone were included. Within-group analyses had to be performed on HRQoL data. Studies that included a heterogeneous sample of patients in terms of type of brain-involved malignancies and/or studies in which different types of treatment were evaluated, were included only if the results for patients with BM treated with SRS alone were reported separately. Inclusion and exclusion criteria in terms of PICOs (patient, intervention, comparison, outcome) and search strategies are presented in Online Resource <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Study selection</title><p id="Par11">All studies were screened by the first author (E.V.) based on title and abstract. If eligibility was not clear from the title and abstract, the full text was screened. Papers that potentially met the eligibility criteria after full text screening were also reviewed by the second author (K.G.). Consensus was reached in all cases. This review is a qualitative synthesis of empirical studies. The same two authors extracted data from the included studies and results were compared; there were no disagreements. Reference lists of eligible articles were screened for additional articles.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Assessment of included studies</title><p id="Par12">Factors that were cross-checked and critically evaluated among the studies included the following: type of cohorts/study samples included (e.g., different histologies of primary cancers), prior BM treatment, compliance or reasons for dropout reported, primary endpoints, HRQoL questionnaire used, timing of baseline HRQoL assessment, and timing and place of post-measurements.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec7"><title>Selected studies</title><p id="Par13">The systematic literature search identified 3638 unique records (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). After screening title and abstract, 1290 full texts were considered, and ultimately 9 studies were included in the review (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>PRISMA flowchart of the study selection</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="520_2019_5136_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Prospective studies of the HRQoL of patients with BM undergoing SRS</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>First author, year<break/>Study design<break/>Modality (dose)</th><th>Participants (<italic>n</italic>), median (range)</th><th>Histology (<italic>n</italic>)</th><th>Primary endpoint</th><th>HRQoL questionnaire<break/>Scales</th><th>HRQoL after SRS<sup>b</sup></th><th>Comments</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="7">Studies using brain cancer&#x02013;specific HRQoL questionnaires</td></tr><tr><td><p> Skeie, 2017 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]</p><p>Single-arm study</p><p>Gamma knife</p><p>(mean 22.7; 15&#x02013;25 Gy)</p></td><td><p>97 patients with 1&#x02013;6 BM</p><p>Age 64 (32&#x02013;86)</p><p>Female (51)</p><p>Mean BM volume 6.3 cm<sup>3</sup> (0.072&#x02013;25.2)</p><p>KPS 80 (60&#x02013;100)<sup>a</sup></p></td><td><p>Lung (45)</p><p>Colorectal (17)</p><p>Skin (12)</p><p>Other (23)</p></td><td>Health-related quality of life</td><td><p>FACT-Br</p><p>All 8 scales</p></td><td><p>Group level: stable HRQoL after SRS up to 12 months, except for general HRQoL.</p><p>Individual level: less or stable additional concerns (brain cancer subscale) for 64%, 60%, 66%, 72%, and 60% of the patients at respectively 1, 3, 6, 9, and 12 months (based on MCIDs; cutoff point unclear).</p></td><td><p>Prior treatment with the following: WBRT (<italic>n</italic> = 9), surgery (<italic>n</italic> = 6), surgery and WBRT (<italic>n</italic> = 5).</p><p>Follow-up questionnaires sent by mail.</p></td></tr><tr><td><p> Bragstad, 2017 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]</p><p>Single-arm study</p><p>Gamma knife (mean 40.4; 16&#x02013;25 Gy)</p></td><td><p>44 patients with 1&#x02013;5 BM</p><p>Age 62.8 (42&#x02013;82)</p><p>Female (19)</p><p>KPS 100 (5); 90 (14); 80 (9); 70 (10); &#x0003c; 70 (6)</p><p>Steroid use at GKRS (34)</p></td><td><p>NSCLC (39)</p><p>SCLC (5)</p></td><td>Health-related quality of life</td><td><p>FACT-Br</p><p>All 8 scales</p></td><td><p>Group level: stable HRQoL up to 12 months after SRS</p><p>Individual level: at 1 month (<italic>n</italic> = 39), 23 patients had less, 6 had stable, and 9 had more additional concerns (brain cancer subscale).</p></td><td><p>Only patients with primary lung cancer included.</p><p>Prior treatment with the following: surgery, WBRT, or surgery and WBRT (number of patients not reported).</p><p>Reasons for dropout not reported.</p><p>Follow-up questionnaires sent by mail.</p></td></tr><tr><td><p> Chang, 2007 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]</p><p>Single-arm study</p><p>(pilot)</p><p>Linear accelerator (median 20; 15&#x02013;24 Gy)</p></td><td><p>15 patients with 1&#x02013;3 BM</p><p>Age 64.9 (31.5&#x02013;77)</p><p>Female (10)</p><p>Total BM volume 1.76 cm<sup>3</sup> (0.16&#x02013;19.98)</p><p>KPS 90 (70&#x02013;100)<sup>a</sup></p></td><td><p>NSCLC (8)</p><p>Melanoma (4)</p><p>Renal cell (3)</p></td><td>Cognitive functioning</td><td><p>FACT-Br</p><p>One preselected total score; FACT-Brain score</p></td><td><p>Individual level: 11 patients with stable and 2 patients with declined HRQoL scores 1 month after SRS (based on the RCI).</p><p>For 4 out of 5 long-term survivors (patients with an evaluation &#x02265; 200 days after SRS) scores remained relatively stable up to their last evaluation after SRS (&#x000b1; 8.5 months); a decline was observed in a patient who was hospitalized because of edema.</p></td><td><p>Measurement of pretreatment HRQoL after SRS in an unknown number of patients.</p><p>Reasons for dropout not reported.</p><p>No report of mean HRQoL scores at all time points.</p></td></tr><tr><td><p> Kirkpatrick, 2015 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]</p><p>Single-arm study (randomized per lesion)</p><p>Linear accelerator (15&#x02013;24 Gy)</p></td><td><p>49 patients with 1&#x02013;3 BM</p><p>Age 61 (26&#x02013;87)</p><p>Female (33)</p><p>KPS 90 (70&#x02013;100)<sup>a</sup></p><p>Chemotherapy before SRS (28)</p><p>Chemotherapy after SRS (43)</p></td><td><p>NSCLC (25)</p><p>Melanoma (8)</p><p>Breast (6)</p><p>Other (10)</p></td><td>Local recurrence</td><td><p>FACT-Br</p><p>All 8 scales</p></td><td>Group level: stable HRQoL 3 months after SRS (<italic>n</italic> = 24).</td><td><p>Reasons for dropout not reported.</p><p>Poor compliance with HRQoL assessment.</p><p>Randomized per lesion to a 1- or 3-mm margin expansion group.</p></td></tr><tr><td><p> Habets, 2016 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]</p><p>Single-arm study</p><p>Linear accelerator (18&#x02013;24 Gy)</p></td><td><p>97 patients with 1&#x02013;4 BM</p><p>Mean age 63 (33&#x02013;82)</p><p>Female (51)</p><p>Total BM volume 7.8 cm<sup>3</sup> (0.12&#x02013;63.9)</p><p>KPS 80 (60&#x02013;100)</p><p>Chemotherapy &#x0003c; 3 months of SRS (13)</p><p>Use of corticosteroids (85)</p><p>Use of anti-epileptic drugs (21)</p></td><td><p>NSCLC (48)</p><p>Renal (12)</p><p>Melanoma (9)</p><p>Other (28)</p></td><td>Cognitive functioning</td><td><p>EORTC-QLQ-C30</p><p>All 9 scales and 6 single items</p><p>EORTC-QLQ-BN20</p><p>All 4 scales and 7 single items</p></td><td><p>Group level: worse scores on physical functioning, nausea, appetite loss, and (more bothered by) hair loss over 6 months&#x02019; time after SRS.</p><p>Other aspects of HRQoL were stable over time.</p></td><td><p>No report of mean HRQoL scores at follow-up.</p><p>Patients treated with WBRT during the study were no longer followed (<italic>n</italic> = 13).</p><p>BM with volumes &#x0003e; 13 cm<sup>3</sup> or near the brainstem were treated in 3 fractions of 8 Gy; other BM were treated in 1 fraction of 18&#x02013;21 Gy.</p></td></tr><tr><td><p> van der Meer, 2018 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]</p><p>Single-arm study</p><p>Linear accelerator (18&#x02013;24 Gy)</p></td><td><p>55 patients with 1&#x02013;4 BM</p><p>Mean age 63, SD 9</p><p>Female (30)</p><p>Total BM volume 7.3 cm<sup>3</sup> (0.12&#x02013;63.9)</p><p>KPS 80 (interquartile range 80&#x02013;90)</p><p>Chemotherapy (6)</p><p>Use of corticosteroids (48)</p><p>Use of anti-epileptic drugs (12)</p></td><td><p>NSCLC (27)</p><p>Renal (11)</p><p>Melanoma (4)</p><p>Other (13)</p></td><td>Cognitive functioning</td><td><p>EORTC-QLQ-C30</p><p>6 preselected scales; global health status, physical, emotional, role, cognitive functioning, and fatigue</p><p>EORTC-QLQ-BN20</p><p>2 preselected scales; motor dysfunction and communication deficits</p></td><td><p>Individual level, scale: at 3 months, on 4 out of 8 HRQoL scales, most patients had stable scores; on 3 scales, most patients had a decline in scores; and on 1 scale, most patients had improved scores. At 6 months, on 7 HRQoL scales, most patients had stable scores; and on 1 scale, most patients had worse scores (based on an increase or decrease of &#x02265; 10 points).</p><p>Individual level, patient: after 3 and 6 months, 22% and 21% of patients reported a decline on at least one HRQoL scale (other scales declined as well or remained stable), 12% and 18% an improvement on at least one HRQoL scale, 64% and 58% both a decline as an improvement, and 2% and 3% had stable scores on all HRQoL scales, respectively (based on an increase or decrease of &#x02265; 10 points).</p></td><td><p>No report of mean HRQoL scores at all time points.</p><p>Patients treated with WBRT during the study were no longer followed (number of patients not reported).</p><p>BM with volumes &#x0003e; 13 cm<sup>3</sup> or near the brainstem were treated in 3 fractions of 8 Gy; other BM were treated in 1 fraction of 18&#x02013;21 Gy.</p></td></tr><tr><td colspan="7">Studies using generic HRQoL questionnaires</td></tr><tr><td><p> Miller, 2017 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]</p><p>Single-arm</p><p>Gamma knife (median 22; 20&#x02013;24 Gy)</p></td><td><p>67 patients</p><p>Mean age 59, SD 11</p><p>Female (37)</p><p>KPS 80 (70&#x02013;90)</p><p>Chemotherapy in past month (67)</p></td><td><p>NSCLC (30)</p><p>Breast (14)</p><p>Melanoma (9)</p><p>Other (14)</p></td><td>Time to health state (EQ-5D index) failure</td><td><p>EQ-5D</p><p>All 5 dimensions</p></td><td><p>Group level: worse scores on all dimensions at patients&#x02019; last follow-up (analyzed on the basis of 122 treatments)</p><p>Individual level: overall health state failure in 28% and improvement in 24% of treatments (MCID of 0.1) and self-perceived health state failure in 50% and improvement in 41% of treatments (MCID of 10).</p></td><td><p>Limited patient characteristics (mostly per treatment).</p><p>Prior treatment with the following: WBRT (<italic>n</italic> = 41) and resection (<italic>n</italic> = 21).</p><p>Reasons for dropout not reported.</p><p>Measurement of pretreatment HRQoL after SRS in an unknown number of patients.</p><p>Mean HRQoL scores only reported at last follow-up.</p><p>Only HRQoL data at a patients&#x02019; last follow-up was analyzed.</p><p>HRQoL data analyzed per treatment.</p></td></tr><tr><td><p> Kotecha, 2017 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]</p><p>Single-arm study</p><p>Gamma knife (15&#x02013;24 Gy)</p></td><td><p>59 patients with 1&#x02013;11 BM</p><p>Baseline characteristics of the 27 patients with HRQoL assessment not reported</p></td><td>NA</td><td>Intracranial recurrence patterns after multiple SRS courses</td><td><p>EQ-5D</p><p>All 5 dimensions</p></td><td><p>Group level: longitudinal overall health state remained relatively stable over time. Worse scores on mobility, self-care, usual activities, overall health state, and self-perceived health state at patients&#x02019; last follow-up (data abstracted from a table).</p><p>Individual level: at patients&#x02019; last follow-up, most patients declined (48%, 54%) or improved (45%, 45%) on overall health state and self-perceived health state, respectively, based on the MCIDs (data abstracted from a table). At 1 year, most patients were free from HRQoL failure (overall health state 77%; self-perceived health state 69%).</p></td><td><p>patients who underwent a minimum of 3 SRS courses for BM were included.</p><p>Prior treatment with the following: WBRT (<italic>n</italic> = 19).</p><p>Reasons for dropout not reported.</p><p>Mean HRQoL scores only reported at last follow-up.</p><p>Only HRQoL data at a patients&#x02019; last follow-up was analyzed.</p></td></tr><tr><td><p> Randolph, 2017 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]</p><p>Single-arm study</p><p>Gamma knife (median 20; 10&#x02013;24 Gy)</p></td><td><p>114 patients with 1&#x02013;4 BM</p><p>Baseline characteristics of the 39 patients with HRQoL assessment not reported</p></td><td>NA</td><td><p>Local control</p><p>Distant control</p><p>Overall survival</p></td><td><p>SQLI</p><p>Total score</p></td><td><p>Group level: significant decline in HRQoL scores 6 and 12 months after SRS compared with baseline</p><p>No significant difference between 6 and 12 months after SRS.</p></td><td><p>Subgroup of geriatric patients (age &#x02265; 70).</p><p>Previous treatments not reported.</p><p>Reasons for dropout not reported.</p></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>BM</italic> brain metastases, <italic>EORTC-QLQ-BN20</italic> European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer Quality of Life Questionnaire Brain Cancer Module, <italic>EORTC-QLQ-C15-PAL</italic> European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer Quality of Life Questionnaire Core 15 Palliative care, <italic>EORTC-QLQ-C30</italic> European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer Quality of Life Questionnaire Core 30, <italic>EQ-5D</italic> EuroQol 5 Dimensions, <italic>FACT-Br</italic> Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy-Brain, <italic>HRQoL</italic> health-related quality of life, <italic>KPS</italic> Karnofsky Performance Status, <italic>MCID</italic> minimum clinically importance difference, <italic>n</italic> number of patients, <italic>NA</italic> not applicable, <italic>NSCLC</italic> non&#x02013;small cell lung cancer, <italic>RCI</italic> reliable change index, <italic>SCLC</italic> small cell lung cancer, <italic>SD</italic> standard deviation, <italic>SQLI</italic> Spitzer Quality of Life Index, <italic>SRS</italic> stereotactic radiosurgery, <italic>WBRT</italic> whole brain radiation therapy</p><p><sup>a</sup>Calculated from data presented in table with patient characteristics, <sup>b</sup>Group level: analyses of mean scores of the total group; individual level: number/percentage of patients with deviant scores according to a normative threshold/cutoff</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Characteristics of studies</title><p id="Par14">All studies included a heterogeneous group of patients with different primary histologies, except for one study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>], in which only patients with primary lung cancer were included. In one study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>], only geriatric patients (age &#x02265; 70) were included. In one other study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>], patients were included who already received 3 courses of SRS, whereas in most studies, patients were included before their first course of SRS. Baseline characteristics of patients with baseline HRQoL scores were not reported in two studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. For two studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>], a proportion of patients was also included in a subsequent study (respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]). Sample sizes in the 9 selected studies ranged from 15 to 97 patients. In most studies, patients were female (range 43.2 to 67.3%), had primary lung cancer (range 37.3 to 100%), and had a median Karnofsky Performance Status (KPS) score of 80 (range &#x0003c; 70 to 100) (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). In four studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>], patients with newly diagnosed BM were included; in four other studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>], patients received prior BM treatment; and in one study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>], it was not reported if patients received prior BM treatment. Reasons for dropout were not reported in 6 studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>], and in two studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>], reasons of dropout were reported, but without the numbers of patients (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>HRQoL assessments</title><p id="Par15">Results on HRQoL over time of all reviewed studies are presented in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. In three [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>] out of nine studies, HRQoL was the primary outcome measure. Four studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>] evaluated HRQoL both at the group level and at the individual level, two studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>] evaluated HRQoL at the group level only, and two studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>] evaluated HRQoL at the individual level only. In the studies reviewed, HRQoL was measured with 5 different self-report questionnaires. The most frequently used questionnaire was the brain cancer&#x02013;specific Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy Brain (FACT-Br), used in 4 studies (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). The most commonly investigated aspects of HRQoL at the group level were physical, general/global, social, and emotional aspects. In six studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>], cancer-specific HRQoL self-report questionnaires were used to measure HRQoL, and in three studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>], generic HRQoL self-report questionnaires were used to measure HRQoL. In two studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>], an unknown number of patients completed the &#x0201c;pretreatment&#x0201d;/baseline HRQoL measurement after SRS. Follow-up questionnaires were sent by mail in two studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>], and in the other studies, administration was scheduled to coincide with hospital visits after SRS. In five studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>], mean HRQoL scores during follow-up were not reported, although in two of them [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>], mean HRQoL at patients&#x02019; last follow-up were reported (this point is not the same for each patient).<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>HRQoL questionnaires</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>HRQoL instrument</th><th>Description</th><th>Scales/items</th><th>Used by</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy-Brain (FACT-Br)</td><td>The FACT-Br was developed for patients with primary brain tumors. Questions are answered on a 5-point Likert scale ranging from 0 (not at all) to 4 (very much). The FACT-Br consists of 5 subscales, 2 total scales, and 1 index. The FACT-General is a summary of general HRQoL and can be used in diverse patient groups. The FACT-Br combines the FACT-G with a disease-specific subscale score for patients with a brain tumor. The TOI is assumed to be more responsive to change after treatment than a total HRQoL score. Higher scores on each (sub)scale indicate better health-related quality of life [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. The FACT-Br has high validity and reliability coefficients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>] and is a valid measure for use in patients with brain metastases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>].</td><td><p>&#x02022; Five subscales</p><p>o Physical well-being</p><p>o Social/family well-being</p><p>o Emotional well-being</p><p>o Functional well-being</p><p>o Brain cancer subscale (additional concerns specific for patients with brain tumors)</p><p>&#x02022; Two total scales</p><p>o FACT-General (FACT-G; physical + social + emotional + functional well-being)</p><p>o FACT-Brain (FACT-BR; FACT-G + brain cancer subscale)</p><p>&#x02022; One index</p><p>o Trial Outcome Index (TOI; physical + functional well-being + brain cancer subscale)</p></td><td><p>Chang, 2007 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]</p><p>Kirkpatrick, 2015 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]</p><p>Skeie, 2017 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]</p><p>Bragstad, 2017 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]</p></td></tr><tr><td>European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer Quality of Life Questionnaire Core 30 (EORTC-QLQ-C30)</td><td>The EORTC QLQ-C30 consists of 5 functional scales, 3 symptom scales, 1 global health/quality of life scale and 6 single items. All of the scales and single-item measures range in scores from 0 to 100, with higher scores reflecting more severe symptoms. In case of functional scales, higher scores reflect better functioning. The EORTC QLQ-C30 is a reliable and valid measure of the quality of life of patients with cancer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>].</td><td><p>&#x02022; Five functional scales</p><p>o Physical functioning</p><p>o Role functioning</p><p>o Cognitive functioning</p><p>o Emotional functioning</p><p>o Social functioning</p><p>&#x02022; Three symptom scales</p><p>o Fatigue</p><p>o Pain</p><p>o Nausea and vomiting</p><p>&#x02022; One global quality of life scale</p><p>&#x02022; Six single items (dyspnea, insomnia, appetite loss, constipation, diarrhea, financial difficulties)</p></td><td><p>Habets, 2016 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]</p><p>van der Meer, 2018 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]</p></td></tr><tr><td>EORTC-QLQ Brain Cancer Module (EORTC-QLQ-BN20)</td><td>The EORTC-QLQ-BN20 was developed for brain cancer patients and is designed to complement the QLQ-C30. It consists of 20 items and four subscales. All items and scale scores are linearly transformed to a 0&#x02013;100 scale, with higher scores reflecting more severe symptoms. The BN20 has adequate psychometric properties for use in assessing the HRQoL of brain cancer patients in international studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>].</td><td><p>&#x02022; Four subscales</p><p>o Future uncertainty</p><p>o Motor dysfunction</p><p>o Visual disorder</p><p>o Communication deficit</p><p>&#x02022; Seven single items (headaches, hair loss, weakness of legs, seizures, itchy skin, bladder control, drowsiness)</p></td><td><p>Habets, 2016 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]</p><p>van der Meer, 2018 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]</p></td></tr><tr><td>Spitzer Quality of Life Index (SQLI)</td><td>The Spitzer Quality of Life Index was developed for use by physicians to assess the relative benefits and risks of various treatments for serious illness. It consists of 5 questions concerning HRQoL according to five factors. For each item, a score of 0, 1, or 2 is obtained; the maximum score is 10. Lower scores reflect better performance. The SQLI has convergent discriminant and content validity among cancer patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>].</td><td><p>&#x02022; One index consisting of 5 factors</p><p>o Activity</p><p>o Support</p><p>o Daily living</p><p>o Outlook</p><p>o Health</p></td><td>Randolph, 2017 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td>EuroQol 5 Dimensions questionnaire (EQ-5D)</td><td>The EQ-5D was developed as standardized measure of health state, applicable to a wide range of patient populations. It consists of 5 items representing 5 dimensions. Each item is answered on a 3-point scale; 1 no problems, 2 some problems, and 3 extreme problems. The index score overall health state consists of all 5 items and ranges between 0 (dead) and 1 (best possible health). Self-perceived health state is measured on a 20-cm vertical scale with endpoints 0 (worst imaginable health) and 100 (best imaginable health) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>].</td><td><p>&#x02022; Five subscales/dimensions</p><p>o Mobility</p><p>o Self-care</p><p>o Usual activities</p><p>o Pain/discomfort</p><p>o Anxiety/depression</p><p>&#x02022; One index</p><p>o Overall health state (all 5 subscales)</p><p>&#x02022; One vertical visual analogue scale</p><p>o Self-perceived health state</p></td><td><p>Kotecha, 2017 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]</p><p>Miller, 2017 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]</p></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>FACT-Br</italic> Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy-Brain, <italic>FACT-G</italic> FACT-General, <italic>TOI</italic> Trial Outcome Index, <italic>EORTC-QLQ-C30</italic> European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer Quality of Life Questionnaire Core 30, <italic>EORTC-QLQ-BN20</italic> European Organization for Research and Treatment of Cancer Quality of Life Questionnaire Brain Cancer Module, <italic>SQLI</italic> Spitzer Quality of Life Index, <italic>EQ-5D</italic> EuroQol 5 Dimensions</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par16">The aim of this review was to summarize findings of studies on (changes in) the HRQoL of patients with BM after SRS. Nine studies were included. Conclusions on HRQoL after SRS however should be drawn with caution, as several (methodological) limitations (discussed below) complicate the interpretation of findings. In two studies on individual scores only, stable overall HRQoL was demonstrated in most patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. In four out of seven studies evaluating group scores, overall HRQoL remained stable in patients with BM after SRS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>], even up to 12 months after SRS in small groups of long-term survivors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. However, the three other studies found a decline in overall HRQoL after SRS. One of these studies reported a decline in overall HRQoL 6 and 12 months after treatment in an otherwise undefined small subgroup of geriatric patients (age &#x02265; 70) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>], and two other studies reported a statistically significant decline in overall HRQoL at patients&#x02019; last follow-up [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>].</p><p id="Par17">These last two studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>] most likely assessed HRQoL at the point of progressive disease for many patients, as no further follow-up assessments could be completed. As several studies report a decline in HRQoL after progressive disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>], the occurrence of progressive disease might explain why these two studies found a decline in HRQoL while other studies reported stable HRQoL during multiple follow-up assessments. Differences in negative and stable outcomes might also be due to different patient or treatment characteristics. In one of these studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>], patients underwent a minimum of three SRS courses before inclusion and patient characteristics were not reported. However, baseline patient and treatment characteristics in the other study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>] were comparable with the baseline characteristics in the studies reporting stable HRQoL after SRS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>].</p><p id="Par18">Although HRQoL scores on the group level appear to remain stable over time, they may mask individual changes in HRQoL. Habets et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>] reported stable HRQoL over time on the group level, while analysis of individual results from a portion of the same study sample on a selection of the scales by van der Meer et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>] showed that most patients demonstrated both improvements as well as deterioration in different aspects of HRQoL over time. Four other studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>] evaluated both group and individual changes in HRQoL after SRS. Two studies found stable mean group scores on <italic>additional concerns</italic> over time, while on the individual level, the majority of patients (60%) reported less <italic>additional concerns</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>] and small groups of patients (23 to 36%) reported more <italic>additional concerns</italic> 1 month after SRS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. Two other studies that investigated HRQoL at patients&#x02019; last follow-up (median HRQoL follow-up 12 and 19 months) found a decline in group scores on <italic>overall health state</italic> and <italic>self-perceived health state</italic>, whereas on the individual level, similar and substantial percentages of&#x000a0;patients improved (<italic>overall health state</italic>, 24% versus 45%; and <italic>self-perceived health state</italic>, 41% versus 45%) and declined (<italic>overall health state</italic>, 28% versus 48%; and <italic>self-perceived health state</italic>, 50% versus 54%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. Differences in the percentages of improved and declined <italic>overall health state</italic>s between both studies may be explained by chance due to the small sample size (<italic>n</italic> = 27) in one of these studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]; in addition, patients in this study had already undergone a minimum of three SRS courses before inclusion in the study.</p><p id="Par19">Similarly, combining the multidimensional aspects of HRQoL, including physical, social, and emotional functioning [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>], into a single overall HRQoL score may also lead to a loss of information or mask potential improvements and declines in more specific aspects of HRQoL. One study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>] evaluated an overall HRQoL score only, limiting conclusions about the full range of potentially different HRQoL effects. However, preselecting certain HRQoL subscales based on existing literature and/or clinical insights is a more conservative approach than assessing a wide range of HRQoL outcomes which might lead to potential problems with type I errors in statistical testing due to multiple comparisons.</p><p id="Par20">At the group level, the most frequently evaluated aspects of HRQoL were physical, general/global, social, and emotional aspects. Mean scores of these aspects remained stable over time [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>], except for physical well-being/functioning and general/global HRQoL. On these aspects, contradictory results were reported. Three studies using the EORTC-QLQ-C30 or EQ-5D reported a decline in the physical aspect of HRQoL [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>], while 3 other studies using the FACT-Br reported stable scores over time [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. This can be explained by the different questionnaires that were used. For example, the subscale <italic>physical functioning</italic> of the EORTC-QLQ-C30 and the subscales <italic>mobility</italic>, <italic>self-care</italic>, and <italic>usual-activities</italic> of the EQ-5D are more focused on physical <italic>activities</italic>, while the subscale <italic>physical well-being</italic> of the FACT-Br is more focused on physical <italic>symptoms</italic>. It should be noted in addition that declines were reported by the two studies in which HRQoL was assessed at a patients&#x02019; last follow-up. This might also explain the difference in findings among studies on general/global HRQoL; the two studies measuring HRQoL at patients&#x02019; last follow-up reported a decline [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>], while four other studies reported stable scores [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. However, the different setup in questionnaires might also play a role. Since there is no standard assessment tool for HRQoL in patients with BM, comparing results from studies using different HRQoL measurements remains a challenge [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>].</p><p id="Par21">It should be noted that in two studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>] an unknown number of patients completed the pretreatment HRQoL measurement after SRS, which may have affected conclusions on HRQoL over time. In addition, in five studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>], previous treatments directed at the BM could have negatively affected the HRQoL of the patients. In two studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>], follow-up questionnaires were sent by mail; consequently, it was not known whether patients completed the self-report questionnaire themselves without the influence of significant others. On the other hand, patients could fill out these questionnaires at home, which may cause less stress or anxiety compared with the other studies, in which questionnaires were administered in the hospital at control visits, and thus provide a more realistic representation of HRQoL in daily life.</p><p id="Par22">Among the other methodological limitations of studies on HRQoL after SRS was the lack of (reporting of) within-group analyses. To investigate changes in HRQoL after SRS, within-group analyses are needed to be able to draw conclusions on the effect of SRS on HRQoL over time. Unfortunately, several studies did not perform such analyses or did not report the results [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>] and were therefore not included in this review.</p><p id="Par23">When interpreting results from longitudinal studies on HRQoL after SRS, it is important to be aware that a range of other factors, besides the treatment of interest, may influence HRQoL over time, including medication use (e.g., steroids), effects of treatment for the primary tumor (including chemotherapy, immunotherapy, radiation, surgery), pseudo-progression or progression of disease, HRQoL before treatment, cognitive symptoms, and the mere passage of time. For example, low mood after the diagnosis of BM may be alleviated by the use of an antidepressant or just passage of time. In four of the included studies, factors that affected (changes in) HRQoL after SRS were evaluated. These studies suggested that HRQoL after SRS was associated with KPS, total tumor volume in the brain, symptomatic BM, time since SRS, and disease progression (e.g., intra- and extracranial tumor activity) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>], while the number of BM, sex, and age did not appear to influence HRQoL [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]. However, due to differences between these studies in statistical techniques employed (univariate and multivariate), differences in the choice as to which predictors were investigated and at which time points, it was not possible to draw reliable conclusions.</p><p id="Par24">In addition, a potential effect of &#x0201c;response shift&#x0201d; should be considered. A response shift refers to changes in patients&#x02019; internal standards, values, and conceptualization of HRQoL that may occur during the course of their disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]. Studies have shown that although the clinical health status of patients with cancer might deteriorate considerably over time, HRQoL scores often remain stable [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. Most of the studies reviewed did not find considerable deterioration of HRQoL, which may be (partly) explained by the response shift phenomenon. However, although patients might have shifted their response pattern over time, their self-reported HRQoL may still reflect their actual <italic>personal interpretation</italic> of their HRQoL at a given point in time [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>].</p><p id="Par25">High attrition and low response rates are very common in studies that include patients whose life expectancy is short [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]. In many of the studies reviewed, the number of patients completing (long-term) follow-up assessments dropped substantially. In most studies, reasons for dropout (e.g., decease, disease progression, personal motivation) were not or only partly described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. As a result, interpretation of results is complicated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>], and results might not be generalizable to the whole population of patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>]. However, if the reasons for dropout are related to the disease (progression or death), rather than personal motivation, the results still are very informative with respect to the subgroup of patients who survive on the longer term. Reporting the reasons for dropout is therefore very important for proper interpretation of study results.</p><p id="Par26">The timing of follow-up measurements varied across the studies reviewed and only 3 studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>] had follow-up periods longer than 6 months; in two other studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>], HRQoL was assessed at last follow-up, which differed for each patient.</p><p id="Par27">Several limitations of the review process should be noted as well. Abstract screening was carried out by only one author, and thus, we cannot rule out the possibility that one or more additional relevant articles might have been identified if another author had been involved in this screening process. However, we believe that the screening process as carried out was very thorough. It is also possible that relevant studies were excluded due to language constraints. A risk of publication bias cannot be ruled out, since, for example, gray literature was not included in this review.</p><sec id="Sec11"><title>Future research</title><p id="Par28">The synthesis of the findings of the nine relevant studies revealed that future clinical trials on the effects of SRS on HRQoL of patients with BM are needed to further investigate the multiple aspects of HRQoL over time, individual changes in HRQoL after treatment, and factors that influence HRQoL. Studies should report within-group changes and clearly describe statistical analyses and reasons for dropout. For the assessment of HRQoL in this patient population, brain cancer&#x02013;specific self-report HRQoL questionnaires, evaluating the different aspects of HRQoL, should be used. To minimize patient burden and therefore prevent high dropout rates, dedicated personnel should be available to administer HRQoL questionnaires, and follow-up HRQoL assessments should be scheduled to coincide with and take place before, instead of after, standard hospital visits after SRS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>]. In addition, more studies with adequate sample sizes at long-term follow-ups (e.g., &#x0003e; 6 months) are needed to analyze different aspects of HRQoL at these time points, especially because irreversible and progressive radiation-induced brain injury, including cognitive impairment, usually emerges &#x0003e; 6 months after treatment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]. There are many methodological and logistical challenges in performing serial HRQoL assessments in these patients, but the payoff in terms of increased understanding of the effect of both the disease and its treatment on the functional health, symptom burden, and well-being of our patients justifies the additional investment required.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Relevance for clinical practice</title><p id="Par29">HRQoL appears to be an independent prognostic factor for survival in cancer patients with and without BM [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>], and in a recent study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>], HRQoL was rated by patients with BM as the most important factor to be considered in choosing among available treatment options. Since more patients with multiple BM are treated with SRS, it is important to know how this treatment may affect the HRQoL of patients over time. In general, results of the studies reviewed here suggest that SRS does not have a significant negative effect on patients&#x02019; overall HRQoL over time (even up to 12 months after SRS). This indicates that, in terms of HRQoL, SRS can be safely used in the management of patients with BM. Although more research is needed on factors influencing HRQoL of patients with BM, the current evidence suggests that clinicians should pay additional attention to patients with low KPS, large tumor volumes, symptomatic BM, and disease progression. In addition, assessment of HRQoL in clinical practice may improve communication between patients and clinicians, is helpful to identify patients&#x02019; concerns [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>], and helps clinicians to provide patients with personalized information. This emphasizes the importance of incorporating HRQoL measures as a standard part of clinical care in patients with BM.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><sec id="Sec13"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="520_2019_5136_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><label>ESM 1</label><caption><p>(DOCX 21 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><p>The authors thank Wichor M. Bramer, a biomedical information specialist of the library service of the Erasmus Medical Center, The Netherlands, for the assistance in building and performing search strategies used for this systematic review.</p></ack><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding information</title><p>This study was funded by ZonMw, The Netherlands Organization for Health Research and Development (project numbers 842003006 and 842003008).</p></notes><notes notes-type="ethics"><title>Compliance with ethical standards</title><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p id="Par30">The authors declare that they have no conflict of interest.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaal</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ni&#x000eb;l</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Vecht</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Therapeutic management of brain metastasis</article-title><source>Lancet Neurol</source><year>2005</year><volume>4</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>289</fpage><lpage>298</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15847842</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Rahmathulla G, Toms SA, Weil RJ (2012) The molecular biology of brain metastasis. J Oncol 2012</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arvold</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>EQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Margolin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>NU</given-names></name><name><surname>Anders</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name><surname>Soffietti</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Camidge</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Vogelbaum</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>IF</given-names></name><name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>PY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Updates in the management of brain metastases</article-title><source>Neuro-Oncology</source><year>2016</year><volume>18</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1043</fpage><lpage>1065</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27382120</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gerosa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicolato</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Foroni</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of gamma knife radiosurgery in the treatment of primary and metastatic brain tumors</article-title><source>Curr Opin Oncol</source><year>2003</year><volume>15</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>188</fpage><lpage>196</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12778010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hanssens</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Karlsson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeo</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name><name><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Beute</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detection of brain micrometastases by high-resolution stereotactic magnetic resonance imaging and its impact on the timing of and risk for distant recurrences</article-title><source>J Neurosurg</source><year>2011</year><volume>115</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>499</fpage><lpage>504</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21639696</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nayak</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>EQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>PY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epidemiology of brain metastases</article-title><source>Curr Oncol Rep</source><year>2012</year><volume>14</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>48</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22012633</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soffietti</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruda</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Trevisan</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Brain metastases: current management and new developments</article-title><source>Curr Opin Oncol</source><year>2008</year><volume>20</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>676</fpage><lpage>684</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18841050</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McTyre</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chinnaiyan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Whole brain radiotherapy for brain metastasis</article-title><source>Surg Neurol Int</source><year>2013</year><volume>4</volume><issue>Suppl 4</issue><fpage>S236</fpage><lpage>S244</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23717795</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barani</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Larson</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Future directions in treatment of brain metastases</article-title><source>Surg Neurol Int</source><year>2013</year><volume>4</volume><issue>Suppl 4</issue><fpage>S220</fpage><lpage>S230</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23717793</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsao</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Brain metastases: advances over the decades</article-title><source>Annals of palliative medicine</source><year>2015</year><volume>4</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>225</fpage><lpage>232</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26541403</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soliman</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Larson</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sahgal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stereotactic radiosurgery (SRS) in the modern management of patients with brain metastases</article-title><source>Oncotarget</source><year>2016</year><volume>7</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>12318</fpage><lpage>12330</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26848525</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahluwalia</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>OH</given-names></name><name><surname>Asher</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wefel</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Gondi</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Whole-brain radiotherapy for brain metastases: evolution or revolution? Journal of Clinical Oncology</article-title><source>JCO.</source><year>2017</year><volume>2017</volume><issue>2075</issue><fpage>9589</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abe</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Aoyama</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of whole brain radiation therapy for the management of brain metastases in the era of stereotactic radiosurgery</article-title><source>Curr Oncol Rep</source><year>2012</year><volume>14</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>79</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22006098</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suh</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stereotactic radiosurgery for the management of brain metastases</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2010</year><volume>362</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1119</fpage><lpage>1127</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20335588</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barnett</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Linskey</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Cozzens</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name><surname>Heilbrun</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Lunsford</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulder</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sloan</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><collab>American Association of Neurological Surgeons</collab><collab>Congress of Neurological Surgeons Washington Committee Stereotactic Radiosurgery Task Force</collab></person-group><article-title>Stereotactic radiosurgery&#x02014;an organized neurosurgery-sanctioned definition</article-title><source>J Neurosurg</source><year>2007</year><volume>106</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17240553</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gavrilovic</surname><given-names>IT</given-names></name><name><surname>Posner</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Brain metastases: epidemiology and pathophysiology</article-title><source>J Neuro-Oncol</source><year>2005</year><volume>75</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>14</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Suntharalingam</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Amin</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of three treatment options for single brain metastasis from lung cancer</article-title><source>Int J Cancer</source><year>2000</year><volume>90</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>45</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10725856</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suh</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Chao</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name><surname>Angelov</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Vogelbaum</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Barnett</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of stereotactic radiosurgery for multiple (&#x0003e; 4) brain metastases</article-title><source>J Radiosurg SBRT</source><year>2011</year><volume>1</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29296295</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>McCoy</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name><surname>Bourland</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>DeGuzman</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cavity-directed radiosurgery as adjuvant therapy after resection of a brain metastasis</article-title><source>J Neurosurg</source><year>2011</year><volume>114</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1585</fpage><lpage>1591</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21166567</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pham</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lo</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Sahgal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neurocognition and quality-of-life in brain metastasis patients who have been irradiated focally or comprehensively</article-title><source>Expert Review of Quality of Life in Cancer Care</source><year>2016</year><volume>1</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>45</fpage><lpage>60</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soffietti</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kocher</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Abacioglu</surname><given-names>UM</given-names></name><name><surname>Villa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fauchon</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Baumert</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A European Organisation for Research and Treatment of Cancer phase III trial of adjuvant whole-brain radiotherapy versus observation in patients with one to three brain metastases from solid tumors after surgical resection or radiosurgery: quality-of-life results</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>2012</year><volume>31</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23213105</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Popovic</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chow</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Poon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chow</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quality of life in patients with primary and metastatic brain cancer as reported in the literature using the EORTC QLQ-BN20 and QLQ-C30</article-title><source>Expert Review of Pharmacoeconomics &#x00026; Outcomes Research</source><year>2012</year><volume>12</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>831</fpage><lpage>837</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23252363</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Witgert</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyers</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neurocognitive and quality of life measures in patients with metastatic brain disease</article-title><source>Neurosurg Clin N Am</source><year>2011</year><volume>22</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>79</fpage><lpage>85</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21109152</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wong J, Hird A, Kirou&#x02013;Mauro, A., Napolskikh, J., &#x00026; Chow, E. (2008) Quality of life in brain metastases radiation trials: a literature review. Curr Oncol 15(5):25&#x02013;45</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pinkham</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanghera</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Wall</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Dawson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitfield</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neurocognitive effects following cranial irradiation for brain metastases</article-title><source>Clin Oncol</source><year>2015</year><volume>27</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>630</fpage><lpage>639</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kirkbride</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Tannock</surname><given-names>IF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trials in palliative treatment&#x02014;have the goal posts been moved?</article-title><source>Lancet Oncol</source><year>2008</year><volume>9</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>186</fpage><lpage>187</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18308238</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Raman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sahgal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Soliman</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wendzicki</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Patient preference for stereotactic radiosurgery plus or minus whole brain radiotherapy for the treatment of brain metastases</article-title><source>Annals of palliative medicine</source><year>2017</year><volume>6</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>S155</fpage><lpage>S160</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28866900</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Jacobsen, P. B., Davis, K., &#x00026; Cella, D. (2002). Assessing quality of life in research and clinical practice. Oncology, 16(9; SUPP/10), 133&#x02013;140.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gotay</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawamoto</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name><surname>Bottomley</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Efficace</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The prognostic significance of patient-reported outcomes in cancer clinical trials</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>2008</year><volume>26</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1355</fpage><lpage>1363</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18227528</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coates</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>McLeod</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Hersey</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Olver</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prognostic value of quality of life scores in a trial of chemotherapy with or without interferon in patients with metastatic malignant melanoma</article-title><source>Eur J Cancer</source><year>1993</year><volume>29</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>1731</fpage><lpage>1734</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>H-C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>M-H</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>CC-C</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C-J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C-H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheehan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neuroimaging and quality-of-life outcomes in patients with brain metastasis and peritumoral edema who undergo Gamma Knife surgery</article-title><source>J Neurosurg</source><year>2008</year><volume>109</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>90</fpage><lpage>98</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19123894</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bragstad S, Flateb&#x000f8; M, Natvig GK, Eide GE, Skeie GO, Behbahani M et al (2017) Predictors of quality of life and survival following Gamma Knife surgery for lung cancer brain metastases: a prospective study. J Neurosurg:1&#x02013;13</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Skeie</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Eide</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>Flateb&#x000f8;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Heggdal</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><name><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Bragstad</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pedersen</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name><surname>Enger</surname><given-names>P&#x000d8;</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quality of life is maintained using Gamma Knife radiosurgery: a prospective study of a brain metastases patient cohort</article-title><source>J Neurosurg</source><year>2017</year><volume>126</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>708</fpage><lpage>725</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27058206</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wefel</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Maor</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hassenbusch</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name><name><surname>Mahajan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>FF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A pilot study of neurocognitive function in patients with one to three new brain metastases initially treated with stereotactic radiosurgery alone</article-title><source>Neurosurgery</source><year>2007</year><volume>60</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>277</fpage><lpage>284</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17290178</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kirkpatrick</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Sampson</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>McSherry</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Herndon</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Defining the optimal planning target volume in image-guided stereotactic radiosurgery of brain metastases: results of a randomized trial</article-title><source>Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys</source><year>2015</year><volume>91</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>100</fpage><lpage>108</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25442342</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Habets</surname><given-names>Esther J.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dirven</surname><given-names>Linda</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiggenraad</surname><given-names>Ruud G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Verbeek-de Kanter</surname><given-names>Antoinette</given-names></name><name><surname>Lycklama &#x000e0; Nijeholt</surname><given-names>Geert J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zwinkels</surname><given-names>Hanneke</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>Martin</given-names></name><name><surname>Taphoorn</surname><given-names>Martin J.B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neurocognitive functioning and health-related quality of life in patients treated with stereotactic radiotherapy for brain metastases: a prospective study</article-title><source>Neuro-Oncology</source><year>2015</year><volume>18</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>435</fpage><lpage>444</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26385615</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">van der Meer, P. B., Habets, E. J., Wiggenraad, R. G., Verbeek-de Kanter, A., &#x000e0; Nijeholt, G. J. L., Zwinkels, H., et al. (2018). Individual changes in neurocognitive functioning and health-related quality of life in patients with brain oligometastases treated with stereotactic radiotherapy. Journal of Neuro-Oncology, 1&#x02013;10.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kotecha</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Barnett</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Suh</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Angelov</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Vogelbaum</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohammadi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Chao</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quality of life following stereotactic radiosurgery for single and multiple brain metastases</article-title><source>Neurosurgery</source><year>2017</year><volume>81</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>147</fpage><lpage>155</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/neuros/nyw166</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28327994</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kotecha</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Damico</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Suh</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Reddy</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Barnett</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Vogelbaum</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Angelov</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohammadi</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Chao</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Three or more courses of stereotactic radiosurgery for patients with multiply recurrent brain metastases</article-title><source>Neurosurgery</source><year>2017</year><volume>80</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>871</fpage><lpage>879</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28327948</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Randolph</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>McTyre</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Klepin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Peiffer</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ayala-Peacock</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lester</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Laxton</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Dohm</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tatter</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of radiosurgical management of geriatric patients with brain metastases: Clinical and quality of life outcomes</article-title><source>J Radiosurg SBRT</source><year>2017</year><volume>5</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29296461</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muacevic</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wowra</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Siefert</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tonn</surname><given-names>J-C</given-names></name><name><surname>Steiger</surname><given-names>H-J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kreth</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microsurgery plus whole brain irradiation versus Gamma Knife surgery alone for treatment of single metastases to the brain: a randomized controlled multicentre phase III trial</article-title><source>J Neuro-Oncol</source><year>2008</year><volume>87</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>299</fpage><lpage>307</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>DiBiase</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chin</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influence of gamma knife radiosurgery on the quality of life in patients with brain metastases</article-title><source>Am J Clin Oncol</source><year>2002</year><volume>25</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>131</fpage><lpage>134</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11943889</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Holden</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lauzon</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Quality of life in patients with brain metastases using the EORTC QLQ-BN20 and QLQ-C30</article-title><source>J Radiat Oncol</source><year>2012</year><volume>1</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>179</fpage><lpage>186</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wefel</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hess</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>FF</given-names></name><name><surname>Kornguth</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Arbuckle</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Swint</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Shiu</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Maor</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyers</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neurocognition in patients with brain metastases treated with radiosurgery or radiosurgery plus whole-brain irradiation: a randomised controlled trial</article-title><source>Lancet Oncol</source><year>2009</year><volume>10</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1037</fpage><lpage>1044</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19801201</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerba</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Chow</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Quality of life in patients with brain metastases receiving upfront as compared to salvage stereotactic radiosurgery using the EORTC QLQ-C15-PAL and the EORTC QLQ BN20+ 2: a pilot study</article-title><source>J Radiat Oncol</source><year>2013</year><volume>2</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>217</fpage><lpage>224</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>Paul D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaeckle</surname><given-names>Kurt</given-names></name><name><surname>Ballman</surname><given-names>Karla V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Farace</surname><given-names>Elana</given-names></name><name><surname>Cerhan</surname><given-names>Jane H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>S. Keith</given-names></name><name><surname>Carrero</surname><given-names>Xiomara W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>Fred G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Deming</surname><given-names>Richard</given-names></name><name><surname>Burri</surname><given-names>Stuart H.</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000e9;nard</surname><given-names>Cynthia</given-names></name><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>Caroline</given-names></name><name><surname>Stieber</surname><given-names>Volker W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pollock</surname><given-names>Bruce E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Galanis</surname><given-names>Evanthia</given-names></name><name><surname>Buckner</surname><given-names>Jan C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Asher</surname><given-names>Anthony L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of Radiosurgery Alone vs Radiosurgery With Whole Brain Radiation Therapy on Cognitive Function in Patients With 1 to 3 Brain Metastases</article-title><source>JAMA</source><year>2016</year><volume>316</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>401</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27458945</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sprangers</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quality-of-life assessment in oncology</article-title><source>Acta Oncol</source><year>2002</year><volume>41</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>229</fpage><lpage>237</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12195741</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>NU</given-names></name><name><surname>Wefel</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>EQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schiff</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>van den Bent</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Soffietti</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Challenges relating to solid tumour brain metastases in clinical trials, part 2: neurocognitive, neurological, and quality-of-life outcomes. A report from the RANO group</article-title><source>Lancet Oncol</source><year>2013</year><volume>14</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>e407</fpage><lpage>e416</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23993385</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dirven</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Reijneveld</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Aaronson</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name><name><surname>Bottomley</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Uitdehaag</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Taphoorn</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Health-related quality of life in patients with brain tumors: limitations and additional outcome measures</article-title><source>Curr Neurol Neurosci Rep</source><year>2013</year><volume>13</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>359</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23666388</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Bode</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Repucci</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sprangers</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Fayers</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The clinical significance of adaptation to changing health: a meta-analysis of response shift</article-title><source>Qual Life Res</source><year>2006</year><volume>15</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1533</fpage><lpage>1550</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17031503</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ubel</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Peeters</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Abandoning the language of &#x0201c;response shift&#x0201d;: a plea for conceptual clarity in distinguishing scale recalibration from true changes in quality of life</article-title><source>Qual Life Res</source><year>2010</year><volume>19</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>465</fpage><lpage>471</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20112000</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lien</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Caissie</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Culleton</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Holden</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Chow</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The EORTC QLQ-BN20 for assessment of quality of life in patients receiving treatment or prophylaxis for brain metastases: a literature review</article-title><source>Expert Review of Pharmacoeconomics &#x00026; Outcomes Research</source><year>2011</year><volume>11</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>693</fpage><lpage>700</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22098285</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dirven</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Koekkoek</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Reijneveld</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Taphoorn</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Health-related quality of life in brain tumor patients: as an endpoint in clinical trials and its value in clinical care</article-title><source>Expert Review of Quality of Life in Cancer Care</source><year>2016</year><volume>1</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>44</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lien</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cramarossa</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Cella</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Caissie</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Holden</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Culleton</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sahgal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Chow</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>FACT-Br for assessment of quality of life in patients receiving treatment for brain metastases: a literature review</article-title><source>Expert Review of Pharmacoeconomics &#x00026; Outcomes Research</source><year>2011</year><volume>11</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>701</fpage><lpage>708</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22098286</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tofilon</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Fike</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The radioresponse of the central nervous system: a dynamic process</article-title><source>Radiat Res</source><year>2000</year><volume>153</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>357</fpage><lpage>370</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10798963</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greene-Schloesser</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Robbins</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Peiffer</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Wheeler</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Radiation-induced brain injury: a review</article-title><source>Front Oncol</source><year>2012</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>73</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22833841</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>