<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Parasit Vectors</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Parasit Vectors</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Parasites &#x00026; Vectors</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1756-3305</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31924254</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6954605</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">3881</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13071-020-3881-1</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Molecular diversity of <italic>Bulinus</italic> species in Madziwa area, Shamva district in Zimbabwe: implications for urogenital schistosomiasis transmission</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mutsaka-Makuvaza</surname><given-names>Masceline Jenipher</given-names></name><address><email>mascelinejeni@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Xiao-Nong</given-names></name><address><email>zhouxn1@chinacdc.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tshuma</surname><given-names>Cremance</given-names></name><address><email>tshuma.cremance@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Abe</surname><given-names>Eniola</given-names></name><address><email>abeeniola11@126.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Manasa</surname><given-names>Justen</given-names></name><address><email>jmanasa@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Manyangadze</surname><given-names>Tawanda</given-names></name><address><email>manyangadze.tawanda@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Allan</surname><given-names>Fiona</given-names></name><address><email>f.allan@nhm.ac.uk</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff7">7</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chin&#x000f3;mbe</surname><given-names>Nyasha</given-names></name><address><email>nyasha.chinombe@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Webster</surname><given-names>Bonnie</given-names></name><address><email>b.webster@nhm.ac.uk</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff7">7</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Midzi</surname><given-names>Nicholas</given-names></name><address><email>midzinicholas@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0572 0760</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.13001.33</institution-id><institution>Department of Medical Microbiology, College of Health Sciences, </institution><institution>University of Zimbabwe, </institution></institution-wrap>P.O. Box A178, Avondale, Harare, Zimbabwe </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0572 0760</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.13001.33</institution-id><institution>National Institute of Health Research, Ministry of Health and Child Care, </institution></institution-wrap>P.O. Box CY573, Causeway, Harare, Zimbabwe </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 8803 2373</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.198530.6</institution-id><institution>National Institute of Parasitic Diseases, </institution><institution>Chinese Centre for Disease Control and Prevention, </institution></institution-wrap>Shanghai, 200025 China </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label>Mashonaland Central Provincial Health Office, Ministry of Health and Child Care, Bindura, Mashonaland Central Zimbabwe </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0648 4659</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.469393.2</institution-id><institution>Geography Department, Faculty of Science, </institution><institution>Bindura University of Science Education, </institution></institution-wrap>Bag 1020, Bindura, Zimbabwe </aff><aff id="Aff6"><label>6</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0723 4123</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.16463.36</institution-id><institution>School of Nursing and Public Health, </institution><institution>Department of Public Health Medicine University of KwaZulu-Natal, </institution></institution-wrap>Durban, South Africa </aff><aff id="Aff7"><label>7</label>Wolfson Wellcome Biomedical Laboratories, Department of Life Sciences, Natural History 14 Museum, Cromwell Road, London, SW7 5BD UK </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>10</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>13</volume><elocation-id>14</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>18</day><month>7</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>2</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated in a credit line to the data.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1"><italic>Bulinus</italic> species are freshwater snails that transmit the parasitic trematode <italic>Schistosoma haematobium</italic>. Despite their importance, the diversity of these intermediate host snails and their evolutionary history is still unclear in Zimbabwe. <italic>Bulinus globosus</italic> and <italic>B. truncatus</italic> collected from a urogenital schistosomiasis endemic region in the Madziwa area of Zimbabwe were characterized using molecular methods.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">Malacological survey sites were mapped and snails were collected from water contact sites in four communities in the Madziwa area, Shamva district for a period of one year, at three-month intervals. <italic>Schistosoma haematobium</italic> infections in snails were determined by cercarial shedding and the partial mitochondrial cytochrome <italic>c</italic> oxidase subunit 1 gene (<italic>cox</italic>1) was used to investigate the phylogeny and genetic variability of the <italic>Bulinus</italic> spp. collected.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">Among the 1570 <italic>Bulinus</italic> spp. snails collected, 30 (1.9%) <italic>B. globosus</italic> were shedding morphologically identified schistosomes. None of the <italic>B. truncatus</italic> snails were shedding. The mitochondrial <italic>cox</italic>1 data from 166 and 16 samples for <italic>B. globosus</italic> and <italic>B. truncatus</italic>, respectively, showed genetically diverse populations within the two species. Twelve <italic>cox</italic>1 haplotypes were found from the 166 <italic>B. globosus</italic> samples and three from the 16 <italic>B. truncatus</italic> samples with phylogenetic analysis showing that the haplotypes fall into well-supported clusters within their species groups. Both <italic>B. truncatus</italic> and <italic>B. globosus</italic> clustered into two distinct lineages. Overall, significant negative values for both Tajima&#x02019;s D statistic and the Fu&#x02019;s Fs statistic were observed for <italic>B. globosus</italic> and <italic>B. truncatus</italic>.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par4">The study provided new insights into the levels of genetic diversity within <italic>B. globosus</italic> and additional information on <italic>B. truncatus</italic> collected from a small geographical area in Zimbabwe. Low prevalence levels of infection observed in the snails may reflect the low transmission level of urogenital schistosomiasis in the area. Our results contribute towards the understanding of the distribution and population genetic structure of <italic>Bulinus</italic> spp. supporting the mapping of the transmission or risk of transmission of urogenital schistosomiasis, particularly in Zimbabwe.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd><italic>Bulinus globosus</italic></kwd><kwd><italic>Bulinus truncatus</italic></kwd><kwd><italic>Cox</italic>1</kwd><kwd>Diversity</kwd><kwd>Phylogenetics</kwd><kwd>Zimbabwe</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par6">Freshwater snails of the genus <italic>Bulinus</italic> act as intermediate hosts for <italic>Schistosoma haematobium</italic>, the human blood fluke that causes the chronic and debilitating disease, urogenital schistosomiasis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. <italic>Bulinus</italic> species are extensively distributed throughout Africa, countries bordering the Mediterranean and some areas of the Middle East, but there is a considerable variation in compatibility between the different <italic>Bulinus</italic> species and schistosome parasites in different geographical areas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. The host-parasite compatibility is influenced by both biotic and abiotic factors such as temperature, rainfall, water velocity, desiccation, salinity and the genetics of the snail hosts and the parasites [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>].</p><p id="Par7">Among the <italic>Bulinus</italic> species, <italic>B. globosus</italic> (Morelet, 1866) and <italic>B. truncatus</italic> (Audouin, 1827) are recognized as the most important intermediate hosts for <italic>S. haematobium</italic> and the species are distributed widely in Africa [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. In Zimbabwe, <italic>B. globosus</italic> is the only intermediate host for <italic>S. haematobium</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. The intermediate host snail prefers diverse habitat types and is more abundant in the northeast and southeast parts of the country with a patchy distribution in the southwest, correlating with the distribution of urogenital schistosomiasis in Zimbabwe. <italic>Bulinus truncatus</italic> is more common to the southwest preferring dams and marshy habitats [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>].</p><p id="Par8">While both <italic>B. truncatus</italic> and <italic>B. globosus</italic> are hermaphroditic, <italic>B. globosus</italic> preferentially cross-fertilizes if possible whereas <italic>B. truncatus</italic> preferentially self-fertilizes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Both species inhabit diverse habitats such as rivers, irrigation systems, ponds and lakes and are tolerant to differing water levels and seasonal changes, and have the ability to aestivate during dry seasons [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Geographical and temporal variability in ecological factors can cause large fluctuations in snail abundance within and between sites, possibly resulting in population extinction and/or recolonization. Selfing and population bottlenecks reduce genetic diversity within a population while increasing genetic differences between isolated populations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Investigating snail population structure will help understand snail-parasite relationships and parasite transmission dynamics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>].</p><p id="Par9">Due to the high levels of variation in shell morphology within and among <italic>Bulinus</italic> species, morphological identification can be subjective [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. Nevertheless, it has been the main method used to characterize <italic>Bulinus</italic> species in Zimbabwe [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>], except for a few studies that utilized iso and alloenzyme analysis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>] and random amplification of polymorphic nuclear DNA (RAPD) analysis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. However, several studies conducted in the region have characterized <italic>Bulinus</italic> populations using the DNA sequence analysis of the internal transcribed spacer (ITS) rDNA regions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>] and the mitochondrial cytochrome <italic>c</italic> oxidase subunit 1 (<italic>cox</italic>1) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>], with <italic>cox</italic>1 data being more informative for resolving species level affinities within the genus <italic>Bulinus</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. Abe et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>] have reported six unique mitochondrial <italic>cox</italic>1 haplotypes for <italic>B. truncatus</italic> in Zimbabwe. However, no information exists regarding <italic>cox</italic>1 diversity for Zimbabwean <italic>B. globosus</italic> in the sequence databases. Here, we use mitochondrial <italic>cox</italic>1 data to identify and characterize <italic>Bulinus</italic> snails sampled from different water contact sites in a urogenital schistosomiasis endemic area, Madziwa in Zimbabwe and discuss the findings in relation to schistosomiasis transmission.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Study area</title><p id="Par10">Natural populations of <italic>Bulinus</italic> species were collected from four rural communities in Mashonaland province, in a district highly endemic for urogenital schistosomiasis, as described in a previous study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. The communities are in semiarid areas and they rely on local rivers and streams for most of the household activities including bathing, fishing, swimming, washing, gardening and subsistence farming. There are only a few boreholes that are used by the residents for provision of drinking water but these are located ~&#x02009;5&#x000a0;km away. Within the four communities, there are distinct periods of high and low rainfall patterns, with the main rainfall period being from late October to April.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Sample collection, morphological analysis and patent testing</title><p id="Par11">This study was part of a larger project investigating the burden of urogenital schistosomiasis in a highly endemic area of Zimbabwe, during which snail survey sites were selected by asking the residents to identify the sites which they frequently used for human water contact activity. The water contact sites are described in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>. Spatial variation in snail populations was investigated by collecting snails at each water contact point in the communities and all the surveyed sites were mapped using a global positioning system (GPS) (Trimble Navigation Ltd, California, USA). At each water contact site, sampling was performed at four different time points representing the rainy season, post-rainy season, winter and hot-dry season to investigate the temporal effects of season on the snail populations. Snail sampling at all sites was performed using a metal scoop or by handpicking the snails for 30&#x000a0;min at both the main parts of the water body and at the water edges. The snails were transported to the field laboratory where they were identified using shell morphology as described by Brown [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Snails with globose, ovate shells of small to medium size, and sinistral with a pseudobranch were grouped as belonging to the genus <italic>Bulinus</italic>. From the snails identified as <italic>Bulinus</italic> spp., <italic>B. globosus</italic> was identified by their truncate columella and microsculpture of nodules with short ridges or corrugations. <italic>Bulinus</italic> snails with a straight or evenly concave or twisted columella with no truncation were identified as <italic>B. truncatus</italic>. Both species were tested for patent parasitic infections by cercarial shedding. The snails were individually placed in flat-bottomed glass vials containing dechlorinated water and exposed to artificial light for a maximum of 4&#x000a0;h [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. During the 4-hour period, the emergence of cercariae was checked at regular short intervals. Cercarial identification was based on morphology using a binocular microscope as described by Frandsen &#x00026; Christensen [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. Bifurcate cercariae were considered to be of mammalian origin. After shedding, the snails were counted and preserved in absolute ethanol for molecular analysis.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Location of the water contact sites where <italic>Bulinus</italic> snails were collected in Madziwa area, Shamva district, Zimbabwe</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13071_2020_3881_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>DNA extraction and amplification</title><p id="Par12">Among the collected and morphologically identified snails, a subset of 166 <italic>B. globosus</italic> and all the collected 16 <italic>B. truncatus</italic> were molecularly analysed. Up to eight adult snails were randomly selected per site for molecular analysis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. The preserved snails were transported to the Key Schistosomiasis Laboratory, National Institute of Parasitic Diseases, Shanghai, China, for molecular analysis. Snails were removed from ethanol and their soft parts were removed from the snail shell using forceps. For each snail, the soft part was then transferred to a clean Petri dish and immersed in TE buffer (10&#x000a0;mM Tris, 0.1&#x000a0;mM EDTA) pH 7.4 for 1&#x000a0;h. DNA extraction was performed from the head and foot region of the snail tissue using the DNeasy Blood and Tissue Kit (Qiagen, Crawley, UK) following the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. DNA quantification and purity were measured using a Nanodrop ND-1000 spectrophotometer (Nanodrop Technologies Inc., Willington, USA).</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Amplification and sequencing of mitochondrial DNA</title><p id="Par13">The <italic>cox</italic>1 fragment was amplified by PCR, using the BulCox 5 forward (5&#x02032;-CCT TTA AGA GGN CCT ATT GC-3&#x02032;) and BulCox 14 reverse (5&#x02032;-GGA AAT CAG TAM AYA AAA CCA GC-3&#x02032;) primers previously described by Kane et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>] in a C1000TM thermal cycler (Bio-Rad, California, USA). Amplification was carried out in 25&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l PCR reactions containing a premixed master mix (2.5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l of 20&#x000a0;mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 2.5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l, 5&#x000d7; buffer, 2.5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l of 20&#x000a0;mM dNTPs, one unit of Taq DNA polymerase), 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l (10&#x000a0;pmol) of each forward and reverse primer and 1&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l (10&#x02013;100&#x000a0;ng) of the DNA template. The PCR conditions were as follows: denaturation at 95&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 5&#x000a0;min followed by 45 cycles of 95&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 5&#x000a0;min, 45&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 30&#x000a0;s and 72&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 1&#x000a0;min and a final extension step at 72&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C for 10&#x000a0;min. Negative controls (no template DNA) were included with each set of reactions. PCR products were viewed by 1% gel electrophoresis (Electrophoresis power supplies E455, CONSORT, Turnhout, Belgium) and read with a Molecular Imager, Gel Doc<sup>TM</sup> XRt Imaging system (Bio-Rad). Amplicons were purified and Sanger sequenced in both forward and reverse directions using the BigDye v3.1 Terminator Cycle Sequencing Kit and read with the automated DNA fragment analyzer ABI-377 (Applied Biosystems, Carlsbad, USA) at Sangon Biotech, Shanghai, China.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Data analysis</title><p id="Par14">All <italic>cox</italic>1 sequences were manually checked and edited using Sequencher v5.1 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.Genecodes">http://www.Genecodes</ext-link>) to remove any ambiguities between forward and reverse strands. The consensus sequences of each sample were aligned in Sequencher v5.1 and any ambiguities between sequences were checked by visualisation of the original sequence chromatograms. Sequences were identified by BLAST searching [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>] against the GenBank database.</p><sec id="Sec8"><title>Haplotype analysis</title><p id="Par15">The consensus sequences from all samples were grouped and aligned in MacClade 4.05 and then collapsed together using Collapse v1.2 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://darwin.uvigo.es/software/collapse.html">http://darwin.uvigo.es/software/collapse.html</ext-link>) to identify samples with identical sequences/haplotypes. Within each site, and also overall, unique sequences and any group of identical sequences represented unique individual haplotypes. A group was defined as a collection of sequences regardless of the site where they were collected. Haplotypes were given a site-haplotype identifier code, consisting of a site number, letter H (haplotype for <italic>B</italic>. <italic>globosus</italic>) or T (haplotype for <italic>B</italic>. <italic>truncatus</italic>) and a number representing the different haplotypes in the area. Overall and in each site, the number of individual <italic>Bulinus</italic> snails presenting the same haplotype was recorded. Haplotype data were submitted to the EMBL/GenBank database under the accession numbers MN397785&#x02013;MN397822.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Phylogenetic analysis</title><p id="Par16">The haplotype data were exported to MEGA 6.0 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>] and aligned using the Clustal W algorithm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. Phylogenetic relationships between the haplotypes were inferred using the Neighbor-Joining (NJ), Minimum Evolution (ME) and Maximum Likelihood (ML) methods and the tree topologies were tested using 1000 bootstrap replicates in MEGA 6.0 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. The analysis was run using the Tamura-Nei with Gamma distribution nucleotide substitution model, which was the best-fit model for the data, inferred using the model test function in MEGA 6.0 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. A sequence for <italic>Biomphalaria glabrata</italic> (GenBank: AY380531) was used as the outgroup. Additional sequences for <italic>Bulinus</italic> spp. (<italic>B. globosus</italic>, <italic>B. africanus</italic> and <italic>B. truncatus</italic>) from Uganda, South Africa, Egypt, Tanzania, Kenya, Senegal, Portugal and Zimbabwe available on GenBank were also included in the analysis (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S1). The net nucleotide divergence between the main haplotype groups found within the study was calculated in MEGA 6.0 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>] with the Juke-Cantor model [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Population genetic analysis</title><p id="Par17">The data were exported into DnaSP v6 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>] to determine the interpopulation and intrapopulation diversity of the <italic>Bulinus</italic> populations analysed. A population was defined as a collection of sequences from the same site or community or overall. Only 16 <italic>B. truncatus</italic> were collected, with not enough representatives per site and so were analysed as a single population. For <italic>B. globosus</italic> the overall diversity, diversity within the sites and also within the communities was measured. Haplotype diversity (h) and nucleotide diversity (&#x003c0;), was calculated using the Juke-Cantor model [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. The diversification index (<italic>Fst</italic>) between each pair of sites and between <italic>B. globosus</italic> and <italic>B. truncatus</italic> was estimated in DnaSP v6 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Test for selection</title><p id="Par18">To investigate if there was significant selection occurring, Tajima&#x02019;s D [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>] and Fu&#x02019;s Fs statistic neutrality tests for selection were conducted in DnaSP v6. Nucleotide divergence within and between the communities was calculated in DnaSP v6 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>].</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec13"><title>Morphological identification and infection status of <italic>Bulinus</italic> species</title><p id="Par19">From the collected snails, 1558 were putatively identified as <italic>Bulinus</italic> spp. based on their sinistral, ovate, globose shells. Among these, 1542 were morphologically identified as <italic>B. globosus</italic> and 16 as <italic>B. truncatus</italic>, based on the shape of the columella. Of these, a subset of 166 <italic>B. globosus</italic> and all 16 <italic>B. truncatus</italic> were molecularly characterized with a 100% match between the morphological and molecular species identification.</p><p id="Par20">Among the <italic>B. globosus</italic> collected and tested for patent infections, 30/1542 (1.9%) were shedding schistosome cercariae (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The breakdown of infected snails by time point was as follows: 18 snails at baseline (end of February 2018; rainy season) and 12 snails at 6 months follow-up (September 2018; summer). No snails were shedding at 3 (winter season), 9 (early rainy season), or 12 (rainy season) months follow-up. None of the <italic>B. truncatus</italic> were found to be infected.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Demographic information of the <italic>Bulinus</italic> samples analysed in Madziwa, Zimbabwe</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Community (prevalence of USCH%)<sup>a</sup></th><th align="left">Water body</th><th align="left">Latitude</th><th align="left">Longitude</th><th align="left">Collection site ID</th><th align="left">No. of snails collected</th><th align="left">No. of <italic>B. globosus</italic> collected</th><th align="left"><italic>B. globosus</italic> shedding cercariae<break/><italic>n</italic> (%)</th><th align="left">No. of <italic>B. truncatus</italic> collected<sup>b</sup></th><th align="left">Haplotypes</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4">Chihuri (22.8)</td><td align="left">Nyarukunda R</td><td align="left">16&#x000b0;56.185&#x02032;S</td><td align="left">31&#x000b0;26.762&#x02032;E</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">117</td><td align="left">117</td><td align="left">0 (0)</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">H1, H3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Pachibani pool</td><td align="left">16&#x000b0;54.899&#x02032;S</td><td align="left">31&#x000b0;25.721&#x02032;E</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">20</td><td align="left">20</td><td align="left">0 (0)</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">H1, H2, H7</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Nyamaruru R</td><td align="left">16&#x000b0;55.452&#x02032;S</td><td align="left">31&#x000b0;25.768&#x02032;E</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">64</td><td align="left">63</td><td align="left">1 (1.6)</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">H1, H2, T1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Nyamaruru R</td><td align="left">16&#x000b0;55.439&#x02032;S</td><td align="left">31&#x000b0;25.848&#x02032;E</td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">81</td><td align="left">81</td><td align="left">0 (0)</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">H2, H3, H6, H12</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Sub-total</td><td align="left" colspan="4"/><td align="left">282</td><td align="left">281</td><td align="left">1 (0.4)</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">Kaziro (12.3)</td><td align="left">Mupfure R</td><td align="left">16&#x000b0;56.997&#x02032;S</td><td align="left">31&#x000b0;28.622&#x02032;E</td><td align="left">7</td><td align="left">22</td><td align="left">20</td><td align="left">0 (0)</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">H1, T2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Mupfure R</td><td align="left">16&#x000b0;56.961&#x02032;S</td><td align="left">31&#x000b0;28.551&#x02032;E</td><td align="left">8</td><td align="left">52</td><td align="left">50</td><td align="left">0 (0)</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">H1, T2, H3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Mupfure R</td><td align="left">16&#x000b0;56.706&#x02032;S</td><td align="left">31&#x000b0;28.249&#x02032;E</td><td align="left">9</td><td align="left">35</td><td align="left">35</td><td align="left">1 (2.9)</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">H1, H3, H5, H7</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Sub-total</td><td align="left" colspan="4"/><td align="left">109</td><td align="left">105</td><td align="left">1 (1.0)</td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="12">Mupfure (17.7)</td><td align="left">Mupfure R</td><td align="left">16&#x000b0;56.655&#x02032;S</td><td align="left">31&#x000b0;28.194&#x02032;E</td><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">42</td><td align="left">41</td><td align="left">0 (0)</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">H1, H5, H8, T2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Mupfure R</td><td align="left">16&#x000b0;56.218&#x02032;S</td><td align="left">31&#x000b0;27.667&#x02032;E</td><td align="left">6</td><td align="left">112</td><td align="left">112</td><td align="left">0 (0)</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">H1, H3, H5, H8, H11</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Mupfure R</td><td align="left">16&#x000b0;51.986&#x02032;S</td><td align="left">31&#x000b0;28.347&#x02032;E</td><td align="left">10</td><td align="left">208</td><td align="left">208</td><td align="left">2 (1.0)</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">H1, H3, H6</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Mupfure R</td><td align="left">16&#x000b0;51.723&#x02032;S</td><td align="left">31&#x000b0;29.283&#x02032;E</td><td align="left">11</td><td align="left">45</td><td align="left">45</td><td align="left">0 (0)</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">H1, H2, H3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Mupfure R</td><td align="left">16&#x000b0;51.624&#x02032;S</td><td align="left">31&#x000b0;29.422&#x02032;E</td><td align="left">12</td><td align="left">26</td><td align="left">25</td><td align="left">1 (4.0)</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">H1, H4, T3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Mupfure R</td><td align="left">16&#x000b0;51.565&#x02032;S</td><td align="left">31&#x000b0;29.422&#x02032;E</td><td align="left">13</td><td align="left">57</td><td align="left">57</td><td align="left">5 (8.8)</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">H1, H2, H3, H9</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Mupfure R</td><td align="left">16&#x000b0;51.472&#x02032;S</td><td align="left">31&#x000b0;29.622&#x02032;E</td><td align="left">14</td><td align="left">85</td><td align="left">85</td><td align="left">0 (0)</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">H1, H3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Mupfure R</td><td align="left">16&#x000b0;51.442&#x02032;S</td><td align="left">31&#x000b0;29.621&#x02032;E</td><td align="left">15</td><td align="left">135</td><td align="left">135</td><td align="left">11 (8.1)</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">H1, H2, H4</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Mupfure R</td><td align="left">16&#x000b0;51.417&#x02032;S</td><td align="left">31&#x000b0;29.644&#x02032;E</td><td align="left">16</td><td align="left">9</td><td align="left">9</td><td align="left">0 (0)</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">H1, H2, H7, H10</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Mupfure R</td><td align="left">16&#x000b0;51.344&#x02032;S</td><td align="left">31&#x000b0;29.746&#x02032;E</td><td align="left">17</td><td align="left">11</td><td align="left">10</td><td align="left">0 (0)</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">H1, H2, T1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Zvisokwe S</td><td align="left">16&#x000b0;52.842&#x02032;S</td><td align="left">31&#x000b0;29.450&#x02032;E</td><td align="left">18</td><td align="left">75</td><td align="left">75</td><td align="left">0 (0)</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">H1, H4</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Zvisokwe S</td><td align="left">16&#x000b0;53.007&#x02032;S</td><td align="left">31&#x000b0;29.583&#x02032;E</td><td align="left">19</td><td align="left">220</td><td align="left">220</td><td align="left">5 (2.3)</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">H1, H4</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Sub-total</td><td align="left" colspan="4"/><td align="left">1025</td><td align="left">1022</td><td align="left">24 (2.3)</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">Nduna (12.9)</td><td align="left">Kamoyo S</td><td align="left">16&#x000b0;53.735&#x02032;S</td><td align="left">31&#x000b0;24.405&#x02032;E</td><td align="left">20</td><td align="left">20</td><td align="left">16</td><td align="left">0 (0)</td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">H1, T1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Kamoyo S</td><td align="left">16&#x000b0;53.746&#x02032;S</td><td align="left">31&#x000b0;24.415&#x02032;E</td><td align="left">21</td><td align="left">58</td><td align="left">54</td><td align="left">2 (3.7)</td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">H1, T1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Kamoyo S</td><td align="left">16&#x000b0;53.761&#x02032;S</td><td align="left">31&#x000b0;24.376&#x02032;E</td><td align="left">22</td><td align="left">64</td><td align="left">64</td><td align="left">2 (3.1)</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">H1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Sub-total</td><td align="left" colspan="4"/><td align="left">142</td><td align="left">134</td><td align="left">4 (3.0)</td><td align="left">8</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="5">Total of all sites</td><td align="left">1558</td><td align="left">1542</td><td align="left">30 (1.9)</td><td align="left">16</td><td align="left"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>Prevalence of the disease in women and preschool aged children in the communities studied [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]</p><p><sup>b</sup>None of the <italic>B. truncatus</italic> snails collected was infected</p><p><italic>Notes</italic>: Details for the sites and locations where the snail samples were collected, the times of the collections, the total numbers of snails collected and those infected with schistosomes. The haplotypes column shows the different haplotypes that were observed at each site</p><p><italic>Abbreviations</italic>: R, river; S, stream; H, haplotype of <italic>B. globosus</italic>; T, haplotype of <italic>B. truncatus</italic>; USCH, urogenital schistosomiasis</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Analysis of sequence data</title><p id="Par21">After alignment and editing, the query length of the <italic>cox</italic>1 sequences was 607 bp. The query sequences for <italic>B. globosus</italic> were highly similar (&#x0003e;&#x02009;98.0%) to <italic>B. globosus</italic> from Pietermaritzburg, South Africa (GenBank: AM286290 and AM286289). The <italic>B. truncatus</italic> query sequences had a high similarity (99.34%) to <italic>B. truncatus</italic> (GenBank: MG759464) from Zimbabwe.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Haplotype and population genetic diversity, and genetic divergence of <italic>B. globosus</italic></title><p id="Par22">Twelve unique <italic>B. globosus cox</italic>1 haplotypes were found from the 166 samples sequenced. The overall haplotype diversity exceeded 0.5 with a nucleotide diversity estimate of 0.002. The haplotypes were not highly divergent (pairwise distance of 0.002&#x02013;0.007). Within the sites and within communities as expected, haplotype diversity was generally low but ranging between 0&#x02013;0.786 (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). The percentage occurrence of each haplotype differed among sites and communities. One common haplotype (H1) was found in all but one locality representing 114 (68.7%) of the 166 samples analysed. Some haplotypes were locally restricted being observed in one site only but for those represented by a considerable number of snails, there was a clear pattern of haplotype sharing within the river systems with high haplotype sharing being observed in sites that are close to each other or within the same river (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). In Mupfure River, which had the highest number of haplotypes among the rivers, sites that were close together shared the same haplotypes (Tables&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>, <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Some sites had complete <italic>B. globosus</italic> homogeneity and this was observed mainly in Kamoyo stream where all sites had only one haplotype (H1). The homogeneity in Nduna/Kamoyo stream was also supported by lack of haplotype diversity. However, among the sites that had more than one haplotype, overall intra-site haplotype diversity estimates ranged between 0.250&#x02013;0.786 and a considerable number of sites recorded a haplotype diversity of more than 0.5. The maximum number of haplotypes that could be found per site did not exceed four. The mean overall diversity for <italic>B. globosus</italic> was 0.002.<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Mitochondrial cytochrome <italic>c</italic> oxidase 1 diversity of <italic>B. globosus</italic> and <italic>B. truncatus</italic> collected from the Madziwa area, Zimbabwe</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Species</th><th align="left">Location</th><th align="left"><italic>n</italic></th><th align="left">H</th><th align="left">Hd&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD</th><th align="left">&#x003c0;</th><th align="left">&#x003b8;</th><th align="left">Tajima&#x02019;s D statistic</th><th align="left">Fu&#x02019;s Fs statistic</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="27"><italic>B. globosus</italic></td><td align="left">Overall</td><td align="left">166</td><td align="left">12</td><td align="left">0.514&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.046</td><td align="left">0.002</td><td align="left">0.008</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x02009;2.136*</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x02009;3.604</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Chihuri C</td><td align="left">32</td><td align="left">6</td><td align="left">0.637&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.076</td><td align="left">0.003</td><td align="left">0.009</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x02009;2.307**</td><td align="left">0.397</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Site 1</td><td align="left">8</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">0.250&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.180</td><td align="left">0.000</td><td align="left">0.001</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x02009;1.055</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x02009;0.182</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Site 2</td><td align="left">8</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">0.464&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.200</td><td align="left">0.001</td><td align="left">0.001</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x02009;1.310</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x02009;0.999</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Site 3</td><td align="left">8</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">0.536&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.123</td><td align="left">0.001</td><td align="left">0.001</td><td align="left">1.167</td><td align="left">0.866</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Site 4</td><td align="left">8</td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">0.786&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.113</td><td align="left">0.010</td><td align="left">0.014</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x02009;1.466</td><td align="left">2.726</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Kaziro C</td><td align="left">19</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">0.374&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.130</td><td align="left">0.001</td><td align="left">0.001</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x02009;0.729</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x02009;0.671</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Site 7</td><td align="left">7</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Site 8</td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">0.500&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.265</td><td align="left">0.001</td><td align="left">0.001</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x02009;0.612</td><td align="left">0.172</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Site 9</td><td align="left">8</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">0.607&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.164</td><td align="left">0.001</td><td align="left">0.001</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x02009;0.448</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x02009;0.478</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Mupfure C</td><td align="left">98</td><td align="left">10</td><td align="left">0.558&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.057</td><td align="left">0.002</td><td align="left">0.009</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x02009;2.202**</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x02009;2.108</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Site 5</td><td align="left">10</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">0.644&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.101</td><td align="left">0.002</td><td align="left">0.002</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x02009;0.356</td><td align="left">0.390</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Site 6</td><td align="left">9</td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">0.583&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.183</td><td align="left">0.001</td><td align="left">0.002</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x02009;1.610</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x02009;1.283</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Site 10</td><td align="left">8</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">0.714&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.123</td><td align="left">0.014</td><td align="left">0.013</td><td align="left">0.675</td><td align="left">6.022</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Site 11</td><td align="left">8</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">0.679&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.122</td><td align="left">0.001</td><td align="left">0.001</td><td align="left">0.069</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x02009;0.224</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Site 12</td><td align="left">7</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">0.476&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.171</td><td align="left">0.001</td><td align="left">0.001</td><td align="left">0.559</td><td align="left">0.589</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Site 13</td><td align="left">8</td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">0.643&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.184</td><td align="left">0.001</td><td align="left">0.002</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x02009;1.448</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x02009;1.832</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Site 14</td><td align="left">8</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">0.250&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.180</td><td align="left">0.000</td><td align="left">0.001</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x02009;1.055</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x02009;0.182</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Site 15</td><td align="left">8</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">0.607&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.164</td><td align="left">0.001</td><td align="left">0.001</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x02009;0.448</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x02009;0.478</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Site 16</td><td align="left">8</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">0.464&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.200</td><td align="left">0.001</td><td align="left">0.002</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x02009;1.448</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x02009;0.305</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Site 17</td><td align="left">8</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">0.250&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.180</td><td align="left">0.000</td><td align="left">0.001</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x02009;1.055</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x02009;0.182</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Site 18</td><td align="left">8</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">0.571&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.094</td><td align="left">0.001</td><td align="left">0.001</td><td align="left">1.444</td><td align="left">0.966</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Site 19</td><td align="left">8</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">0.250&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.180</td><td align="left">0.000</td><td align="left">0.001</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x02009;1.055</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x02009;0.182</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Nduna C</td><td align="left">17</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Site 20</td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Site 21</td><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Site 22</td><td align="left">8</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4"><italic>B. truncatus</italic></td><td align="left">Overall</td><td align="left">16</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">0.575&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.080</td><td align="left">0.017</td><td align="left">0.012</td><td align="left">1.617</td><td align="left">11.547</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Nyamaruru R</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Mupfure R</td><td align="left">7</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">0.286&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.196</td><td align="left">0.005</td><td align="left">0.007</td><td align="left">&#x02212;&#x02009;1.610*</td><td align="left">4.273</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Kamoyo S</td><td align="left">8</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td><td align="left">&#x02013;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>Abbreviations</italic>: n, number of sequences, h, number of unique haplotypes per site; Hd, haplotype diversity; &#x003c0;, nucleotide diversity; &#x003b8;, theta per site; C, Community; R, River; S, Stream; SD, standard deviation</p><p>*<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, **<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par23">Nucleotide divergence between and within communities was low ranging between 0&#x02013;0.003 (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Expectedly, the genetic divergence between <italic>B. globosus</italic> and <italic>B. truncatus</italic> was high (<italic>Fst</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.920) supporting the species delimitation. When the pairwise fixation index (<italic>Fst</italic>) among the sites was estimated between the populations, a significant number of the populations showed significant levels of differentiation from each other whilst others showed no genetic differentiation. The pairwise <italic>Fst</italic> values ranged between 0&#x02013;0.429 for <italic>B. globosus.</italic> A high genetic differentiation of &#x0003e;&#x02009;30% and above was mainly found among different river systems demonstrating geographically defined gene population structuring (see pairwise <italic>Fst</italic> values for <italic>B. globosus</italic> in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S2). This suggests that the river system maybe acting as a barrier to outbreeding. However, genetic differentiation was very low, ranging between 0.004&#x02013;0.061. Within the communities and river systems, evolutionary divergence ranged between 0&#x02013;0.003 (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Nucleotide divergences among <italic>B. globosus</italic> populations in different communities</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Community</th><th align="left">Mupfure</th><th align="left">Kaziro</th><th align="left">Chihuri</th><th align="left">Nduna</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Mupfure</td><td align="left">0.002</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Kaziro</td><td align="left">0.002</td><td align="left">0.001</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Chihuri</td><td align="left">0.003</td><td align="left">0.002</td><td align="left">0.003</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Nduna</td><td align="left">0.001</td><td align="left">0.0003</td><td align="left">0.002</td><td align="left">0.000</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>Estimation of evolutionary divergence within localities</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Locality</th><th align="left">Mean distance&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><italic>B. globosus</italic> overall</td><td align="left">0.002&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Mupfure community</td><td align="left">0.002&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Kaziro community</td><td align="left">0.001&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Chihuri community</td><td align="left">0.003&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Nduna community</td><td align="left">0.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>B. truncatus</italic> overall</td><td align="left">0.017&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.003</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Mupfure River</td><td align="left">0.017&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.004</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Kamoyo Stream</td><td align="left">0.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Overall mean distance</td><td align="left">0.022&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.003</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>Abbreviation</italic>: SD, standard deviation</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Haplotype, population genetic diversity and genetic divergence of <italic>B. truncatus</italic></title><p id="Par24"><italic>Bulinus truncatus</italic> populations were lower in number compared to <italic>B. globosus</italic> and they were only found in the Nyamaruru, Mupfure rivers and Kamoyo stream. Out of the 16 samples of <italic>B. truncatus</italic> analysed there were three unique <italic>cox</italic>1 haplotypes. The overall haplotype diversity was 0.575 with an estimated nucleotide diversity of 0.017. The average haplotype diversity for <italic>B. truncatus</italic> was also 0.017.</p><p id="Par25">Within the river systems, haplotype diversity ranged between 0&#x02013;0.286 (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). All the three haplotypes were recorded in Mupfure River while the other two rivers exhibited a complete homogeneity (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). The mean pairwise divergence among the haplotypes ranged from 0.017 to 0.034. The pairwise <italic>Fst</italic> value of <italic>B. truncatus</italic> was generated only for Mupfure River and Kamoyo stream, which had more than one sample (0.922). Nucleotide divergence between the Mupfure River and Kamoyo stream was 0.031 (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Neutrality tests</title><p id="Par26">Tajima&#x02019;s D statistic and Fu&#x02019;s Fs statistic showed no selection among the <italic>B. globosus</italic> populations among the sites. However, overall there were significant negative values for both Tajima&#x02019;s D statistic and Fu&#x02019;s Fs statistic. In the case of <italic>B. truncatus</italic>, overall, both neutrality tests were not significant, but Tajima&#x02019;s D was significant for Mupfure River (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Phylogenetic structuring</title><sec id="Sec19"><title>Bulinus globosus</title><p id="Par27">Eleven of the 12 <italic>B. globosus</italic> haplotypes clustered closely with <italic>B. globosus</italic> from South Africa. H8 also had strong support for divergence away from the main haplotype group. One haplotype (H6) was an outlier and clustered more closely with a sample from Tanzania (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>, <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). The topology of the three phylogenetic trees (Figs&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>, <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>; ML, NJ and ME, respectively) was the same. H6 was found in two rivers (Nyamaruru and Mupfure), while H8 occurred in Mupfure River only. H4 was present in Mupfure River and Zvisokwe, a small stream branching into Mupfure River (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). These water systems are also mapped in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>. The accession numbers corresponding to each sequence for all the haplotypes are found in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S3.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Maximum likelihood phylogenetic analysis of the <italic>B. globosus</italic> and <italic>B. truncatus</italic> haplotypes collected in Madziwa, Zimbabwe, in relation to other <italic>Bulinus</italic> species. Each terminal bar is marked using the species name and the code given to the haplotype, e.g. H1 or T1. <italic>Bulinus globosus</italic> and <italic>B. truncatus</italic> haplotypes are represented by the letter H and T, respectively. The bootstrap values below 80% are not shown. There were a total of 607 positions in the final dataset. The accession numbers of the individual sequences forming the haplotypes are shown in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S3. The distribution of sequences among <italic>B. globosus</italic> haplotypes was as follows: haplotype 1 (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;114 samples); haplotype 2 (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;14); haplotype 3 (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;11); haplotype 4 (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;9); haplotype 5 (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;8); haplotype 6 (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3); haplotype 8 (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;2); haplotypes 7, 9, 10, 11 and 12 (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1 sample each). For <italic>B. truncatus</italic>, there were only three haplotypes. Among these three, the most common haplotype (T1) represented 10 samples, T2 representing 5 samples and T3 representing 1 sample</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13071_2020_3881_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig>
<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Neighbor-joining phylogenetic tree of the <italic>B. globosus</italic> and <italic>B. truncatus</italic> haplotypes collected in Madziwa, Zimbabwe, in relation to other <italic>Bulinus</italic> species. Each terminal bar is marked using the species name and the code given to the haplotype, e.g. H1 or T1. <italic>Bulinus globosus</italic> and <italic>B. truncatus</italic> haplotypes are represented by the letter H and T, respectively. The bootstrap values below 80% are not shown. The accession numbers of the individual sequences forming the haplotypes are shown in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S3</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13071_2020_3881_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig>
<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>Minimum evolution phylogenetic tree of the <italic>B. globosus</italic> and <italic>B. truncatus</italic> haplotypes collected in Madziwa, Zimbabwe, in relation to other <italic>Bulinus</italic> species. Each terminal bar is marked using the species name and the code given to the haplotype, e.g. H1 or T1. <italic>Bulinus globosus</italic> and <italic>B. truncatus</italic> haplotypes are represented by the letter H and T, respectively. The significant bootstrap values for 1000 replicates are shown next to the branches. The accession numbers of the individual sequences forming the haplotypes are shown in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S3</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13071_2020_3881_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig>
<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig.&#x000a0;5</label><caption><p>Detailed Maximum Likelihood phylogenetic tree of <italic>B. globosus</italic> and <italic>B. truncatus</italic> showing distribution of haplotypes by site, community and water system. Each terminal bar is marked using the species name, site number and the code given to the haplotype, e.g. H1 or T1. <italic>Bulinus globosus</italic> and <italic>B. truncatus</italic> haplotypes are represented by the letter H and T, respectively. The significant bootstrap values for 1000 replicates are shown next to the branches. The accession numbers of the individual sequences forming the haplotypes are shown in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S3</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13071_2020_3881_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title><italic>Bulinus truncatus</italic></title><p id="Par28">The three <italic>B. truncatus</italic> haplotypes clustered with data from previously characterized samples from Zimbabwe, but there was a considerable phylogenetic separation between the groups (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>, <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). The topology of the three phylogenetic trees (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>, <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>; ML, NJ and ME, respectively) was the same. There was a strong geographical clustering as the clusters were made up of haplotypes from localities that were close together or from a single locality (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). While T2 and T3 were found in Mupfure River, T1 was present in Kamoyo stream and Nyamaruru River. The accession numbers corresponding to each sequence for all the haplotypes are found in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S3.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par29">The present results show that <italic>Bulinus</italic> population diversity exists in Madziwa, Zimbabwe. While the shell microsculpture clearly differed between the two species, as previously observed by Brown [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>], identification can be confusing due to the twisting of the columella in <italic>B. truncatus</italic> and <italic>B. africanus</italic>-group. Within the <italic>B. africanus</italic>-group, it is difficult to clearly distinguish between <italic>B. africanus</italic> and <italic>B. globosus</italic> because the main morphologically variable feature, the penis, varies in size and shape due to parasitic infection, thus was not used in the present study to differentiate the two species. Likewise, as corroborated by Brown [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>], it was difficult to construct a dichotomous key within the <italic>B. tropicus/truncatus</italic> group because of the continuous variation in shell shape between the species in this group.</p><p id="Par30">Amplification of the <italic>cox</italic>1 shows that, within the species morphologically identified as <italic>B. globosus</italic> and <italic>B. truncatus</italic>, complete homogeneity for both was only recorded in Kamoyo stream, Nduna. In other sites, on average within the same site, approximately 25% of the samples had a different haplotype. Although the diversity recorded is low, it is expected within species. However, the diversity recorded in this study is greater than that recorded in Cameroon by Nalugwa et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>] in <italic>B. truncatus</italic> and <italic>B. forskalii</italic> populations where on average 16% of the snails sampled had a different haplotype. The ability of <italic>Bulinus</italic> spp. to self-fertilize and cross-breed induces some genetic consequences [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. <italic>Bulinus globosus</italic> preferentially outbreeds increasing its diversity, therefore, higher genetic variability in the species is expected compared to that of <italic>B. truncatus</italic>, which preferentially self-fertilizes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. However, a previous study has shown that diversification is high in polyploid species such as <italic>B. truncatus</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>].</p><p id="Par31">Except for the dominant <italic>B. globosus cox</italic>1 haplotype, which spanned across almost all the sites where <italic>B. globosus</italic> was found, the diversity in haplotypes among the sites showed that genetic drift most likely due to bottleneck effects is a probable factor in determining diversity within and between species in this area. Our results showed homogeneity within the <italic>B. globosus</italic> originating from Nduna, Kamoyo stream, compared to the other communities. The complete homogeneity could be a result of natural selection, drift or perhaps a recent introduction of the intermediate host snail into these sites. Nevertheless, as presented by Schmid-hempel &#x00026; Stauffer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>], host-parasite susceptibility can increase with loss of genetic variation; the snails in this river had the highest infection rates compared to the other rivers regardless of the fact that very few sites were sampled. On the contrary, a schistosomiasis prevalence study in the area has shown that Nduna community has a significantly low prevalence of the disease compared to Chihuri and Mupfure communities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. Both Mupfure and Chihuri had a higher genetic diversity of the intermediate host as compared to Nduna. Furthermore, the two areas had some infected snails at some point during the year. Thus, the contradicting scenario might be explained by other factors related to water contact behaviour of the human communities, given that schistosomiasis infection is a function of duration of exposure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. We may also hypothesize that the transmission of the disease in Nduna started relatively recently compared to other communities due to the absence of the intermediate host snail. Alternatively, it is highly probable that there is a risk of occurrence of schistosomiasis-transmitting genotypes becoming widely successful with selection of traits independent of parasitic infection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. The expanding population theory is corroborated by the significant test of neutrality for both Tajima&#x02019;s D statistic and Fu&#x02019;s Fs statistic for the whole <italic>B. globosus</italic> population or the <italic>B. truncatus</italic> population in Mupfure River. Similar results have also been reported by Zein-Eddine et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>].</p><p id="Par32">Samples that were collected and analysed in this study, were from sites within close proximity to one another and they had an overall low genetic variation contrary to expectations due to limited gene flow between the populations. However, reproductive isolation, due to the different river systems, may have allowed independent evolution and divergence of these populations leading to formation of different haplotypes. The reproductive isolation might result in complete homogeneity in Kamoyo stream and the presence of &#x02018;unique&#x02019; haplotypes in some of the rivers. Like in the previous study by Standley et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>] for <italic>Biomphalaria choanomphala</italic> in Lake Victoria where the &#x02018;unique&#x02019; haplotypes were locally restricted to the central and western regions of the lakeshore in Uganda, in the present study, the &#x02018;unique&#x02019; haplotypes are also restricted to Nyamaruru and Mupfure rivers.</p><p id="Par33">To our knowledge, the present study provides the first genetic assessment of combined data for <italic>B. globosus</italic> and <italic>B. truncatus</italic> from Zimbabwe, where urogenital schistosomiasis is endemic. However, more sophisticated statistical analyses of these haplotypes should be performed to examine the levels of divergence which may lead to species delimitation.</p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par34">A detailed understanding of genetic variability within intermediate host snail species is important for understanding disease epidemiology. A novel insight from our study is the mitochondrial <italic>cox</italic>1 variability within <italic>B. globosus</italic> and additional <italic>B. truncatus</italic> haplotypes in Madziwa area, Zimbabwe. Further investigations using new tools for detection of infection will help investigate the snail populations involved in transmission. The identification of <italic>Bulinus</italic> in these areas will support targeted control efforts for schistosomiasis in the study area. Further studies over a large spatial area with higher sample size are also required to understand the genetic demographic patterns of these intermediate host snail species.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary information</title><sec id="Sec23"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="13071_2020_3881_MOESM1_ESM.xlsx"><caption><p><bold>Additional file 1: Table S1.</bold> List of sequences drawn from the Genbank incorporated for phylogenetic analysis. <bold>Table S2.</bold> Fst values for <italic>B. globosus</italic> populations. <bold>Table S3.</bold> Accession numbers of individual sequences for the haplotypes recorded in Madziwa, Zimbabwe.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviation</title><def-list><def-item><term><italic>cox</italic>1</term><def><p id="Par5">cytochrome oxidase subunit 1</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher's Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Supplementary information</title><p><bold>Supplementary information</bold> accompanies this paper at 10.1186/s13071-020-3881-1.</p></sec><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>Our appreciation goes to the Madziwa residents and their leaders who allowed us to work in the area and also assisted in identification of water contact sites.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>MJMM, NM, CT and XNZ designed the study protocol. MJMM and NM collected specimens and GPS data. MJMM, EA and NM performed laboratory analysis of specimens. MJMM, BW, JM and TM performed the analysis. MJMM wrote the initial draft of the manuscript. NM, BW, NC, EA and FA reviewed the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>Sample collection was funded by individuals while laboratory analysis was funded by National Institute of Parasitic Diseases, Shanghai.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>Data supporting the conclusions of this article are included within the article and its additional files. The newly generated sequences were submitted to the GenBank database under the accession numbers MN397785&#x02013;MN397822. The datasets analysed during the present study are available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request.</p></notes><notes><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par35">Prior to the commencement of the study, approval was obtained from the community leaders in the area. Ethical clearance of the study was sought from the Joint Research Ethics Committee (JREC) for the University of Zimbabwe, College of Health Sciences and the Parirenyatwa Group of Hospitals (JREC/251/16). Further approval was sought from the national ethical review board, the Medical Research Council of Zimbabwe (MRCZ) (MRCZ/A/2149). The communities were sensitized about the nature of the study and study objectives in local language (Shona).</p></notes><notes><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par36">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par37">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gryseels</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Polman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Clerinx</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kestens</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Human schistosomiasis</article-title><source>Lancet.</source><year>2006</year><volume>368</volume><fpage>1106</fpage><lpage>1118</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(06)69440-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16997665</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rollinson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Stothard</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Southgate</surname><given-names>VR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interactions between intermediate snail hosts of the genus <italic>Bulinus</italic> and schistosomes of the <italic>Schistosoma haematobium</italic> group</article-title><source>Parasitology.</source><year>2001</year><volume>123</volume><issue>Suppl</issue><fpage>245</fpage><lpage>260</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0031182001008046</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kariuki</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Clennon</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Brady</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitron</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Sturrock</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Ouma</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Distribution patterns and cercarial shedding of <italic>Bulinus nasutus</italic> and other snails in the Msambweni area, Coast Province, Kenya</article-title><source>Am J Trop Med Hyg.</source><year>2004</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>449</fpage><lpage>456</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4269/ajtmh.2004.70.449</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15100463</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Allan</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Emery</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Stothard</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kane</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Use of sentinel snails for the detection of Schistosoma haematobium transmission on Zanzibar and observations on transmission patterns</article-title><source>Acta Trop.</source><year>2013</year><volume>128</volume><fpage>234</fpage><lpage>240</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.actatropica.2013.01.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23318933</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Opisa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Odiere</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Jura</surname><given-names>WGZO</given-names></name><name><surname>Karanja</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mwinzi</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Malacological survey and geographical distribution of vector snails for schistosomiasis within informal settlements of Kisumu city, western Kenya</article-title><source>Parasit Vectors.</source><year>2011</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>226</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1756-3305-4-226</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22152486</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Woolhouse</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandiwana</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Temporal patterns in the epidemiology of schistosome infections of snails: a model for field data</article-title><source>Parasitology.</source><year>1990</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>247</fpage><lpage>253</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0031182000061254</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2345659</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Woolhouse</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandiwana</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spatial and temporal heterogeneity in the population dynamics of <italic>Bulinus globosus</italic> and <italic>Biomphalaria pfeifferi</italic> and in the epidemiology of their infection with schistosomes</article-title><source>Parasitology.</source><year>1989</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>34</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0031182000059655</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2717216</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><source>Freshwater snails of Africa and their medical importance</source><year>1994</year><edition>2</edition><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Taylor and Francis</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Makura O, Kristensen TK. National freshwater snail survey of Zimbabwe. In: The tenth international malacological congress. T&#x000fc;bingen: University of T&#x000fc;bingen Press; 1991. p. 227&#x02013;232.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jarne</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Finot</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Delay</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Thaler</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Self-fertilization <italic>versus</italic> cross-fertilization in the hermaphroditic freshwater snail <italic>Bulinus globosus</italic></article-title><source>Evolution.</source><year>1991</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>1136</fpage><lpage>1146</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1558-5646.1991.tb04380.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28564176</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jarne</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Charlesworth</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The evolution of the selfing rate in functionally hermaphrodite plants and animals</article-title><source>Annu Rev Ecol Syst.</source><year>1993</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>441</fpage><lpage>466</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.es.24.110193.002301</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Viard</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Bremond</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Labbo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Justy</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Delay</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Jarne</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microsatellites and the genetics of highly selfing populations in the freshwater snail <italic>Bulinus truncatus</italic></article-title><source>Genetics.</source><year>1996</year><volume>142</volume><fpage>1237</fpage><lpage>1247</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8846901</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zein-Eddine</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Djuikwo-Teukeng</surname><given-names>FF</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Jawhari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Senghor</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Huyse</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Dreyfuss</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phylogeny of seven <italic>Bulinus</italic> species originating from endemic areas in three African countries, in relation to the human blood fluke <italic>Schistosoma haematobium</italic></article-title><source>BMC Evol Biol.</source><year>2014</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>271</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12862-014-0271-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25528261</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zein-Eddine</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Djuikwo-Teukeng</surname><given-names>FF</given-names></name><name><surname>Darc</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Dreyfussa</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Van den Broeckd</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Population genetics of the <italic>Schistosoma</italic> snail host <italic>Bulinus truncatus</italic> in Egypt</article-title><source>Acta Trop.</source><year>2017</year><volume>172</volume><fpage>36</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.actatropica.2017.04.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28408098</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Charbonnel</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Angers</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Rasatavonjizay</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Remond</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name><surname>Debain</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Jarne</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolutionary aspects of the metapopulation dynamics of <italic>Biomphalaria pfeifferi</italic>, the intermediate host of <italic>Schistosoma mansoni</italic></article-title><source>J Evol Biol.</source><year>2002</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>248</fpage><lpage>261</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1420-9101.2002.00381.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thiele</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Corr&#x000ea;a-Oliveira</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Gazzinelli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Minchella</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Elucidating the temporal and spatial dynamics of <italic>Biomphalaria glabrata</italic> genetic diversity in three Brazilian villages</article-title><source>Trop Med Int Health.</source><year>2013</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>1164</fpage><lpage>1173</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/tmi.12164</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23911082</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stothard</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Rollinson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Partial DNA sequences from the mitochondrial cytochrome oxidase subunit I (COI) gene can differentiate the intermediate snail hosts <italic>Bulinus globosus</italic> and <italic>B. nasutus</italic> (Gastropoda: Planorbidae)</article-title><source>J Nat Hist.</source><year>1997</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>727</fpage><lpage>737</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00222939700770361</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kane</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Stothard</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Emery</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rollinson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular characterization of freshwater snails in the genus <italic>Bulinus</italic>: a role for barcodes?</article-title><source>Parasit Vectors.</source><year>2008</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>15</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1756-3305-1-15</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18544153</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abe</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Mutsaka-Makuvaza</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Habib</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Phylogeography of <italic>Bulinus truncatus</italic> (Audouin, 1827) (Gastropoda: Planorbidae) in selected African countries</article-title><source>Trop Med Infect Dis.</source><year>2018</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>E127</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/tropicalmed3040127</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30572694</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mandahl-Barth</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The species of the genus <italic>Bulinus</italic>, intermediate hosts of <italic>Schistosoma</italic></article-title><source>Bull World Health Organ.</source><year>1965</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5294263</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mukaratirwa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sieglsmund</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kristensen</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandiwana</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Population genetics and genetic variability of <italic>Bulinus globosus</italic> (Gastropoda: Planorbidae) from the two main river systems in Zimbabwe</article-title><source>J Hered.</source><year>1996</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>288</fpage><lpage>294</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/oxfordjournals.jhered.a023002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mukaratirwa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Siegismund</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kristensen</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandiwana</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic structure and parasite compatibility of <italic>Bulinus globosus</italic> (Gastropoda: Planorbidae) from two areas of different endemicity of <italic>Schistosoma haematobium</italic> in Zimbabwe</article-title><source>Int J Parasitol</source><year>1996</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>269</fpage><lpage>280</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0020-7519(95)00130-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8786216</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Webster</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Kr&#x000fc;ger</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Munatsi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ndamba</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Woolhouse</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Host-parasite population genetics: a cross-sectional comparison of <italic>Bulinus globosus</italic> and <italic>Schistosoma haematobium</italic></article-title><source>Parasitology.</source><year>1999</year><volume>119</volume><fpage>295</fpage><lpage>302</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0031182099004722</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10503255</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stothard</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rollinson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Variation within the internal transcribed spacer (ITS) of ribosomal DNA genes of intermediate snail hosts within the genus <italic>Bulinus</italic> (Gastropoda: Planorbidae)</article-title><source>Acta Trop.</source><year>1996</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0001-706X(95)00137-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9133161</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mutsaka-Makuvaza</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsena-Zingoni</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Tshuma</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>XN</given-names></name><name><surname>Webster</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Reinfection of urogenital schistosomiasis in pre-school children in a highly endemic district in northern Zimbabwe: compliance assessment in a 12 months longitudinal study</article-title><source>Infect Dis Poverty.</source><year>2018</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>102</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40249-018-0483-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30268157</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>WHO</collab></person-group><source>Field use of molluscicides in schistosomiasis control programmes: an operational manual for programme managers</source><year>2017</year><publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc><publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frandsen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>N&#x000d8;</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An introductory guide to the identification of cercariae from African freshwater snails with special reference to cercariae of trematode species of medical and veterinary importance</article-title><source>Acta Trop.</source><year>1984</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>181</fpage><lpage>202</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6206702</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Altschul</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Gish</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipman</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Basic local alignment search tool</article-title><source>J Mol Biol.</source><year>1990</year><volume>215</volume><fpage>403</fpage><lpage>410</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0022-2836(05)80360-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2231712</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Stecher</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Filipski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MEGA6: molecular evolutionary genetics analysis version 6.0</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol.</source><year>2013</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>2725</fpage><lpage>2729</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/mst197</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24132122</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CLUSTAL W: improving the sensitivity of progressive multiple sequence alignment through sequence weighting, position-specific gap penalties and weight matrix choice</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>1994</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>4673</fpage><lpage>4680</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/22.22.4673</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7984417</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimation of the number of nucleotide substitutions in the control region of mitochondrial DNA in humans and chimpanzees</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol.</source><year>1993</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>512</fpage><lpage>526</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8336541</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Felsenstein</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Confidence limits on phylogenies: an approach using the bootstrap</article-title><source>Evolution.</source><year>1985</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>783</fpage><lpage>791</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1558-5646.1985.tb00420.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28561359</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jukes</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name><surname>Cantor</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Munro</surname><given-names>HN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolution of protein molecules</article-title><source>Mammalian protein metabolism</source><year>1969</year><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>132</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rozas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferrer-Mata</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>S&#x000e1;nchez-DelBarrio</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Guirao-Rico</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Librado</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramos-Onsins</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>DnaSP 6: DNA sequence polymorphism analysis of large data sets</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol.</source><year>2017</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>3299</fpage><lpage>3302</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msx248</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29029172</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tajima</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Statistical methods for testing the neutral mutation hypothesis by DNA polymorphism</article-title><source>Genetics.</source><year>1989</year><volume>123</volume><fpage>585</fpage><lpage>595</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2513255</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nalugwa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>J&#x000f8;rgensen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nyakaana</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kristensen</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular phylogeny of <italic>Bulinus</italic> (Gastropoda: Planorbidae) reveals the presence of three species complexes in the Albertine Rift freshwater bodies</article-title><source>Int J Genet Mol Biol.</source><year>2010</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>130</fpage><lpage>139</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jarne</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Resistance genes at the population level</article-title><source>Parasitol Today.</source><year>1993</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>216</fpage><lpage>217</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0169-4758(93)90014-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15463759</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Freshwater snails of the <italic>Bulinus truncatus/tropicus</italic> complex in Kenya: tetraploid species</article-title><source>J Mollus Stud.</source><year>1989</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>509</fpage><lpage>532</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/mollus/55.4.509</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmid-hempel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Stauffer</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Parasites and flower choice of bumblebees</article-title><source>Anim Behav.</source><year>1998</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>819</fpage><lpage>825</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/anbe.1997.0661</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9632470</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mutsaka-Makuvaza</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsena-Zingoni</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Katsidzira</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tshuma</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Chin&#x02019;ombe</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>XN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Urogenital schistosomiasis and risk factors of infection in mothers and preschool children in an endemic district in Zimbabwe</article-title><source>Parasit Vectors.</source><year>2019</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>427</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13071-019-3667-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31477172</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dalton</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Pole</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Water-contact patterns in relation to <italic>Schistosoma haematobium</italic> infection</article-title><source>Bull World Health Organ.</source><year>1978</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>417</fpage><lpage>426</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">308406</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Noble</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name><surname>Rollinson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Southgate</surname><given-names>VR</given-names></name><name><surname>Webster</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Low genetic diversity in a snail intermediate host (<italic>Biomphalaria pfeifferi</italic> Krass, 1848) and schistosomiasis transmission in the Senegal River Basin</article-title><source>Mol Ecol.</source><year>2010</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>241</fpage><lpage>256</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-294X.2009.04463.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20025653</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Standley</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodacre</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wade</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Stothard</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The population genetic structure of <italic>Biomphalaria choanomphala</italic> in Lake Victoria, East Africa: implications for schistosomiasis transmission</article-title><source>Parasit Vectors.</source><year>2014</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>524</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13071-014-0524-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25406437</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>