<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Insect Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Insect Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jis</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Insect Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1536-2442</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>US</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31925424</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6954386</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jisesa/iez127</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">iez127</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Changes in Morphometric Traits of Ground Beetles Along Urbanization Gradients</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Papp</surname><given-names>Dalma</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8366-6243</contrib-id><name><surname>Mizser</surname><given-names>Szabolcs</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nagy</surname><given-names>Leila</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vidic</surname><given-names>Andreas</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0003">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>Edina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1"/><!--<email>edina.simon@gmail.com</email>--></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>T&#x000f3;thm&#x000e9;r&#x000e9;sz</surname><given-names>B&#x000e9;la</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">2</xref></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>MacRae</surname><given-names>Ted</given-names></name><role>Subject Editor</role></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="AF0001"><label>1</label>
<institution>Department of Ecology, University of Debrecen</institution>, Egyetem t&#x000e9;r 1, Debrecen H-4032, <country country="HU">Hungary</country></aff><aff id="AF0002"><label>2</label>
<institution>MTA-DE Biodiversity and Ecosystem Services Research Group</institution>, Egyetem t&#x000e9;r 1, Debrecen H-4032, <country country="HU">Hungary</country></aff><aff id="AF0003"><label>3</label>
<institution>Department f&#x000fc;r Naturschutzbiologie, Vegetations- und Landschafts&#x000f6;kologie, Universit&#x000e4;t Wien</institution>, Althanstrasse 14, 1090 Wien, <country country="AT">Austria</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="c1">Corresponding author, e-mail: <email>edina.simon@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>1</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2020-01-11"><day>11</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>11</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>20</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>5</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>08</day><month>7</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="editorial-decision"><day>12</day><month>12</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of Entomological Society of America.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><license license-type="cc-by" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="iez127.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><p>Urbanization has a significant impact on abiotic and biotic factors in nature. We examined the morphometric characters of four carabid species (<italic>Abax parallelepipedus</italic>, <italic>Carabus scheidleri</italic>, <italic>Carabus violaceus</italic>, and <italic>Pterostichus oblongopunctatus</italic>) along urbanization gradients in and around the cities of Vienna (Austria) and Debrecen (Hungary). We found significant differences among urban, suburban, and rural areas in the parameters of antennomers, the maxillary palpus, the labial palpus, and the length of the tibia and the elytra of the carabids studied. We also found significant differences between males and females based on the parameters of antennomers, the maxillary palpus, the labial palpus, the femur, and the elytra. An interaction between urbanization and sex was found in the case of antennomers, the maxillary palpus, the labial palpus, the femur, and the elytra. Our findings suggested that in the cases of species from Carabini tribus the parameters of antennomers, the maxillary palpus, and the elytra could be useful for assessing the effects of urbanization because these morphometric characters responded sensitively to the environmental stress, whereas the most useful parameters are those of antennomers and the tibia for the species of Pterostichini tribus. Our findings also revealed that females are more sensitive to environmental stress than males.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Carabidae</kwd><kwd>bioindication</kwd><kwd>asymmetry</kwd><kwd>morphological abnormality</kwd><kwd>urban stress gradient</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source><named-content content-type="funder-name">OTKA</named-content><named-content content-type="funder-identifier">10.13039/501100003549</named-content></funding-source><award-id>K 116639</award-id><award-id>KH 126481</award-id><award-id>KH 126477</award-id></award-group></funding-group><counts><page-count count="9"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><p>The effects of human activities have a significant impact on terrestrial ecosystems. A wide variety of emitted substances (mostly trace elements) directly and indirectly influences abiotic and biotic factors in urbanized areas (<xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">G&#x000e1;l et al. 2008</xref>). The emitted chemical and biological pollutants can change environmental conditions and thereby affect the biodiversity and also the conditions of organisms (<xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">Clarke 1993</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">Peters et al. 2001</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">Cachada et al. 2013</xref>). In addition, unnatural climatic conditions, increasing traffic density and buildup rates, habitat fragmentation, and isolation can also result in specific changes in habitat quality and bring environmental stress (<xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">Saunders et al. 1991</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">Ikeda 2006</xref>). Due to the continuously changing environmental factors, the diversity and community structure of invertebrates may change significantly in urban habitats compared with rural ones (<xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">Faeth et al. 2005</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">Biaggin et al. 2007</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">McKinney 2008</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">Lagucki et al. 2017</xref>). In extreme cases, populations become extinct from areas, which are affected by anthropogenic stress (<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">Acevedo-Whitehouse and Duffus 2009</xref>). However, the damage can also be detected at moderate levels such as in abnormalities of their life cycle and reproduction, as well as in morphometric changes whose effects have been less widely investigated in previous studies (<xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">Peakall 1992</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">Eeva et al. 2000</xref>). Changes in the metric parameters of arthropods can be successfully used as indicators of anthropogenic disturbance (<xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">Lagisz 2008</xref>). In bioindicator arthropods, contaminations and habitat degradation have a significant effect on the occurrence of morphological abnormalities (<xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">Cattaneo et al. 2004</xref>). Abiotic factors such as nutrition quality, buildup rate, and habitat fragmentation can also vary greatly among habitats and affect the development and morphometry of these organisms (<xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">Parsons 1992</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">Weller and Ganzhorn 2003</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0051" ref-type="bibr">Vandewoestijne et al. 2005</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">Shingleton et al. 2007</xref>).</p><p>Arthropod species occur in various habitats. Due to their life cycle, high density, and variability, they are widely used as indicators in environmental risk assessments (<xref rid="CIT0055" ref-type="bibr">Z&#x000f6;ld and Wittmann 2003</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">Magura et al. 2010</xref>). Stress factors can cause morphological abnormalities such as lower body mass and/or asymmetry of the body. To survive, individuals living in disturbed habitats concentrate more energy on elimination processes (<xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">Cortet et al. 1999</xref>). Thus, a lower amount of energy is used for developmental processes. Under constant conditions the development of the phenotype is stable, but overcoming stress factors can induce morphological disorders such as decreased symmetry and body size (<xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">Van Dongen et al. 2001</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">Lens et al. 2002</xref>). Stress-induced asymmetry and the relationship between asymmetry and urbanization were also tested for a variety of arthropod species (<xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">Godet et al. 2012</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">Olivero et al. 2014</xref>). In some cases, the morphological abnormalities were associated with air, soil, and water pollution; pesticides; poor nutrition quality; food deficiency; and isolating factors such as artificial barriers (<xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">Weller and Ganzhorn 2003</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">De Anna et al. 2013</xref>).</p><p>Ground beetles (Coleoptera: Carabidae) are well known both taxonomically and ecologically. These species are sensitive indicators of biotic and abiotic pressure; thus, they are frequently used to explore the effects of soil pollution, forest management, and tourist flow (<xref rid="CIT0052" ref-type="bibr">Venn 2007</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">Sukhodolskaya 2013</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">T&#x00151;zs&#x000e9;r et al. 2019</xref>). Changes in morphological parameters such as the body size and symmetry of carabid beetles potentially indicate different types of extrinsic stress factors (<xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">McGeoch 1998</xref>). There is a highly significant relationship between the functional morphological trait characters of carabid species and the characteristics of their habitat (<xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">Ribera et al. 2001</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">Weller and Ganzhorn 2003</xref>). Thus, carabid species are useful for the investigation of anthropogenic effects. Although many studies have investigated the impacts of urbanization on beetle diversity and richness, fewer studies have been performed regarding the responses of species&#x02019; morphometric traits (e.g., body size and asymmetry). Because reduced body size and the disruption of symmetry reflect severe environmental stresses and/or inbreeding depression, which can be a sign of population decline and local extinction, these need to be explored in the context of urbanization.</p><p>The aim of our study was to examine morphological traits of four ground beetle species (<italic>Abax parallelepipedus</italic>, <italic>Carabus scheidleri</italic>, <italic>Carabus violaceus</italic>, and <italic>Pterostichus oblongopunctatus</italic>) along an urbanization gradient in and around the cities of Vienna and Debrecen. The following metric traits were measured in all studied species, based on the earlier study by <xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">Elek et al. (2014)</xref>: the lengths of three antennomers of the right and left antennae, the lengths of the femur and tibia of the front legs, and the lengths of the right and left elytra (inner edges). Two palpomers of the right and left maxillary palpus and labial palpus were measured in <italic>A. parallelepipedus</italic>, <italic>C. scheidleri</italic>, and <italic>C. violaceus</italic>. We hypothesized that the tested morphometric traits change under different levels of anthropogenic stress. Therefore, we predicted that 1) along an urbanization gradient detectable differences are found based on Carabid morphometry, 2) the size of the measured traits is greater in males than in females, and 3) the symmetry of morphological traits is affected by urbanization; thus, the tested areas could be separated from each other based on the level of asymmetry of the beetles&#x02019; bodies.</p><sec sec-type="materials" id="s1"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s2"><title>Study Area and Sampling Design</title><p>Sampling areas were located in and around the cities of Vienna (Austria) and Debrecen (Hungary) similarly to the globenet protocol (<xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">Niemel&#x000e4; et al. 2000</xref>). We used an identical sampling design in both countries; based on <xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">Simon et al. (2013</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>), a gradient was chosen to represent the effects of urbanization on morphological characteristics in various habitats. Along the gradient three areas were selected with increasing levels of urbanization: rural, suburban, and urban. Four spatial replicates (sites) were selected within each sampling area. In each site, 20 traps were used. Thus, in summary, 80 traps were used in each area. Adult carabids were collected by trapping during their reproductive period from May to August in 2010 in both cities. Until the measurement processes, the samples were stored in polyethylene bags at &#x02212;18&#x000b0;C.</p><p>There were <italic>A. parallelepipedus</italic> (Pterostichini tribus) and <italic>C. scheidleri</italic> (Carabini tribus) specimens collected in and around the city of Vienna along an urbanization gradient. From the studied areas, the number of <italic>A. parallelepipedus</italic> specimens was 47 (urban: <italic>n</italic> = 10, suburban: <italic>n</italic> = 20, rural: <italic>n</italic> = 17), and the number of collected <italic>C. scheidleri</italic> specimens was 55 (urban: <italic>n</italic> = 18, suburban: <italic>n</italic> = 19, rural: <italic>n</italic> = 18).</p><p>In and around Vienna, all sampling areas of the gradient were characterized by high habitat dynamics, and specific soil parameters and vegetation types. The urban area was located in the Wiener Prater (48&#x000b0;12&#x02032;N, 16&#x000b0;24&#x02032;E) near the city center in a forested park. In this area, the proportion of green space was 39.1%, and the transport system is remarkable in this area of the city. The suburban area was in the district of Leopoldstadt (48&#x000b0;11&#x02032;N, 16&#x000b0;26&#x02032;E) where the green space made up 63.5% of the total area. The rural area (48&#x000b0;10&#x02032;N, 16&#x000b0;31&#x02032;E) was located within the Donau-Auen National Park along the Donau-Oder-Kanal. In this area, the green space was 99.5%, and forest management, traffic, and tourism intensity were reduced.</p><p>There were <italic>C. violaceus</italic> (Carabini tribus) and <italic>P. oblongopunctatus</italic> (Pterostichini tribus) specimens collected in and around Debrecen along an urbanization gradient similar to that in Vienna. The number of <italic>C. violaceus</italic> was 188 (urban: <italic>n</italic> = 98, suburban: <italic>n</italic> = 13, rural: <italic>n</italic> = 77), and the number of <italic>P. oblongopunctatus</italic> was 57 (urban: <italic>n</italic> = 25, suburban: <italic>n</italic> = 11, rural: <italic>n</italic> = 21). The urban area was located within a forested park in the city center (47&#x000b0;32&#x02032;N, 21&#x000b0;37&#x02032;E) similar to the studied urban area in Vienna. This area was characterized by a high traffic load. The suburban area (47&#x000b0;33&#x02032;N, 21&#x000b0;38&#x02032;E) was located between urban and rural areas. These forest fragments are characterized by moderate anthropogenic disturbance, and there was park maintenance activity. The rural area (47&#x000b0;34&#x02032;N, 21&#x000b0;37&#x02032;E) was located in a forested area outside Debrecen (<xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">Simon et al. 2014</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Morphometry of Carabid Beetles</title><p>During data acquisition, the following metric traits were measured in all species studied, based on the earlier study by <xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">Elek et al. (2014)</xref>: 1) the lengths of the right and left second, 2) third, and 3) fourth segments of the antennomers, 4) the lengths of the first femora, 5) the first tibiae, and 6) the lengths of the elytra (inner edges; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1 F2 F3">Figs. 1&#x02013;3</xref>). 7) The lengths of the second palpomer and 8) the lengths and 9) widths of the third palpomer of the right and left maxillary palpus; 10) the distance between the two extreme setae on the first palpomer; and 11) the widths and 12) lengths of the second palpomer of the right and left labial palpus were measured in <italic>A. parallelepipedus</italic>, <italic>C. scheidleri</italic>, and <italic>C. violaceus</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). The removal process of maxillary palpus and labial palpus was impracticable for <italic>P. oblongopunctatus</italic> due to the small average body size (10.3 mm) of this species (<xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr">H&#x0016f;rka 1996</xref>). Each individual was measured three times. A digital camera (Olympus C-7070) attached to a stereomicroscope (Olympus SZX7) was used to photograph the ground beetles. During the photo documentation, the samples were kept wet; thus, the original lengths and shapes of individuals were maintained. The measurement of the metric traits was performed by the WinImag 1.0 data acquisition system.</p><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p>The measured morphological traits. Notations: a2, length of the second segment (antennomer) of the antenna; a3, length of the third segment (antennomer) of the antenna; a4, length of the fourth segment (antennomer) of the antenna; pm2, length of the second palpomer of the maxillary palpus; pm3l, length of the third palpomer of the maxillary palpus; pm3w, width of the third palpomer of the maxillary palpus; pl1, distance between the two extreme setae on the first palpomer of the labial palpus; pl2l, length of the second palpomer of the labial palpus; pl2w, width of the second palpomer of the labial palpus.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="iez127f0001"/></fig><fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><p>The measured morphological traits. Notations: 1lf, femur length of the front leg, 1lt, length of tibia of the front leg.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="iez127f0002"/></fig><fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><p>The measured morphological traits. Notation: el, length of the elytron (inner edges).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="iez127f0003"/></fig></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Data Analysis</title><p>SPSS/PC+ and CANOCO program packages were used during the statistical analyses. The homogeneity of variances was tested by Levene&#x02019;s test. Principal component analysis (PCA) was used to explore the differences in the measured traits. Generalized linear model (GLM) was used to test the differences in the morphological traits of the studied species in the studied areas (urban, suburban, and rural), and the sex of the specimens (female and male), and for the interaction analysis between urbanization and sex. Asymmetry (right and left) was tested by the Mann&#x02013;Whitney <italic>U</italic> test.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Results</title><p>Using PCA, there were overlaps among the studied areas (urban, suburban, and rural) based on morphological traits (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>). In the case of sex, there was little overlap between males and females based on the morphological traits by PCA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>).</p><fig id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 4.</label><caption><p>Principal component biplot of morphological traits of the studied carabid species. Notations: filled square&#x02014;males from urban areas, blank square&#x02014;females from urban areas, filled circle&#x02014;males from suburban areas, blank circle&#x02014;females from suburban areas, filled triangle&#x02014;males from rural areas, blank triangle&#x02014;females from rural areas.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="iez127f0004"/></fig><p>Using GLM, a significant difference was found among areas in the width of the second palpomer of the labial palpus and the length of the tibia in the case of <italic>A. parallelepipedus</italic>. The greatest width of the second palpomer of the labial palpus was found in the suburban, whereas the greatest length of the tibia was found in the urban area. In the case of <italic>C. scheidleri</italic>, the greatest length of the second segment of the antenna and the greatest width of the third palpomer of the maxillary palpus were found in the urban area. The length of the third segment of the antenna, the length of the fourth segment of the antenna, and the width of the second palpomer of the labial palpus were all greater in the surburban area than in the rural area. Based on the measured traits of <italic>C. violaceus</italic>, the greatest length of the fourth segment of the antenna, and the greatest length and width of the third palpomer of the maxillary palpus, and the greatest length of the elytra were found in the suburban area. In the case of <italic>P. oblongopunctatus</italic>, the length of the third segment of the antenna was the highest in the rural area, whereas the length of the fourth segment of the antenna and the length of tibia was the highest in the suburban area (<xref rid="T1 T2 T3" ref-type="table">Tables 1&#x02013;3</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Descriptive statistics of morphological traits (mean &#x000b1; SE) of <italic>Carabus scheidleri</italic> and <italic>Abax parallelepipedus</italic></p></caption><table frame="vsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Traits</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urban</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Suburban</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rural</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Carabus scheidleri</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">a2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93 + 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93 + 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92 + 0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90 + 0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93 + 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95 + 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89 + 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89 + 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78 + 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83 + 0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92 + 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94 + 0.02</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">a3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.57 + 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.56 + 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.39 + 0.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.42 + 0.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.58 + 0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.53 + 0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.49 + 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.48 + 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.35 + 0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.35 + 0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.57 + 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.55 + 0.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">a4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.32 + 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.31 + 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.29 + 0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.26 + 0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.31 + 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.30 + 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.23 + 0.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.22 + 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14 + 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.15 + 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.32 + 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.29 + 0.02</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pm2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03 + 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03 + 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02 + 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02 + 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08 + 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.11 + 0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08 + 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09 + 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01 + 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99 + 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03 + 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03 + 0.02</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pm3l</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10 + 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07 + 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09 + 0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09 + 0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14 + 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14 + 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09 + 0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.11 + 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.11 + 0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.13 + 0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06 + 0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05 + 0.06</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pm3w</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53 + 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52 + 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50 + 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50 + 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55 + 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54 + 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53 + 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54 + 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49 + 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50 + 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53 + 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53 + 0.02</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pl1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42 + 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40 + 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50 + 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49 + 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42 + 0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40 + 0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43 + 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47 + 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45 + 0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43 + 0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44 + 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39 + 0.02</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pl2l</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.27 + 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.28 + 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.36 + 0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.34 + 0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.31 + 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.35 + 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.34 + 0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.35 + 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.31 + 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.30 + 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.28 + 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.29 + 0.03</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pl2w</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54 + 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55 + 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57 + 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56 + 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57 + 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56 + 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57 + 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57 + 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52 + 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53 + 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54 + 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54 + 0.02</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">femur</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.75 + 0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.85 + 0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.13 + 0.18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.16 + 0.18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.90 + 0.16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.97 + 0.16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.98 + 0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.21 + 0.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.62 + 0.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.65 + 0.22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.06 + 0.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.20 + 0.15</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">tibia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.82 + 0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.74 + 0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.21 + 0.21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.29 + 0.16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.82 + 0.20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.80 + 0.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.12 + 0.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.17 + 0.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.60 + 0.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.60 + 0.23</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.08 + 0.16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.12 + 0.15</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">elytra</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.4 + 0.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.5 + 0.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.0 + 0.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.1 + 0.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.7 + 0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.8 + 0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.4 + 0.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.4 + 0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.8 + 0.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.9 + 0.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.8 + 0.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.9 + 0.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Abax parallelepipedus</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">a2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65 + 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64 + 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.66 + 0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62 + 0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63 + 0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62 + 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65 + 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63 + 0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65 + 0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63 + 0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60 + 0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60 + 0.05</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">a3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.92 + 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93 + 0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89 + 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90 + 0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91 + 0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90 + 0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87 + 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86 + 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93 + 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93 + 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86 + 0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87 + 0.05</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">a4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93 + 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93 + 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87 + 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89 + 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93 + 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91 + 0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87 + 0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87 + 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94 + 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94 + 0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84 + 0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86 + 0.04</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pm2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.66 + 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67 + 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67 + 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67 + 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67 + 0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68 + 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63 + 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65 + 0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.66 + 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.66 + 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68 + 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67 + 0.04</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pm3l</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78 + 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76 + 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76 + 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74 + 0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73 + 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72 + 0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75 + 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74 + 0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75 + 0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72 + 0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73 + 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74 + 0.02</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pm3w</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23 + 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24 + 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23 + 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24 + 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23 + 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24 + 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22 + 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24 + 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23 + 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24 + 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22 + 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23 + 0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pl1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15 + 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14 + 0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15 + 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14 + 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15 + 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16 + 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16 + 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17 + 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15 + 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14 + 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14 + 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13 + 0.02</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pl2l</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86 + 0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86 + 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87 + 0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86 + 0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84 + 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84 + 0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89 + 0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90 + 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88 + 0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88 + 0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87 + 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88 + 0.03</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pl2w</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17 + 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17 + 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16 + 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15 + 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20 + 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20 + 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15 + 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15 + 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14 + 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14 + 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13 + 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12 + 0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">femur</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.62 + 0.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.69 + 0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.67 + 0.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.72 + 0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.74 + 0.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.82 + 0.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.58 + 0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.70 + 0.21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.73 + 0.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.77 + 0.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.58 + 0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.68 + 0.15</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">tibia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.67 + 0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.71 + 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.69 + 0.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.73 + 0.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.61 + 0.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.65 + 0.16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.51 + 0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.55 + 0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.67 + 0.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.69 + 0.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.58 + 0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.62 + 0.06</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">elytra</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.6 + 0.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.8 + 0.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.7 + 0.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.7 + 0.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.7 + 0.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.8 + 0.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.8 + 0.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.8 + 0.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.6 + 0.4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.1 + 0.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.3 + 0.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.3 + 0.6</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="fn-0100"><p>Notations: a2, length of the second segment of the antennomer flagellum; a3, length of the third segment of the antennomer; a4, length of the fourth segment of the antennomer; pm2, length of the second palpomer of the maxillary palpus; pm3l, length of the third palpomer of the maxillary palpus; pm3w, width of the third palpomer of the maxillary palpus; pl1, distance between the two extreme setae on the first palpomer of labial palpus; pl2l, length of the second palpomer of labial palpus; pl2w, width of the second palpomer of labial palpus; femur, length of femur in front leg; tibia, length of tibia in front leg; elytra, length of elytra, mm.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Descriptive statistics of morphological traits (mean &#x000b1; SE) of <italic>Carabus violaceus</italic> and <italic>Pterostichus oblongopunctatus</italic></p></caption><table frame="vsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Traits</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urban</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Suburban</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rural</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Right</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Left</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Carabus violaceus</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">a2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07 &#x000b1; 0.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07 &#x000b1; 0.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07 &#x000b1; 0.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09 &#x000b1; 0.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.16 &#x000b1; 0.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17 &#x000b1; 0.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.05 &#x000b1; 0.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06 &#x000b1; 0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06 &#x000b1; 0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07 &#x000b1; 0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07 &#x000b1; 0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10 &#x000b1; 0.06</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">a3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.50 &#x000b1; 0.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.50 &#x000b1; 0.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.52 &#x000b1; 0.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.52 &#x000b1; 0.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.64 &#x000b1; 0.21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.67 &#x000b1; 0.21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.49 &#x000b1; 0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.46 &#x000b1; 0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.51 &#x000b1; 0.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.50 &#x000b1; 0.12</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.51 &#x000b1; 0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.51 &#x000b1; 0.09</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">a4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18 &#x000b1; 0.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18 &#x000b1; 0.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20 &#x000b1; 0.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20 &#x000b1; 0.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.31 &#x000b1; 0.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.31 &#x000b1; 0.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18 &#x000b1; 0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20 &#x000b1; 0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18 &#x000b1; 0.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18 &#x000b1; 0.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20 &#x000b1; 0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20 &#x000b1; 0.08</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pm2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07 &#x000b1; 0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07 &#x000b1; 0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07 &#x000b1; 0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08 &#x000b1; 0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.11 &#x000b1; 0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.12 &#x000b1; 0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09 &#x000b1; 0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10 &#x000b1; 0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09 &#x000b1; 0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10 &#x000b1; 0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09 &#x000b1; 0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09 &#x000b1; 0.07</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pm3l</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17 &#x000b1; 0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17 &#x000b1; 0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.14 &#x000b1; 0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.13 &#x000b1; 0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.22 &#x000b1; 0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.22 &#x000b1; 0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20 &#x000b1; 0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.19 &#x000b1; 0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20 &#x000b1; 0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.19 &#x000b1; 0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17 &#x000b1; 0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.15 &#x000b1; 0.04</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pm3w</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77 &#x000b1; 0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77 &#x000b1; 0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64 &#x000b1; 0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65 &#x000b1; 0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78 &#x000b1; 0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77 &#x000b1; 0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76 &#x000b1; 0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77 &#x000b1; 0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76 &#x000b1; 0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77 &#x000b1; 0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63 &#x000b1; 0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64 &#x000b1; 0.06</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pl1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84 &#x000b1; 0.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89 &#x000b1; 0.18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76 &#x000b1; 0.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79 &#x000b1; 0.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80 &#x000b1; 0.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86 &#x000b1; 0.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89 &#x000b1; 0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88 &#x000b1; 0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89 &#x000b1; 0.18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88 &#x000b1; 0.18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83 &#x000b1; 0.16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79 &#x000b1; 0.16</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pl2l</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.36 &#x000b1; 0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.37 &#x000b1; 0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.24 &#x000b1; 0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.26 &#x000b1; 0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.35 &#x000b1; 0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.36 &#x000b1; 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.29 &#x000b1; 0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.31 &#x000b1; 0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.36 &#x000b1; 0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.36 &#x000b1; 0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.28 &#x000b1; 0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.30 &#x000b1; 0.07</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pl2w</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86 &#x000b1; 0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87 &#x000b1; 0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.71 &#x000b1; 0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70 &#x000b1; 0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83 &#x000b1; 0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84 &#x000b1; 0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77 &#x000b1; 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74 &#x000b1; 0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86 &#x000b1; 0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87 &#x000b1; 0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68 &#x000b1; 0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69 &#x000b1; 0.05</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">femur</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.96 &#x000b1; 0.29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.03 &#x000b1; 0.27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.94 &#x000b1; 0.22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.01 &#x000b1; 0.22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.09 &#x000b1; 0.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.17 &#x000b1; 0.27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.86 &#x000b1; 0.41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00 &#x000b1; 0.27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.98 &#x000b1; 0.26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.01 &#x000b1; 0.26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.98 &#x000b1; 0.29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.05 &#x000b1; 0.27</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">tibia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.78 &#x000b1; 0.24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.81 &#x000b1; 0.24</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.84 &#x000b1; 0.20</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.95 &#x000b1; 0.27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.88 &#x000b1; 0.22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.94 &#x000b1; 0.21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.76 &#x000b1; 0.29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.85 &#x000b1; 0.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.77 &#x000b1; 0.26</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.78 &#x000b1; 0.28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.90 &#x000b1; 0.26 </td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.97 &#x000b1; 0.27</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">elytra</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.7 &#x000b1; 0.8</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.7 &#x000b1; 0.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.9 &#x000b1; 0.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.9 &#x000b1; 0.9</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.1 &#x000b1; 0.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.0 &#x000b1; 0.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.8 &#x000b1; 1.2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.8 &#x000b1; 1.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.5 &#x000b1; 1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.5 &#x000b1; 1.0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.5 &#x000b1; 0.7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.4 &#x000b1; 0.7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Pterostichus oblongopunctatus</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">a2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33 &#x000b1; 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34 &#x000b1; 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31 &#x000b1; 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33 &#x000b1; 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.330 &#x000b1; 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34 &#x000b1; 0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34 &#x000b1; 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35 &#x000b1; 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34 &#x000b1; 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33 &#x000b1; 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33 &#x000b1; 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33 &#x000b1; 0.04</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">a3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54 &#x000b1; 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54 &#x000b1; 0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53 &#x000b1; 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52 &#x000b1; 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55 &#x000b1; 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54 &#x000b1; 0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55 &#x000b1; 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54 &#x000b1; 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57 &#x000b1; 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57 &#x000b1; 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55 &#x000b1; 0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56 &#x000b1; 0.03</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">a4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49 &#x000b1; 0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50 &#x000b1; 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48 &#x000b1; 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48 &#x000b1; 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51 &#x000b1; 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50 &#x000b1; 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51 &#x000b1; 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51 &#x000b1; 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52 &#x000b1; 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52 &#x000b1; 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49 &#x000b1; 0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50 &#x000b1; 0.03</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">femur</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.09 &#x000b1; 0.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.06 &#x000b1; 0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.02 &#x000b1; 0.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.01 &#x000b1; 0.15</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.15 &#x000b1; 0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.11 &#x000b1; 0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.12 &#x000b1; 0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.09 &#x000b1; 0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.01 &#x000b1; 0.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.01 &#x000b1; 0.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.13 &#x000b1; 0.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.10 &#x000b1; 0.11</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">tibia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.24 &#x000b1; 0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.18 &#x000b1; 0.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.12 &#x000b1; 0.14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.04 &#x000b1; 0.17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.28 &#x000b1; 0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.26 &#x000b1; 0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.23 &#x000b1; 0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.18 &#x000b1; 0.08</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.16 &#x000b1; 0.13</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.11 &#x000b1; 0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.22 &#x000b1; 0.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.18 &#x000b1; 0.12</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">elytra</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.47 &#x000b1; 0.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.49 &#x000b1; 0.46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.50 &#x000b1; 0.36</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.64 &#x000b1; 0.39</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.53 &#x000b1; 0.51</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.79 &#x000b1; 0.46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.64 &#x000b1; 0.47</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.64 &#x000b1; 0.44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.22 &#x000b1; 0.32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.26 &#x000b1; 0.37</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.68 &#x000b1; 0.22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.71 &#x000b1; 0.22</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="fn-0101"><p>Notations: a2, length of the second segment of the antennomer flagellum; a3, length of the third segment of the antennomer; a4, length of the fourth segment of the antennomer; pm2, the length of the second palpomer of the maxillary palpus; pm3l, length of the third palpomer of the maxillary palpus; pm3w, width of the third palpomer of the maxillary palpus; pl1, distance between the two extreme setae on the first palpomer of labial palpus; pl2l, length of the second palpomer of the labial palpus; pl2w, width of the second palpomer of the labial palpus; femur, length of the femur in front leg; tibia, length of the tibia in front leg; elytra, length of the elytra, mm.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>
<italic>P</italic> values of morphological traits based on carabid species, studied areas, sex, and interaction between areas and sex</p></caption><table frame="vsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Abax parallelepipedus</italic>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Carabus scheidleri</italic>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Carabus violaceus</italic>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Pterostichus oblongopunctatus</italic>
</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Area</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Area &#x000d7; sex</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Area</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Area &#x000d7; sex</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Area</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Area &#x000d7; sex</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Area</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sex</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Area &#x000d7; sex</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">a2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.343</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.218</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.059</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.008</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.161</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.225</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.055</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.015</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.309</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.623</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.314</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">a3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.208</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.341</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.023</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.806</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.179</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.017</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.201</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.745</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">a4</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.478</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.050</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.013</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.369</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.036</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.123</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.015</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.123</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.110</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pm2</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.919</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.449</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.658</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.559</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.518</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.012</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.648</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.953</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.m.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.m.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.m.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pm3l</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.233</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.590</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.085</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.216</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.138</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.233</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.891</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.m.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.m.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.m.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pm3w</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.569</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.129</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.767</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.952</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.012</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.113</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.340</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.m.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.m.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.m.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pl1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.017</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.916</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.602</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.387</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.021</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.012</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.359</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.022</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.229</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.m.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.m.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.m.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pl2l</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.482</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.101</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.086</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.196</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.204</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.169</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.116</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.028</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.m.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.m.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.m.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pl2w</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.053</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.866</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.097</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.m.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.m.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">n.m.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">femur</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.763</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.027</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.056</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.305</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.139</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.605</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.119</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.200</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.049</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.855</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">tibia</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.023</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.139</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.325</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.245</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.545</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.957</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.203</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.073</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.008</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.069</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">elytra</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.233</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.148</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.078</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.103</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.169</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.018</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0,019</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="fn-0102"><p>Notations: a2, length of segment of second antennomer; a3, length of segment of third antennomer; a4, length of segment of fourth antennomer; pm2, the length of second palpomer of maxillary palpus; pm3l, length of third palpomer of maxillary palpus; pm3w, the width of third palpomer of maxillary palpus; pl1, distance between the two extreme setae on the first palpomer of labial palpus; pl2l, length of second palpomer of labial palpus; pl2w, width of second palpomere of labial palpus; femur, length of femur in front leg; tibia, length of tibia in front leg; elytra, length of elytra. n.m. means that parameters were not measured.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Significant differences were found between males and females for the length of the third and fourth segments of the antenna, the length and width of the third palpomer of the maxillary palpus, the length and width of the second palpomer of labial palpus, and the lengths of the femur and the elytra. The length of the third segment of the antenna was greater in <italic>A. parallelepipedus</italic> and <italic>C. violaceus</italic> males than in females. The fourth segment of the antenna was also longer in <italic>A. parallelepipedus</italic> males than in females. The length of the third palpomer of the maxillary palpus, the width of the third palpomer of the maxillary palpus, and the length of the second palpomer of the labial palpus were greater in <italic>C. violaceus</italic> males than in females. The width of the second palpomer of the labial palpus was greater in <italic>A. parallelepipedus</italic> and <italic>C. violaceus</italic> males than in females. The length of the femur was greater in <italic>A. parallelepipedus</italic> males than in females. The elytra lengths of <italic>C. scheidleri</italic>, <italic>C. violaceus</italic>, and <italic>P. oblongopunctatus</italic> in females were greater than in males (<xref rid="T1 T2 T3" ref-type="table">Tables 1&#x02013;3</xref>).</p><p>Studying the interaction between urbanization and sex we found significant differences in the following traits: all tested antennomers in <italic>C. scheidleri</italic> and <italic>C. violaceus</italic>, the width of the third palpomer of the maxillary palpus, and the distance between the two extreme setae on the first palpomer of the labial palpus in <italic>C. scheidleri</italic>, the width of the second palpomer of the labial palpus in <italic>A. parallelepipedus</italic>, the length of femur and tibia in <italic>P. oblongopunctatus</italic>, and the length of the elytra in <italic>C. violaceus</italic> and <italic>P. oblongopunctatus</italic>.</p><p>Significant asymmetry was found in the lengths and widths of the third palpomer of the right and left maxillary palpus and the widths of the second palpomer of the right and left labial palpus for all tested species along the gradient (<xref rid="T1 T2 T3" ref-type="table">Tables 1&#x02013;3</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Discussion</title><p>Morphometric abnormalities are frequently caused by pollution and/or unfavorable habitat conditions (<xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">Saunders et al. 1991</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">Cachada et al. 2013</xref>). We found differences along the urbanization gradient based on the following parameters of the studied traits: antennomers, the maxillary palpus, the labial palpus, and the length of tibia and the elytra. <xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">Weller and Ganzhorn (2003)</xref> also found morphological changes along the urbanization gradient where the body length of <italic>Carabus nemoralis</italic> declined toward the city center. <xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">Marya&#x00144;ski et al. (2002)</xref> found that metal-contaminated food also had morphometric effects on <italic>Poecilus cupreus</italic> L. under laboratory conditions. They found morphometric effects of lifetime exposure in the case of both zinc and cadmium; these differences were highly significant. In metal-treated individuals, the lengths of the middle femur and front tibia were significantly reduced. <xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">Marya&#x00144;ski et al. (2002)</xref> concluded that individuals exposed to metal-contaminated food concentrated less energy on growth and fat accumulation and more energy on the detoxification process.</p><p>Our results suggested that in the cases of the species of Carabini tribus, the antennomers, the maxillary palpus, and the elytra could be useful for assessing the effects of urbanization, whereas in the case of species of Pterostichini tribus, the most useful would be the antennomers and the tibia. Smaller carabid species were more abundant in highly disturbed urban sites; in contrast, large species, which are flightless and therefore have limited dispersal power, are more abundant in a mosaic landscape (<xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">Den Boer 1990</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">Blake et al. 1994</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">Ribera et al. 2001</xref>). Generalist species that occur at all sites and prefer disturbed areas are more resistant to disturbance. Due to their resistance, these species is less affected by urbanization, and the urbanization effects are less traceable by measuring parameters of body parts (<xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">Weller and Ganzhorn 2003</xref>). <xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">Sukhodolskaya (2013)</xref> found that the morphometric traits of <italic>Carabus granulatus</italic> specimens were higher in suburban habitats than in natural ones. They also found that forested urban habitats are more heterogeneous than homogenous natural areas in size and food supply. In urbanized areas, the elevated temperature may be an additional component in influencing the development and life cycle of beetles, but in these areas, contamination and fragmentation constitute the major negative pressures on sensitive carabid species. <xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">Stone et al. (2001)</xref> showed that <italic>P. oblongopunctatus</italic> from chronically metal-polluted sites were less tolerant to additional environmental stressors; the study examined the relationship between metal toxicity and the state of energy reserves and metabolic rates of <italic>P. oblongopunctatus</italic>.</p><p>In our study, we found significant differences between male and female individuals based on the parameters of the antennomers, the maxillary palpus, the labial palpus and the length of the tibia, the femur, and the elytra. Under stable environmental conditions, morphological differences between males and females can be explained by their roles in reproduction. For example, the energy allocation of females is concentrated on gamete production and contributes greatly to the explanation of sexual size dimorphism (<xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">Nylin and Gotthard 1998</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr">Tammaru et al. 2002</xref>). <xref rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr">Thiele (1977)</xref> and <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">Lagisz (2008)</xref> demonstrated that the elytra length of <italic>P. oblongopunctatus</italic> females was significantly larger than in males, which is typical in carabid species. Similarly to these studies, we found that the elytra length of female <italic>C. scheidleri</italic>, <italic>C. violaceus</italic>, and <italic>P. oblongopunctatus</italic> was larger than it was in males. The effects of environmental stress can disrupt the normal energy distribution of the beetles&#x02019; body (<xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">Cortet et al. 1999</xref>). Thus, the different reaction of males and females to external stress is one of the most decisive reasons for their divergent morphological appearance (<xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">Badyaev 2002</xref>). <xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">Sukhodolskaya (2013)</xref> demonstrated that urbanization significantly contributes to elytra length variation. In urban habitats, <italic>Carabus aeruginosus</italic> males&#x02019; elytra length increased but that of females decreased, and in <italic>C. granulatus</italic> and <italic>Pterostichus niger</italic>, this trait did not change significantly along the urban&#x02013;rural gradient. In rural habitats, the elytra length increased in <italic>Carabus cancellatus</italic> males and in both sexes in <italic>P. cupreus</italic>. In our study, we found morphological differences between sexes only in one species along the tested gradient. In urban areas, the elytra length increased in <italic>P. oblongopunctatus</italic> males, but decreased in females.</p><p>Earlier studies demonstrated that the symmetry and body size of arthropods (woodlice, fruit fly) can be influenced by environmental stress (<xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">Peters et al. 2001</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">Trotta et al. 2005</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">Vilisics et al. 2005</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">Godet et al. 2011</xref>). The influence of special conditions in urbanized areas on the morphometry of ground beetle species is very variable and contradictory (<xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">Braun et al. 2004</xref>). <xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">Weller and Ganzhorn (2003)</xref> tested the fluctuating asymmetry (FA) of carabid species along an urban&#x02013;rural gradient. In the tested species, including <italic>A. parallelepipedus</italic>, <italic>C. violaceus</italic>, and <italic>P. oblongopunctatus</italic>, the asymmetry of the elytra increased toward the city center and with increasing isolation of the studied areas. In contrast to these studies, <xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">Henr&#x000ed;quez et al. (2009)</xref> demonstrated that the asymmetry of the posterior femur of <italic>Carabus chilensis</italic> individuals did not increase in fragmented habitats. <xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">Elek et al. (2014)</xref> tested the asymmetry of the lengths of the antennomers, the elytra, the first and second tibiae, the first tarsi and the distance between the end of the femur, and the proximal and distal spines on the first femora of <italic>C. nemoralis</italic>, <italic>Nebria brevicollis</italic>, and <italic>Pterostichus melanarius</italic>. The authors did not find any increase in FA along an urbanization gradient. <xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">Marya&#x00144;ski et al. (2002)</xref> demonstrated that zinc- or cadmium-contaminated food had no effect on symmetry in major and minor axes of the elytra, nor on the length of the front, middle, and hind femur and tibia of <italic>P. cupreus</italic>. In our study, the symmetry of the lengths and widths of the third palpomer of the right and left maxillary palpus and the widths of the second palpomer of the right and left labial palpus changed along the gradient for all species. Differences in the sensitivity between the traits showed that the occurrence of asymmetry also depends on many internal factors. Stress does not affect all tested traits similarly because particular groups of traits and/or organisms may provide stronger asymmetry&#x02013;stress relationships (<xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">Leung and Forbes 1996</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">Anci&#x000e3;es and Marini 2000</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">Lens et al. 2002</xref>). In our study, asymmetry was found only for a few parts of the body. We found that the symmetry of the maxillary palpus and the labial palpus could be useful in estimating anthropogenic effects. The asymmetry may reflect the development of surviving individuals (<xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">Floate and Fox 2000</xref>); maintaining symmetry may be more important for survival and reproduction than maintaining normal and/or large body size.</p><sec id="s7"><title>Conclusion</title><p>We demonstrated that the effect of urbanization on the body size and on the asymmetry of morphometric characters is a complex process. We found that urbanization influenced the morphology of carabid beetles; urbanization influenced the morphological traits of each species. We also demonstrated that male and female specimen sensitivity to urbanization was different. The species of Carabini tribus and females of the species of Pterostichini tribus responded sensitively to anthropogenic influences. In the case of asymmetry, the variance between traits showed that particular groups of traits and/or organisms may provide stronger asymmetry&#x02013;stress relationships. We found that the symmetry of the left and right antennomers, maxillary palpus, labial palpus, tibia, and femur is useful in estimating the effect of urbanization. Our results also suggested that the elytra provided the strongest size&#x02013;stress relationships, and that large species, and females of small species such as <italic>P. oblongopunctatus</italic>, could be useful for assessing the effects of urbanization because they respond sensitively to the anthropogenic effects.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack id="a1"><title>Acknowledgment</title><p>The research was supported by the OTKA K 116639, KH 126481, and KH 126477 grants.</p></ack><ref-list id="r1"><title>References Cited</title><ref id="CIT0001"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Acevedo-Whitehouse</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Duffus</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Effects of environmental change on wildlife health</article-title>. <source>Philos. Trans. R. Soc. Lond. B Biol. Sci</source>. <volume>364</volume>: <fpage>3429</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3438</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19833653</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0002"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anci&#x000e3;es</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Marini</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>The effects of fragmentation on fluctuating asymmetry in passerine birds of Brazilian tropical forests</article-title>. <source>J. Appl. Ecol</source>. <volume>37</volume>: <fpage>1013</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1028</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0003"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Badyaev</surname><given-names>A. V</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Growing apart: an ontogenetic perspective on the evolution of sexual size dimorphism</article-title>. <source>Trends Ecol. Evol</source>. <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>369</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>378</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0004"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Biaggin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Consorti</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dapporto</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dellacasa</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Paggetti</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Corti</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>The taxonomic level order as a possible tool for rapid assessment of arthropod diversity in agricultural landscapes</article-title>. <source>Agric. Ecosystems. Environ</source>. <volume>122</volume>: <fpage>183</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>191</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0005"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Blake</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>G. N.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eyre</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Luff</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>1994</year>
<article-title>Effects of habitat type and grassland management practices on the body size distribution of carabid beetles</article-title>. <source>Pedobiologia</source><volume>38</volume>: <fpage>502</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>512</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0006"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Braun</surname><given-names>S. D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>T. H.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Perner</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Shifting average body size during regeneration after pollution: a case study using ground beetle assemblages</article-title>. <source>Ecol. Entomol</source>. <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>543</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>554</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0007"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cachada</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dias</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pato</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mieiro</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rocha-Santos</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ferreira da Silva</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Duarte</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Major inputs and mobility of potentially toxic elements contamination in urban areas</article-title>. <source>Environ. Monit. Assess</source>. <volume>185</volume>: <fpage>279</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>294</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22350347</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0008"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cattaneo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Couillard</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wunsam</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Courcelles</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Diatom taxonomic and morphological changes as indicators of metal pollution and recovery in Lac Dufault (Quebec, Canada)</article-title>. <source>J. Paleolimnol</source>. <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>163</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>175</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0009"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>G. M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1993</year>
<article-title>Fluctuating asymmetry of invertebrate populations as a biological indicator of environmental quality</article-title>. <source>Environ. Pollut</source>. <volume>82</volume>: <fpage>207</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>211</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15091791</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0010"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cortet</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gomot-De Vauflery</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Poinsot-Balaguer</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gomot</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Texier</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Daniel</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>The use of invertebrate soil fauna in monitoring pollutant effects</article-title>. <source>Eur. J. Soil Biol</source>. <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>115</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>134</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0011"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>De Anna</surname><given-names>E. B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bonisoli-Alquati</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Mousseau</surname><given-names>T. A.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>The use of fluctuating asymmetry as a measure of environmentally induced developmental instability: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Ecol. Ind</source>. <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>218</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>226</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0012"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Den Boer</surname><given-names>P. J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1990</year>
<article-title>Density limits and survival of local populations in 64 carabid species with different powers of dispersal</article-title>. <source>J. Evol. Biol</source>. <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>19</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>48</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0013"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eeva</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tanhuanp&#x000e4;&#x000e4;</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>R&#x000e5;bergh</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Airaksinen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nikinmaa</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Lehikoinen</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Biomarkers and fluctuating asymmetry as indicators of pollution-induced stress in two hole-nesting passerines</article-title>. <source>Funct. Ecol</source>. <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>235</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>243</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0014"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Elek</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>L&#x000f6;vei</surname><given-names>G. L.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>B&#x000e1;tki</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>No increase in fluctuating asymmetry in ground beetles (Carabidae) as urbanisation progresses</article-title>. <source>Com. Ecol</source>. <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>131</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>138</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0015"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Faeth</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>P. S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shochat</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Marussich</surname><given-names>W. A.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Trophic dynamics in urban communities</article-title>. <source>BioScience</source><volume>55</volume>: <fpage>399</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>407</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0016"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Floate</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Flies under stress: a test of fluctuating asymmetry as a biomonitor of environmental quality</article-title>. <source>Ecol. Appl</source>. <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>1541</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1550</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0017"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>G&#x000e1;l</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Markiewicz-Patkowska</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hursthouse</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Tatner</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Metal uptake by woodlice in urban soils</article-title>. <source>Ecotox. Environ. Safe</source><volume>69</volume>: <fpage>139</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>149</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0018"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Godet</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Demuynck</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Waterlot</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lemi&#x000e8;re</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Souty-Grosset</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Douay</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lepr&#x000ea;tre</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Pruvot</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Growth and metal accumulation in <italic>Porcellio scaber</italic> exposed to poplar litter from Cd-, Pb-, and Zn-contaminated sites</article-title>. <source>Ecotox. Environ. Safe</source><volume>74</volume>: <fpage>451</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>458</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0019"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Godet</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Demuynck</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Waterlot</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lemi&#x000e8;re</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Souty-Grosset</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Douay</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lepr&#x000ea;tre</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Pruvot</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Fluctuating asymmetry analysis on <italic>Porcellio scaber</italic> (Crustacea, Isopoda) populations living under metals-contaminated woody habitats</article-title>. <source>Ecol. Ind</source>. <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>130</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>139</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0020"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Henr&#x000ed;quez</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Donoso</surname><given-names>D. S.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Grez</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Population density, sex ratio, body size and fluctuating asymmetry of <italic>Ceroglossus chilensis</italic> (Carabidae) in the fragmented Maulino forest and surrounding pine plantations</article-title>. <source>Acta Oecol</source>. <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>811</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>818</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0021"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>H&#x0016f;rka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1996</year>
<source>Carabidae of the Czech and Slovak Republics</source>. <publisher-loc>Ing. Vit Kabourek Zlin, Czech Republic</publisher-loc> pp. 
<fpage>565</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0022"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ikeda</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Homma</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Kubota</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Body sizes of some carabid beetles on Sado Island, Japan, compared with the mainland</article-title>. <source>Biogeography</source><volume>8</volume>: <fpage>11</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>16</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0023"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lagisz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Changes in morphology of the ground beetle <italic>Pterostichus oblongopunctatus</italic> F. (Coleoptera; Carabidae) from vicinities of a zinc and lead smelter</article-title>. <source>Environ. Tox. Chem</source>. <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>1744</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1747</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0024"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lagucki</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Burdine</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>McCluney</surname><given-names>K. E.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Urbanization alters communities of flying arthropods in parks and gardens of a medium sized city</article-title>. <source>Peer J</source>. <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>3620</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0025"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lens</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van Dongen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Salit</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Matthysen</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Fluctuating asymmetry as an indicator of fitness: can we bridge the gap between the studies?</article-title><source>Biol. Rev. Camb. Philos. Soc</source>. <volume>77</volume>: <fpage>27</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>38</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11911372</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0026"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Forbes</surname><given-names>M. R.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>1996</year>
<article-title>Fluctuating asymmetry in relation to stress and fitness: effects of trait type as revealed by meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Ecoscience</source><volume>3</volume>: <fpage>400</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>413</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0027"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Magura</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>L&#x000f6;vei</surname><given-names>G. L.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>T&#x000f3;thm&#x000e9;r&#x000e9;sz</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Does urbanization decrease diversity in ground beetle (Carabidae) assemblages?</article-title><source>Global Ecol. Biogeogr</source>. <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>16</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>26</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0028"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marya&#x00144;ski</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kramarz</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laskowski</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Nikli&#x00144;ska</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Decreased energetic reserves, morphological changes and accumulation of metals in carabid beetles (<italic>Poecilus cupreus</italic> L.) exposed to zinc- or cadmium-contaminated food</article-title>. <source>Ecotoxicology</source><volume>11</volume>: <fpage>127</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>139</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11990769</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0029"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McGeoch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1998</year>
<article-title>The selection, testing and application of terrestrial insects as bioindicators</article-title>. <source>Biol. Rev</source>. <volume>73</volume>: <fpage>181</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>201</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0030"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McKinney</surname><given-names>M. L</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Effects of urbanization on species richness: a review of plants and animals</article-title>. <source>Urban Ecosyst</source>. <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>161</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>176</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0031"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Niemel&#x000e4;</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kotze</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ashworth</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brandmayr</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Desender</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>New</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Penev</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Samways</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Spence</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>The search for common anthropogenic impacts on biodiversity: a global network</article-title>. <source>J. Insect Conserv</source>. <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>3</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0032"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nylin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Gotthard</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>1998</year>
<article-title>Plasticity in life-history traits</article-title>. <source>Annu. Rev. Entomol</source>. <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>63</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>83</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9444750</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0033"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Olivero</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vrech</surname><given-names>D. E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peretti</surname><given-names>A. V.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Mattoni</surname><given-names>C. I.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Patterns of asymmetry in body traits and genitalia in two distant populations of a Neotropical scorpion</article-title>. <source>J. Nat. Hist</source>. <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>853</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>872</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0035"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Parsons</surname><given-names>P. A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1992</year>
<article-title>Fluctuating asymmetry: a biological monitor of environmental and genomic stress</article-title>. <source>Heredity</source><volume>68</volume>: <fpage>361</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>364</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1563968</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0036"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peakall</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1992</year>
<source>Animal biomarkers as pollution indicators</source>. <publisher-name>Chapman &#x00026; Hall</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>London, United Kingdom</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0037"><mixed-citation publication-type="confproc">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>E. L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jagoe</surname><given-names>C. H.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>T. J.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Effects of accumulation of hazardous metals on terrestrial isopod (<italic>Armadillidium vulgare</italic>) in urban environments</article-title>. Abstracts of the 86. <conf-name>Annual meeting of the Ecological Society of America</conf-name>, <publisher-loc>Madison, WI</publisher-loc> pp. 
<fpage>329</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0038"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ribera</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Doledec</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Downie</surname><given-names>I. S.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>G. N.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Effect of land disturbance and stress on species traits of ground beetle assemblages</article-title>. <source>Ecology</source><volume>82</volume>: <fpage>1112</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1129</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0039"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saunders</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hobbs</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Margules</surname><given-names>C. R.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>1991</year>
<article-title>Biological consequences of ecosystem fragmentation: a review</article-title>. <source>Conserv. Biol</source>. <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>18</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>32</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0040"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shingleton</surname><given-names>A. W.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Frankino</surname><given-names>W. A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Flatt</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nijhout</surname><given-names>H. F.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Emlen</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Size and shape: the developmental regulation of static allometry in insects</article-title>. <source>Bioessays</source><volume>29</volume>: <fpage>536</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>548</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17508394</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0041"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vidic</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Braun</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>F&#x000e1;bi&#x000e1;n</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>T&#x000f3;thm&#x000e9;r&#x000e9;sz</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Trace element concentrations in soils along urbanization gradients in the city of Wien, Austria</article-title>. <source>Environ. Sci. Poll. R</source><volume>20</volume>: <fpage>917</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>924</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0042"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baranyai</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Braun</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cserh&#x000e1;ti</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>F&#x000e1;bi&#x000e1;n</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>T&#x000f3;thm&#x000e9;r&#x000e9;sz</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Elemental concentrations in deposited dust on leaves along an urbanization gradient</article-title>. <source>Sci. Total Environ</source>. <volume>490</volume>: <fpage>514</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>520</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24875264</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0043"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harangi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baranyai</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Braun</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>F&#x000e1;bi&#x000e1;n</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mizser</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nagy</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>T&#x000f3;thm&#x000e9;r&#x000e9;sz</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Distribution of toxic elements between biotic and abiotic components of terrestrial ecosystem along an urbanization gradient: soil, leaf litter and ground beetles</article-title>. <source>Ecol. Ind</source>. <volume>60</volume>: <fpage>258</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>264</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0044"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jepson</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kramarz</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Laskowski</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Time to death response in carabid beetles exposed to multiple stressors along a gradient of heavy metal pollution</article-title>. <source>Environ. Poll</source>. <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>239</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>244</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0045"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sukhodolskaya</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Intraspecific body size variation in ground beetles (Coleoptera, Carabidae) in urban&#x02013;natural gradient</article-title>. <source>Acta Biol. Univer. Daugavpiliens</source>. <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>121</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>128</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0046"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tammaru</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Esperk</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Castellanos</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>No evidence for costs of being large in females of <italic>Orgyia</italic> spp. (Lepidoptera Lymantriidae): larger is always better</article-title>. <source>Oecologia</source><volume>133</volume>: <fpage>430</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>438</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28466206</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0047"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thiele</surname><given-names>H. U</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1977</year>
<source>Carabid beetles in their environments: a study on habitat selection by adaptations in physiology and behavior</source>. <publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0048"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>T&#x00151;zs&#x000e9;r</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Magura</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mizser</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Papp</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>T&#x000f3;thm&#x000e9;r&#x000e9;sz</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2019</year>
<article-title>Pollution intensity-dependent metal accumulation in ground beetles: a meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Environ. Sci. Pollut. Res</source>. <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>32092</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>32102</lpage>. doi.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11356-019-06294-5</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0049"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Trotta</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Calboli</surname><given-names>F. C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Garoia</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grifoni</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Cavicchi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Fluctuating asymmetry as a measure of ecological stress in <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> (Diptera: Drosophilidae)</article-title>. <source>Eur. J. Entomol</source>. <volume>102</volume>: <fpage>195</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>200</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0050"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Van Dongen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lens</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Molenberghs</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Recent developments and shortcomings in the analysis of individual asymmetry: can Bayesian statistics help us?</article-title><italic>In</italic><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Polak</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (ed.), <source>Developmental instability: causes and consequences</source>. <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Oxford, United Kingdom</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0051"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vandewoestijne</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Polus</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Baguette</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Fragmentation and insects: theory and application to calcareous grasslands</article-title>. <source>Biotechn. Agronom. Soc. Environ</source>. <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>139</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>142</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0052"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Venn</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Morphological responses to disturbance in wing-polymorphic carabid species (Coleoptera: Carabidae) on managed urban grasslands</article-title>. <source>Baltic J. Coleopterol</source>. <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>51</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>60</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0053"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vilisics</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>S&#x000f3;lymos</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Hornung</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Measuring fluctuating asymmetry of the terrestrial isopod <italic>Trachelipus rathkii</italic> (Crustacea: Isopoda, Oniscidea)</article-title>. <source>Eur. J. Soil Biol</source>. <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>85</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>90</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0054"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weller</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Ganzhorn</surname><given-names>J. U.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Carabid beetle community composition, body size, and fluctuating asymmetry along an urban&#x02013;rural gradient</article-title>. <source>Basic Appl. Ecol</source>. <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>193</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>201</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0055"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Z&#x000f6;ld</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Wittmann</surname><given-names>K. J.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Effects of sampling, preparation and defection on metal concentrations in selected invertebrates at urban sites</article-title>. <source>Chemosphere</source><volume>52</volume>: <fpage>1095</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1110</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12820990</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>