<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="case-report"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Diagn Pathol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Diagn Pathol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Diagnostic Pathology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1746-1596</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31926551</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6954539</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">913</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13000-019-0913-2</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Uterine intravenous leiomyomatosis with an isolated large metastasis to the right atrium: a case report</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yano</surname><given-names>Mitsutake</given-names></name><address><email>yano1210@oita-u.ac.jp</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Katoh</surname><given-names>Tomomi</given-names></name><address><email>tomokato22@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nakajima</surname><given-names>Yoshie</given-names></name><address><email>yoshie-n@amber.plala.or.jp</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Iwanaga</surname><given-names>Shiro</given-names></name><address><email>shiro.iwanaga@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kin</surname><given-names>Rei</given-names></name><address><email>jinling@saitama-med.ac.jp</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kozawa</surname><given-names>Eito</given-names></name><address><email>8kozawa@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-0769-360X</contrib-id><name><surname>Yasuda</surname><given-names>Masanori</given-names></name><address><email>m_yasuda@saitama-med.ac.jp</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Pathology, Saitama Medical, University International Medical Center, 1397-1 Yamane, Hidaka-City, Saitama 350-1298 Japan </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0665 3553</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412334.3</institution-id><institution>Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, </institution><institution>Oita University Faculty of Medicine, </institution></institution-wrap>1-1 Idaigaoka, Hasama-machi, Yufu-shi, Oita, 879-5593 Japan </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412377.4</institution-id><institution>Department of Cardiology, </institution><institution>Saitama Medical University International Medical Center, </institution></institution-wrap>1397-1 Yamane, Hidaka-City, Saitama 350-1298 Japan </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0640 5017</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.430047.4</institution-id><institution>Department of Pathology, </institution><institution>Saitama Medical University Hospital, </institution></institution-wrap>38 Morohongo, Iruma-Gun, Moroyama, Saitama 350-0495 Japan </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0640 5017</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.430047.4</institution-id><institution>Department of Diagnostic Radiology, </institution><institution>Saitama Medical University Hospital, </institution></institution-wrap>38 Morohongo, Iruma-Gun, Moroyama, Saitama 350-0495 Japan </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>11</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>11</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>4</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>7</day><month>8</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>6</day><month>12</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s). 2020</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">An intravenous leiomyomatosis is a special type of uterine leiomyoma characterized by the formation of benign leiomyomatous tissue within the vascular wall. Although histologically benign, intracardiac metastasis can lead to circulatory failure, and death, if untreated. Herein, we report on a case of a uterine intravenous leiomyomatosis with an isolated large adherent metastasis in the right atrium of the heart.</p></sec><sec><title>Case Presentation</title><p id="Par2">A 52-year-old Japanese woman sought medical attention at our hospital for lower abdominal pain. A 27-cm uterine mass was detected on clinical imaging, with a 78&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;47-mm mass in the right atrium detected on preoperative echocardiography. Intracardiac mass resection and tricuspid annuloplasty were performed as the first-stage surgery. The pedicle of the tumor was adherent to the wall of the atrium. On histological examination, the tumor was found to consist of spindle-shaped cells with eosinophilic cytoplasm, without atypia, but with a myxoid change, and rich microvascularization of the pedicle. Total abdominal hysterectomy was performed as the second-stage surgery, with confirmation of the diagnosis as uterine intravenous leiomyomatosis with an isolated metastasic lesion to the right atrium. There has been no evidence of tumor recurrence in the 15&#x02009;months since surgery.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par3">We report a unique case in which a large right atrial leiomyoma was identified following a uterine intravenous leiomyomatosis. Our case exemplifies that intravenous leiomyomatosis metastatic tumors have the potential to grow via their vascularization.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Uterus</kwd><kwd>Intravenous leiomyomatosis</kwd><kwd>Cardiac metastasis</kwd><kwd>Right atrium</kwd><kwd>Case report</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Sekiguchi Memorial Award at Saitama Medical University</institution></funding-source><award-id>18-C-1-02</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Yano</surname><given-names>Mitsutake</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Grants-in-Aid from the Ministry of Education, Science, Sports and Culture of Japan</institution></funding-source><award-id>18K06997</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Yasuda</surname><given-names>Masanori</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par10">Intravenous leiomyomatosis (IVL) is a special type of uterine leiomyoma, characterized by the formation of benign leiomyomatous tissue within the vascular vessels of the uterus. The tumor typically grows along vascular vessels and, thus, can extend to the iliac vein, inferior vena cava and, even to the heart. IVL develops in only 0.1% of women with uterine leiomyomas, with intracardiac involvement identified in 10&#x02013;40% of IVL cases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. IVL with intracardiac involvement was first reported in 1907, with fewer than 300 cases presently documented in the literature, since then [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Although histologically benign, intracardiac IVL extension can lead to circulatory failure or death if left untreated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. The typical features of IVL include contiguous pelvic and intravenous masses, with sausage-shaped lesions in the inferior vena cava, whereas intracardiac tumors arising from IVL typically show a worm-like appearance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Some studies have reported on isolated intracardiac tumor from uterine IVL that are adherent to the cardiovascular wall [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Herein, we report such a case of uterine IVL that clinicopathologically preceded IVL metastasis into the right atrium.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Case presentation</title><p id="Par11">The patient provided consent for publication of this case report.</p><sec id="Sec3"><title>Clinical history</title><p id="Par12">The patient was a 52-year-old Japanese woman, gravida 2, para 2, who sought medical attention at our hospital because of lower abdominal pain. The patient had a past history of uterine leiomyoma and duodenal ulcer, the latter having been managed conservatively with medication. A huge uterine mass was detected by abdominal computed tomography (CT). Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) revealed the presence of a 27-cm mass in the uterus, indicative of a leiomyoma (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a). No tumor was detected in the inferior vena cava, iliac vein, or ovarian vein (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a, b). The patient was scheduled for surgery for removal of the uterine tumor. However, during routine preoperative follow-up, a 78&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;47-mm mass was identified in the right atrium of her heart on echocardiography (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>c). Other features of the echocardiography included a respiratory variation of the diameter of the inferior vena cava of 12&#x02009;mm, and a left ventricular ejection fraction of 64%, both of which were within normal range. Systemic enhanced CT revealed a 75-mm mass in the right atrium (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>d), with no evidence of lung metastases. Under a preoperative diagnosis of metastatic lesion or cardiac myxoid tumor, intracardiac mass resection and tricuspid annuloplasty were performed as the first-stage surgery. After surgery for the cardiac mass, gonadotropin releasing hormone agonist therapy was administered for 6&#x02009;months for the management of the uterine mass. With no change in the tumor size, total abdominal hysterectomy was performed as a second-stage surgery. The diagnosis was confirmed as uterine IVL, with an isolated metastasis to the right atrium. There has been no recurrence of the tumor over the period of 15&#x02009;months following surgery, with no requirement for anti-estrogen therapy during this period.
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Clinical imaging findings: <bold>a</bold> and <bold>b</bold> T2-weighted MRI revealed a 27-cm mass in the uterus. No tumor was detected in the iliac vein (A, red arrows) or in the inferior vena cava (B, red arrows). <bold>c</bold> Echocardiography imaging revealed a 78&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;47-mm mass (asterisk) in the right atrium. <bold>d</bold> Enhanced computed tomography imaging confirmed a 75-mm mass (asterisk) in the right atrium</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13000_2019_913_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Gross and microscopic findings</title><p id="Par13">An ovoid, gray-white colored mass, with a tough texture, was removed (78&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;55&#x02009;mm in size). The mass was adherent to the wall of the right atrium via a pedicle (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a, b). Histologically, the tumor consisted of spindle-shaped cells, with eosinophilic cytoplasm, lacked atypia, and was accompanied by a myxoid change. The pedicle adhering to the right atrium was richly microvascularized (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>c, d). Immunohistochemical staining was positive for &#x003b1;-smooth muscle actin (&#x003b1;-SMA), desmin (focal), and estrogen receptor (ER), but negative for progesterone receptor (PgR) and CD10 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>e, f).
<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>The macroscopic and microscopic findings and immunohistochemical staining of the intracardiac tumor: <bold>a</bold> and <bold>b</bold> Macroscopically, the tumor was a 78&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;58&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;55-mm mass, with a pedicle (red arrows) clinging to the right atrium. <bold>b</bold> The cut surface showed a gray-white colored solid mass. <bold>c</bold> and <bold>d</bold> Microscopically, the rich microvasculature of the pedicle was shown (red arrows); <bold>d</bold> The tumor consisted of spindle-shaped cells, with eosinophilic cytoplasm, lacked atypia, and was accompanied by a myxoid change (high power view). <bold>e</bold> and <bold>f</bold> Immunohistochemically, the tumor cells were positive for (<bold>e</bold>) desmin and (<bold>f</bold>) ER</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13000_2019_913_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p><p id="Par14">Macroscopically, the uterus was enlarged and the cut surface showed a white solid mass with a &#x0201c;worm-like&#x0201d; appearance (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a). Histopathologic examination revealed multiple benign leiomyomatous tissues within the vascular vessels (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>b, c). Immunohistochemical stains were positive for &#x003b1;-SMA, desmin (focal), ER, and PgR, but negative for CD10 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>d, e). Peritoneal cytology was negative for malignancy.
<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>The macroscopic and microscopic findings and immunohistochemical staining of the uterine mass: <bold>a</bold> Macroscopically, the cut surface presented as a gray-white colored mass, with a &#x0201c;worm-like&#x0201d; appearance (red arrows). <bold>b</bold> Microscopically, the uterine large myoma presented spindle-like smooth muscle cells without atypia and mitosis. <bold>c</bold> and <bold>d</bold> The tumor showed a growth of benign leiomyomatous tissues within vascular vessels (C, H&#x00026;E; D, Elastica van Gieson). <bold>e</bold> Immunohistochemically, the tumor was positive for &#x003b1;-SMA</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13000_2019_913_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Discussion and conclusions</title><p id="Par15">IVL has the potential to grow along blood vessels, extending to the iliac vein, inferior vena cava, and even to the heart. Typically with IVL, the pelvic and intravenous masses are continuous and the intravenous lesions do not invade or adhere to the vessel wall [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>].</p><p id="Par16">In the present case, however, the intracardiac metastasis arising from the uterine IVL was isolated and was adherent to the endocardium of the atrium, with no evidence of tumor occurrence in the inferior vena cava, internal iliac vein or ovarian vein. The tumor of the right atrium was an independent metastasis of the uterine IVL, mimicking a primary cardiac myxoma. In the presence of uterine IVL, it is necessary to distinguish the nature of the intracardiac mass, regardless of the absence of its continuity with the uterus. Of note, the intracardiac tumor in the present case was larger than the diameter of the inferior vena cava and, thus, was considered to have developed within the heart. This differs from the report by Maneyama et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>] in which a spontaneous migration of a residual IVL to the heart, via the blood stream after hysterectomy, was described. The intracardiac tumor of the present case was adherent to the wall of the right atrium wall via a richly vascularized pedicle. This microvasculature is what likely allowed the tumor to grow.</p><p id="Par17">A summary of previous reports [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>] on the occurrence of an isolated cardiac metastasis from uterine IVL is provided in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. The tumor diameter of the present case was more than twice that of previously reported cases. The intracardiac mass was identified after hysterectomy for IVL in 3 of 5 cases, with uterine fibroids identified in the other 2 cases. Of note, in all previously reported cases, there was concurrent evidence of lung metastases, which was not the case for our patient. Tumor progression after surgery was not identified in any of these previous cases. Ordulu et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>] reported the expression of HMGA2 protein, a driver for tumor metastasis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>], in 58% of IVL cases, which is higher than the 32% in cases with typical uterine leiomyoma. Regional chromosomal alterations of variable frequencies were also observed in IVL, showing overlaps with uterine leiomyosarcoma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Thus, IVL has an intermediate biological propensity between a benign and malignant status. Recurrence of IVL tends to occur in younger patients. Du et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>] have suggested that young patients should be treated using hysterectomy and salpingo-oophorectomy if the patient does not wish to maintain fertility. Mizoguchi et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>] pointed out that anti-estrogen therapy may be an effective treatment if the patient has not yet entered menopause. These results suggest that IVL treatment requires tumor reduction and blockage of blood flow and estrogen to limit continued growth of the tumor and possible metastasis.
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Cardiac metastasis of intravenous leiomyomatosis</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Case (year)</th><th>Age (years)</th><th>Past history</th><th>Symptoms</th><th>Size (mm)</th><th>Adhere</th><th>Metastasis</th><th>Treatment</th><th>Prognosis (follow-up)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="2">Present case (2018)</td><td>52</td><td>Uterine leiomyoma</td><td>Abdominal pain</td><td>78</td><td>Anterior wall of RA</td><td>Heart</td><td>TR&#x02009;+&#x02009;TH&#x02009;+&#x02009;TVP</td><td>PFS</td></tr><tr><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td>+GnRHa</td><td>(14&#x02009;months)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Thukkani et al., (2005) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]</td><td>36</td><td>TH&#x02009;+&#x02009;USO for IVL</td><td>Abdominal swelling</td><td>15</td><td>TV</td><td>Heart, lung</td><td>TR&#x02009;+&#x02009;USO&#x02009;+&#x02009;TVP</td><td>PFS</td></tr><tr><td/><td>(at 26&#x02009;years)</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td>+GnRHa</td><td>(12&#x02009;months)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Baboci et al., (2014) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]</td><td>51</td><td>TH for IVL</td><td>Shortness of breath</td><td>NA</td><td>Anterior wall of RA,</td><td>Heart, lung</td><td>TR&#x02009;+&#x02009;lung</td><td>PFS</td></tr><tr><td/><td>(at 47&#x02009;years)</td><td/><td/><td>TV, chordae tendineae</td><td/><td>segmentectomy</td><td>(2&#x02009;years)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Lin and Liu, (2014) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]</td><td>43</td><td>TH&#x02009;+&#x02009;BSO for IVL</td><td>Palpitation,</td><td>15</td><td>TV</td><td>Heart, lung</td><td>None</td><td>PFS</td></tr><tr><td/><td>(at 42&#x02009;years)</td><td>chest distress</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td>(7&#x02009;years)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Zhang and Lang, (2016) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]</td><td>40</td><td>Uterine mass</td><td>None</td><td>30</td><td>Chordae tendineae,</td><td>Heart, lung</td><td>TR&#x02009;+&#x02009;TH&#x02009;+&#x02009;BSO</td><td>PFS</td></tr><tr><td/><td/><td/><td/><td>papillary muscles</td><td/><td>+TVP&#x02009;+&#x02009;GnRHa</td><td>(2&#x02009;months)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>RA</italic> Right atrium, <italic>TR</italic> Tumor resection, <italic>TH</italic> Total hysterectomy, <italic>TVP</italic> Tricuspid valvuloplasty; <italic>GnRHa</italic> Gonadotropin releasing hormone agonist, <italic>PFS</italic> Progression free survival, <italic>USO</italic> Unilateral salpingo-oophorectomy, <italic>IVL</italic> Intravenous leiomyomatosis, <italic>TV</italic> Tricuspid valve, <italic>NA</italic> Not available, <italic>BSO</italic> Bilateral salpingo-oophorectomy</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par18">In conclusion, we report a unique case in which a right atrial leiomyoma was identified following a uterine leiomyoma. The uterine IVL had an isolated large metastasis to the right atrium that was adherent to the endocardium via a richly vascularized pedicle. Our case exemplifies that IVL metastatic tumors have the potential to grow via their vascularization.</p></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>CT</term><def><p id="Par4">Computed tomography</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ER</term><def><p id="Par5">Estrogen receptor</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IVL</term><def><p id="Par6">Intravenous leiomyomatosis</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MRI</term><def><p id="Par7">Magnetic resonance imaging</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PgR</term><def><p id="Par8">Progesterone receptor</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>&#x003b1;-SMA</term><def><p id="Par9">&#x003b1;-smooth muscle actin</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We would like to thank Editage (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.editage.jp">www.editage.jp</ext-link>) for English language editing.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>MiY: conceptualization, pathologic diagnosis, immunohistochemical analysis, and writing of manuscript. YN, SI: collection of clinical data. TK, RK: pathologic diagnosis and immunohistochemical analysis. EK: radiologic analysis. MaY (the last author): pathologic diagnosis and revision of manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript prior to submission.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>This work was supported by Sekiguchi Memorial Award (grant no. 18-C-1-02) at Saitama Medical University and Grants-in-Aid from the Ministry of Education, Science, Sports and Culture of Japan (Research Project Numbers: 18&#x02009;K06997).</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>All data generated or analyzed during this study are included in this published article.</p></notes><notes><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par19">The patient provided consent for publication of the case report.</p></notes><notes><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par20">Written informed consent was obtained from the patient for the publication of this case report.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par21">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intravenous leiomyomatosis of the uterus: a clinicopathologic study of 18 cases, with emphasis on early diagnosis and appropriate treatment strategies</article-title><source>Hum Pathol</source><year>2011</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>1240</fpage><lpage>1246</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.humpath.2010.10.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21777942</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuo</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>NY</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>One-stage surgery for removal of intravascular leiomyomatosis extending to right ventricle</article-title><source>Medicine</source><year>2018</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>e0051</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000010051</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29538195</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Opeskin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Death due to intravenous leiomyomatosis extending to the right pulmonary artery</article-title><source>Pathology.</source><year>2004</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>202</fpage><lpage>203</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00313020410001672075</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15203761</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Nie</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Contrast-enhanced CT findings of intravenous leiomyomatosis</article-title><source>Clin Radiol</source><year>2018</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>503.e1</fpage><lpage>503.e6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.crad.2017.12.016</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thukkani</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ravichandran</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Slater</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Leiomyomatosis metastatic to the tricuspid valve complicated by pelvic hemorrhage</article-title><source>Ann Thorac Surg</source><year>2005</year><volume>79</volume><fpage>707</fpage><lpage>709</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.athoracsur.2003.08.038</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15680873</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intravenous leiomyomatosis with inferior vena cava or intracardiac extension and concurrent bilateral multiple pulmonary nodules: A report of 2 cases</article-title><source>Medicine</source><year>2016</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>e4722</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/MD.0000000000004722</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27583911</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baboci</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Prifti</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Xhabija</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Alimehmeti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Surgical removal of an intravenous leiomyoma with intracardiac extension and pulmonary benign metastases</article-title><source>Heart Lung Circ</source><year>2014</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>174</fpage><lpage>176</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.hlc.2013.10.058</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24200983</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pelvic intravascular leiomyomatosis associated with benign pulmonary metastasizing leiomyoma: clinicopathologic, clonality, and copy number variance analysis</article-title><source>Int J Gynecol Pathol</source><year>2014</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>140</fpage><lpage>145</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/PGP.0b013e31828def26</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24487468</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maneyama</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyasaka</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Wakana</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakamury</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitazume</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kubota</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vanishing intravenous leiomyomatosis after hysterectomy: Assessment of the need to perform complete resection</article-title><source>J Obstet Gynaecol Res</source><year>2016</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>1058</fpage><lpage>1062</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jog.13012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27080990</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ordulu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Nucci</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Cin</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Hollowell</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Otis</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name><surname>Hornick</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Intravenous leiomyomatosis: an unusual intermediate between benign and malignant uterine smooth muscle tumors</article-title><source>Mod Pathol</source><year>2016</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>500</fpage><lpage>510</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/modpathol.2016.36</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26892441</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morishita</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zaidi</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitoro</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sankarasharma</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Szabolcs</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Okada</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>HMGA2 is a driver of tumor metastasis</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>2013</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>4289</fpage><lpage>4299</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-12-3848</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23722545</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buza</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Carr</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hui</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recurrent chromosomal aberrations in intravenous leiomyomatosis of the uterus: high-resolution array comparative genomic hybridization study</article-title><source>Hum Pathol</source><year>2014</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>1885</fpage><lpage>1892</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.humpath.2014.05.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25033729</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mizoguchi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Nasu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Arakane</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Narahara</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intravenous leiomyomatosis treated with radical hysterectomy and adjuvant aromatase inhibitor therapy</article-title><source>J Obstet Gynaecol Res</source><year>2016</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>1405</fpage><lpage>1408</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jog.13063</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27436168</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>