<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Commun</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Commun</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nature Communications</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2041-1723</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31924793</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6954229</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">14035</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-019-14035-y</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Influence of energy gap between charge-transfer and locally excited states on organic long persistence luminescence</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Zesen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3647-4262</contrib-id><name><surname>Kabe</surname><given-names>Ryota</given-names></name><address><email>ryota.kabe@oist.jp</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-9860-2282</contrib-id><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Kai</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-6117-9604</contrib-id><name><surname>Adachi</surname><given-names>Chihaya</given-names></name><address><email>adachi@cstf.kyushu-u.ac.jp</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2242 4849</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.177174.3</institution-id><institution>Center for Organic Photonics and Electronics Research (OPERA), </institution><institution>Kyushu University, </institution></institution-wrap>744 Motooka, Nishi-ku, Fukuoka 819-0395 Japan </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9805 2626</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.250464.1</institution-id><institution>Organic Optoelectronics Unit, </institution><institution>Okinawa Institute of Science and Technology Graduate University, </institution></institution-wrap>1919-1 Tancha, Onna-son, Okinawa 904-0495 Japan </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2242 4849</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.177174.3</institution-id><institution>JST, ERATO Adachi Molecular Exciton Engineering Project, </institution><institution>Kyushu University, </institution></institution-wrap>744 Motooka, Nishi-ku, Fukuoka 819-0395 Japan </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0198 0694</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.263761.7</institution-id><institution>Institute of Functional Nano and Soft Materials (FUNSOM) and Jiangsu Key Laboratory for Carbon-Based Functional Materials and Devices, </institution><institution>Soochow University, </institution></institution-wrap>Suzhou, Jiangsu 215123 China </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2242 4849</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.177174.3</institution-id><institution>International Institute for Carbon Neutral Energy Research (WPI-I2CNER), </institution><institution>Kyushu University, </institution></institution-wrap>744 Motooka, Nishi-ku, Fukuoka 819-0395 Japan </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>10</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>191</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>4</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>13</day><month>12</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Organic long-persistent luminescence (LPL) is an organic luminescence system that slowly releases stored exciton energy as light. Organic LPL materials have several advantages over inorganic LPL materials in terms of functionality, flexibility, transparency, and solution-processability. However, the molecular selection strategies for the organic LPL system still remain unclear. Here we report that the energy gap between the lowest localized triplet excited state and the lowest singlet charge-transfer excited state in the exciplex system significantly controls the LPL performance. Changes in the LPL duration and spectra properties are systematically investigated for three donor materials having a different energy gap. When the energy level of the lowest localized triplet excited state is much lower than that of the charge-transfer excited state, the system exhibits a short LPL duration and clear two distinct emission features originating from exciplex fluorescence and donor phosphorescence.</p></abstract><abstract id="Abs2" abstract-type="web-summary"><p id="Par2">Long-persistent luminescence can be realized in all-organic systems (OLPL) but still with unsatisfactory performance. Here the authors investigate the relationships between energy levels and emission properties in a series of OLPL materials and propose a design strategy for efficient OLPL performance.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Photochemistry</kwd><kwd>Optical spectroscopy</kwd><kwd>Chemical physics</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">https://doi.org/10.13039/501100001691</institution-id><institution>MEXT | Japan Society for the Promotion of Science (JSPS)</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>JP18H02049</award-id><award-id>JP18H04522</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Kabe</surname><given-names>Ryota</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">https://doi.org/10.13039/501100004398</institution-id><institution>Mitsubishi Foundation</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">https://doi.org/10.13039/501100009024</institution-id><institution>MEXT | JST | Exploratory Research for Advanced Technology (ERATO)</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>JPMJER1305</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Adachi</surname><given-names>Chihaya</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par3">Long-persistent luminescence (LPL), also known as the glow-in-the-dark effect or afterglow, is a phenomenon by which a material emits light for a very long time after the cutoff of photoexcitation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. The first LPL emitters were based on inorganic crystals and performance was greatly improved through doping<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. Several charge accumulation mechanisms, such as electron or hole trapping mechanisms, have been proposed to explain inorganic LPL<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. Unlike phosphorescence, which can also be long-lived but is a transition between different spin states (usually from a triplet excited state to the singlet ground state), LPL systems do not follow an exponential decay and usually follow a power-law decay because of the presence of the intermediate states (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><title>Differences between LPL and phosphorescence.</title><p><bold>a</bold> Schematic diagram of fluorescence, phosphorescence, and LPL. Phosphorescence is a transition from the triplet excited state (T<sub>1</sub>) to the singlet ground state (S<sub>0</sub>). LPL is an emission mechanism in which the energy passes through an intermediate state such as a trapped state. There is no restriction regarding the spin state. Although LPL is long-lived because of charge separation and subsequent slow recombination (second-order kinetics) of initially generated excitons, phosphorescence is long-lived because of the low probability of the transition (first-order kinetics) occurring in the initially generated excitons. <bold>b</bold> The ideal emission decay profiles of phosphorescence and LPL on logarithmic plots. Phosphorescence follows an exponential decay and LPL a power-law decay.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_14035_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e370"/></fig></p><p id="Par4">Since the mid-1990s, the blending of inorganic LPL materials with a polymer matrix has been the main route for achieving it in commercial applications such as watch dials, fire safety signs, and glow-in-the-dark toys<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. However, inorganic LPL materials exhibit poor compatibility and transparency in common polymers. Moreover, the most efficient inorganic LPL materials nearly all contain rare earth elements such as Sr, Eu, and Dy<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par5">Recently, we realized the LPL emission from purely organic-based materials, including organic small molecules and polymers<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. These organic LPL (OLPL) materials can be easily fabricated by mixing an electron donor and an electron acceptor using various methods such as melt-casting, spin coating, or thermal evaporation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. Moreover, the emission color of OLPL systems can be controlled by the addition of dopants<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. However, a large performance gap still exists between the present OLPL system and the commercial high-performance inorganic LPL products (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>).</p><p id="Par6">The OLPL emission originates from the charge-transfer (CT) transition of a photo-generated exciplex formed between a donor and an acceptor. Some exciplexes can dissociate to form partially charge-separated (CS) states with very long times. The slow recombination of these separated charge carriers leads to continuous emission for over 1&#x02009;h at room temperature. The LPL process is governed by the recombination of dissociated radical cations and anions with a power-law emission decay<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>, so that the emission duration of OLPL materials is significantly longer than that of conventional room-temperature phosphorescence, which is ideally a first-order reaction with an exponential emission decay<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. The power-law kinetic results (power-law kinetic, <italic>I</italic>(<italic>t</italic>) ~ <italic>t</italic><sup>&#x02212;<italic>m</italic></sup>, <italic>m</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.1&#x02013;2) from charge recombination can be explained by several physical models discussed in previous literatures about LPL from organic molecules (<italic>N,N,N</italic>&#x02032;<italic>,N</italic>&#x02032;-tetramethylbenzidine (TMB)/poly(alkyl methacrylate)s)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup> and thermoluminescence of the inorganic LiF<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>, and the organic molecule polyethylene terephthalate<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. These models can be separated into the diffusion model<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup> and the electron tunneling model<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup> of geminate ion recombination. In the diffusion model, we consider the distribution of electrons (radical anions) after the charge separation process. The electron tunneling model is mainly used to explain the isothermal recombination luminescence at low temperatures for irradiated organic compounds.</p><p id="Par7">Although a molecule&#x02019;s chemical structure greatly influences its optical and mechanical properties such as absorption and emission spectra, flexibility, and biocompatibility, the strategy for the design and selection of molecules for the OLPL system still remains unclear. We have noted in a previous report that the LPL process, which proceeds through charge dissociation and subsequent recombination, might be affected by the excited-state energy levels of the donor and acceptor, and the exciplex formed between them<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. However, more detailed relationships are still needed to unlock ways to improve the performance of OLPL materials.</p><p id="Par8">Herein, we demonstrate that the energy gap between the lowest singlet excited state of the exciplex (<sup>1</sup>CT) and the lowest triplet excited state of the donor (<sup>3</sup>LE<sub>D</sub>) strongly affects OLPL performance. Changes in the OLPL properties and the emission mechanism are systematically investigated for three donor materials having similar molecular structures but different energy levels. Optimization of excited-state energy levels based on the uncovered relationships between energy levels and performance will aid the development of efficient OLPL systems aiming for future applications.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>OLPL materials</title><p id="Par9">The OLPL systems were fabricated by the melt-casting of a mixture containing 1% of an electron donor and 99% of an electron acceptor<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. The electron donors, TMB, <italic>N</italic>,<italic>N&#x02019;</italic>-dimethyl-<italic>N,N&#x02019;</italic>-ditolylbenzidine (DMDTB), and <italic>N,N,N</italic>&#x02032;<italic>,N</italic>&#x02032;-tetratolylbenzidine (TTB), and the electron acceptor, 2,8-bis(diphenylphosphoryl)dibenzo[b,d]thiophene (PPT), are shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>. The highest occupied molecular orbital (HOMO) levels of the donors were determined from the first redox peaks of cyclic voltammograms (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2</xref>) and the HOMO levels of DMDTB (&#x02212;4.9&#x02009;eV) and TTB (&#x02212;5.0&#x02009;eV) were found to be slightly deeper than that of TMB (&#x02212;4.8&#x02009;eV) because of the <italic>&#x003c0;</italic>-extension provided by the substituent benzene rings.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><title>Photoluminescence and LPL characteristics of the OLPL systems.</title><p><bold>a</bold> Chemical structures and HOMO or LUMO energy levels of the three electron donors (TMB, DMDTB, and TTB) and the electron acceptor (PPT). <bold>b</bold>, <bold>c</bold> Semi-logarithmic plots (<bold>b</bold>) and logarithmic plots (<bold>c</bold>) of the emission decay profiles of TMB/PPT, DMTDB/PPT, and TTB/PPT at 300&#x02009;K. Emission decay profiles contain all of the emission over wavelengths from 400 to 900&#x02009;nm. Samples were excited for 60&#x02009;s (from &#x02212;60 to 0&#x02009;s) by a 340&#x02009;nm LED source. PL means the steady-state photoluminescence, LPL means the long-persistent luminescence, and Phos. means the phosphorescence. <bold>d</bold>&#x02013;<bold>f</bold> The steady-state photoluminescence and time-resolved photoluminescence spectra of 1&#x02009;mol% TMB/PPT (<bold>d</bold>), DMDTB/PPT (<bold>e</bold>), and TTB/PPT (<bold>f</bold>) films at 300&#x02009;K. The time-resolved spectra were integrated over periods of 1&#x02013;2, 4&#x02013;5, 10&#x02013;30, and 100&#x02013;300&#x02009;s after stopping excitation. The dashed lines indicate the onset of the LPL spectra.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_14035_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e582"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Photoluminescence and LPL performances</title><p id="Par10">The LPL performance of these donor/acceptor systems greatly depends on the donor. Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> shows the steady-state photoluminescence and time-resolved (1&#x02013;2&#x02009;s, 4&#x02013;5&#x02009;s, 10&#x02013;30&#x02009;s, and 100&#x02013;300&#x02009;s after stopping excitation) emission spectra of these LPL systems. TMB/PPT and DMDTB/PPT systems showed a slight change of spectral width with the passage of time. On the other hand, the TTB/PPT system exhibits apparent spectral transformation, i.e., two emission peaks, within 10&#x02009;s after excitation cutoff, indicating the presence of a second emission process. The emission decay profiles of all of the systems are inverse-power functions of time <italic>t</italic><sup>&#x02212;m</sup> (<italic>m</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.9&#x02013;1.3) after 10&#x02009;s (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2c</xref> and Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). This non-exponential decay behavior indicates that the LPL emission originates from intermediate CS states<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. The presence of CS states was proved by using transient absorption measurements in our previous publication<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup> and time-resolved electron spin resonance (ESR) measurements. The ESR signal attributed to the organic radicals clearly increases after photoexcitation and gradually decreases by time (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">3</xref>).</p><p id="Par11">To understand the detailed emission mechanisms, we obtained time-resolved emission spectra from the OLPL systems on nanosecond through millisecond timescales by using a streak camera (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> and Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">4</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">9</xref>). Also, the fluorescence and phosphorescence spectra of the donors were obtained from 1wt% donor-doped films of the cyclic olefin copolymer ZEONOR, which acts as a nonpolar solid matrix that does not form a CT complex with the donor dopants<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>. The optical properties of the donors doped in ZEONOR films are almost identical to those in toluene solutions, indicating that there are no aggregation or polarization effects (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">10</xref>). Moreover, as the solid-state matrix can prevent the nonradiative deactivation of the dopants, the room-temperature phosphorescence of the donors can be obtained. The phosphorescence decays of the donors (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">10</xref>) are exponential with lifetimes of 1.43&#x02009;s (TMB), 0.79&#x02009;s (DMDTB), and 0.72&#x02009;s (TTB). The fluorescence spectra were obtained in air, which quenches the photo-generated triplet excitons because of the presence of oxygen. Optical properties and the energy levels calculated from the onsets of the emission spectra are summarized in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><title>Study-state and time-resolved emission spectra of the OLPL systems.</title><p><bold>a</bold> Fluorescence and phosphorescence spectra (top), steady-state photoluminescence (PL), and LPL spectra (middle), and time-resolved emission spectra (bottom) of TMB/PPT. <bold>b</bold> DMDTB/PPT. <bold>c</bold> TTB/PPT. Optical properties of TMB, DMDTB, and TTB were obtained in ZEONOR films at 300&#x02009;K. Fluorescence and phosphorescence spectra of PPT were obtained from a neat thin film at 300&#x02009;K and 77&#x02009;K, respectively. Time-resolved emission spectra were obtained from streak images at 300&#x02009;K.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_14035_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e660"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Photophysical properties of the donors, acceptors, and OLPL systems.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Sample</th><th>HOMO [eV]<sup>a</sup></th><th>LUMO [eV]<sup>a</sup></th><th><italic>&#x003a6;</italic><sub>PL</sub></th><th><italic>&#x003c4;</italic><sub>flu.</sub> [NS]</th><th><italic>&#x003c4;</italic><sub>phos</sub> [s]</th><th><sup>1</sup>LE<sub>D</sub> or <sup>1</sup>LE<sub>A</sub> [eV]<sup>b</sup></th><th><sup>3</sup>LE<sub>D</sub> or <sup>3</sup>LE<sub>A</sub> [eV]<sup>b</sup></th><th>Sample</th><th><italic>&#x003a6;</italic><sub>PL</sub></th><th><sup>1</sup>CT [eV]<sup>c</sup></th><th>&#x00394;<italic>E</italic>(<sup>1</sup>CT&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;<sup>3</sup>LE<sub>D</sub>) [eV]</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>TMB</td><td>&#x02212;4.8</td><td/><td>52%<sup>d</sup></td><td>9.92<sup>d</sup></td><td>1.43<sup>d</sup></td><td>3.56<sup>d</sup></td><td>2.63<sup>d</sup></td><td>TMB/PPT</td><td>24%</td><td>2.79</td><td>0.16</td></tr><tr><td>DMDTB</td><td>&#x02212;4.9</td><td/><td>50%<sup>d</sup></td><td>1.76<sup>d</sup></td><td>0.79<sup>d</sup></td><td>3.43<sup>d</sup></td><td>2.62<sup>d</sup></td><td>DMDTB/PPT</td><td>27%</td><td>2.87</td><td>0.25</td></tr><tr><td>TTB</td><td>&#x02212;5.0</td><td/><td>47%<sup>d</sup></td><td>1.30<sup>d</sup></td><td>0.72<sup>d</sup></td><td>3.25<sup>d</sup></td><td>2.50<sup>d</sup></td><td>TTB/PPT</td><td>28%</td><td>3.04</td><td>0.54</td></tr><tr><td>PPT</td><td/><td>&#x02212;2.2</td><td>1%<sup>e</sup></td><td>1.15<sup>e</sup></td><td>1.01<sup>f</sup></td><td>3.76<sup>e</sup></td><td>2.91<sup>f</sup></td><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>Calculated from CV or DPV peaks</p><p><sup>b</sup>Calculated from the onset of the emission spectra</p><p><sup>c</sup>Calculated from the onset of the LPL spectra</p><p><sup>d</sup>In ZEONOR film at 300&#x02009;K</p><p><sup>e</sup>In the neat film at 300&#x02009;K</p><p><sup>f</sup>In the neat film at 77&#x02009;K</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par12">The time-resolved emission spectra of TMB/PPT system indicate the presence of weak fluorescence from TMB for at least 3&#x02009;ns after excitation cutoff (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3a</xref> and Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">5</xref>). This fluorescence originates from the TMB molecules, which do not form CT with PPT. After the initial fluorescence of TMB, an exciplex emission that slightly shifts with time was obtained. The temperature dependencies of the time-resolved emission spectra and the emission decay profiles on a microsecond timescale clearly indicate the presence of thermally activated delayed fluorescence (TADF), which is often obtained from exciplex systems (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">7</xref>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>. The spectral shift of the exciplex emission can be explained by the large dipole moment of PPT. As the CT excited states have large dipole moments (Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2</xref>), reorganization of the PPT matrix in the excited-state&#x02014;so-called solid-state solvation&#x02014;induces the spectral shift during the TADF process<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Emission mechanism</title><p id="Par13">The proposed emission mechanism and energy diagrams obtained from the onsets of the emission spectra are shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>. As the lowest triplet excited-state emission of the exciplex (<sup>3</sup>CT) could not be obtained directly, we assume that <sup>3</sup>CT is almost identical to the lowest singlet excited-state of the exciplex (<sup>1</sup>CT), because excellent separation of the HOMO and the LUMO orbitals on the donor and acceptor, respectively, of the exciplex induces a small energy gap between <sup>1</sup>CT and <sup>3</sup>CT<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. Recent studies of TADF molecules indicate that the locally excited triplet state of donor or acceptor units, which are analogous to the triplet states located on the donor or acceptor molecule in an exciplex, contribute the reverse intersystem crossing (RISC) process; thus, this is one important factor we considered when investigating the emission mechanism<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><title>Proposed emission mechanism of the OLPL systems.</title><p>Proposed emission mechanism before (<bold>a</bold>) and after (<bold>b</bold>) recombination of charges and LPL path in TMB/PPT (<bold>c</bold>), DMDTB/PPT (<bold>d</bold>), and TTB/PPT (<bold>e</bold>). The energy levels were calculated from the onsets of the corresponding emission spectra. Abbreviations of electron donor (D), acceptor (A), charge transfer (CT), electron transfer (ET), charge-separated state (CSS), charge separation (CS), and charge recombination (CR) are used. The dotted lines represent weaker luminescence processes and the solid lines stronger ones.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41467_2019_14035_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e1081"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>OLPL from TMB/PPT system</title><p id="Par14">In the case of TMB, the lowest triplet excited-state of the donor (<sup>3</sup>LE<sub>D</sub>) is slightly lower than the lowest singlet CT excited-state of the exciplex (<sup>1</sup>CT). This relatively small energy gap between <sup>3</sup>LE<sub>D</sub> and <sup>1</sup>CT (&#x00394;<italic>E</italic>(<sup>1</sup>CT&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;<sup>3</sup>LE<sub>D</sub>)&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.16&#x02009;eV) enhances the TADF activity through the processes of ISC and RISC. Although the emission decay of an ideal TADF material follows a bi-exponential decay consisting of a fast fluorescence component and a slow TADF component, the emission decay of TMB/PPT is mostly dominated by the power-law decay originating from the charge recombination process and, therefore, does not exhibit bi-exponential decay. The emission decay profiles and the corresponding time-resolved spectra indicate that the TMB/PPT system exhibits fluorescence from TMB, prompt fluorescence from exciplexes, TADF from exciplexes, and finally LPL emission from exciplexes via charge separation and recombination processes, successively.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>OLPL from TTB/PPT system</title><p id="Par15">The steady-state photoluminescence spectrum of the TTB/PPT system exhibits clear two distinct emission features with the peaks at 440&#x02009;nm and 530&#x02009;nm originating from exciplex fluorescence and donor phosphorescence, respectively (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2f</xref>). Although the emission peak at 440&#x02009;nm is close to the peaks of PPT phosphorescence and TTB fluorescence, this peak can be attributed to exciplex fluorescence for two reasons. First, PPT phosphorescence is quenched by oxygen, but the TTB/PPT film in air still exhibits a similar peak at 435&#x02009;nm. Second, the emission decay at 440&#x02009;nm of TTB/PPT is much longer than that of TTB fluorescence. The sharpness of the exciplex emission can be ascribed to the self-absorption by the radical cation species of TTB (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">11</xref>). The contribution of delayed fluorescence by triplet&#x02013;triplet annihilation is almost negligible, as the donor concentration is only 1% and the phosphorescence timescale is much shorter than that of LPL. The TTB concentration dependence of the emission spectra and emission decay profiles (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">12</xref>) are also consistent with exciplex emission. The LPL duration becomes shorter at higher concentrations of the donor, because the accumulated changes can more easily recombine with donor molecules. For higher donor concentrations, the exciplex emission was slightly redshifted and the room-temperature phosphorescence from donors became weaker because of aggregation of donor molecules.</p><p id="Par16">In the case of the TTB/PPT system, the TADF process is almost completely quenched, because the <sup>3</sup>LE<sub>D</sub> of TTB is much lower than the <sup>1</sup>CT. This large energy gap (&#x00394;<italic>E</italic>(<sup>1</sup>CT&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;<sup>3</sup>LE<sub>D</sub>)&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.54&#x02009;eV) suppresses the RISC process, so that photo-generated excitons are becomes trapped on <sup>3</sup>LE<sub>D</sub>, leading to room-temperature phosphorescence from TTB. As the energy gap between the <sup>1</sup>CT and the lowest triplet excited-state of the acceptor (<sup>3</sup>LE<sub>A</sub>) is small enough, these energy levels should contribute to the TADF process. However, the generated <sup>3</sup>LE<sub>A</sub> excitons can easily decay to the lower <sup>3</sup>LE<sub>D</sub><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>. As the TADF process is suppressed at low temperatures, the emission spectra at 10&#x02009;K contain stronger phosphorescence components from TTB than the spectrum at room temperature (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">13</xref>). Further, after the decay of phosphorescence from the TTB triplet excited states, the emission occurs from the excitons generated by the CS state. As charge recombination generates both singlet (<sup>1</sup>CT) and triplet (<sup>3</sup>CT) exciplexes, the LPL emission consists of both exciplex fluorescence from <sup>1</sup>CT and donor phosphorescence from <sup>3</sup>LE<sub>D</sub>, which is populated by the transfer of excitons from <sup>3</sup>CT to <sup>3</sup>LE<sub>D</sub>. Because of the dual emission from <sup>1</sup>CT and <sup>3</sup>LE<sub>D</sub>, TTB/PPT system exhibits white emission. The CIE coordinates (CIE<sub><italic>x</italic></sub>, CIE<sub><italic>y</italic></sub>) of the steady-state photoluminescence and LPL spectra are (0.27, 0.33) and (0.31, 0.37), respectively (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">14</xref> and Supplementary Movie&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">1</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>OLPL from DMDTB/PPT system</title><p id="Par17">The energy gap &#x00394;<italic>E</italic>(<sup>1</sup>CT&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;<sup>3</sup>LE<sub>D</sub>)&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.25&#x02009;eV of the DMDTB/PPT system is between those of TMB/PPT and TTB/PPT systems. Therefore, DMDTB/PPT system also exhibits dual emission from both exciplex fluorescence (<sup>1</sup>CT) and DMDTB phosphorescence (<sup>3</sup>LE<sub>D</sub>). The exciplex emission of DMDTB/PPT shows a large spectral shift during the TADF process. This large emission shift would be derived from the excited-state conformational change between the structural conformers of DMDTB (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">15</xref>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. Because of this large spectral shift, the exciplex fluorescence and DMDTB phosphorescence have a large spectral overlap. The lack of spectral shift and TADF emission in the LPL emission spectrum at 10&#x02009;K confirms the contribution of TADF to the emission of the DMDTB/PPT system at room temperature.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec9" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par18">These results clearly indicate the importance of the energy level of <sup>3</sup>LE<sub>D</sub> for obtaining efficient LPL emission. As <sup>3</sup>LE excitons are less likely to undergo the charge-transfer step needed for creating separated charges that contribute to LPL, the higher exciton population on <sup>3</sup>LE<sub>D</sub> induced by a large energy gap of &#x00394;<italic>E</italic>(<sup>1</sup>CT&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;<sup>3</sup>LE<sub>D</sub>) will reduce the number of excitons that can convert into CS states. Thus, efficient LPL emission requires a small energy gap to ensure a higher number of <sup>1</sup>CT excitons that can contribute to the accumulation of separated charges.</p><p id="Par19">Notably, the presented photoluminescence quantum yields (<italic>&#x003a6;</italic><sub>PL</sub>) do not completely reflect the LPL components (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The quantum efficiency of LPL emission is difficult to define, because the charge accumulation and release processes are slow and complicated in contrast to those of long-lived phosphorescence. Furthermore, the LPL emission depends on the excitation time as well as the excitation power, whereas the phosphorescence component is constant (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">16</xref> and Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">17</xref>). As the LPL system continuously provides the new excited states after turning off the photoexcitation, we cannot calculate the <italic>&#x003a6;</italic><sub>PL</sub> from the steady-state photoluminescence spectra (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">18</xref>). This is why <italic>&#x003a6;</italic><sub>PL</sub> is not discussed even in inorganic LPL materials<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par20">In conclusion, we demonstrated that the <sup>3</sup>LE<sub>D</sub> influences LPL emission by changing the energy gap of &#x00394;<italic>E</italic>(<sup>1</sup>CT&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;<sup>3</sup>LE<sub>D</sub>). When the energy level of <sup>3</sup>LE<sub>D</sub> is significantly lower than that of the <sup>1</sup>CT, the OLPL efficiency was reduced. As a large energy gap induces a higher <sup>3</sup>LE<sub>D</sub> population through ISC and energy transfer from <sup>3</sup>CT to <sup>3</sup>LE<sub>D</sub>, the emission from both <sup>1</sup>CT and <sup>3</sup>LE<sub>D</sub> contributed to LPL. This dual emission from both <sup>1</sup>CT and <sup>3</sup>LE<sub>D</sub> produced white light without the use of additional dopants. Moreover, we found that absorption by radical cation species generated by the charge separation process also affects the LPL emission spectra. Future efficient OLPL systems using both small molecules and polymers will be developed based on these considerations.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec11"><title>Materials</title><p id="Par21">TMB and TTB were purchased from TCI Chemicals (Tokyo, Japan). DMDTB was synthesized according to <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">Supplementary Methods</xref>. PPT was prepared as described in the literature. All materials were purified by recrystallization and sublimation, and were stored in amber bottles in a glovebox. ZEONOR 1060R was obtained from ZEON Japan (Tokyo, Japan). Other materials were used as received. Inorganic LPL product was obtained from LTI Corporation (Kyoto, Japan).</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Film fabrication</title><p id="Par22">Thick films (0.4&#x02009;mm) for the optical measurement were fabricated by a melt-casting method<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. Mixed materials were heated up the melting point of the acceptor (250&#x02009;&#x000b0;C) in a nitrogen-filled glovebox. After melting, the substrate was cooled rapidly to room temperature. Thin films for the UV-visible absorption measurements were fabricated by sandwiching the heat-melted materials between two quartz substrates. Film thickness were 18&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4&#x02009;&#x003bc;m (PPT), 25&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3&#x02009;&#x003bc;m (TMB/PPT), 7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4&#x02009;&#x003bc;m (DMDTB/PPT), and 16&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;8&#x02009;&#x003bc;m (TTB/PPT). The ZEONOR doped films were fabricated by solution processing<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. Materials were dissolved in xylene by ultrasonication and drop-cast on the substrate at 80&#x02009;&#x000b0;C and then annealed for 1&#x02009;h at 170&#x02009;&#x000b0;C in a nitrogen-filled glovebox.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Characterization</title><p id="Par23"><sup>1</sup>H nuclear magneticresonance (NMR) (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">19</xref>) and <sup>13</sup>C NMR spectra (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">20</xref>) were recorded with a Bruker AVANCE III 500&#x02009;MHz spectrometer. Molecular weight was measured in positive-ion atmospheric-pressure chemical ionization mode on a Waters 3100 mass detector (APCI-MS). Elemental analysis (C, H, and N) was carried out with a Yanaco MT-5 elemental analyzer. Film thicknesses were measured in five different positions on each film using a micrometer screw gauge and averaged. The cyclic voltammetry (CV) and differential pulse voltammetry (DPV) measurements were carried out using an electrochemical analyzer (Model 608D&#x02009;+&#x02009;DPV, BAS). The measurements were performed in dried and oxygen-free CH<sub>2</sub>Cl<sub>2</sub> using 0.1&#x02009;M tetrabutylammonium hexafluorophosphate (TBAPF<sub>6</sub>) as a supporting electrolyte. A platinum fiber was used as a working electrode, glassy carbon as a counter electrode, and Ag/Ag<sup>+</sup> as a reference electrode. Redox potentials were referenced against ferrocene/ferrocenium (Fc/Fc<sup>+</sup>). The CV curves were recorded at a scan rate of 100&#x02009;mV&#x02009;s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and the DPV curves were obtained with a pulse width (&#x00394;<italic>E</italic><sub>pulse</sub>) of 0.2&#x02009;s. The HOMO energy levels of the three donors were calculated according to the equations of <italic>E</italic><sub>HOMO or LUMO</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x02013;<italic>E</italic><sub>redox</sub>(vs. Fc/Fc<sup>+</sup>)&#x02009;&#x02013;&#x02009;4.8 eV<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup> and <italic>E</italic><sub>redox</sub>&#x02009;=&#x02009;<italic>E</italic><sub>peak</sub>&#x02009;+&#x02009;&#x00394;<italic>E</italic><sub>pulse</sub>/2, where <italic>E</italic><sub>redox</sub> and <italic>E</italic><sub>peak</sub> are the formal electrode potentials and the DPV peak potentials of the redox, respectively. The LUMO energy level of PPT was calculated from the CV data in DMF<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Optical measurements</title><p id="Par24">The absorption spectra were recorded on a UV-vis-NIR spectrophotometer (LAMBDA 950, Perkin Elmer). The absorption spectra of the radical species were obtained under electrical oxidation in a solution containing 0.1&#x02009;M TBAPF<sub>6</sub>. The photoluminescence spectra in air were recorded on a spectrofluorometer (FP-8600, JASCO). The phosphorescence spectra at 77&#x02009;K were recorded on a multi-channel spectrometer (PMA-12, Hamamatsu Photonics) excited using a 340&#x02009;nm LED (M340L4, Thorlabs) with a bandpass filter (340&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5&#x02009;nm). The absolute photoluminescence quantum yields (<italic>&#x003a6;</italic><sub>PL</sub>) were measured using a quantum yield spectrometer (C9920-02, Hamamatsu Photonics). The streak images, transient photoluminescence spectra, and decay profiles on various timescales were measured in vacuum using a streak camera system (C4334, Hamamatsu Photonics) equipped with a cryostat (GASESCRT-006-2000, Iwatani) and excitation was provided by a nitrogen gas laser (KEN-X, USHO). LPL performance was obtained using a homemade measurement setup with an excitation power of 230&#x02009;&#x003bc;W and an excitation duration of 60&#x02009;s<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. Supplementary Movie&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">1</xref> was recorded on a Sony &#x003b1;7sII digital camera with 1&#x02009;mol% TTB/PPT film excited by 365&#x02009;nm UV lamp for 5&#x02009;min at 300&#x02009;K.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>ESR measurements</title><p id="Par25">The ESR spectra were recorded on a JEOL JES-FA200 spectrometer. The samples were photo-excited by using a 340&#x02009;nm LED (M340L4, Thorlabs).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary information</title><sec id="Sec16"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41467_2019_14035_MOESM1_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Supplementary information</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="41467_2019_14035_MOESM2_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Peer Review File</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3"><media xlink:href="41467_2019_14035_MOESM3_ESM.docx"><caption><p>Description of Additional Supplementary Files</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM4"><media xlink:href="41467_2019_14035_MOESM4_ESM.mp4"><caption><p>Supplementary Movie 1</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Peer review information</bold>
<italic>Nature Communications</italic> thanks Dongpeng Yan, and other, anonymous, reviewer(s) for their contribution to the peer review of this work. Peer reviewer reports are available.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s note</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Supplementary information</title><p><bold>Supplementary information</bold> is available for this paper at 10.1038/s41467-019-14035-y.</p></sec><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This work was supported by the Japan Science and Technology Agency (JST), ERATO, Adachi Molecular Exciton Engineering Project, under JST ERATO Grant Number JPMJER1305, Japan; the International Institute for Carbon Neutral Energy Research (WPI-I2CNER) sponsored by the Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science, and Technology (MEXT); JSPS KAKENHI Grant Numbers JP18H02049 and JP18H04522; and the Mitsubishi Foundation. Z.L. was supported by the Japanese Government (MEXT) Scholarship and also acknowledges the MEXT Top Global University Project and the China Scholarship Council (CSC). We thank Dr. W. Potscavage for his assistance in writing this manuscript.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>R.K. proposed the project. Z.L. designed molecules and perfomed all experiments. Z.L. and K.W. performed the computational calucularation. R.K. and C.A. supervised the project. Z. L., R.K., and C.A. wrote the manuscript and all authors reviewed the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>The data that support the findings of this study are available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par26">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wu, S., Pan, Z., Chen, R. &#x00026; Liu, X. <italic>Long Afterglow Phosphorescent Materials</italic> 21&#x02013;22 (Springer, 2017).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanabe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Persistent luminescence instead of phosphorescence: history, mechanism, and perspective</article-title><source>J. Lumin.</source><year>2019</year><volume>205</volume><fpage>581</fpage><lpage>620</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jlumin.2018.09.047</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matsuzawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Aoki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeuchi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Murayama</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A new long phosphorescent phosphor with high brightness, SrAl<sub>2</sub>O<sub>4</sub>:&#x02009;Eu<sup>2+</sup>,&#x02009;Dy<sup>3+</sup></article-title><source>J. Electrochem. Soc.</source><year>1996</year><volume>143</volume><fpage>2670</fpage><lpage>2673</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1149/1.1837067</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Social and environmental impact of the rare earth industries</article-title><source>Resources</source><year>2014</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>123</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/resources3010123</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kabe</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Adachi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Organic long persistent luminescence</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2017</year><volume>550</volume><fpage>384</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature24010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28967911</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Kabe</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishimura</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Jinnai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Adachi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Organic long-persistent luminescence from a flexible and transparent doped polymer</article-title><source>Adv. Mater.</source><year>2018</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>180371</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jinnai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishimura</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kabe</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Adachi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fabrication-method independence of organic long-persistent luminescence performance</article-title><source>Chem. Lett.</source><year>2019</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>270</fpage><lpage>273</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1246/cl.180949</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jinnai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kabe</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Adachi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Wide-range tuning and enhancement of organic long-persistent luminescence using emitter dopants</article-title><source>Adv. Mater.</source><year>2018</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>1800365</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/adma.201800365</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abell</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name><surname>Mozumder</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Application of diffusion model for recombination of isolated pairs in condensed media</article-title><source>J. Chem. Phys.</source><year>1972</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>4079</fpage><lpage>4085</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/1.1677818</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Noolandi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Solution of the Smoluchowski equation with a Coulomb potential. I. General results</article-title><source>J. Chem. Phys.</source><year>1978</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>5163</fpage><lpage>5171</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/1.435636</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hirata</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ultralong-lived room temperature triplet excitons: molecular persistent room temperature phosphorescence and nonlinear optical characteristics with continuous irradiation</article-title><source>J. Mater. Chem. C.</source><year>2018</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>11785</fpage><lpage>11794</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C8TC01417E</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Mei</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nano-photosensitizer based on layered double hydroxide and isophthalic acid for singlet oxygenation and photodynamic therapy</article-title><source>Nat. Commun.</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>2798</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-018-05223-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30022060</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ohkita</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakai</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsuchida</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Charge recombination luminescence via the photoionization of a dopant chromophore in polymer solids</article-title><source>Macromolecules</source><year>1997</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>5376</fpage><lpage>5383</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ma970585q</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A kinetic study of the thermoluminescence of lithium fluoride</article-title><source>J. Chem. Phys.</source><year>1949</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>1221</fpage><lpage>1226</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/1.1747146</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hama</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsumura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Omi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Studies on the recombination of cation&#x02014;electron pairs by long-range tunneling, as studied by ITL measurement in irradiated polymers</article-title><source>Chem. Phys.</source><year>1980</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>115</fpage><lpage>122</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0301-0104(80)87059-5</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Debye</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long&#x02010;lifetime phosphorescence and the diffusion process</article-title><source>J. Chem. Phys.</source><year>1952</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>236</fpage><lpage>239</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/1.1700385</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stolzenburg</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ries</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x000e4;ssler</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Kinetics of geminate pair recombination in polyvinylcarbazole</article-title><source>Ber. Bunsenges. Phys. Chem.</source><year>1987</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>853</fpage><lpage>858</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bbpc.19870910905</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tachiya</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mozumder</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Kinetics of geminate-ion recombination by electron tunnelling</article-title><source>Chem. Phys. Lett.</source><year>1975</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>79</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0009-2614(75)80204-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">K&#x000f6;hler, A. &#x00026; B&#x000e4;ssler, H. <italic>Electronic Processes in Organic Semiconductors</italic> 260&#x02013;263 (Wiley-VCH, 2015).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamazaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Industrialization and application development of cyclo-olefin polymer</article-title><source>J. Mol. Catal. A: Chem.</source><year>2004</year><volume>213</volume><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>87</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcata.2003.10.058</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goushi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshida</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Adachi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Organic light-emitting diodes employing efficient reverse intersystem crossing for triplet-to-singlet state conversion</article-title><source>Nat. Photonics</source><year>2012</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>253</fpage><lpage>258</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nphoton.2012.31</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sarma</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>K-T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exciplex: an intermolecular charge-transfer approach for TADF</article-title><source>ACS Appl. Mater. Interfaces</source><year>2018</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>19279</fpage><lpage>19304</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acsami.7b18318</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29613766</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mylon</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Smirnov</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Braun</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exciplex dipole moments:&#x02009;Cyanoanthracene acceptors and methyl-substituted benzene donors</article-title><source>J. Phys. Chem. A</source><year>1998</year><volume>102</volume><fpage>6558</fpage><lpage>6564</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jp981637w</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsuboi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exciton- and polaron-induced reversible dipole reorientation in amorphous organic semiconductor films</article-title><source>Adv. Opt. Mater.</source><year>2019</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>1801644</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/adom.201801644</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>M&#x000e9;hes</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Goushi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Potscavage</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Adachi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influence of host matrix on thermally-activated delayed fluorescence: effects on emission lifetime, photoluminescence quantum yield, and device performance</article-title><source>Org. Electron.</source><year>2014</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>2027</fpage><lpage>2037</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.orgel.2014.05.027</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>Y-S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Exciplex-forming co-host for organic light-emitting diodes with ultimate efficiency</article-title><source>Adv. Funct. Mater.</source><year>2013</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>4914</fpage><lpage>4920</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/adfm.201300547</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jankus</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>C-J</given-names></name><name><surname>Dias</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Monkman</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Deep blue exciplex organic light-emitting diodes with enhanced efficiency; P-type or E-type triplet conversion to singlet excitons?</article-title><source>Adv. Mater.</source><year>2013</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>1455</fpage><lpage>1459</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/adma.201203615</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23281058</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Etherington</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Higginbotham</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name><name><surname>Penfold</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Monkman</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Revealing the spin&#x02013;vibronic coupling mechanism of thermally activated delayed fluorescence</article-title><source>Nat. Commun.</source><year>2016</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>13680</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms13680</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27901046</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Noda</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakanotani</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Adachi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Excited state engineering for efficient reverse intersystem crossing</article-title><source>Sci. Adv.</source><year>2018</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>eaao6910</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/sciadv.aao6910</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29942856</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mamada</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakanotani</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Adachi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Importance of excited-state energy alignment for efficient exciplex systems based on a study of phenylpyridinato boron derivatives</article-title><source>Angew. Chem.</source><year>2018</year><volume>130</volume><fpage>12560</fpage><lpage>12564</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ange.201804218</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Nonaromatic amine containing exciplex for thermally activated delayed fluorescent electroluminescence</article-title><source>Adv. Opt. Mater.</source><year>2019</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1801554</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/adom.201801554</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Layered host&#x02013;guest long-afterglow ultrathin nanosheets: high-efficiency phosphorescence energy transfer at 2D confined interface</article-title><source>Chem. Sci.</source><year>2017</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>590</fpage><lpage>599</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C6SC03515A</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28451206</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hydrogen-bonded two-component ionic crystals showing enhanced long-lived room-temperature phosphorescence via TADF-assisted F&#x000f6;rster resonance energy transfer</article-title><source>Adv. Funct. Mater.</source><year>2019</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>1807599</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/adfm.201807599</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Jen</surname><given-names>AK-Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synthesis and characterization of a novel and highly efficient light-emitting polymer</article-title><source>Acta Polym.</source><year>1999</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>105</fpage><lpage>108</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1521-4044(19990201)50:2/3&#x0003c;105::AID-APOL105&#x0003e;3.0.CO;2-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>