<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Open Access Maced J Med Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Open Access Maced J Med Sci</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Open Access Macedonian Journal of Medical Sciences</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1857-9655</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Republic of Macedonia</publisher-name><publisher-loc>ID Design 2012/DOOEL Skopje</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31949514</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6953942</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">OAMJMS-7-3189</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3889/oamjms.2019.798</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Clinical Science</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Risk Factors Analysis for Catheter-Associated Urinary Tract Infection in Medan, Indonesia</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hariati</surname><given-names>Hariati</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Suza</surname><given-names>Dewi Elizadiani</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tarigan</surname><given-names>Rosina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">Faculty of Nursing, Universitas Sumatera Utara, Jl. Prof. Maas No. 3 Kampus USU Medan 20155, Indonesia</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label><bold>Correspondence:</bold> Hariati Hariati. Faculty of Nursing, Universitas Sumatera Utara, Jl. Prof. Maas No. 3 Kampus USU Medan 20155, Indonesia. E-mail: <email xlink:href="hariati1092@gmail.com">hariati1092@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><day>15</day><month>10</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>9</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>19</issue><fpage>3189</fpage><lpage>3194</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>5</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>14</day><month>10</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>15</day><month>10</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; 2019 Hariati Hariati, Dewi Elizadiani Suza, Rosina Tarigan.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/CC BY-NC/4.0"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License (CC BY-NC 4.0)</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec id="st1"><title>BACKGROUND:</title><p>Catheter-associated urinary tract infection (CAUTI) is one of the most common infections in health care caused by several risk factors.</p></sec><sec id="st2"><title>AIM:</title><p>This study aims at analysing the risky factors triggering CAUTI.</p></sec><sec id="st3"><title>METHODS:</title><p>This research was designed by applying prospective study. It was conducted from July to November 2018 by involving 82 patients attached to the catheter and treated in the General Hospital of Medan as the sample. The study instrument used observational sheets by measuring the occurrence of urinary tract infection using urine culture analysis &#x02265; 105 CFU/ml.</p></sec><sec id="st4"><title>RESULTS:</title><p>The results showed that there was a relationship (p &#x0003c; 0.05) amongs age (p = 0.01; RR = 0.51), diabetes mellitus (p = 0.00; RR = 7.61), duration of catheterization (p = 0.00; RR = 0.01), indications for catheter use (p = 0.00; RR = 0.34) with CAUTI, and there were not significant relationship (p &#x0003e; 0.05) amongs genre (p = 0.06; RR = 1.72), drainage system (p = 0.43; RR = 0.43) and catheter care (p = 0.08; RR = 0.50) with CAUTI. Diabetes mellitus (p = 0.00; OR = 8.92 95% CI = 1.02-11.83) and duration of catheterization (p = 0, 00; OR = 32.84 95% CI = 3.81-322.74) were the most significant factor related to CAUTI.</p></sec><sec id="st5"><title>CONCLUSION:</title><p>CAUTI is influenced by various factors, and it can be controlled by understanding those factors so that the right interventions to prevent the infections can be taken and the quality of nursing care can be increased as well.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Urinary Tract Infection</kwd><kwd>Catheter</kwd><kwd>Risk Factor</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Urinary tract infection is the most common infectious disease in healthcare services worldwide. Urinary tract infection is mostly caused by catheter placement. About 40% of infections in healthcare are urinary tract infection in which 80% of it is triggered by catheter placement [<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Approximately 12%-16% of the adult patients used indwelling catheters during a stay in the hospital, and 3%-7% of patients had catheter-associated urinary tract infection [<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Urinary tract infection is the most common infection, which 560.000 per year and 387.550 were catheter-associated urinary tract infection [<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. The number of urinary tract infection estimated 222 million people worldwide. The number of urinary tract infection estimated 90-100 cases of 100.000 people or 180.000 new cases for one year in Indonesia [<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>].</p><p>Infection often occurs after placement of urine catheter, and infection increases 5% urine bacteria for catheter placement every day [<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. The number of infections 3%-5% and 3%-10% every day for indwelling catheter placement in short-term and long-term [<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Urinary tract infection increases morbidity, mortality, length of stay and charge in the hospital. Catheter-associated urinary tract infection spends maintenance cost as much as 876 dollars for diagnosis and 1.764 dollars for treating patients in the intensive care unit [<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. A patient suffering from urinary tract infection got the harmful impact the presence of bacteria in the urine [<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], [<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], [<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. The impact can cause harm to patients. The nurse has a big role in care patients with catheter placement [<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>].</p><p>The nurses are very important for preventing the infection at patient by identifying potential risk factor that can affect urinary tract infection through a methodology approach to nursing care, namely assessment, diagnoses, planning, implementation and evaluation [<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Data about risk factor analysis catheter-associated urinary tract infection was very required judgment to do appropriate nursing care as a measurement tool for assessing the success of nursing care provided. To prevent the occurrence of urinary tract infections, it is necessary to know the risk factor catheter-associated urinary tract infection as basic to care for the patient. This study aims at analysing the risk factor catheter-associated urinary tract infection.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="sec1-2"><title>Methods</title><p>This research was designed by applying prospective study. It was conducted from July to November 2018 by involving 82 patients attached to the catheter and treated in the General Hospital of Medan as the sample. The sampling technique was a nonprobability sampling, namely; convenience sampling. The inclusion criteria of sample were: 1) patient placed in a catheter placement at General Hospital Medan showing signs and symptoms such as fever &#x02265; 38&#x000b0;C, suprapubic and costovertebral pain &#x0003e; 48 hours; 2) the culture result &#x02265; 10<sup>5</sup> CFU/ml or more than two bacteria identified; and 3) length of stay patient was a least two days. The exclusion criteria of the sample were: 1) patients were diagnosed with an infectious disease; 2) patient placed in a catheter placement showing signs and symptoms such as fever &#x02265; 38&#x000b0;C, suprapubic and costovertebral pain &#x0003c; 48 hours; 3) patients were treated in paediatric room; and 4) patient didn&#x02019;t want to be respondent. The study has been approved by the Ethics Commission of Nursing Faculty Universitas Sumatera Utara number 1503/VI/SP/2018 and the researcher also asked for respondent&#x02019;s agreement with informed consent.</p><p>Measurement to determine catheter-associated urinary tract infection used Center Disease Control (CDC) criteria such as temperature &#x02265; 38&#x000ba;C, suprapubic and costovertebral pain &#x0003e; 48 hours, the culture result &#x02265; 10<sup>5</sup> CFU/ml or more than two bacteria identified. The study steps have been performed by researchers, namely: 1) the researcher filled the respondents&#x02019; demographic data, such as age, genre, diabetes mellitus, an indication of catheter placement in the observation sheet. The researcher observed the duration of catheter placement, drainage system, catheter care, and signs and symptoms of catheter-associated urinary tract infection, such as temperature &#x02265; 38&#x000b0;C, suprapubic and costovertebral pain, the culture result &#x02265; 10<sup>5</sup> CFU/ml or more than two bacteria identified; 2) The patients were observed about signs and symptoms of catheter-associated urinary tract infection after catheter placement by the researchers; 3) The patients were observed for seven days long-time according to signs and symptoms of catheter-associated urinary tract infection by the researchers, and 4) The urine specimen of patients were collected for urine culture.</p><p>The authors made the fifth day of catheterisation was taken as the cut-off point for this study because according the research by Al-Hazmi showed that 7 patients from 46 patient who got catheterised placement have infections at third days and 30 patients from 44 patients at the seventh days. The author estimated the seventh day as the longest of the day &#x02014; fifth days as the cut-off point in this study and median in this research. CAUTI could occur at after second days of catheter placement. The CAUTI began on the third day.</p><p>A urine catheter was collected for culture. Hand hygiene was performed before, and after the specimen&#x02019;s collection, gloves were used during the procedure. The drainage port was cleansed with an antiseptic before and after specimen&#x02019;s collection. The drainage system was clamped under the port drainage. The specimen was collected with a sterile syringe. A urine sample was aspirated 3 ml to 5 ml. The clamp was removed to prevent urine reflux. The urine sample was transferred from the sterile syringe to the specimen cup. The specimen cup was put into cooler-box and transferred to the laboratory.</p><p>The urine culture was performed by microbiologists. The urine specimens were inoculated on Blood Agar and Mac Conkey. The plates were incubated at 35&#x000b0;C for 24 hours and counted the total plate (CFU/ml). The identification of bacteria morphology and type of bacteria used conventional microbiology methods. It was found that urinary tract infection occurred if there was &#x02265;10<sup>5</sup> CFU/ml or more than two bacteria identified.</p><p>Statistical analysis test was performed by using SPSS. Chi-square and Fisher&#x02019;s exact test was used for bivariate analysis because the variable had an ordinal scale, and Logistic regression test was used for multivariate analysis. The p-value significance level was set at <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05. The multivariate quantified analysis was the most influential variable to catheter-associated urinary tract infection. The significance level to enter the logistic regression models was set at <italic>p &#x0003c;</italic> 0.25. The logistic regression models were performed for six times. The Two most influential variables were obtained finally.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec1-3"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec2-1"><title>The study population: Characteristics of Patients</title><p>During the study period, there was 82 patient who attracted by urine catheter. Which, 36 patients were suffering from catheter-associated urinary tract infection, and 46 patients did not suffer from catheter-associated urinary tract infection. The characteristic of patients is illustrated in <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Characteristics of Patients in the Study (n = 82)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" width="100%"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Characteristic</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Absolut Frequency (n)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Relative Frequency (%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Gender</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Male</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.66</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Female</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.34</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Age</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x0003c; 60 Years &#x000b1; Mean</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54 &#x000b1; 45.66</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65.85</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x0003e; 60 Years &#x000b1; Mean</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 &#x000b1; 62.10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.15</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Diabetes mellitus (DM)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Type II DM</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.22</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;No DM</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.78</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Long History of Diabetes Mellitus</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x0003e; 10 Years &#x000b1; Mean</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20 &#x000b1; 4.30</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.40</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x0003c; 10 Years &#x000b1; Mean</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 &#x000b1; 12.63</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.80</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Immobilisation</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.59</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;No</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.41</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Type of Immobilization</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Total</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.20</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Partial immobilization</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.40</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Duration of catheterisation</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x0003c; 5 days &#x000b1; Mean</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34 &#x000b1; 3.42</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.46</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x0003e; 5 days &#x000b1; Mean</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48 &#x000b1; 6.42</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.53</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Indication catheter used</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Surgery</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.12</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Urology noninfection</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.07</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Cardiology</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.53</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Others (noninfectious disease)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.28</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Catheter care</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.39</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;No</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.61</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Catheter Size</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;16 fr</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.98</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;18 fr</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.02</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Based on <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. the proportion of males was higher than females 53.66%. The mean age was &#x000b1; 45.66 to &#x000b1; 62.10 years. The percentage of patients with diabetes mellitus 51.22% with long history was &#x000b1; 4.30 to &#x000b1; 12.63 years. Majority patient has immobilisation 86.59% with type partial immobilisation 63.4%. The mean duration of catheterisation was &#x000b1; 3.42 to &#x000b1; 6.42 days. The indication catheter used was surgery at 45.12%. Majority of urine catheter care was not done by nurses 75.61%. The catheter size was 16 as much as 60.98%.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-2"><title>Description of Research Result</title><p>Based on <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, Data was analysed by Chi-square. There was a significant relationship (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) amongst age, diabetes mellitus, duration of catheterisation, indication catheter used and catheter size with catheter-associated urinary tract infection. There was not a significant relationship (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003e; 0.05) amongst gender and catheter care catheter-associated urinary tract infection. Diabetes mellitus and duration of catheterisation were the most influencing variable with catheter-associated urinary tract infection by logistic regression. It showed that the significant variable (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) have a relationship with catheter-associated urinary tract infection, diabetes mellitus (<italic>p</italic> = 0.001) and duration of catheter used (<italic>p</italic> = 0,001). If the strength relationship according to the value of Odds Ratio (OR), so the most influential variable on catheter-associated urinary tract infection were diabetes mellitus (OR = 8.92; 95%CI, 2.09&#x02013;37.95) and duration of catheter used (OR = 32.84; 95%CI, 3.71&#x02013;290.30).</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Analysis of Relationship between risk factor with Catheter-Associated Urinary Tract Infection (n = 82)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" width="100%"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Variable</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">CAUTI</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">No CAUTI</th><th align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">Relative Risk</th><th align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1">95% CI</th><th align="center" rowspan="3" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic>-value</th></tr><tr><th align="center" colspan="4" rowspan="1"><hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" rowspan="1">A. Bivariate<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t2f1">a</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" rowspan="1">Gender</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Female</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.58</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.42</td><td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.57</td><td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.33&#x02013;0.99</td><td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.06</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Male</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54.54</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.45</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" rowspan="1">Age</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x0003c; 60 Years</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.33</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66.67</td><td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">1.92</td><td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">1.20&#x02013;3.07</td><td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x0003e; 60 Years</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.29</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.71</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" rowspan="1">Diabetes mellitus (DM)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Type II DM</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.91</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.81</td><td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">7.61</td><td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">2.96&#x02013;19.60</td><td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;No DM</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.00</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Immobilisation</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.30</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.70</td><td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">5.42</td><td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.82&#x02013;35.66</td><td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;No</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.09</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" rowspan="1">Duration of catheterisation</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x0003c; 5 days</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.94</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.05</td><td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">24.79</td><td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">3.56&#x02013;172.27</td><td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x0003e; 5 days</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.92</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.08</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" rowspan="1">Indication catheter used</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Medical</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.22</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.78</td><td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">2.87</td><td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">1.49&#x02013;5.53</td><td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Surgery</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21.62</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.38</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" rowspan="1">Catheter care</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;No</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.00</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.00</td><td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">2.00</td><td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.90&#x02013;4.46</td><td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.08</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Yes</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.00</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" rowspan="1">Catheter Size</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;16 fr</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.00</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.00</td><td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">1.95</td><td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">1.02&#x02013;3.17</td><td align="center" rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;18 fr</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62.50</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" rowspan="1">B. Multivariate<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t2f2">b</xref></sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Diabetes mellitus (DM)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.92</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.09&#x02013;37.95</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;Duration of catheterization</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.84</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.71&#x02013;290.30</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t2f1"><label>a</label><p>Note:) <italic>Chi-Square;</italic></p></fn><fn id="t2f2"><label>b</label><p>)<italic>Logistic Regression.</italic></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Based on <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>, the result of urine culture identified as various organisms caused by catheter-associated urinary tract infection. The majority organism was Escherichia coli 13 (36.11%).</p><table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Organism (n = 36)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" width="100%"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Organism</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">n</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">%</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Escherichia coli</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.11</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Enterococcus</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.78</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Klebsiella pneumonia</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.78</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.44</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Staphylococcus epidermis</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.33</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.56</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Enterobacter aerogenes</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.78</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Proteus mirabilis</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.78</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Acinetobacter baumannii</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.56</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Enterococcus faecalis</italic></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.56</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec1-4"><title>Discussion</title><p>The catheter placement was a major common urinary tract infection in healthcare. Our finding shows that approximately 43.90% of patients had catheter-associated tract infection [<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. We used the <italic>Center Disease Control</italic> criteria to set as catheter-associated tract infection [<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Bacteria type found was Escherichia coli 36.11%. Similarly, the study [<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], [<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], [<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] that Escherichia coli was the most commons catheter-associated urinary tract infection. Type 1 Fimbriae was Escherichia coli gen causing infection [<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. These bacteria would locate and require the right antibiotic therapy. The risk of inappropriate antibiotic therapy could cause Multidrug Resistance (MDR) to the microorganism in the urinary tract [<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>].</p><p>We found that the genre has not a relationship with catheter-associated tract infection. Male and Female have the same opportunity to suffer from infection, but the numbers of a male suffering from infection were more than female in proportion. The study was contradictive with the theories found that females had more risk to suffer from infection because females have a short urethra [<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. However, the study similarity with) [<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] catheter-associated urinary tract infection. The increasing of catheter-associated urinary tract infection at male caused the difference of hormone and microorganism in urine [<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. The same opportunities to have catheter-associated urinary tract infection were caused by personal hygiene. The poor personal hygiene in the male and female, especially the genital area had risk suffer from disease-related infection [<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>].</p><p>Not surprisingly, we found that more than 60-year-old have more risk to suffer from catheter-associated urinary tract infection. It is consistent with theories of immunosenescence [<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] and the previous study [<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>] with cohort study that high rates catheter-associated urinary tract infection in elderly patients with average age 64.6 years.</p><p>Diabetic Mellitus was as an independent factor for catheter-associated urinary tract infection and has been shown in another study [<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. We found that diabetes mellitus patient had 8.92 times risk have catheter-associated urinary tract infection. The increasing would continue with length to suffering from diabetes mellitus. The Diabetic Mellitus patient has a risk suffer from catheter-associated urinary tract infection because of autonomy neuropathy [<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. This problem can cause incomplete bladder emptying and cause microorganism colonisation. Furthermore, the diabetic Mellitus patient has pancreatic betta cells damage or do not produce enough insulin and cause hyperglycaemia. If there is a hyperglycaemia condition, the kidneys cannot reabsorb glucose. The glucose levels will be high in the urine. The glucosuria influences leukocyte function and performs as a growth medium of pathogenic microorganisms. The poor control and decreasing immune system become a risk factor of diabetic mellitus patients to suffering from catheter-associated urinary tract infection [<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], [<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>].</p><p>A patient who has catheter placement continuously and bed rest can complicate to infection. We found the immobilisation has a relationship with catheter-associated tract infection. Immobilisation could cause urine flow to become static. Urine was flowing from renal pelvis to the bladder through ureter because of gravity in an upright position. When the patient was in the supine position, the peristaltic of the ureter is unable to produce gravity [<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Urine would reflux from bladder to kidney [<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>].</p><p>Duration of catheterisation was the most influential independent factor with catheter-associated urinary tract infection. It has been shown in another study [<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], [<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>], [<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. The odds of the duration of catheterisation 32.85 higher for a patient who inserted a catheter for five days or more. The length the catheter insertion, the more susceptible to infection [<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Patients who insert the indwelling catheter have a risk to growth bacteriuria [<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. The catheter urine will form a biofilm. Bacteria can enter after catheter insertion or after three days [<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Biofilm development occurs when cells (planktonic) contact with the surface of the catheter with the thin film [<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>].</p><p>Indication of catheter placement was indicated by medical and similar with previous studies [<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], [<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>] that indication of catheter placement was indicated by medical, such as orthopaedic, urology and urine incontinence. The appropriate indication can decrease catheter-associated urinary tract infection. The inappropriate indication could cause 1.86-time to decrease catheter-associated urinary tract infection [<xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>].</p><p>We found that catheter care did not have a relation with catheter-associated urinary tract infection. Because of all the number of the patient hadn&#x02019;t performed catheter care were more than the patient had performed. This finding is puzzling because it contradicts with theories of catheter urine care can decrease infection [<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>], [<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Catheter urine care is a nurse&#x02019;s duty. In this study, the nurse is more likely to do the non-nursing job so it can increase nursing workload. The survey in 2017 conducted by AMN Healthcare in California America that approximately 35% of nurses performed a non-nursing job [<xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. The relationship between catheter care and catheter-associated urinary tract infection warrants more research.</p><p>Catheter size affects the incidence of urinary tract infections in patients with catheters. Larger urine catheter sizes are used for the management of blockages or sediments. The nurses also believe that a larger catheter size prevents urine leakage. But on the other hand, a larger catheter size can irritate the bladder sphincter and aggravate leakage [<xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. A smaller catheter size recommendation is recommended [<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Small catheters can reduce trauma during insertion [<xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>].</p><p>Our study had several limitations. First, patients may have been performed catheter-associated urinary tract infection. This is suspected that the use of diapers in patients. The organism enters the urinary tract from anal or area around the perineum. Second, the error location of urine catheter fixation caused urine catheter touch with perineal area. Third, clinical specimens may have been collected incorrectly and contaminated by the organism. It can be possible to caused bias in this study.</p><p>Besides our study have a limitation, our study has an implication too. Our finding is useful as information for health workers especially nurse and for hospital staff decided hospital&#x02019;s policies in infection prevention control by considering risk factor catheter-associated urinary tract infection, namely: maintaining hand hygiene, training infection prevention control for all hospital staff, socializing the catheter-associated urinary tract infection bundle and removing catheter before seven days.</p><p>In conclusion, catheter-associated urinary tract infection can be influenced by various factors. This infection can be controlled by understanding the risk factor infection so that it can determine the right intervention to prevent infection the number of infection and increase the quality of nursing care as well. The specific nursing care is necessary from the nurse for a patient who has inserted a urine catheter with diabetes mellitus and duration of catheterisation for five days or more. Future research is needed to clarify the relationship between drainage system, catheter care, and catheter-associated urinary tract infection.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgement</title><p>The author, thanks to Prof.DR.Runtung Sitepu as a Rector of Universitas Sumatera Utara, Setiawan, BSN., MNS., PhD as a Dean of Nursing Universitas Sumatera Utara, Dr.dr.Syah Mirsya Warli, as a Director of Universitas Sumatera Utara Hospital who has permitted to do research and Dr R. Lia Kusumawati, MSc, PhD. (clinical microbiologist) for supporting this research.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="supported-by"><p><bold>Funding:</bold> This research did not receive any financial support</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Competing Interests:</bold> The authors have declared that no competing interests exist</p></fn></fn-group><sec id="sec1-5"><title>Authors Contribution</title><p>Hariati conceived and carried out the research and wrote the manuscript. Dewi Elizadiani Suza and Rosina Tarigan reviewed the research process, design and results analysis of research.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>K&#x000f6;ves</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagenlehner</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tenke</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Cek</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartoletti</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Global Prevalence of Infections in Urology Study:A Long-Term, Worldwide Surveillance Study on Urological Infections</article-title><source>Pathogens</source><year>2016</year><volume>5</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>10</fpage><comment>https://doi.org/10.3390/pathogens5010010 PMid:26797640 PMCid:PMC4810131</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Center Disease Control, Ncezid, DHQP</article-title><source>Urinary Tract Infection (Catheter-Associated Urinary Tract Infection [CAUTI] and Non-Catheter-Associated Urinary Tract Infection [UTI]) and Other Urinary System Infection [USI]) Events</source><year>2019</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>17</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Editor</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Aviles</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Preventing Catheter-Associated Urinary Tract Infections</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2016</year><volume>375</volume><issue>13</issue><fpage>1297</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><comment>https://doi.org/10.1056/NEJMc1609988</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>KEMENKES</collab><article-title>Profil Kesehatan Indonesia (Demografi)</article-title><source>Kementerian Kesehatan Republik Indonesia</source><year>2015</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Letica-kriegel</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Salmasian</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Vawdrey</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Youngerman</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Furuya</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identifying the risk factors for catheter-associated urinary tract infections:a large cross-sectional study of six hospitals</article-title><source>BMJ Open</source><year>2019</year><volume>9</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><comment>https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjopen-2018-022137 PMid:30796114 PMCid:PMC6398917</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nicolle</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Infections associated with urinary catheters</article-title><source>Clin Infect Dis Second Ed</source><year>2015</year><fpage>722</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><comment>https://doi.org/10.1017/CBO9781139855952.122</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hollenbeak</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Schilling</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The attributable cost of catheter-associated urinary tract infections in the United States:A systematic review</article-title><source>Am J Infect Control</source><year>2018</year><volume>46</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>751</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><comment>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ajic.2018.01.015 PMid:2947&#x02238;</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29478760</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Conway</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Larson</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Risk factor for nosocomial bacteremia secondary to urinary catheter-associated bacteriuria</article-title><source>Am J Crit Care</source><year>2016</year><volume>26</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><comment>https://doi.org/10.4037/ajcc2017220 PMid:27965229 PMCid:PMC5160996</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27965229</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jim&#x000e9;nez-alcaide</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Medina-polo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a-gonz&#x000e1;lez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Arr&#x000e9;bola-pajares</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Healthcare-associated urinary tract infections in patients with a urinary catheter:Risk factor, microbiological characteristic, and patterns of antibiotic resistance</article-title><source>Arch Esp Urol</source><year>2015</year><volume>68</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>541</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26179791</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vincitorio</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbadoro</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Pennacchietti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Pellegrini</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>David</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ponzio</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Risk factors for catheter-associated urinary tract infection in Italian elderly</article-title><source>Am J Infect Control [Internet]</source><year>2014</year><volume>42</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>898</fpage><lpage>901</lpage><comment>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ajic.2014.05.006 PMid:250&#x0220a;2</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hagerty</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kertesz</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Agarwal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Claassen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayer</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Risk Factors for Catheter-Associated Urinary Tract Infections in Critically Ill Patients With Subarachnoid Hemorrhage</article-title><source>J Neurosci Nurs</source><year>2015</year><volume>47</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>2013</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><comment>https://doi.org/10.1097/JNN.0000000000000111 PMid:25503544</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hariati</surname><given-names>Suza DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Tarigan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A Systematic Review;Urinary Tract Infection Caused the Catheter Used:Risk Factor</article-title><source>Proceeding. International Health Environment Technology Caring Science Conference</source><year>2018</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multistate point-prevalence survey of health care-associated infection</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>2015</year><volume>370</volume><issue>13</issue><fpage>1198</fpage><lpage>208</lpage><comment>https://doi.org/10.1056/NEJMoa1306801 PMid:24670166 PMCid:PMC4648343</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guidance</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Instructions</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identifying Healthcare-associated Infections (HAI) for NHSN Surveillance</article-title><year>2018</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>26</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sugishita</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwamoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Risk factors for nursing- and healthcare-associated urinary tract infection</article-title><source>Geriatr Gerontol Int</source><year>2018</year><volume>18</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><comment>https://doi.org/10.1111/ggi.13438 PMid:29770546</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reisner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Maierl</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>J&#x000f6;rger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Krause</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Haid</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Type 1 Fimbriae Contribute to Catheter-Associated Urinary Tract Infections Caused by Escherichia coli</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>2014</year><volume>196</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>931</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><comment>https://doi.org/10.1128/JB.00985-13 PMid:24336940 PMCid:PMC3957706</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24336940</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhardwaj</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Susceptibility of Urinary Tract Bacteria to Newer Antimicrobial Drugs</article-title><source>Open Acess Maced J Med Sci</source><year>2016</year><volume>4</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>22</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><comment>https://doi.org/10.3889/oamjms.2016.020 PMid:27275323 PMCid:PMC4884245</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Potter</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fundamental of Nurses</article-title><year>2013</year><fpage>2</fpage><lpage>5</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sohn</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Ha</surname><given-names>U-S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoon B</surname><given-names>Il</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>Y-H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Factors That Affect Nosocomial Catheter-Associated Urinary Tract Infection in Intensive Care Units:2-Year Experience at a Single Center</article-title><source>Korean J Urol</source><year>2013</year><volume>54</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>59</fpage><comment>https://doi.org/10.4111/kju.2013.54.1.59 PMid:23362450 PMCid:PMC3556556</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23362450</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Whiteside</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Razvi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Dave</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeremy</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The microbiome of the urinary tract - a role beyond infection</article-title><source>Nat Publ Gr</source><year>2015</year><volume>12</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>90</lpage><comment>https://doi.org/10.1038/nrurol.2014.361 PMid:25600098</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mohammadzadeh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Behnaz</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Incidence and risk factors of catheter-associated urinary tract infection in Yazd - Iran</article-title><source>Int J Urol Nurs</source><year>2012</year><volume>6</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>60</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><comment>https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1749-771X.2011.01133.x</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ventura</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Casciaro</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gangemi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Buquicchio</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immunosenescence in aging:between immune cells depletion and cytokines up-regulation</article-title><source>Clin Mol Allergy</source><year>2017</year><fpage>1-8</fpage><comment>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12948-017-0077-0 PMid:29259496 PMCid:PMC5731094</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28096738</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gillen</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Isbell</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Michaels</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Sawyer</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Risk Factors for Urinary Tract Infections in Cardiac Surgical Patients</article-title><source>Surgical Infection</source><year>2015</year><volume>16</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>504</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><comment>https://doi.org/10.1089/sur.2013.115 PMid:26115336 PMCid:PMC4593882</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nitzan</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Elias</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chazan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Saliba</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Urinary tract infections in patients with type 2 diabetes mellitus:a review of prevalence, diagnosis, and management</article-title><source>Diabetes Metab Syndr Obes</source><year>2015</year><fpage>129</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><comment>https://doi.org/10.2147/DMSO.S51792 PMid:25759592 PMCid:PMC4346284</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25759592</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Al-Rubean</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Moharram</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Naqeb</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hassan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rafiullah</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of urinary tract infection and risk factors among Saudi patients with diabetes</article-title><source>World J Urol</source><year>2013</year><volume>31</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>573</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><comment>https://doi.org/10.1007/s00345-012-0934-x PMid:22956119</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22956119</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Frandsen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Kozier&#x00026;Erb's</article-title><source>Fundamental of Nursing:Concepts, Process, and Practice</source><year>2016</year><fpage>1542</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuzmanovska</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Risteski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kambovska</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Trpcevski</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sahpazova</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Petrovski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Voiding urosonography with Second-Generation Ultrasound Contrast Agent for Diagnosis of Vesicoureteric Reflux:First Local Pilot Study</article-title><source>Open Acess Maced J Med Sci</source><year>2017</year><volume>5</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>215</fpage><lpage>221</lpage><comment>https://doi.org/10.3889/oamjms.2017.055 PMid:28507631 PMCid:PMC5420777</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dawa</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kever</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name><surname>Dathini</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Babaji</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Garba</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessment Of Risk Factors Influencing The Development Of Urinary Tract Infections Among Catheterized Patients In University Of Maiduguri Teaching Hospital (Umth)</article-title><source>IOSR J Nurs Heal Sci</source><year>2014</year><volume>3</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>64</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><comment>https://doi.org/10.9790/1959-03416471</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Naik</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ts</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Etiology and risk factors of catheter-associated urinary tract infections in ICU patients</article-title><year>2017</year><volume>3</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>65</fpage><lpage>70</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Al-Hazmi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of duration of catheterization and length of hospital stay on the rate of catheter-related hospital-acquired urinary tract infections</article-title><source>Res Reports Urol</source><year>2015</year><volume>25</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><comment>https://doi.org/10.2147/RRU.S75419 PMid:25848551 PMCid:PMC4378875</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chenoweth</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Saint</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Preventing Catheter-Associated Urinary Tract Infections in the Intensive Care Unit</article-title><source>Crit Care Clin</source><year>2013</year><volume>29</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><comment>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ccc.2012.10.005 PMid:23182525</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23182525</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nicolle</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Catheter-associated urinary tract infections</article-title><source>Antimicrob Resist Infect Control</source><year>2014</year><volume>23</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><comment>https://doi.org/10.1186/2047-2994-3-23 PMid:25075308 PMCid:PMC4114799</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><source>Association for Professionals in Infection Control and Epidemiology State of the Association June 2014 2014 APIC Officers and Board of Directors</source><year>2014</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Giles</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Suthers</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Watts</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Brien</surname><given-names>TO</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Avoiding inappropriate urinary catheter use and catheter-associated urinary tract infection (CAUTI):a pre-post control intervention study</article-title><source>BMC Health Serv Res</source><year>2017</year><volume>17</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><comment>https://doi.org/10.1186/s12913-017-2268-2 PMid:28464815 PMCid:PMC5414128</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28049468</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sugimoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Makimoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujino</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyazaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaneda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujiwara</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Relationship between catheter care and catheter-associated urinary tract infection at Japanese general hospitals:A prospective observational study</article-title><source>Int J Nurs Stud</source><year>2006</year><volume>45</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>352</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><comment>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijnurstu.2006.10.006 PMid:17173921</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17173921</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><collab>AMN Healthcare</collab><source>Survey of registered nurses</source><year>2017</year><comment>Available from: <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.amnhealthcare.com/uploadedFiles/MainSite/Content/Campaigns/AMN%20Healthcare%202017%20RN%20Survey%20-%20Full%20Report.pdf">https://www.amnhealthcare.com/uploadedFiles/MainSite/Content/Campaigns/AMN%20Healthcare%202017%20RN%20Survey%20-%20Full%20Report.pdf</uri></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilde</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>McMahon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Crean</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Brasch</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exploring Relationships of Catheter Associated Urinary Tract Infection and Blockage in People with Long-Term Indweling Urinary Catheters</article-title><source>J Clin Nurs</source><year>2017</year><volume>26</volume><issue>17-18</issue><fpage>2558</fpage><lpage>2571</lpage><comment>https://doi.org/10.1111/jocn.13626 PMid:27805758 PMCid:PMC5413425</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27805758</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cottenden</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bliss</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Buckley</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Fader</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gartley</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Management Using Continence Products</article-title><source>Incontinence:5th International Consultation on Incontinence</source><year>2013</year><publisher-loc>Arnheim, The Netherlands</publisher-loc><publisher-name>ICUD-EAU Publisher</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Connor</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><source>Reducing Catheter-Associated Urinary Tract Infection</source><year>2018</year><comment>Available from: <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.americannursetoday.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/02/ANT_BestPractices_CautiPrevention.pdf">https://www.americannursetoday.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/02/ANT_BestPractices_CautiPrevention.pdf</uri></comment></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>