<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Heliyon</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Heliyon</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Heliyon</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2405-8440</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31938742</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6953639</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S2405-8440(19)36704-0</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.heliyon.2019.e03045</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e03045</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Concurrent nicotine exposure to prenatal alcohol consumption alters the hippocampal and cortical neurotoxicity</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name><surname>Bhattacharya</surname><given-names>Dwipayan</given-names></name><xref rid="PC_affjLLjqcVYzg" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name><surname>Fujihashi</surname><given-names>Ayaka</given-names></name><xref rid="PC_affjLLjqcVYzg" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3"><name><surname>Majrashi</surname><given-names>Mohammed</given-names></name><xref rid="PC_affjLLjqcVYzg" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="PC_affEBMzxfR3v7" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4"><name><surname>Bloemer</surname><given-names>Jenna</given-names></name><xref rid="PC_affjLLjqcVYzg" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au5"><name><surname>Bhattacharya</surname><given-names>Subhrajit</given-names></name><xref rid="PC_affjLLjqcVYzg" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au6"><name><surname>Buabeid</surname><given-names>Manal</given-names></name><xref rid="PC_affjLLjqcVYzg" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au7"><name><surname>Escobar</surname><given-names>Martha</given-names></name><xref rid="PC_aff1HjZr6ufY7" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au8"><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>Timothy</given-names></name><xref rid="PC_affjLLjqcVYzg" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au9"><name><surname>Suppiramaniam</surname><given-names>Vishnu</given-names></name><xref rid="PC_affjLLjqcVYzg" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au10"><name><surname>Dhanasekaran</surname><given-names>Muralikrishnan</given-names></name><email>dhanamu@auburn.edu</email><xref rid="PC_affjLLjqcVYzg" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#x02217;</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="PC_affjLLjqcVYzg"><label>a</label>Department of Drug Discovery and Development, Harrison School of Pharmacy, Auburn University, Auburn, AL, 36849, USA</aff><aff id="PC_affEBMzxfR3v7"><label>b</label>Department of Pharmacology, Faculty of Medicine, University of Jeddah, Jeddah, 23881, Saudi Arabia</aff><aff id="PC_aff1HjZr6ufY7"><label>c</label>Department of Psychology, Auburn University, Auburn, Alabama, United States of America</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x02217;</label>Corresponding author. <email>dhanamu@auburn.edu</email></corresp><fn id="fn1"><label>1</label><p id="ntpara0010">Equal Contributions.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>08</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>1</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>08</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>e03045</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>1</day><month>7</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>2</day><month>8</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>12</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2019 The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><license license-type="CC BY" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="abs0010"><sec><title>Aims</title><p>This study investigated the neurotoxic effects of prenatal alcohol and nicotine exposure in the cortex and hippocampus of rodents.</p></sec><sec><title>Main methods</title><p>Behavioral alterations, electrophysiological changes, and biochemical markers associated with cholinergic neurotransmission, neural oxidative stress, mitochondrial function, and apoptosis were evaluated.</p></sec><sec><title>Key findings</title><p>Prenatal alcohol exposure induced the generation of ROS, nitrite and lipid peroxide, decreased mitochondrial Complex-I and IV activities, increased Caspase-1 and 3 activities, had no effect on cholinergic neurotransmission, increased expression of PSD-95, decreased LTP and decreased performance on spatial memory tasks. However, nicotine exposure, in addition to alcohol exposure, was found to mitigate the negative effects of alcohol alone on ROS generation and spatial memory task performances. Furthermore, we also studied the role of ILK in prenatal alcohol and nicotine exposure.</p></sec><sec><title>Significance</title><p>Prenatal Smoking and/or drinking is a major health concern around the world. Thus, our current study may lead to better insights into the molecular mechanisms of fetal alcohol and nicotine exposure on the developing offspring.</p></sec></abstract><abstract abstract-type="teaser" id="abs0015"><p>Neuroscience; Aging; Mitochondrial function; Oxidative stress</p></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Neuroscience</kwd><kwd>Aging</kwd><kwd>Mitochondrial function</kwd><kwd>Oxidative stress</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0010">A growing concern in developed countries is drinking during pregnancy. A large number of women (around 15%) have admitted to have consumed alcohol at some stage of their pregnancy. A significant number of such women are heavy drinkers [<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. It is well known that drinking during pregnancy can damage the central nervous system (CNS) in the developing offspring impairing developmental and cognitive enrichments. Prenatal alcohol exposure can therefore cause some serious developmental problems collectively known as Fetal Alcohol Spectrum Disorders (FASD) [<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Alcohol is a serious teratogen that can cause problems associated with the CNS, such as hyperactivity, poor movement coordination and muscle control, lower than average IQ, and cognitive deficits [<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Some of these effects have been attributed to neuronal dysfunction in various regions of the brain of the offspring notably the hippocampus [<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], and children with FASD experience difficulty in spatial and memory tasks [<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Many animal models were used to study the effect of prenatal alcohol on overall brain development and memory. There was a significant reduction (20%) in the number of dorsal hippocampal neurons and long-term potentiation (LTP) in FASD rodent model. Like women consuming alcohol during pregnancy, there is a significant proportion of women (20&#x02013;25%) who smoke nicotine during pregnancy [<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Prenatal nicotine exposure augments the risk of sudden infant death syndrome (SIDS), low birthweight, and ectopic pregnancy [<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Epidemiological reports indicate children exposed to nicotine during development have similar cognitive and behavioral problems as prenatal alcohol expsoure. The behavioral problems are hyperactivity and impulsivity, impaired learning and memory, and lower IQ. With respect to neuroanatomy, nicotine exposure during pregnancy leads to reduced cortical thickness and cell packing density, as well as altered neuronal morphology [<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Clinical and experimental trials have indicated a strong association between nicotine and alcohol use [<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], pointing to their concurrent usage. Thus, it appears that a significant population of women who consumes both these teratogens during pregnancy, yet a few clinical data exist on the cumulative effects of alcohol and nicotine on developing offspring [<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. As such, the interactive role of prenatal alcohol and nicotine on fetal brain development is not well understood. Some studies have shown deleterious effect of prenatal alcohol and nicotine on developing brain growth spurt and neuroanatomical organization of the brain [<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. In this study, we assessed the effect of prenatal alcohol and nicotine on neuronal stress, underlying signaling mechanisms and behavior in rat model. We specifically focused on the cortex and hippocampus of the during postnatal days of the offspring. The study was aimed to understand the effect of oxidative stress in these brain regions and their effect on synaptic receptor expression and electrophysiological output. Our previous reports identified Integrin Linked Kinase (ILK) as a potential signaling molecule that can alter synaptic receptor expression and Long Term Potentiation in FASD rat model [<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. We also looked into some of these mechanisms in the present alcohol + nicotine model.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><label>2</label><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="sec2.1"><label>2.1</label><title>Animals</title><p id="p0015">Auburn University Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee's (IACUC) approval was obtained for this study. Sprague Dawley (Time pregnant) rats were purchased from Charles River Laboratories (Wilmington, MA) and under isoflurane anesthesia the osmotic mini pumps (Alzet, Cupertino, CA) were implanted to deliver subcutaneous nicotine as per the previous study [<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>].</p><p id="p0020">The various groups used in this study:<list list-type="simple" id="olist0010"><list-item id="o0010"><label>(i)</label><p id="p0025">Control: Water was administrated orally and subcutaneous saline via mini pump</p></list-item><list-item id="o0015"><label>(ii)</label><p id="p0030">Alcohol: Alcohol (10% v/v) mixed with water was administrated orally and subcutaneous saline via mini pump</p></list-item><list-item id="o0020"><label>(iii)</label><p id="p0035">Alcohol + nicotine: Alcohol (10% v/v) mixed with water was administrated orally and subcutaneous nicotine dissolved in sterile saline was used to deliver 6 mg/kg/day via mini pump</p></list-item></list></p><p id="p0040">After birth, offsprings (5 male/group) were used to elucidate the neurotoxic effects of nicotine in prenatal alcohol exposure in the cortex and hippocampus. The offspring were sacrificed six weeks postnatally. The doses for the present study was based on our publication [<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] and other previous studies [<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. The dams consumed around 20 ml of alcohol solution (equivalent to 6 g/kg/day) which is comparable to 1&#x02013;2 drinks per day for a human adult [<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. The consumption rate of 6 mg/kg/day is the most commonly studied dose for prenatal nicotine exposure in rats. This is thought to give plasma levels comparable to moderate to heavy smokers [<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Alcohol was administered during dark cycle, because the animals are more active during this period, but was replaced with water during the light cycle to prevent dehydration. Food was administered ad libitum. The pumps were removed immediately after birth. Animals were housed at 12 h:12 h light:dark cycle (lights on at 6:00 am) and at a temperature of 22&#x02013;24 &#x000b0;C. Pregnant dams were housed individually where as the pups were housed three per cage. Carbon dioxide based euthanasia was used in the current study.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><label>2.2</label><title>Chemicals</title><p id="p0045">Chemicals were purchased from Sigma (St. Louis, MO).</p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><label>2.3</label><title>Biochemical studies</title><p id="p0050">To avoid diurnal variations of biogenic molecules (endogenous amines, enzymes, and other antioxidant molecules), control, alcohol, and alcohol + nicotine exposed animals were sacrificed in the morning. The cortex and hippocampus was dissected out, immediately flash frozen in liquid nitrogen, and stored at &#x02212; 80 &#x000b0;C. The cortical homogenate for the biochemical tests was prepared by homogenizing the tissue in 0.1 M phosphate buffer (pH 7.8), using a glass-Teflon homogenizer, followed by centrifugation at 10,000<italic>g</italic> for 60 min at 4 &#x000b0;C and the supernatant was isolated [<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec2.4"><label>2.4</label><title>Assessment of reactive oxygen species (ROS)</title><p id="p0055">Generation of reactive oxygen species (ROS): Spectrofluorometric method was used to determine ROS in the cortex of the control, alcohol and alcohol + nicotine treated animals. The ROS generated was measured at 492 nm (excitation) and 527 nm (emission). ROS (fluorescence units) measured was normalized to total protein content as relative fluorescence intensity/mg protein. The results are expressed as (%) change as compared to the control [<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec2.5"><label>2.5</label><title>Nitrite content</title><p id="p0060">Nitrite content in the control, alcohol, and alcohol + nicotine treated rats were measured using Griess reagent at 545 nm [<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec2.6"><label>2.6</label><title>Assessment of lipid peroxidation</title><p id="p0065">Spectrophotometric method using thiobarbituric acid was used to assess lipid peroxidation in the cortex of the control, alcohol, and alcohol + nicotine treated animals. Lipid peroxidation was estimated by the formation of thiobarbituric acid-reactive substances (TBARS) at 532 nm. TBARS was normalized to total protein content as TBARS formed/mg protein. The results are expressed as (%) change as compared to the control [<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec2.7"><label>2.7</label><title>Glutathione (GSH) content quantification</title><p id="p0070">Spectrofluorometric method (327 nm excitation and 423 nm emission) was used to determine GSH using o-phthalaldehyde (OPT). GSH measured was normalized to total protein content and reported as relative GSH content (&#x003bc;M)/mg protein [<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec2.8"><label>2.8</label><title>Glutathione peroxidase activity</title><p id="p0075">Spectrophotometric method was used to measure glutathione peroxidase activity in the cortex of the control, alcohol and alcohol + nicotine treated animals. The glutathione peroxidase activity was expressed as NADPH oxidized/mg total protein [<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec2.9"><label>2.9</label><title>Superoxide dismutase activity (SOD)</title><p id="p0080">Spectrophotometric method using pyrogallol was used to measure superoxide dismutase activity in the cortex of the control, alcohol, and alcohol + nicotine treated animals. The superoxide dismutase activity refers to inhibition of pyrogallol autoxidation/mg total protein [<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec2.10"><label>2.10</label><title>Catalase activity</title><p id="p0085">Spectrophotometric method using hydrogen peroxide as a substrate was used to measure catalase activity (240 nm) in the cortex of the control, alcohol, and alcohol + nicotine treated animals. The catalase activity refers to hydrogen peroxide oxidized/mg total protein [<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec2.11"><label>2.11</label><title>Monoamine oxidase (MAO) activity</title><p id="p0090">Spectrofluorometric method using kynuramine as a substrate was used to measure MAO activity (315 nm excitation and 380 nm emission) in the cortex of the control, alcohol and alcohol + nicotine treated animals. MAO activity refers to 4-hydroxy quinolone (&#x003bc;M)/formed/mg protein [<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec2.12"><label>2.12</label><title>Complex-I activity</title><p id="p0095">Spectrophotometric method using NADH as a substrate was used to measure Complex-I activity (340 nm) in the cortex of the control, alcohol and alcohol + nicotine treated animals. The Complex-I activity refers to NADH oxidized/mg protein [<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec2.13"><label>2.13</label><title>Complex-IV activity</title><p id="p0100">Spectrophotometric method using cytochrome <italic>c</italic> as a substrate was used to measure Complex-IV activity (550 nm) in the cortex of the control, alcohol and alcohol + nicotine treated animals. The Complex-IV activity refers to cytochrome <italic>c</italic> oxidized/mg protein [<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec2.14"><label>2.14</label><title>Caspase-1 activity</title><p id="p0105">Spectrofluorometric method using Ac-Tyr-Val-Ala-Asp-7-amino-4-Trifluoromethlcoumarin (Ac-YVAD-AMC) as a substrate was used to measure Caspase-1 (3260nm excitation and 460nm emission) activity (in the cortex of the Control, alcohol and alcohol + nicotine treated animals. The catalase activity refers to free AMC/mg total protein [<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec2.15"><label>2.15</label><title>Caspase-3 activity</title><p id="p0110">Spectrofluorometric method using N-Acetyl-Asp-Glu-Val-Asp-7-amido-4-Methylcoumarin (Ac-DEVD-AMC) as a substrate was used to measure Caspase-3 (3260nm excitation and 460nm emission) activity in the cortex of the Control, alcohol and alcohol + nicotine treated animals. The catalase activity refers to free AMC/mg total protein [<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec2.16"><label>2.16</label><title>Choline acetyltransferase (ChAT) activity</title><p id="p0115">Spectrophotometric method using choline chloride as a substrate was used to measure choline acetyltransferase activity (324nm) in the cortex of the control, alcohol and alcohol + nicotine treated animals. The ChAT activity refers to amount of 4-thiopyridone formed/mg protein. 4-thiopyridone (4-TP) is the product formed when reduced CoA reacts with 4,4&#x02032;-dithiopyrdine (4-PDS) [<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec2.17"><label>2.17</label><title>Acetylcholinesterase (AChE) activity</title><p id="p0120">Spectrophotometric method using acetylthiocholine and 5,5&#x02032;-dithio-bis-2-nitrobenzoic acid (DTNB) as substrates was used to measure acetylcholinesterase activity (412nm) in the cortex of the control, alcohol and alcohol + nicotine treated animals. The AChE activity refers to the amount of 5-thio-2-nitrobenzoate formed/mg protein. 5-thio-2-nitrobenzoate is the product formed when thiocholine&#x02014;the product of the breakdown of acetylcholine&#x02014;reacts with DTNB [<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec2.18"><label>2.18</label><title>Western blot analysis</title><p id="p0125">Total protein was isolated using cell lysis buffer (Cell Signaling Technology, Inc., Danvers, MA) containing protease inhibitor cocktail (P8340, Sigma, St. Louis, MO) and phosphatase inhibitors (P 5726, Sigma, St. Louis, MO). The expression of ILK was assessed using 1:1000 anti-ILK antibody (Cell Signaling)<bold>.</bold> &#x003b2;&#x02013;actin was used as a loading control and was estimated using 1:1000 anti-&#x003b2;-actin antibody (Cell Signaling). 1:10000 anti-rabbit IgG, HRP-linked antibody was used as secondary antibody (Cell signaling). Band intensity was calculated by densitometric analysis using AlphaView software, normalized to &#x003b2;-actin, and reported as percentage change from the control. Protein concentration was measured using the Thermo Scientific Pierce 660 nm Protein Assay reagent kit (Pierce, Rockford, IL).</p></sec><sec id="sec2.19"><label>2.19</label><title>Immunoprecipitation</title><p id="p0130">The brains from individual group of animals were pooled and PSD95 in addition to GluR2 were immunoprecipitated using 1:10 anti-PSD95 and anti- GluR2 antibodies respectively (Santa-Cruz) coated on Pure-Proteome A/G magnetic beads according to the manufacturer's protocol (Millipore). The beads containing the immunoprecipitated fraction was washed several times with 1X IMP buffer, pH = 7.4. Finally, 50ul of Laemmle buffer was added to the beads and boiled at 70 &#x000b0;C and proteins were detected using Western blot analysis.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.20"><label>2.20</label><title>Electrophysiology field recordings</title><p id="p0135">Brains were isolated from euthanized rats and placed in ice-cold dissection solution containing (in mM) 120 NaCl, 11 D-Glucose, 26 NaHCO3, 6 MgCl2, 3 KCl, 0.5 CaCl2, 5 HEPES and 0.3 kynurenic acid. Coronal slices (350 uM) were made with a Leica VT-1200S. The slices were then transferred to artificial cerebrospinal fluid (aCSF, in mM 124 NaCl, 3 KCl, 1.5 MgSO47H20, 1.2 NaH2PO4, 2.4 CaCl2, 26 NaHCO3, and 10 D-Glucose bubbled with 95%CO2/5%O2) for at least 1 h and then maintained at room temperature until recording Electrophysiological recordings were performed as previously described (Bhattacharya 2015). Briefly, recordings were performed in a submerged chamber with continuous perfusion with aCSF (2&#x02013;3 ml/min) bubbled with 95%CO2/5%O2 carbogen. fEPSPs were recorded from Schaffer collateral pathway SC-CA1 synapses with a glass pipette filled with aCSF (2&#x02013;4MO). Stimulating pulses were applied at Schaffer collaterals via a bipolar stimulating electrode positioned 300 &#x003bc;m closer to CA3 subfield than the recording electrode. For LTP experiments, baseline was recorded at 50% of amplitude at which the initial population spike appeared. LTP was induced after 15 min of stable baseline recording using a Theta Burst Stimulation protocol (TBS), and recording was continued for 60 min post TBS. All electrophysiological data are presented as means &#x000b1; SEM.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.21"><label>2.21</label><title>Behavior: Y maze</title><p id="p0140">All animals were approximately 4 weeks old at the time of initiation of the study and there were no significant difference in the weight of the animals between each group (average weight was 57.8 g). Subjects were released into the Start arm and allowed to explore the Start and Other arm for 15 min, upon which time they were removed from the maze and returned to their home cages. Three hours later, all animals were returned to the maze and allowed to explore all three arms for 6 min. All scores were obtained from at least two independent, blinded observers. The following variables were recorded: (1) number of entries into each arm, and (2) dwell time into each arm. Measures for the Start and Other arm were averaged for all variables, and they will be referred as the Familiar arms. Dwell time was analyzed by contrasting the proportion of the total time spent in the maze's arms that subjects spent in the Novel and Familiar arms; these measures reflect exploratory behavior.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.22"><label>2.22</label><title>Contextual fear conditioning</title><p id="p0145">Contextual fear conditioning was performed based on our previous publication on FASD [<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec2.23"><label>2.23</label><title>other behavioral studies</title><p id="p0150">Control, alcohol and alcohol + nicotine treated rats were observed by trained examiners. Straub tail, tremor and ataxic behaviors were monitored [<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec2.24"><label>2.24</label><title>Protein quantification</title><p id="p0155">Protein was quantified using Protein Assay reagent kit (Thermo Scientific Pierce 660 nm, Pierce, Rockford, IL). Bovine serum albumin (BSA) was used as a standard for protein measurement.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.25"><label>2.25</label><title>Statistical analysis</title><p id="p0160">The results are presented as means &#x000b1; SEM. Statistics were performed using the Prism-V software (La Jolla, CA, USA). The experimental data were analyzed using one-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) followed by Dunnet's multiple comparisons test. Statistical differences were considered significant at <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05. Note (*) indicates a statistically significant difference when compared to controls.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><p id="p0165">Alcohol and alcohol + nicotine exposure increased the generation of ROS significantly in the cortex compared to the control (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;1</xref>a, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05). Likewise, nitrite content significantly increased in the cortex after exposure to alcohol and alcohol + nicotine as compared to the control (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;1</xref>b, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05). Due to the increase in the generation of ROS and increased nitrite content, alcohol and alcohol + nicotine exposure significantly increased lipid peroxidation as compared to the control (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;1</xref>c, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05). There was no significant effect on glutathione content (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;1</xref>d). With regard to the other antioxidant enzymes such as glutathione peroxidase, superoxide dismutase and catalase, prenatal exposure to alcohol and alcohol + nicotine did not affect the glutathione peroxidase (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;1</xref>e), but there was a significant decrease in superoxide dismutase activity of both experimental groups compared to the control (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;1</xref>f). There was no significant difference in the catalase activity among the groups (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;1</xref>g). Prenatal exposure to alcohol and alcohol + nicotine significantly increased the monoamine oxidase activity as compared to the control (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;1</xref>h).<fig id="fig1"><label>Figure&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>a: Effect of alcohol and alcohol + nicotine treatment on rat cortex reactive oxygen species generation: Reactive oxygen species was measured spectrofluorimetrically. Alcohol and alcohol + nicotine showed a significant increase in reactive oxygen species generation as compared to the control (*<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, n = 3). Reactive oxygen species generation was measured as relative fluorescence units (492/527 nm)/mg. Results are expressed as (%) change as compared to the control, Mean &#x000b1; SEM. b: Effect of alcohol and alcohol + nicotine treatment on rat cortex nitrite content: Nitrite content was measured spectrophotometrically. Alcohol and alcohol + nicotine showed a significant increase in nitrite content as compared to the control (*<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, n = 5). Results are expressed as (%) change as compared to the control, Mean &#x000b1; SEM. c: Effect of alcohol and alcohol + nicotine treatment on rat cortex lipid peroxide formation: Lipid peroxide was measured spectrophotometrically as thiobarbituric acid reactive substances (TBARS). Due to the increased reactive oxygen species generation and Nitrite content of alcohol and alcohol + nicotine induced a significant formation of lipid peroxide (*<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, n = 5). Lipid peroxide formation was measured as TBARS formed (532 nm)/mg protein. Results are expressed as (%) change as compared to the control &#x000b1;SEM. d: Effect of alcohol and alcohol + nicotine treatment on rat cortex glutathione content: Glutathione content was measured spectrophotometrically. Alcohol and alcohol + nicotine had no significant effect on GSH content (n = 5). Results are expressed as (%) change as compared to the control, Mean &#x000b1; SEM. e: Effect of alcohol and alcohol + nicotine treatment on rat cortex glutathione peroxidase activity: Glutathione peroxidase activity was measured spectrophotometrically using NADPH as substrate. Alcohol and alcohol + nicotine had no significant effect on glutathione peroxidase activity (n = 5). Results are expressed as (%) change as compared to the control, Mean &#x000b1; SEM. f: Effect of alcohol and alcohol + nicotine treatment on rat cortex superoxide dismutase activity: Superoxide dismutase activity was measured colorimetrically using pyrogallol as a substrate. Alcohol and alcohol + nicotine showed a significant reduction in superoxide dismutase activity (*<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, n = 5). Results are expressed as (%) change as compared to the control, Mean &#x000b1; SEM. g: Effect of alcohol and alcohol + nicotine treatment on rat cortex catalase activity: Catalase activity was measured spectrophotometrically using hydrogen peroxide as substrate. Alcohol and alcohol + nicotine had no significant effect on catalase activity (n = 5). Results are expressed as (%) change as compared to the control, Mean &#x000b1; SEM. h: Effect of alcohol and alcohol + nicotine treatment on rat cortex monoamine oxidase activity: Monoamine oxidase activity was measured spectrofluorimetrically using kynuramine as substrate. Alcohol and alcohol + nicotine significantly increased monoamine oxidase activity (*<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, n = 5). Results are expressed as (%) change as compared to the control, Mean &#x000b1; SEM.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0015">Figure&#x000a0;1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig></p><p id="p0170">With reference to the mitochondrial functions, prenatal exposure to alcohol and alcohol + nicotine caused significant deficits in both Complex-I and Complex-IV activity compared to the control (Figures&#x000a0;<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a, 2b). Alcohol exposure caused a significant increase in both Caspase-1 and Caspase-3 activity as compared to the control. Alcohol + nicotine caused a significant increase in Caspase-3 activity only as compared to control (Figures&#x000a0;<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a, 3b). There was no significant change in the acetylcholinesterase activity among the three groups (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;4</xref>a). Similarly, the three groups did not have a significant change in choline acetyltransferase activity (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;4</xref>b).<fig id="fig2"><label>Figure&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>a: Effect of alcohol and alcohol + nicotine treatment on rat cortex Mitochondrial Complex-I activity: Mitochondrial Complex-I activity was measured spectrophotometrically using NADH as substrate. Alcohol and Alcohol + Nicotine showed a significant decrease in Mitochondrial Complex-I activity (*<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, n = 5). Results are expressed as (%) change as compared to the control, Mean &#x000b1; SEM. b: Effect of alcohol and alcohol + nicotine treatment on rat cortex Mitochondrial Complex-IV activity: Mitochondrial Complex-IV activity was measured colorimetrically using Cytochrome-C as substrate. Alcohol and alcohol + nicotine showed a significant decrease in Mitochondrial Complex-IV activity (*<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, n = 5. Results are expressed as (%) change as compared to the control, Mean &#x000b1; SEM.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0020">Figure&#x000a0;2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig><fig id="fig3"><label>Figure&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>a: Effect of alcohol and alcohol + nicotine treatment on rat cortex Caspase-1 activity: Caspase-1 activity was measured spectrofluorimetrically using AC-YVAD-AMC as substrate. Alcohol significantly increased Caspase-1 activity (*<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, n = 5). Results are expressed as (%) change as compared to the control, Mean &#x000b1; SEM. b: Effect of alcohol and alcohol + nicotine treatment on rat cortex Caspase-3 activity: Caspase-3 activity was measured spectrofluorimetrically using AC-DEVD-AMC as substrate. Alcohol and alcohol + nicotine significantly increased Caspase-3 activity (*<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, n = 5). Results are expressed as (%) change as compared to the control, Mean &#x000b1; SEM.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0025">Figure&#x000a0;3</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr3"/></fig><fig id="fig4"><label>Figure&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>a: Effect of alcohol and alcohol + nicotine treatment on rat cortex acetylcholinesterase activity: Acetylcholinesterase activity was measured spectrofluorimetrically. Alcohol and alcohol + nicotine had no significant effect on acetylcholinesterase activity (n = 5). Results are expressed as (%) change as compared to the control, Mean &#x000b1; SEM. b: Effect of alcohol and alcohol + nicotine treatment on rat cortex choline acetyltransferase activity: Choline acetyltransferase activity was measured spectrofluorimetrically. Alcohol and alcohol + nicotine had no significant effect on choline acetyltransferase activity (n = 5). Results are expressed as (%) change as compared to the control, Mean &#x000b1; SEM.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0030">Figure&#x000a0;4</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr4"/></fig></p><p id="p0175">The increase in ROS activity can alter the synaptic AMPA receptor expression and other synaptic proteins directly involving the mechanism of synaptic plasticity and cognitive behavior [<xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Activity dependent changes in LTP are the electrophysiological signature of changes in synaptic protein expression. We previously reported that ILK activity is involved in changes in the synaptic proteins in prenatal alcohol exposure model [<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Hence, we looked into the neurotoxic mechanisms to further evaluate the effect of alcohol + nicotine co-exposure in the prenatal model. There is no significant change in expression of ILK among the three groups (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;5</xref>a). We reported earlier that ILK function change may affect the expression of synaptic AMPA receptors. We used scaffolding protein PSD95 pull down assay to look into the expression of GluR2 in total hippocampal protein lysate. There is almost 2-fold enhanced expression of GluR2 in the alcohol + nicotine group, whereas in the alcohol only group, the increase is around 1.5-fold as compared to the control group (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;5</xref>b) suggesting an additive effect on the synaptic AMPA receptor subtype expression. Increased GluR2 can result in reduced LTP and therefore we measured the electrophysiological field recording. In the hippocampal field recordings, alcohol and alcohol + nicotine showed a reduction in long-term potentiation following theta burst stimulation compared to controls, indicating alterations in synaptic plasticity. However surprisingly, we did not observe any additive effect of the two teratogens (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;6</xref>).<fig id="fig5"><label>Figure&#x000a0;5</label><caption><p>a: Effect of alcohol and alcohol + nicotine treatment on rat hippocampal protein expression (ILK): Alcohol and alcohol + nicotine had no effect on ILK expression (n = 5). Blots were developed using 1:1000 dilution with primary antibody. &#x000e2;-Actin (1:1000) was used as a loading control. Densitometric analysis was performed with AlphaView software. Results are expressed as (%) change as compared to the control, Mean &#x000b1; SEM. b: Effect of alcohol and alcohol + nicotine treatment on rat hippocampal protein expression (GluR2 and PSD95): Prenatal alcohol and nicotine + alcohol exposure significantly increased the expression of GLuR2 (*<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, n = 5). Blots were developed using 1:1000 dilution with primary antibody. &#x000e2;-Actin (1:1000) was used as a loading control. Densitometric analysis was performed with AlphaView software and results are expressed as (%) control &#x000b1;SEM. Please see <xref rid="appsec1" ref-type="sec">supplementary</xref>section for the full blot image.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0035">Figure&#x000a0;5</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr5"/></fig><fig id="fig6"><label>Figure&#x000a0;6</label><caption><p>Effect of alcohol and alcohol + nicotine treatment on long term potentiation (LTP): Alcohol and alcohol + nicotine exposed animals showed significant deficits in LTP compared to control. However, there is no significant difference between the alcohol group and the alcohol + nicotine group.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0040">Figure&#x000a0;6</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr6"/></fig></p><p id="p0180">We further looked into the general behavioral and specialized cognitive changes in the model. A battery of alcohol withdrawal related measurements was considered to assess the impact of teratogen co-exposure [<xref rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. As expected, we did not notice any significant changes in straub tail, tremor and ataxic behaviors as compared to the controls (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;1</xref>). There was no significant difference in the number of pups per litter or body weight observed among groups. Cognitive behavior task was also assessed in our model to understand the effect of these teratogens on rodent's usual exploratory behavior using Y-maze test. It mainly tests the willingness of a rodent to explore a novel arm as compared to the familiar arm which it has explored during training. If these teratogens affect the cognitive development associated with various brain regions, we may see an additive effect for both these teratogens. Unlike LTP data, we observed no significant change in spatial recognition and memory in prenatal alcohol + nicotine exposed rats. However, the prenatal alcohol exposed rats showed significant reduction in this spatial cognitive task (<xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;7</xref>a).<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl1"><label>Table&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Effect of alcohol and alcohol + nicotine on behavioral parameters.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0050">Table&#x000a0;1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Behavioral parameters</th><th>Control</th><th>Alcohol</th><th>Alcohol + Nicotine</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Allergic reaction (redness of the Skin or eye)</td><td>N</td><td>N</td><td>N</td></tr><tr><td>Anaphylactic shock/Death</td><td>N</td><td>N</td><td>N</td></tr><tr><td>Ataxic behaviors</td><td>N</td><td>N</td><td>N</td></tr><tr><td>Diarrhea</td><td>N</td><td>N</td><td>N</td></tr><tr><td>Drooling</td><td>N</td><td>N</td><td>N</td></tr><tr><td>Fighting (aggressive Behavior)</td><td>N</td><td>N</td><td>N</td></tr><tr><td>Hair coat erection</td><td>N</td><td>N</td><td>N</td></tr><tr><td>Head twitching</td><td>N</td><td>N</td><td>N</td></tr><tr><td>Hind limb abduction</td><td>N</td><td>N</td><td>N</td></tr><tr><td>Hyperactivity (excessive Jumping)</td><td>N</td><td>N</td><td>N</td></tr><tr><td>Licking of the<break/>Genitals</td><td>N</td><td>N</td><td>N</td></tr><tr><td>Mortality observed</td><td>N</td><td>N</td><td>N</td></tr><tr><td>Penile erection (stimulatory Behavior)</td><td>N</td><td>N</td><td>N</td></tr><tr><td>Seizure</td><td>N</td><td>N</td><td>N</td></tr><tr><td>Straub tail</td><td>N</td><td>N</td><td>N</td></tr><tr><td>Tremor</td><td>N</td><td>N</td><td>N</td></tr><tr><td>Tumor</td><td>N</td><td>N</td><td>N</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig id="fig7"><label>Figure&#x000a0;7</label><caption><p>Effect of alcohol and alcohol + nicotine treatment on spatial memory tasks: Alcohol and alcohol + nicotine resulted in significant deficits in spatial memory tasks in the alcohol only treated group as compared to the control. Interestingly, the offspring exposed to prenatal nicotine and alcohol showed significant improvement in the spatial task as compared to the alcohol treatment. Bar chart shows the significant reduction in the number of entries by mice exposed to alcohol in exploring the novel arm in the Y-maze than the control mice and the alcohol + nicotine mice (*p &#x0003c; 0.05, n = 5).</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0045">Figure&#x000a0;7</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr7"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec4"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0185">Prenatal nicotine exposure has been associated with low birth weight, cognitive deficits in the offspring including low motor skills, hyperactivity, and learning disabilities and as well as an increased incidence of sudden infant death syndrome [<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Maternal smoking induces oxidative stress in the offspring, as measured using F2-isoprostanes as the primary marker [<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Mice embryo treated with nicotine exhibited an elevated Ca<sup>2+</sup> concentration that is surmised to have led to an increase in the generation of reactive oxygen species and apoptosis [<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Apoptotic effects of prenatal nicotine exposure have been supported by other studies in which nicotine exposure during pregnancy led to cell death in the midbrains and cerebral cortices of offspring [<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Prenatal nicotine exposure in Wistar rats was also found to impair mitochondrial functions as seen by significantly reduced Complex-IV activity [<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>].</p><p id="p0190">Interestingly, similar developmental problems and toxic effects can be observed in prenatal alcohol exposure. Behavioral problems, such as aggression and poor social communication skills, deficits in intellectual functioning, namely, in short-term memory and encoding, reading &#x00026; math skills, and overall mental processing can be observed in children prenatally exposed to alcohol. Human fetal brain cells have cytochrome P450 2E1, an enzyme that metabolizes alcohol into hydroxyl radicals that can further increase the generation of reactive oxygen species. Similarly, alcohol exposure during gestation in rodents has been shown to increase levels of oxidative stress in all organs, though the developing brain is most susceptible to oxidative stress-induced damage due to its high oxygen metabolic rate [<xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Indeed, this generation of free radicals also affects mitochondrial functioning leading to reduced expression of Complex IV genes and ATP generation [<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Alcohol exposure also increases caspase-3 activity and increased expression of pro-apoptotic genes leading to programmed cell death [<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>].</p><p id="p0195">Despite the mounting evidence on the harmful effects of alcohol and nicotine, some studies support the contrary. In fact, nicotine and its structural analogues have especially been of great interest as a potential therapeutic substance in treating Parkinson's disease [<xref rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. In rat models of Parkinson's disease, nicotine infusions via a subcutaneous mini-osmotic pump stimulated the release of dopamine, leading to partial preservation of nigral dopamine neurons [<xref rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Indeed, epidemiological studies have found correlations between smoking and a lower incidence of Parkinson's disease [<xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. Cigarette smoke exposure has also been found to mitigate the effects of MPTP [<xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Nicotine primarily acts on the nicotinic acetylcholine receptor (nAChRs), which can mediate protection against toxicity caused by glutamate, amyloid-&#x003b2;, and ethanol. Nicotine also exhibits antioxidant activity and reduces lipid peroxidation provoked by treatment with 6-hydroxydopamine [<xref rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Like nicotine, ethanol has also been suggested in potentially having a neuroprotective effect. Various epidemiological studies have found that moderate, non-binge consumers of alcohol had a significantly lower risk of cognitive loss or dementia [<xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. However, some of the potential benefits of moderate alcohol consumption may be due to polyphenols found in alcohols such as wine [<xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Resveratrol, a polyphenol found in wine, is especially touted for its anti-inflammatory properties that have a cardioprotective effect by reducing infarct volume [<xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>].</p><p id="p0200">Various signaling processes are regulated by ILK and other growth factor signaling. &#x003b2;1 integrins in humans and rodents appear to be localized to ILK [<xref rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. ILK plays a vital role in cancer research and facilitates various cellular functions such as survival, cytoskeletal dynamics, and proliferation [<xref rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. ILK is required to promote neurite growth factor (NGF) mediated neurogenesis [<xref rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. ILK interacts to AMPAR and PSD95 to modulate the effect of cocaine induced synaptic plasticity and memory [<xref rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. ILK-related mechanisms are compromised in neurodegenerative diseases (e.g., Alzheimer's disease and Parkinson's disease) characterized by learning and memory deficits [<xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>, <xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. We previously reported that alcohol exposure reduced ILK activity and also its interaction to GluR2 AMPA receptors [<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. ILK inhibition could result in reduced phosphorylation of certain residues on GluR2 thereby increasing the stability of GluR2 at the surface. Increased expression of calcium impermeable AMPARs GluR2, would reduce the extent of depolarization at the synapse and therefore, would also contribute less to calcium influx thereby reducing LTP generation and maintenance [<xref rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. However, prenatal alcohol + nicotine group failed to improve the synaptic plasticity deficits. The synaptic expression of increased GluR2 is not significantly reduced in alcohol + nicotine exposed animals. Moreover, the probability of GluR1 to GluR2 containing receptor switch responsible for LTP maintenance will be impaired with increased synaptic GluR2 [<xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. This suggest that reduced plasticity in both alcohol and nicotine +alcohol group may be dependent on increased synaptic GluR2 expression. The complex interplay among the molecules GSK3&#x003b2;, BDNF, ILK and Akt strengthen the notion that ILK is critically involved in LTP. Analysis of basal synaptic transmission illustrates that ILK inhibition attenuates fEPSPs. These findings highlight a functional link between ILK, basal synaptic transmission and LTP in the hippocampus. Reduced LTP can also be due to increased GSK3&#x003b2; activation which could affect receptor trafficking and protein expression required for LTP maintenance in FASD model. Likewise, prenatal alcohol + nicotine group failed to improve the synaptic plasticity deficits as seen with FASD model. The enhanced GluR2 expression is one possible cause of plasticity deficits. Our previous study assessed the effects of prenatal exposure to ethanol on memory, using a contextual fear conditioning paradigm. This study revealed that prenatal alcohol exposure can cause the hippocampus related contextual memory deficit. Here, we tested the spatial memory task, a simpler way to understand the same complex brain development and its processing of spatial information. As expected, the prenatal alcohol exposure showed significant deficit in the memory development. Previous finding with prenatal nicotine only group also suggested impaired AMPA receptor function and LTP impairment as we see here in our co-administrative model. Therefore, we expected to see even stronger deficit in memory impairment with alcohol + nicotine exposure. On the contrary, we observed improved spatial task in our model of co-exposure as compared to control and alcohol only groups. This suggests nicotine can have a differential effect on memory development by antagonizing the deleterious effect of alcohol.</p><p id="p0205">In summary, we demonstrated clearly that prenatal exposure to teratogens certainly has a significant change in neuronal circuit development involving the synaptic receptors and neurotransmitters. However, some protective effect with nicotine was observed in our cognitive task. This requires further exploration as various brain regions are involved in the exploratory behavior of these rodents. In this study we also compared the effects of alcohol + nicotine in the cortex and cerebellum (<xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">Table&#x000a0;2</xref>), however further specific behavioral tasks required to address the issue. More studies using specific pharmacological interventions are required to tease out the entire mechanism of synaptic regulation by these teratogens. The role of other AMPARs and NMDARs is to be assessed in order to understand the magnitude of neurotoxicity involved with these teratogens.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl2"><label>Table&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Comparison of Markers of oxidative stress, mitochondrial functions, apoptosis and cellular signaling in Cortex and Cerebellum.</p></caption><alt-text id="alttext0055">Table&#x000a0;2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Marker</th><th>Cerebellum</th><th>Cortex</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>ILK</td><td>Significant decrease in both alcohol and alcohol + nicotine</td><td>No significant difference between three groups</td></tr><tr><td>PSD-95</td><td>Significant decrease in both alcohol and alcohol + nicotine, alc + nic decreased more than alcohol alone</td><td>Significant increase in both alcohol and alcohol + nicotine</td></tr><tr><td>COMPLEX-I</td><td>No significant difference between three groups</td><td>Significant decrease in both alcohol and alcohol + nicotine, alcohol decreased more than alc + nic</td></tr><tr><td>COMPLEX IV</td><td>No significant difference between three groups</td><td>Significant decrease in both alcohol and alcohol + nicotine, alcohol decreased more than alc + nic</td></tr><tr><td>CASPASE-3</td><td>Significant increase in both alcohol and alcohol + nicotine</td><td>Significant increase in both alcohol and alcohol + nicotine, alcohol is slightly higher than alcohol + nicotine</td></tr><tr><td>ROS</td><td>Significant increase in both alcohol and alcohol + nicotine</td><td>Significant increase in alcohol, slight, insignificant increase in alcohol + nicotine</td></tr><tr><td>LIPID PEROXIDATION</td><td>Significant increase in both alcohol and alcohol + nicotine, with no significant difference between the two experimental groups</td><td>Significant increase in both alcohol and alcohol + nicotine, alcohol greater than alc + nic</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec5"><label>5</label><title>Conclusion</title><p id="p0210">In our earlier studies, we have shown that the ILK pathway appears to play a significant role in memory and synaptic plasticity impairments in the prenatal alcohol exposed offspring(s). However, alcohol + nicotine did not affect ILK expression and also had less effect on the electrophysiological and behavioral changes. Based on the results obtained, at this particular dose and duration of prenatal alcohol + nicotine exposure has shown to reduce the neurotoxicity-induced by prenatal alcohol exposure alone. Further in-depth prenatal neurochemical studies exposing to various doses and duration should be conducted to understand the prenatal effects of prenatal alcohol + nicotine.</p></sec><sec id="sec6"><title>Declarations</title><sec id="sec6.1"><title>Author contribution statement</title><p id="p0215">Dwipayan Bhattacharya, Ayaka Fujihashi, Mohammed Majrashi, Jenna Bloemer, Subhrajit Bhattacharya, Manal Buabeid, Timothy Moore: Conceived and designed the experiments; Performed the experiments; Analyzed and interpreted the data.</p><p id="p0220">Martha Escobar, Vishnu Suppiramaniam, Muralikrishnan Dhanasekaran: Conceived and designed the experiments; Contributed reagents, materials, analysis tools or data; Wrote the paper.</p></sec><sec id="sec6.2"><title>Funding statement</title><p id="p0225">This research did not receive any specific grant from funding agencies in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p></sec><sec id="sec6.3"><title>Competing interest statement</title><p id="p0230">The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec id="sec6.4"><title>Additional information</title><p id="p0235">No additional information is available for this paper.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Waterson</surname><given-names>E.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Murray-Lyon</surname><given-names>I.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Drinking and smoking patterns amongst women attending an antenatal clinic--II. During pregnancy</article-title><source>Alcohol Alcohol</source><volume>24</volume><year>1989</year><fpage>163</fpage><lpage>173</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2785805</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Riley</surname><given-names>E.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Infante</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>K.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fetal alcohol Spectrum Disorders: an overview</article-title><source>Neuropsychol. Rev.</source><volume>21</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>73</fpage><lpage>80</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21499711</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Batty</surname><given-names>G.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Deary</surname><given-names>I.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Macintyre</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Childhood IQ and life course socioeconomic position in relation to alcohol induced hangovers in adulthood: the Aberdeen children of the 1950s study</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Epidemiol. Community Health</source><volume>60</volume><year>2006</year><fpage>872</fpage><lpage>874</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16973534</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parnell</surname><given-names>S.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>West</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neonatal alcohol and nicotine exposure limits brain growth and depletes cerebellar Purkinje cells</article-title><source>Alcohol</source><volume>15</volume><year>1998</year><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9426835</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Archibald</surname><given-names>S.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fennema-Notestine</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gamst</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Riley</surname><given-names>E.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mattson</surname><given-names>S.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jernigan</surname><given-names>T.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Brain dysmorphology in individuals with severe prenatal alcohol exposure</article-title><source>Dev. Med. Child Neurol.</source><volume>43</volume><year>2001</year><fpage>148</fpage><lpage>154</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11263683</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kodituwakku</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sutherland</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Savage</surname><given-names>D.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Children with Fetal Alcohol Syndrome are impaired at place learning but not cued-navigation in a virtual Morris water task</article-title><source>Behav. Brain Res.</source><volume>143</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>94</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12842299</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mattson</surname><given-names>S.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Riley</surname><given-names>E.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Implicit and explicit memory functioning in children with heavy prenatal alcohol exposure</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Int. Neuropsychol. Soc.</source><volume>5</volume><year>1999</year><fpage>462</fpage><lpage>471</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10439591</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ernster</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaufman</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nichter</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Samet</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>S.Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Women and tobacco: moving from policy to action</article-title><source>Bull. World Health Organ.</source><volume>78</volume><year>2000</year><fpage>891</fpage><lpage>901</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10994262</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abel</surname><given-names>E.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Smoking during pregnancy: a review of effects on growth and development of offspring</article-title><source>Hum. Biol.</source><volume>52</volume><year>1980</year><fpage>593</fpage><lpage>625</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7009384</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bruin</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerstein</surname><given-names>H.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Holloway</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long-term consequences of fetal and neonatal nicotine exposure: a critical review</article-title><source>Toxicol. Sci.</source><volume>116</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>364</fpage><lpage>374</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20363831</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wickstrom</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of nicotine during pregnancy: human and experimental evidence</article-title><source>Curr. Neuropharmacol.</source><volume>5</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>213</fpage><lpage>222</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19305804</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>T.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seidler</surname><given-names>F.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Slotkin</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prenatal nicotine exposure evokes alterations of cell structure in hippocampus and somatosensory cortex</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Pharmacol. Exp. Ther.</source><volume>300</volume><year>2002</year><fpage>124</fpage><lpage>133</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11752107</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="book" id="sref13"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fertig</surname><given-names>J.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name><collab>National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism (U.S.)</collab></person-group><source>Alcohol and Tobacco&#x000a0;: from Basic Science to Clinical Practice</source><year>1995</year><publisher-name>National Institutes of Health, National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cornelius</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leech</surname><given-names>S.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldschmidt</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Day</surname><given-names>N.L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prenatal tobacco exposure: is it a risk factor for early tobacco experimentation?</article-title><source>Nicotine Tob. Res.</source><volume>2</volume><year>2000</year><fpage>45</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11072440</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>W.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parnell</surname><given-names>S.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>West</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of alcohol and nicotine on developing olfactory bulb: loss of mitral cells and alterations in neurotransmitter levels</article-title><source>Alcohol Clin. Exp. Res.</source><volume>23</volume><year>1999</year><fpage>18</fpage><lpage>25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10029199</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhattacharya</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunaway</surname><given-names>E.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhattacharya</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bloemer</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Buabeid</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Escobar</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Suppiramaniam</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dhanasekaran</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impaired ILK function is associated with deficits in hippocampal based memory and synaptic plasticity in a FASD rat model</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><volume>10</volume><year>2015</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e0135700</object-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Younes-Rapozo</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moura</surname><given-names>E.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Manh&#x000e3;es</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinheiro</surname><given-names>C.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barradas</surname><given-names>P.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Oliveira</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lisboa</surname><given-names>P.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neonatal nicotine exposure leads to hypothalamic gliosis in adult overweight rats</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Neuroendocrinol.</source><volume>27</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>887</fpage><lpage>898</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26453898</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>&#x000c5;berg</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hofstetter</surname><given-names>C.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bren&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Moderate ethanol consumption increases hippocampal cell proliferation and neurogenesis in the adult mouse</article-title><source>Int. J. Neuropsychopharmacol.</source><volume>8</volume><year>2005</year><fpage>557</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16202182</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref19"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhattacharya</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Majrashi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramesh</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Govindarajulu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bloemer</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujihashi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Crump</surname><given-names>B.-R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hightower</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhattacharya</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Suppiramaniam</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dhanasekaran</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessment of the cerebellar neurotoxic effects of nicotine in prenatal alcohol exposure in rats</article-title><source>Life Sci.</source><year>2018</year><fpage>194</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ahuja</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Buabeid</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdel-Rehman</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Majrashi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parameshwaran</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Amin</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramesh</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thiruchelvan</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pondugula</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Suppiramaniam</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dhanasekaran</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immunological alteration {&#x00026;} toxic molecular inductions leading to cognitive impairment {&#x00026;} neurotoxicity in transgenic mouse model of Alzheimer{textquotesingle}s disease</article-title><source>Life Sci.</source><year>2017</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>D.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Majrashi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramesh</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Govindarajulu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhattacharya</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhattacharya</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shalgum</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bradford</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Suppiramaniam</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Deruiter</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>C.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dhanasekaran</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparing the dopaminergic neurotoxic effects of benzylpiperazine and benzoylpiperazine</article-title><source>Toxicol. Mech. Methods</source><year>2017</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>35</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref22"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Majrashi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Almaghrabi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fadan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujihashi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Deruiter</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Randall Clark</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dhanasekaran</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dopaminergic neurotoxic effects of 3-TFMPP derivatives</article-title><source>Life Sci.</source><volume>209</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>357</fpage><lpage>369</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30067941</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref23"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thrash-Williams</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Karuppagounder</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhattacharya</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahuja</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Suppiramaniam</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dhanasekaran</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Methamphetamine-induced dopaminergic toxicity prevented owing to the neuroprotective effects of salicylic acid</article-title><source>Life Sci.</source><volume>154</volume><year>2016</year><fpage>24</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26926078</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref24"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Usha</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Muralikrishnan</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mandal</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohanakumar</surname><given-names>K.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Region-specific attenuation of a trypsin-like protease in substantia nigra following dopaminergic neurotoxicity by 1-methyl-4-phenyl-1,2, 3,6-tetrahydropyridine</article-title><source>Brain Res.</source><volume>882</volume><year>2000</year><fpage>191</fpage><lpage>195</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11056198</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref25"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chao</surname><given-names>L.-P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolfgram</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spectrophotometric assay for choline acetyltransferase</article-title><source>Anal. Biochem.</source><volume>46</volume><year>1972</year><fpage>114</fpage><lpage>118</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5017650</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref26"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ellman</surname><given-names>G.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Courtney</surname><given-names>K.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Andres</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Featherstone</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A&#x000a0;new and rapid colorimetric determination of acetylcholinesterase activity</article-title><source>Biochem. Pharmacol.</source><volume>7</volume><year>1961</year><fpage>88</fpage><lpage>95</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13726518</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref27"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muralikrishnan</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohanakumar</surname><given-names>K.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neuroprotection by bromocriptine against 1-methyl-4-phenyl-1,2,3,6-tetrahydropyridine-induced neurotoxicity in mice</article-title><source>FASEB J.</source><volume>12</volume><year>1998</year><fpage>905</fpage><lpage>912</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9657530</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref28"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sheng</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Caspases in synaptic plasticity</article-title><source>Mol. Brain</source><volume>5</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>15</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22583788</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref29"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Metten</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlumbohm</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>L.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>G.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hack</surname><given-names>W.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Spence</surname><given-names>S.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Crabbe</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An alcohol withdrawal test battery measuring multiple behavioral symptoms in mice</article-title><source>Alcohol</source><volume>68</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>35</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29427828</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref30"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barcel&#x000f3;-Coblijn</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wold</surname><given-names>L.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>E.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prenatal ethanol exposure increases brain cholesterol content in adult rats</article-title><source>Lipids</source><volume>48</volume><year>2013</year><fpage>1059</fpage><lpage>1068</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23996454</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref31"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wold</surname><given-names>L.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Natavio</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>B.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hannigan</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Influence of prenatal alcohol exposure on myocardial contractile function in adult rat hearts: role of intracellular calcium and apoptosis</article-title><source>Alcohol Alcohol</source><volume>37</volume><year>2002</year><fpage>30</fpage><lpage>37</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11825854</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref32"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jurado-Coronel</surname><given-names>J.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Loaiza</surname><given-names>A.,E.</given-names></name><name><surname>D&#x000ed;az</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cabezas</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashraf</surname><given-names>G.,M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sahebkar</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Echeverria</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barreto</surname><given-names>G.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>(E)-Nicotinaldehyde O-cinnamyloxime, a nicotine analog, attenuates neuronal cells death against rotenone-induced neurotoxicity</article-title><source>Mol. Neurobiol.</source><volume>56</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>1221</fpage><lpage>1232</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29881944</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref33"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takeuch</surname><given-names>i H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yanagidam</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Indenm</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Takatam</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitamuram</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamakawam</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sawadam</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Izumim</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamamotom</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiharam</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Uemuram</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Inouem</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Taniguchim</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Akaikem</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Takahashim</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimohama</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nicotinic receptor stimulation protects nigral dopaminergic neurons in rotenone-induced Parkinson's disease models</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Neurosci. Res.</source><volume>87</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>576</fpage><lpage>585</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18803299</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref34"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Does smoking reduce the risk of Parkinson's disease through stimulation of the ubiquitin-proteasome system?</article-title><source>Med. Hypotheses</source><volume>73</volume><year>2009</year><fpage>887</fpage><lpage>891</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19540050</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref35"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parain</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hapdey</surname><given-names>reC.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rousselet</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marchand</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dumery</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirsch</surname><given-names>E.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cigarette smoke and nicotine protect dopaminergic neurons against the 1-methyl-4-phenyl-1,2,3,6-tetrahydropyridine Parkinsonian toxin</article-title><source>Brain Res.</source><volume>984</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>224</fpage><lpage>232</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12932857</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref36"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>J.Y.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barber</surname><given-names>J.E.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nash</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Le</surname><given-names>A.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>F.,</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>A.H.C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The neuroprotective effect of nicotine in Parkinson's disease models is associated with inhibiting PARP-1 and caspase-3 cleavage</article-title><source>PeerJ</source><volume>5</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>e3933</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29062606</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref37"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rehm</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasan</surname><given-names>O.S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Black</surname><given-names>S.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shield</surname><given-names>K.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwarzinger</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alcohol use and dementia: a systematic scoping review</article-title><source>Alzheimer's Res. Ther.</source><volume>11</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30611304</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref38"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Snopek</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mlcek</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sochorova</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baron</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hlavacova</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jurikova</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kizek</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sedlackova</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sochor</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Contribution of red wine consumption to human health protection</article-title><source>Molecules</source><volume>23</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>E1684</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29997312</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref39"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dehghani</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hafizibarjin</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Najjari</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaseb</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Safari</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Resveratrol and 1,25-dihydroxyvitamin D co-administration protects the heart against D-galactose-induced aging in rats: evaluation of serum and cardiac levels of klotho</article-title><source>Aging Clin. Exp. Res.</source><volume>31</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>1195</fpage><lpage>1205</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30484255</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref40"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Periostin enhances migration, invasion, and adhesion of human endometrial stromal cells through integrin-linked kinase 1/Akt signaling pathway</article-title><source>Reprod. Sci.</source><volume>22</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>1098</fpage><lpage>1106</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25759370</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref41"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hannigan</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Troussard</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dedhar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Integrin-linked kinase: a cancer therapeutic target unique among its ILK</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Cancer</source><volume>5</volume><year>2005</year><fpage>51</fpage><lpage>63</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15630415</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref42"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Digicaylioglu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Legg</surname><given-names>A.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>C.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>S.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barr</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fletcher</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Connor</surname><given-names>T.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dedhar</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of integrin-linked kinase in nerve growth factor-stimulated neurite outgrowth</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Neurosci.</source><volume>23</volume><year>2003</year><fpage>1638</fpage><lpage>1648</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12629168</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref43"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wetsel</surname><given-names>W.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>T.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Integrin-linked kinase is involved in cocaine sensitization by regulating PSD-95 and synapsin I expression and GluR1 Ser845 phosphorylation</article-title><source>J.&#x000a0;Mol. Neurosci.</source><volume>40</volume><year>2010</year><fpage>284</fpage><lpage>294</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19629758</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref44"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benitez-King</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ram&#x000ed;rez-Rodr&#x000ed;guez</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ort&#x000ed;z</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meza</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The neuronal cytoskeleton as a potential therapeutical target in neurodegenerative diseases and schizophrenia</article-title><source>Curr. Drug Targets - CNS Neurol. Disord.</source><volume>3</volume><year>2004</year><fpage>515</fpage><lpage>533</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15581421</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref45"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>M&#x000fc;ller</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>H.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Egensperger</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marcus</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The amyloid precursor protein intracellular domain (AICD) as modulator of gene expression, apoptosis, and cytoskeletal dynamics&#x02014;relevance for Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease</article-title><source>Prog. Neurobiol.</source><volume>85</volume><year>2008</year><fpage>393</fpage><lpage>406</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18603345</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref46"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Agopyan</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miu</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiong</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerlai</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Taverna</surname><given-names>F.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Velumian</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>MacDonald</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carlen</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Abramow-Newerly</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roder</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enhanced LTP in mice deficient in the AMPA receptor GluR2</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>17</volume><year>1996</year><fpage>945</fpage><lpage>956</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8938126</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref47"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jonas</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Burnashev</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular mechanisms controlling calcium entry through AMPA-type glutamate receptor channels</article-title><source>Neuron</source><volume>15</volume><year>1995</year><fpage>987</fpage><lpage>990</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7576666</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec id="appsec1" sec-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix A</label><title>Supplementary data</title><p id="p0245">The following is the supplementary data related to this article:<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc1"><caption><title>Blots.pdf</title></caption><media xlink:href="mmc1.pdf"><alt-text>Blots.pdf</alt-text></media></supplementary-material></p></sec></back></article>