<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31924819</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6954247</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">56906</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-56906-w</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><italic>In vivo</italic> evidence of significant placental growth factor release by normal pregnancy placentas</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cerdeira</surname><given-names>Ana Sofia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kandzija</surname><given-names>Neva</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pargmae</surname><given-names>Pille</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tome</surname><given-names>Mariana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Wei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cooke</surname><given-names>William R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Agrawal</surname><given-names>Swati</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>James</surname><given-names>Tim</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Redman</surname><given-names>Christopher</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Vatish</surname><given-names>Manu</given-names></name><address><email>manu.vatish@wrh.ox.ac.uk</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1936 8948</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.4991.5</institution-id><institution>Nuffield Department of Women&#x02019;s Health and Reproductive Research, </institution><institution>University of Oxford, Level 3, Women&#x02019;s Center, John Radcliffe Oxford University Hospital, </institution></institution-wrap>Oxford, OX3 9DU United Kingdom </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, Women&#x02019;s Center, John Radcliffe Oxford University Hospital, Oxford, OX3 9DU United Kingdom </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>Department of Biochemistry, John Radcliffe Oxford University Hospital, Oxford, OX3 9DU United Kingdom </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2157 2938</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.17063.33</institution-id><institution>University of Toronto, </institution></institution-wrap>Toronto, Canada </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>10</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>132</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>13</day><month>9</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>26</day><month>11</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Placental growth factor (PlGF) is an angiogenic factor identified in the maternal circulation, and a key biomarker for the diagnosis and management of placental disorders. Furthermore, enhancing the PlGF pathway is regarded as a promising therapy for preeclampsia. The source of PlGF is still controversial with some believing it to be placental in origin while others refute this. To explore the source of PlGF, we undertook a prospective study enrolling normal pregnant women undergoing elective caesarean section. The level of PlGF was estimated in 17 paired serum samples from the uterine vein (ipsilateral or contralateral to the placental insertion) during caesarean section and from a peripheral vein on the same day and second day post-partum. PlGF levels were higher in the uterine than in the peripheral vein with a median difference of 52.2 (IQR 20.1&#x02013;85.8) pg/mL p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0006. The difference when the sampled uterine vein was ipsilateral to the placenta was 54.8 (IQR 37.1&#x02013;88.4) pg/mL (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;11) and 23.7 (IQR &#x02212;11; 70.5) pg/mL (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;6) when the sample was contralateral. Moreover, PlGF levels fell by 83% on day 1&#x02013;2 post-partum. Our findings strongly support the primary source of PlGF to be placental. These findings will be of value in designing target therapies such as PlGF overexpression, to cure placental disorders during pregnancy.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Diagnostic markers</kwd><kwd>Pregnancy outcome</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Roche Diagnostics supplied PlGF kits for this study.</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">There is discrepancy in the literature as to whether the placenta is a significant source of maternal circulating PlGF in normal pregnancies. <italic>In vitro</italic> studies have shown placental production and release of PlGF<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. In fact, PlGF was first identified in 1991 by Maglione <italic>et al</italic>. in a placenta cDNA library<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>, hence its name. Since then however, PlGF has been found to be produced by malignant cells, endothelium, smooth muscle, pericytes, myocites and immune cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. <italic>In vivo</italic> studies in pregnancy show conflicting data as to the primary source of PlGF<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. The question remains as to how much maternal circulating PlGF is of placental origin.</p><p id="Par3">Understanding PlGF biology in both healthy and diseased pregnancies is of major importance. PlGF plays a role in normal placental formation; changes in PlGF are associated with preeclampsia and adverse fetal outcomes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>. Circulating PlGF forms a key component of novel preeclampsia biomarker assays recently introduced to clinical practice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. Strategies are currently being developed to enhance the PlGF pathway as a potential treatment for preeclampsia<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>; thus a better understanding of PlGF biodynamics will be crucial to designing the delivery mode and dosing.</p><p id="Par4">Previous studies have examined <italic>in vivo</italic> PlGF placental production by interrogating the PlGF concentration gradient between the uterine vein (closer to placenta) and a peripheral vein. Whilst a difference has been shown by one group<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>, implicating the placenta as a main source of PlGF, this was not shown by another<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>. This discrepancy could be due to different methodologies used.</p><p id="Par5">We aimed to determine if the placenta is the primary source of PlGF in normal pregnancies <italic>in vivo</italic>. We optimized previous conditions by using an automated assay with a low coefficient of variation, interrogating patients with lateral placentas, as well as making a comparison with postpartum peripheral levels.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><p id="Par6">The study was conducted at the John Radcliffe Hospital, Oxford, United Kingdom. We recruited women admitted for an elective cesarean section. All pregnancies were uncomplicated and indications for caesarean section were previous caesarean section or breech presentation. sFlt-1 levels in this cohort have previously been reported<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par7">All women included in the study had an ultrasound scan to assess placental location prior to the elective caesarean section. Patients with a midline placenta or with any signs of early labour were excluded.</p><p id="Par8">Serum samples were collected from the antecubital fossa (peripheral vein) and the uterine vein (UV) during the caesarean section, prior to delivery of the fetus. Uterine veins were identified laterally to the uterus and exposed by gentle displacement of the uterus towards the midline. Patients had a second peripheral sample taken on day 1&#x02013;2 postnatally.</p><p id="Par9">Uterine vein samples were labelled as contralateral or ipsilateral depending on their location in relation to the placenta. In the majority of cases the surgeon collected one sample either from the ipsilateral or contralateral uterine vein, at their own description or depending on surgical accessibility. In three cases of extreme lateral placentas it was possible to take bilateral uterine vein samples. Extreme lateral placenta was defined as a placenta located mostly on one side of the uterus: lateral left: all or almost all the placenta is located to the left of the midline; lateral right: all or almost all the placenta is located to the right of the midline; Midline placenta was defined as a placenta with a similar percentage of tissue towards the left and the right of the midline.</p><p id="Par10">Non-parametric analysis, Wilcoxon rank test, was used to assess differences between paired PlGF results and P&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 was considered significant.</p><p id="Par11">Samples were centrifuged within 3&#x02009;hours of collection and frozen at &#x02212;80C until analysis. PlGF was measured on a Roche e411 analyzer (Roche Diagnostics Limited, Burgess Hill, UK). Inter-assay percentage coefficient of variation was 3.0% at 106.1&#x02009;pg/mL and 2.9% at 1068.5&#x02009;pg/mL.</p><p id="Par12">All patients provided informed written consent prior to the start of the study. The study was approved by the Central Oxfordshire Research Ethics Committee C (07/H0607/74) and was in accordance with the ethical standards of the institutional and/or national research committee and with the Helsinki Declaration and its amendments.</p></sec><sec id="Sec3" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p id="Par13">We obtained seventeen paired uterine and peripheral samples at the time of caesarean section. Mean gestational age was 39.4 (IQR 39.1&#x02013;40) weeks. Overall median uterine vein PlGF was 168.9 (IQR 135.4&#x02013;252) pg/mL and overall median peripheral PlGF was 118.2 (IQR 89.8&#x02013;187.9) pg/mL (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;17 paired samples, paired <italic>Wilcoxon</italic> test p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0006) (Figs.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> and <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Placental growth factor levels for uterine and peripheral vein. Data is presented as individual values with median and interquartile range. Paired <italic>Wilcoxon</italic> test was performed. P&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 was considered significant (*).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_56906_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e418"/></fig><fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Placental growth factor levels for uterine and peripheral vein showing paired samples and placental location. (<bold>A</bold>) all paired samples are presented (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;17 pairs); (<bold>B</bold>) contralateral samples are presented (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;6 pairs). (<bold>C</bold>) Ipsilateral samples are presented (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;11 pairs). Paired <italic>Wilcoxon</italic> test was performed. P&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 was considered significant (*).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_56906_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e439"/></fig></p><p id="Par14">The median difference between PlGF uterine and peripheral vein concentrations was 52.2 (IQR 20.1&#x02013;85.8) pg/mL, being 23.7 (IQR &#x02212;11; 70.5) pg/ml when the UV sample was contralateral to the placenta (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;6; paired <italic>Wilcoxon</italic> test p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.12) and 54.8 (IQR 37.1&#x02013;88.4) pg/mL when the UV sample was ipsilateral to the placenta (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;11; paired <italic>Wilcoxon</italic> test p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.003) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Importantly, in 3 patients where bilateral UV samples were collected, PlGF levels from ipsilateral UV samples were consistently higher than contralateral ones (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Placental growth factor levels for three patients with lateral placentas who had both (ipsilateral and contralateral) uterine vein samples collected. UV: uterine vein.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_56906_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e462"/></fig></p><p id="Par15">Peripheral PlGF levels fell by 83% postpartum [median PlGF: 23.5 (IQR 15.8&#x02013;28.3); n&#x02009;=&#x02009;8; paired <italic>Wilcoxon</italic> test p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.012] (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>).<fig id="Fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Placental growth factor levels at delivery and postnatal. Delivery stands for the peripheral samples collected at the time of caesarean section. Postnatal samples were collected at day 1&#x02013;2 after delivery (Caesarean section) (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;8). Data presented with all the samples all together and samples with their respective pairs; Paired <italic>Wilcoxon</italic> test was performed. P&#x0003c;0.05 was considered significant (*).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_56906_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e482"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec4" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par16">PlGF is an angiogenic factor that belongs to the vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF) family. It has an important role in normal placental function and can be detected in maternal circulation as early as the first trimester<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. PlGF is tightly linked with the pathogenesis of preeclampsia and fetal growth restriction; thus understanding PlGF biodynamics will be crucial to making progress in therapeutics in these diseases. We demonstrate that the placenta is an important source of maternal circulating PlGF by showing a significant gradient between uterine and peripheral PlGF levels. This is most evident in uterine vein samples acquired from the same side as the placenta (ipsilateral). In support of this, bilateral samples collected from lateral placentas consistently showed higher PlGF levels in the ipsilateral uterine vein compared to the contralateral. Finally, when the placenta is removed (i.e. postnatal period) there is an 83% fall in PlGF levels in the peripheral circulation. It has been suggested that the uterus itself could be a key source of PlGF, rather than the placenta. <italic>In vitro</italic> studies showing significant production and expression of PlGF by normal placentas<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup> and our data from bilateral samples and postnatal samples (showing a significant drop of PlGF after the placenta is removed) suggests that this is unlikely. This study was performed on term patients and therefore the conclusions may not be applicable to other trimesters.</p><p id="Par17">Most of our knowledge of placental biology is derived from human <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>ex vivo</italic> data, which is easier to access than <italic>in vivo</italic> samples, but remains a model. <italic>In vitro</italic> studies show that both VEGF and PlGF are produced by the placenta<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. Intriguingly, in contrast with PlGF, <italic>in vivo</italic> data suggests that maternal circulating VEGF is taken up by the placenta and mostly produced by peripheral organs (shown by a lower concentration of VEGF in the uterine vein when compared to the radial artery)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. This not only demonstrates the value of <italic>in vivo</italic> data, but also has important implications. For example, when designing target-specific strategies, such as the recent use of RNAi to downregulate the production of sFlt-1 only in the placenta (the main source of sFlt-1) and not in other organs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par18">In summary, these data strongly suggest that the placenta is the main source of maternal PlGF in normal pregnancy.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s note</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We acknowledge support from the National Institute for Health Research to ASC and WC who are NIHR Academic Clinical Lecturer and Clinical Fellow respectively. The authors would like to acknowledge all the patients, Obstetricians, Anaesthetists, Theatre Nurses and Research Midwifes who made this work possible. We acknowledge support from Roche Diagnostics in supplying PlGF kits for this study. Roche Diagnostics had no role in study design, interpretation of data or drafting the manuscript.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>A.S.C., M.V. and C.R. conceived the study. A.S.C. and M.T. wrote the first draft. A.S.C., M.V. and P.P. collected the samples, N.K., W.R.C. and W.Z. processed the samples and T.J. performed the test. A.S.C. and S.A. prepared figures. A.S.C., M.T., S.A., W.R.C., M.V. and C.R. wrote the manuscript and all authors reviewed and approved the final version.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par19">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Clark D. E., Smith S. K., Licence D., Evans A. L. &#x00026; Charnock-Jones D. S. Comparison of expression patterns for placenta growth factor, vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF), VEGF-B and VEGF-C in the human placenta throughout gestation. <italic>J. Endocrinol. Dec</italic>, <bold>159</bold>(3), 459&#x02013;67 (1998).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Depoix C., Tee M. K. &#x00026; Taylor R. N. Molecular regulation of human placental growth factor (PlGF) gene expression in placental villi and trophoblast cells is mediated via the protein kinase a pathway. <italic>Reprod. Sci.</italic> Mar., <bold>18</bold>(3), 219&#x02013;28 (2011).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gobble R. M., Groesch K. A., Chang M., Torry R. J. &#x00026; Torry D. S. Differential regulation of human PlGF gene expression in trophoblast and nontrophoblast cells by oxygen tension. <italic>Placenta. Oct,</italic><bold>30</bold>(10), 869&#x02013;75 (2009).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Maglione D., Guerriero V., Viglietto G., Delli-Bovi P. &#x00026; Persico M. G. Isolation of a human placenta cDNA coding for a protein related to the vascular permeability factor. <italic>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA Oct</italic> 15, <bold>88</bold>(20), 9267&#x02013;71 (1991).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Dewerchin M.&#x00026; Carmeliet P. PlGF: a multitasking cytokine with disease-restricted activity. <italic>Cold Spring Harb Perspect Med.</italic> Aug 1, <bold>2</bold>(8) (2012).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Torry</surname><given-names>Ronald J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomanek</surname><given-names>Robert J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Wei</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>Steven J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Labarrere</surname><given-names>Carlos A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Torry</surname><given-names>Donald S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hypoxia Increases Placenta Growth Factor Expression in Human Myocardium and Cultured Neonatal Rat Cardiomyocytes</article-title><source>The Journal of Heart and Lung Transplantation</source><year>2009</year><volume>28</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>183</fpage><lpage>190</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.healun.2008.11.917</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19201345</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Nomura M. <italic>et al</italic>. Placenta growth factor (PlGF) mRNA expression in brain tumors. <italic>J. Neurooncol.</italic> Nov., <bold>40</bold>(2), 123&#x02013;30 (1998).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holme</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Roland</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Henriksen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Michelsen</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>In vivo</italic> uteroplacental release of placental growth factor and soluble Fms-like tyrosine kinase-1 in normal and preeclamptic pregnancies</article-title><source>American journal of obstetrics and gynecology.</source><year>2016</year><volume>215</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>782 e1</fpage><lpage>e9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajog.2016.07.056</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27503620</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bujold</surname><given-names>Emmanuel</given-names></name><name><surname>Romero</surname><given-names>Roberto</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaiworapongsa</surname><given-names>Tinnakorn</given-names></name><name><surname>KIM</surname><given-names>Yeon Mee</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Gi Jin</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Mi Ran</given-names></name><name><surname>Espinoza</surname><given-names>Jimmy</given-names></name><name><surname>Gon&#x000e7;alves</surname><given-names>Lu&#x000ed;s F</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwin</surname><given-names>Samuel</given-names></name><name><surname>Mazor</surname><given-names>Moshe</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evidence supporting that the excess of the sVEGFR-1 concentration in maternal plasma in preeclampsia has a uterine origin</article-title><source>The Journal of Maternal-Fetal &#x00026; Neonatal Medicine</source><year>2005</year><volume>18</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>16</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14767050500202493</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16105786</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Michelsen T. M., Henriksen T., Reinhold D., Powell T. L. &#x00026; Jansson T. The human placental proteome secreted into the maternal and fetal circulations in normal pregnancy based on 4-vessel sampling. <italic>FASEB J.</italic> Feb, <bold>33</bold>(2), 2944&#x02013;56 (2019).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Maynard S. E. <italic>et al</italic>. Excess placental soluble fms-like tyrosine kinase 1 (sFlt1) may contribute to endothelial dysfunction, hypertension, and proteinuria in preeclampsia. <italic>J. Clin. Invest.</italic> Mar., <bold>111</bold>(5), 649&#x02013;58 (2003).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Levine R. J. <italic>et al</italic>. Circulating angiogenic factors and the risk of preeclampsia. <italic>N. Engl. J. Med.</italic> Feb. 12, <bold>350</bold>(7), 672&#x02013;83 (2004).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Griffin M. <italic>et al</italic>. Predicting delivery of a small-for-gestational-age infant and adverse perinatal outcome in women with suspected pre-eclampsia. <italic>Ultrasound Obstet. Gynecol.</italic> Mar., <bold>51</bold>(3), 387&#x02013;95 (2018).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Aupont J. E., Akolekar R., Illian A., Neonakis S. &#x00026; Nicolaides K. H. Prediction of stillbirth from placental growth factor at 19&#x02013;24 weeks. <italic>Ultrasound Obstet. Gynecol.</italic> Nov., <bold>48</bold>(5), 631&#x02013;5 (2016).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Cerdeira A. S., Agrawal S., Staff A. C., Redman C. W. &#x00026; Vatish M. Angiogenic factors: potential to change clinical practice in pre-eclampsia? <italic>BJOG.</italic> Oct., <bold>125</bold>(11), 1389&#x02013;95 (2018).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Chau K., Hennessy A. &#x00026; Makris A. Placental growth factor and pre-eclampsia. <italic>J. Hum. Hypertens.</italic> Dec., <bold>31</bold>(12), 782&#x02013;6 (2017).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duhig</surname><given-names>Kate E</given-names></name><name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>Jenny</given-names></name><name><surname>Seed</surname><given-names>Paul T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sparkes</surname><given-names>Jenie</given-names></name><name><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>Jessica</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>Rachael M</given-names></name><name><surname>Shennan</surname><given-names>Andrew H</given-names></name><name><surname>Chappell</surname><given-names>Lucy C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bahl</surname><given-names>Rachna</given-names></name><name><surname>Bambridge</surname><given-names>Gabrielle</given-names></name><name><surname>Barnfield</surname><given-names>Sonia</given-names></name><name><surname>Ficquet</surname><given-names>Jo</given-names></name><name><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>Carolyn</given-names></name><name><surname>Girling</surname><given-names>Joanna</given-names></name><name><surname>Harding</surname><given-names>Kate</given-names></name><name><surname>Khalil</surname><given-names>Asma</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharp</surname><given-names>Andrew</given-names></name><name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>Nigel</given-names></name><name><surname>Tuffnell</surname><given-names>Derek</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Placental growth factor testing to assess women with suspected pre-eclampsia: a multicentre, pragmatic, stepped-wedge cluster-randomised controlled trial</article-title><source>The Lancet</source><year>2019</year><volume>393</volume><issue>10183</issue><fpage>1807</fpage><lpage>1818</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(18)33212-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Cerdeira A. S. <italic>et al</italic>. Randomized Interventional Study on Prediction of Preeclampsia/Eclampsia in Women With Suspected Preeclampsia. <italic>Hypertension.</italic> Aug. 12:HYPERTENSIONAHA11912739 (2019).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">(NICE) NIfHCE. PlGF-based testing to help diagnose suspected pre-eclampsia (Triage PlGF test, Elecsys immunoassay sFlt-1/PlGF ratio, DELFIA Xpress PlGF 1-2-3 test, and BRAHMS sFlt-1 Kryptor/BRAHMS PlGF plus Kryptor PE ratio). <italic>Diagnostics Guidance</italic><bold>23</bold>. (2016).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spradley</surname><given-names>Frank T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>Adelene Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Joo</surname><given-names>Woo S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Daniels</surname><given-names>Garrett</given-names></name><name><surname>Kussie</surname><given-names>Paul</given-names></name><name><surname>Karumanchi</surname><given-names>S. Ananth</given-names></name><name><surname>Granger</surname><given-names>Joey P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Placental Growth Factor Administration Abolishes Placental Ischemia-Induced Hypertension</article-title><source>Hypertension</source><year>2016</year><volume>67</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>740</fpage><lpage>747</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/HYPERTENSIONAHA.115.06783</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26831193</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Makris</surname><given-names>Angela</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeung</surname><given-names>Kristen R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>Shirlene M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sunderland</surname><given-names>Neroli</given-names></name><name><surname>Heffernan</surname><given-names>Scott</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>John F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Iliopoulos</surname><given-names>Jim</given-names></name><name><surname>Killingsworth</surname><given-names>Murray C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yong</surname><given-names>Jim</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Bei</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogle</surname><given-names>Robert F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thadhani</surname><given-names>Ravi</given-names></name><name><surname>Karumanchi</surname><given-names>S. Ananth</given-names></name><name><surname>Hennessy</surname><given-names>Annemarie</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Placental Growth Factor Reduces Blood Pressure in a Uteroplacental Ischemia Model of Preeclampsia in Nonhuman Primates</article-title><source>Hypertension</source><year>2016</year><volume>67</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1263</fpage><lpage>1272</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/HYPERTENSIONAHA.116.07286</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27091894</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumasawa</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikawa</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kidoya</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasuwa</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saito-Fujita</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morioka</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Takakura</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Okabe</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pravastatin induces placental growth factor (PGF) and ameliorates preeclampsia in a mouse model</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source><year>2010</year><volume>108</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1451</fpage><lpage>1455</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1011293108</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cerdeira</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Circulating soluble fms-like tyrosine kinase-1 is placentally derived in normal pregnancy: First <italic>in vivo</italic> evidence</article-title><source>Pregnancy Hypertens.</source><year>2019</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>145</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.preghy.2019.03.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31056150</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kasdaglis</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aberdeen</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Turan</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kopelman</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Atlas</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Blitzer</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Harman</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baschat</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Placental growth factor in the first trimester: relationship with maternal factors and placental Doppler studies</article-title><source>Ultrasound in Obstetrics and Gynecology</source><year>2010</year><volume>35</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>280</fpage><lpage>285</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/uog.7548</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20052659</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaufmann</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayhew</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Charnock-Jones</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aspects of Human Fetoplacental Vasculogenesis and Angiogenesis. II. Changes During Normal Pregnancy</article-title><source>Placenta.</source><year>2004</year><volume>25</volume><issue>2-3</issue><fpage>114</fpage><lpage>26</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.placenta.2003.10.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14972444</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Turanov A. A. <italic>et al</italic>. RNAi modulation of placental sFLT1 for the treatment of preeclampsia. <italic>Nat. Biotechnol.</italic> 2018 Nov 19.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>