<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nucleic Acids Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nar</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nucleic Acids Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0305-1048</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1362-4962</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31799610</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6954441</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkz1018</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">gkz1018</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Nucleic Acid Enzymes</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Oxidative damage diminishes mitochondrial DNA polymerase replication fidelity</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>Andrew P</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Xuemei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>William</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>Y Whitney</given-names></name><!--<email>ywyin@utmb.edu</email>--><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF4">4</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="AFF1"><label>1</label>
<institution>Quantitative and Computational Biosciences, Baylor College of Medicine</institution>, Houston, TX 77030, <country country="US">USA</country></aff><aff id="AFF2"><label>2</label>
<institution>Sealy Center for Structural Biology, University of Texas Medical Branch</institution>, Galveston, TX 77550, <country country="US">USA</country></aff><aff id="AFF3"><label>3</label>
<institution>Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology, University of Texas Medical Branch</institution>, Galveston, TX 77550, <country country="US">USA</country></aff><aff id="AFF4"><label>4</label>
<institution>Department of Pharmacology and Toxicology, University of Texas Medical Branch</institution>, Galveston, TX 77550, <country country="US">USA</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="COR1">To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +1 409 772 9631; Email: <email>ywyin@utmb.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>24</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2019-12-04"><day>04</day><month>12</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>04</day><month>12</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>48</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>817</fpage><lpage>829</lpage><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>11</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>12</day><month>10</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="received"><day>12</day><month>7</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of Nucleic Acids Research.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><license license-type="cc-by" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="gkz1018.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><p>Mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA) resides in a high ROS environment and suffers more mutations than its nuclear counterpart. Increasing evidence suggests that mtDNA mutations are not the results of direct oxidative damage, rather are caused, at least in part, by DNA replication errors. To understand how the mtDNA replicase, Pol &#x003b3;, can give rise to elevated mutations, we studied the effect of oxidation of Pol &#x003b3; on replication errors. Pol &#x003b3; is a high fidelity polymerase with polymerase (<italic>pol</italic>) and proofreading exonuclease (<italic>exo</italic>) activities. We show that Pol &#x003b3; <italic>exo</italic> domain is far more sensitive to oxidation than <italic>pol</italic>; under oxidative conditions, exonuclease activity therefore declines more rapidly than polymerase. The oxidized Pol &#x003b3; becomes editing-deficient, displaying a 20-fold elevated mutations than the unoxidized enzyme. Mass spectrometry analysis reveals that Pol &#x003b3; <italic>exo</italic> domain is a hotspot for oxidation. The oxidized <italic>exo</italic> residues increase the net negative charge around the active site that should reduce the affinity to mismatched primer/template DNA. Our results suggest that the oxidative stress induced high mutation frequency on mtDNA can be indirectly caused by oxidation of the mitochondrial replicase.</p></abstract><funding-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source><named-content content-type="funder-name">National Institutes of Health</named-content><named-content content-type="funder-identifier">10.13039/100000002</named-content></funding-source><award-id>R01GM110591</award-id><award-id>R01AI13461</award-id><award-id>R01NS095747</award-id><award-id>R01AI136031</award-id></award-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source><named-content content-type="funder-name">University of Texas Medical Branch</named-content><named-content content-type="funder-identifier">10.13039/100007865</named-content></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><counts><page-count count="13"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="SEC1"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Human mtDNA codes for two rRNAs, and 22 tRNAs necessary for the translation of 13 genes essential to the oxidative phosphorylation electron transfer process (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). Integrity of mtDNA is vital to cellular functions. It is estimated that mtDNA suffers ten-fold more point mutations than its nuclear counterpart (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). Accumulated somatic mutations on mtDNA cause organelle and cellular dysfunction, and have been implicated in ageing, cancer and neurodegeneration (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4&#x02013;6</xref>).</p><p>The mechanism underlying the accumulation of mtDNA mutations is not well understood. MtDNA is located in an environment high in reactive oxygen species (ROS) [9], which are generated endogenously from the electron transport chain and metabolic redox reactions (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>); the high mutation rate was therefore thought to be a product of direct oxidation of mtDNA. Because the most common DNA oxidation product is 8-oxoguanine (8oxoG), which promotes DNA polymerase to misincorporate dATP, a 30,000-fold increase in G:C to T:A transversions at the oxidized G position is expected (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). Additionally, oxidized nucleotide, 8oxodGTP can complete with dTTP and promotes A:T to C:G transversion (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>), which would further increase transervation mutations. Nonetheless, mtDNA transversion is reported to be much less than transition mutations, at a ratio of 1:9 (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10&#x02013;12</xref>), indicating that 8oxoG either occurs at lower frequency than random mutations on mtDNA or is rapidly repaired.</p><p>In human mitochondria, 8oxoG is primarily removed by base excision repair, where the oxidized guanine is excised by 8oxoG glycosylase (OGG1) (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>), and 8oxo-dGTP is eliminated by Mut homolog (MTH1) (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). However, loss-of-function mutations in OGG1 do not significantly influence the mtDNA mutation rate (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>); Although <italic>ogg1</italic> or <italic>ogg1/mth1</italic> knock-out mice increased the levels of 8-oxoguanine in mtDNA, the overall mtDNA mutation frequency is not significantly increased (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). These studies suggest that direct oxidative damage or its repair is not the primary cause of mtDNA mutations, rather that it likely arises from replication errors.</p><p>Human mtDNA is replicated by DNA polymerase gamma (Pol &#x003b3;), minimally together with Twinkle helicase and single-stranded DNA-binding protein (SSB) (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). Human Pol &#x003b3; is a heterotrimer consisting of a catalytic subunit Pol &#x003b3;A and a dimeric accessory subunit Pol &#x003b3;B. The Pol &#x003b3;A subunit contains at least two active sites: a polymerase (<italic>pol</italic>) site for template-dependent DNA synthesis, and a 3&#x02032;-5&#x02032; exonuclease (<italic>exo</italic>) site for proofreading (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). Pol &#x003b3;B subunit has no independent enzymatic activity but regulates both the <italic>pol</italic> and <italic>exo</italic> activities of the holoenzyme (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). Exonuclease activity is critical to maintain high fidelity during DNA replication (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). Transgenic mice with overexpressed exonuclease-deficient Pol &#x003b3; in cardiac tissue rapidly accumulated mtDNA mutations up to 23-fold more than wild-type and many developed cardiomyopathy (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). Furthermore, mice carrying exonuclease-deficient Pol &#x003b3; (D257A) displayed elevated mtDNA mutations; the animals exhibited a mutator phenotype and suffered from premature ageing (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). These studies established a link between increased replication errors on mtDNA and degenerative symptoms.</p><p>Because the mitochondrial replication machinery also exists in an ROS-rich environment, it is likely that ROS-induced oxidative damage to proteins of the mitochondrial replication machinery might contribute to replication errors in mtDNA. Indeed, oxidized bacteriophage T7 DNA polymerase (T7DNAP) displayed greater reduction in exonuclease than polymerase activity (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). Pol &#x003b3;A shares structural and functional homology with T7 DNAP, and is more sensitive to oxidation than human Pol &#x003b1;&#x000a0;and Pol &#x003b2; (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). These observations raise the question of whether oxidized Pol &#x003b3; could negatively impact mtDNA integrity.</p><p>Here we report studies on oxidation-induced activity changes in Pol &#x003b3;. Oxidized Pol &#x003b3; exhibits a 20-fold reduction in exonuclease activity while polymerase activity is relatively unchanged, suggesting upon oxidation, the high fidelity Pol &#x003b3; is converted into an editing-deficient polymerase. Mass spectrometry analyses further reveal that the Pol &#x003b3; exonuclease active site is a hotspot for oxidation. Our results thus indicate that Pol &#x003b3; could be a major contributor to elevated mtDNA mutations under conditions of oxidative stress.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="SEC2"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec id="SEC2-1"><title>Materials</title><p>Synthetic oligonucleotides (Table <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) were purchased from Integrated DNA Technologies (Coralville, Iowa), dNTPs and restriction enzymes were obtained from New England BioLabs (Ipswich, MA, USA). S-Trap Columns were obtained from PROTIFI (Huntington, NY, USA)</p><table-wrap id="tbl1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Oligonucleotide sequences</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oligonucleotide Name</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequences</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">M13-26-primer (26 nt)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5&#x02032;-GGATTATTTACATTGGCAGATTCACC</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MM-p (26 nt)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5&#x02032;-GGATTATTTACATTGGCAGATTCAAT</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MM-t (40 nt)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5&#x02032;-AATCTAGTCCCAAGCTTGAATCTGCCAATGTAAATAATCC</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MM-p/t duplex&#x000a0;(26/40 nt)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3&#x02032;-CCTAATAAATGTAACCGTCTAAGTT<bold>C</bold>GAACCCTGATCTAA</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5&#x02032;-GGATTATTTACATTGGCAGATTCAA<bold>T</bold></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Buried Mismatch 40&#x000a0;bp&#x000a0;(B40&#x000a0;bp)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3&#x02032;-CCTAATAAATGTAACCGTCTAAGTT<bold>C</bold>GAACCCTGATCTAA</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5&#x02032;-GGATTATTTACATTGGCAGATTCAA<bold>T</bold>CTTGGGACTAGATT</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Excised Mismatch 40&#x000a0;bp&#x000a0;(E40&#x000a0;bp)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3&#x02032;-CCTAATAAATGTAACCGTCTAAGTT<bold>C</bold>GAACCCTGATCTAA</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5&#x02032;-GGATTATTTACATTGGCAGATTC<underline>AA<bold>G</bold>CTT</underline>GGGACTAGATT</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x000a0;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;&#x02003;HindIII site</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="SEC2-2"><title>Pol &#x003b3; and DNA preparation</title><p>Pol &#x003b3; subunits Pol &#x003b3;A and Pol &#x003b3;B were expressed, respectively, in sf9 insect cells and BL21(DE3)-RIL bacteria and purified as previously described (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). Briefly, the proteins were purified using Ni-NTA, RESOURCE S and RESOURCE Q affinity chromatography, followed by gel filtration on a Superdex 200 column.</p><p>M13mp18 DNA was purified from infected IJ338 cells (K-12&#x000a0;<italic>ara thi</italic> &#x00394;(<italic>pro-lac</italic>) <italic>supD</italic>-Tn<italic>10</italic>/F'<italic>traD36 proA<sup>+</sup>B<sup>+</sup> lacI<sup>Q</sup></italic> l<italic>acZ&#x00394;M15</italic>, a kind gift from Dr.&#x000a0;Ian Molineux). A single colony of IJ338 was isolated and grown in LB with tetracycline to mid-log phase at 37&#x000b0;C. The culture was brought to 1 mM IPTG, 400 &#x003bc;g/ml X-gal, and a dilution series of phage was added, and then mixed into soft agar before being poured onto agar plates. After overnight growth at 37&#x000b0;C, a single blue plaque was extracted and added to mid-log phase IJ338, then incubated for 30 min at 37&#x000b0;C. This solution was then used to inoculate a large volume of LB, which was grown overnight at 37&#x000b0;C. The overnight culture was centrifuged at 10,000 RCF for 10 min, and the supernatant was brought to 3% PEG 8000, 0.5 M NaCl and left overnight at 4&#x000b0;C to precipitate the phage. After centrifugation at 5000 RCF for 10 min at 4&#x000b0;C the phage pellet was resuspended in 10 mM Tris pH 7.6, 10 mM NaCl and the single-stranded M13 mp18 circular DNA was purified by phenol-extraction.</p><p>Duplex DNAs were annealed by heating complementary DNA strands in 150 mM NaCl and 20 mM HEPES (pH 7.5) to 95&#x000b0;C for 5 min and slow cooling overnight to 20&#x000b0;C. 5&#x02032;-<sup>32</sup>P oligonucleotide labeling used &#x003b3;-<sup>32</sup>P-ATP and T4 polynucleotide kinase as per the manufacturer (New England Biolab) instructions.</p></sec><sec id="SEC2-3"><title>Oxidation of Pol &#x003b3;</title><p>Pol &#x003b3; (5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M) was incubated with 50, 100, 250, 500 &#x003bc;M or 1 mM hydrogen peroxide (H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>) at 37&#x000b0;C for 1 h. Oxidized Pol &#x003b3; integrity was analyzed by dynamic light scattering (DLS) using a Malven Zetasizer &#x003bc;V apparatus. Briefly, 2.75 &#x003bc;M untreated and 1&#x000a0;mM H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>-treated Pol &#x003b3; were measured at 830 nm at 20&#x000b0;C in solution containing 20 mM HEPES (pH 7.5), 140 mM KCl and 5% glycerol. Data were processed using Zetasizer 7.11 software.</p></sec><sec id="SEC2-4"><title>Exonuclease activity assays</title><p>Reactions were carried out in RX buffer (10 mM HEPES pH 7.5, 10% glycerol, 140 mM KCl and 1 mM EDTA). 200 nM Pol &#x003b3; was pre-incubated with 500 nM 5&#x02032;-<sup>32</sup>P-26 nt DNA (M13-26-primer in Table <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) for 5 min at 37&#x000b0;C. Reactions were initiated by the addition of 10 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, and quenched at the indicated times by addition of four reaction volumes of Q buffer (80% formamide, 1% SDS, 25 mM EDTA, pH 8.0) and heated at 95&#x000b0;C for 5 min. Reaction products were resolved by electrophoresis on a 20% denaturing (7M urea) polyacrylamide gel and quantified on a GE Typhoon 9500 at 100 &#x003bc;m using ImageQuant 7.1. The apparent rate of substrate digestion was estimated by fitting the time-dependent fraction of substrate reduction from the initial rate for untreated and H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> oxidized Pol &#x003b3;.</p></sec><sec id="SEC2-5"><title>Polymerase activity assay</title><p>50 nM Pol &#x003b3; was pre-incubated with 100 nM M13 mp18 ssDNA annealed with the 5&#x02032;-<sup>32</sup>P-26 nt primer (M13-26nt-primer, Table <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) in RX buffer for 5 min at 37&#x000b0;C. Reactions were initiated by addition of 400 &#x003bc;M each dNTPs and 10 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub> and quenched with Q buffer at the indicated times. Reaction products were heated at 95&#x000b0;C and then resolved on an 8% denaturing (7 M urea) polyacrylamide gel and quantified by ImageQuant 7.1</p></sec><sec id="SEC2-6"><title>Mismatch primer DNA excision and extension</title><p>Mismatch excision assays were conducted with 100 nM Pol &#x003b3; pre-incubated with 800 nM 26/40nt DNA containing a single mismatch at the primer 3&#x02032;-end (MM p/t, Table <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Excision of the mismatch was monitored as described above in <italic>Exonuclease activity assay</italic> on ssDNA.</p><p>Mismatch primer extension was carried out on the same 26/40 nt MM p/t DNA in the presences of 100&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M dNTP, 10&#x000a0;mM MgCl<sub>2</sub> for 30 min. The reactions were quenched as designated time by addition of buffer Q and heating to 95&#x000b0;C for 5 min. To distinguish Pol &#x003b3; mismatch removal in the coupled excision and extension reactions, duplicated samples were prepared where HindIII was added following the mismatch p/t synthesis. Reaction products were analyzed on a 20% denaturing acrylamide gel and quantified by ImageQuant 7.1.</p></sec><sec id="SEC2-7"><title>Mass spectrometry</title><sec id="SEC2-7-1"><title>Sample preparation</title><p>Samples were proteolyzed by either trypsin or combination of trypsin and GluC. Prior to protease digestion, 110 &#x003bc;l untreated or oxidized Pol &#x003b3; heterotrimer (1&#x003bc;M) were denatured in 5% SDS at room temperature overnight, then mixed with 4&#x003bc;l iodoacetemide (0.5M) for 40 minutes to alkylate the cysteine residues while being protected from light. 10 &#x003bc;l phosphoric acid (12%) was added to the protein solutions. The proteins were diluted with 650 &#x003bc;l S-Trap Buffer (100 mM triethylammonium bicarbonate (TEAB, pH 8.0) and 90% methanol), and applied to S-Trap Mini Spin Columns. The columns were centrifuged at 1000 RCF for 2 min and washed twice with 150 &#x003bc;l S-Trap buffer.</p><p>For trypsin only digestion, trypsin in 100 mM TEAB (pH 8.0) was added to the S-Trap column at a 1:10 weight to weight ratio of Pol &#x003b3; and digested at 37&#x000b0;C overnight. The digested peptides were eluted by centrifugation at 1000 g for 2 min sequentially with the following solution: 40 &#x003bc;l TEAB (pH 8.0), 40 &#x003bc;l 0.2% aqueous formic acid, 35 &#x003bc;l 50% acetonitrile and 0.2% formic acid, 80% acetonitrile and 0.2% formic acid. The elutants were combined and dried in a SpeedVac vacuum concentrator and reconstituted in 2% acetonitrile and 0.1% formic acid.</p><p>For trypsin and GluC digestions, the trypsin overnight digestion was eluted with 40 &#x003bc;l 100 mM TEAB (pH 8.0) solution, to which GluC was added at a 1:10 weight to weight ratio of Pol &#x003b3;. The protease solution was loaded onto a S-Trap Column and digested at 47 &#x000b0;C for 2 h. The digested peptide was eluted using the procedure described above for final elution of peptides digested by trypsin alone.</p></sec><sec id="SEC2-7-2"><title>Data acquisition and analyses</title><p>Nano-LC/MS/MS was performed on a Thermo Scientific Orbitrap Fusion system, coupled with a Dionex Ultimat 3000 nano HPLC and auto sampler with 40-well standard trays. Samples were injected onto a C18 PepMap100 trap column (300 &#x003bc;m &#x000d7;&#x000a0;5 mm) followed by a C18 reverse-phase nano LC column (75 &#x003bc;m &#x000d7; 25 cm, Thermo Fisher Scientific) at flow rate of 400 nl/min with an acetonitrile gradient (0&#x02013;99.9% in 0.1% formic acid) for 60 min at 50&#x000b0;C. The eluted peptides were sprayed through a +2.2 kV charged 10&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1 &#x003bc;m emitter tip (PicoTip Emitter, New Objective) into the mass spectrometer. Fourier transform mass spectrometry mode was enabled for acquisition of precursor ions, with resolution set to 120 000, and Ion Trap mode was used for subsequent MS/MS via higher-energy collisional dissociation at top speed every 3 s.</p><p>Proteome Discoverer 1.4 was used for protein post-translational modification identification and peak detection. The UniProt human database was used to analyze raw data. Carbamidomethyl cysteine, deaminated asparagine and glutamine as well as other amino acids modifications were treated as dynamic modifications. Two missed protease cleavages were allowed and the precursor mass tolerance was set at 10 ppm. MS/MS fragment mass tolerance was set at 0.6 Da, and peptides with +2, +3 or +4 charges were considered. Only peptides with a false discovery rate &#x0003c;1% were considered.</p><p>For a given residue <italic>r</italic>, its oxidation was defined as in Equation <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="M1">1</xref>: The fraction oxidized (<italic>f<sub>r</sub></italic>) is the sum of the peptide (<italic>P</italic>) peak heights (<italic>h<sub>P</sub></italic>) that contain the oxidized (<italic>ox</italic>) residue divided by the sum of the heights of any form of the peptide. The relative residue oxidation (<italic>F<sub>r</sub></italic>) is <italic>f<sub>r</sub></italic> normalized against the average oxidation fraction (<italic>f&#x02019;</italic>).<disp-formula id="M1"><label>(1)</label><tex-math id="M2">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
}{}$$\begin{equation*}{{{f}}_{{r}}} = \frac{\sum ({Hp\, of\, peptides\, containing\, r}_{ox})}{\sum (Hp\, of\, all\, peptides\, containing\, r)}\ ,\,{{{F}}_{{r}}} = \frac{{{{{f}}_{{r}}}}}{{{{f^{\prime}}}}}\end{equation*}$$\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula></p><p>Oxidized arginines may prevent trypsin digestion, thus reduces the peptide detection in oxidized regions. Furthermore, we set the threshold for oxidation high to reduce false positives. This stringent search strategy could increase false negatives but should decrease false positives, thus likely underestimates oxidized residues.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="SEC3"><title>RESULTS</title><sec id="SEC3-1"><title>Oxidation reduces Pol &#x003b3; exonuclease activity</title><p>The 3&#x02032;&#x02192;5&#x02032; exonuclease activity of untreated and oxidized Pol &#x003b3; was assayed using a 5&#x02032;-<sup>32</sup>P-26 nt single-stranded DNA (M13-26-primer in Table <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The nuclease activity was measured by quantifying the remaining substrate normalized by the total density within the lane, and then fitted to single exponential model to determine the apparent reaction rates (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>).</p><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Oxidation decreases Pol &#x003b3; exo activity. (<bold>A</bold>) the time-dependent exonuclease activity on single-stranded DNA. (<bold>B</bold>) Quantification of digested substrate from each sample normalized by the total accounts within the lane. The means and standard errors are calculated from three independent experiments.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkz1018fig1"/></fig><p>The rate of ssDNA degradation by untreated Pol &#x003b3; was 0.25 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, those for oxidized Pol &#x003b3; treated with 50 &#x003bc;M, 100 &#x003bc;M, 250 &#x003bc;M, 500 &#x003bc;M and 1 mM hydrogen peroxide were 0.19, 0.16, 0.13, 0.11 to 0.03 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, respectively (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B</xref>). Even at the lowest H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> treatment concentration the polymerase already shows an 24% reduction in nucleolytic rate. The maximally oxidized Pol &#x003b3; showed a greater than 8-fold reduction in nuclease excision rate relative to the untreated enzyme.</p></sec><sec id="SEC3-2"><title>Oxidation does not damage Pol &#x003b3; physically</title><p>To analyze whether oxidation-induced Pol &#x003b3; activity changes was caused by its physical damage, we compared molecular dimension of untreated and oxidized Pol &#x003b3; by dynamic light scattering to detect aggregation or protein unfolding. The radius of the enzyme oxidized with 1mM H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> was 7.7 nm compared to 7.4 nm for the untreated enzyme; both forms were also monodispersed (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Figure S1A</xref>). No crosslinking of Pol &#x003b3; due to H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> treatment was detected by SDS PAGE (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Figure S1B</xref>), we thus conclude that oxidative treatment with H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> does not cause significant physical alterations to Pol &#x003b3;.</p></sec><sec id="SEC3-3"><title>Oxidized Pol &#x003b3; maintains normal polymerization activity</title><p>DNA synthesis activity of oxidized Pol &#x003b3; were carried out on a singly primed M13 mp18 ssDNA by a 5&#x02032;-<sup>32</sup>P-26nt primer (M13-26-prime, Table <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Due to the location of the primer to a long hairpin at the M13 replication origin, the maximum extended product is &#x0223c;1000 nt. The untreated and oxidized Pol &#x003b3; exhibited similar activities. Quantification of time-dependent full-length (sum of 500&#x02013;1000 nt) products showed that polymerase oxidized with 50 &#x003bc;M, 100 &#x003bc;M, 250 &#x003bc;M, 500 &#x003bc;M and 1 mM H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> all produced comparable products in length and quantity to the untreated enzyme (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). As the primer is end-labeled, the length and quantify of DNA correlate with processivity and synthesis rate. The results suggest that oxidation has differential effects on Pol &#x003b3; <italic>pol</italic> and <italic>exo</italic> activities, unlike <italic>exo</italic> activity, the <italic>pol</italic> activity is much less sensitive to oxidation.</p><fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Oxidized Pol &#x003b3; pol activity. (<bold>A</bold>) DNA synthesis activity of untreated and treated Pol &#x003b3; measured on a singly primed M13mp18 ssDNA, (<bold>B</bold>) Quantification the fraction of full-length products that sums the product between 500 and 1000 nt then normalized by the total counts within the lane. Data were averaged from three independent reactions.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkz1018fig2"/></fig></sec><sec id="SEC3-4"><title>Synthesis at mismatched DNA</title><p>The above results suggest that oxidation maintains Pol &#x003b3; DNA synthesis but reduces proofreading, thus the oxidized Pol &#x003b3; should become more error-prone relative to the untreated polymerase. To test the hypothesis, we measured oxidized Pol &#x003b3;&#x02019;s ability to synthesize on the 26/40 nt dsDNA where the primer 3&#x02032;-end residue cytosine is a mismatch with the templating T (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref>), which mimics the product of erroneous nucleotide incorporation. The mismatched DNA therefore can assay Pol &#x003b3;&#x02019;s nucleolysis and polymerase activities simultaneously.</p><fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Effects of oxidation on mismatch extension and excision. (<bold>A</bold>) The schematic of the substrate with a 1-nt mismatch at the 3&#x02032;-end primer used in primer extension and excision assays. The asterisk indicates 5&#x02032;-<sup>32</sup>P labeling. (<bold>B</bold>) Time-dependent mismatched primer extension by untreated, treated and exo-deficient Pol &#x003b3;. (<bold>C</bold>) Mismatched primer excision by untreated, H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> treated, and exo-deficient Pol &#x003b3;. (<bold>D</bold>) Quantification of fraction of mismatch primer extension to full-length at 120 s from data presented in (B). (<bold>E</bold>) Quantification mismatched primer in panel (C). The mean and standard deviation were determined from three independent experiments.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkz1018fig3"/></fig><p>Synthesis of the mismatched DNA was assayed with untreated, oxidized, and exo-deficient Pol &#x003b3; (exo<sup>&#x02212;</sup>, containing D198A/E200A substitutions). Pol &#x003b3; exo<sup>&#x02212;</sup> retains wild-type <italic>pol</italic> activity but &#x0223c;1% of <italic>exo</italic> activity (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>), therefore should only perform error-prone DNA synthesis by burying the mismatch. Within 60 s, untreated Pol &#x003b3; completely extended the mismatched primer to full-length 40 nt, but Pol &#x003b3; exo<sup>&#x02212;</sup>&#x000a0;produced less than 1% of 40 nt, indicating extension of the 3&#x02032;-mismatch primer is very slow. The oxidized Pol &#x003b3; displayed H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> concentration-dependent reduction of full-length DNA. The rate of full-length synthesis for the most oxidized Pol &#x003b3; (1 mM H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>) is &#x0223c;10% of the untreated enzyme. Notably, relative to untreated Pol &#x003b3;, the excised product 25 nt appeared later in time for the oxidized samples, and the delay is correlated with H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> concentration. The delayed appearance of the 25 nt DNA is consistent with reduced exonuclease activity in the oxidized polymerase.</p><p>We next tested oxidized Pol &#x003b3; proofreading activity on the same mismatched 26/40 nt duplex. While the untreated Pol &#x003b3; excised 50% of the mismatch nucleotide from the primer in 15 s, resulting apparent rate 1.66 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> for the mismatch removal. Smaller products appeared after longer reaction times, suggesting correctly base-paired primer being excised, but at slower rate than the unpaired. Comparison to the quantity of 25 nt made by untreated enzyme, the least oxidized Pol &#x003b3; (50 &#x003bc;M H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>) is&#x000a0;2.5-fold less, and the most oxidized Pol &#x003b3; (1 mM H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>) is 11-fold less efficient in mismatch removal (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3C</xref>). The results suggest slow extension of mismatched primer by oxidized and exo<sup>&#x02212;</sup> Pol &#x003b3; is, in part, caused by reduced mismatch removal, and mismatch-burying extension is slower than the combined rates of error removal and error-free extension.</p></sec><sec id="SEC3-5"><title>Fidelity of the oxidized Pol &#x003b3;</title><p>The above results suggest that the extension from the mismatched primer is a mixture of mismatch containing and corrected products. We designed the 26/40 nt mismatch dsDNA that allows for distinguishing error-prone from error-free synthesis by including a HindIII site in the error-free full-length product. The error-free product (E40 bp, Table <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) from Pol &#x003b3; excision of the mismatch will constitute a HindIII site and will be cleaved by the restriction enzyme into two fragments of 24/28 nt and 22 nt/26 nt, whereas the full-length product buried the mismatch (B40 bp, Table <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) will be resistant to HindIII digestion and remains as an intact 40 bp DNA in the presence of HindIII (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4A</xref>). The ratio of HindIII undigested to digested 40 bp DNA gives rise ratio of error-prone to error-free synthesis products.</p><fig id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Effect of oxidation on polymerase replication fidelity. (<bold>A</bold>) The scheme for distinguishing error-free and error-prone DNA synthesis on the designed mismatched primer/template DNA. The asterisk indicates 5&#x02032;-<sup>32</sup>P labeling. (<bold>B</bold>) Products of mismatched DNA extension and digestion by HindIII by Pol &#x003b3; treated with H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and the <italic>exo</italic>-deficient variant. (<bold>C</bold>) Quantification of the undigested band divided by the sum of all density within the lane.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkz1018fig4"/></fig><p>Mismatch extension assays were carried out for 30 min to allow oxidized Pol &#x003b3; to produce substantial 40 bp DNA for analyses, and the dNTP concentration is kept low (100 &#x003bc;M) to reduce misincorporation. While the untreated Pol &#x003b3; extended 82% of the primer to full-length (40 nt) product in 60 s (calculated from data in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref>), Pol &#x003b3; exo<sup>&#x02212;</sup> generated only 30% of the full-length product in 30 min (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4B</xref>), suggesting the polymerase generated 82-fold more full-length products from the correctly base paired primer than mismatch-burying synthesis at a unit time. The error-prone/error-free product ratio for the untreated Pol &#x003b3; is &#x0003c;0.9%, whereas the ratio for Pol &#x003b3; exo<sup>&#x02212;</sup>&#x000a0;is 94%, as majority of the 40 bp DNA were undigested. The date show that the <italic>exo</italic> proofreading activity can correct &#x0003e;99% of misincorporated nucleotide, potentially reducing replication error by &#x0223c;100-fold, which are in good agreement with previously reported exonuclease activity on DNA replication fidelity by Pol &#x003b3; and other high fidelity polymerases (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28&#x02013;31</xref>).</p><p>Pol &#x003b3; error-free DNA synthesis declines with increased H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> concentration. Within reported physiological H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> concentration (50&#x02013;200 &#x003bc;M), the error-rate of oxidized Pol &#x003b3; increased 2&#x02013;3-fold relate to the untreated. The ratio error-prone/error-free product for Pol &#x003b3; oxidized at 1 mM H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> is merely 18%, which is 20-fold higher than the untreated Pol &#x003b3; and only 5-fold lower than the catalytic residue double mutant exo-deficient variant (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4C</xref>). These results suggest that Pol &#x003b3; can significantly increase mutations during DNA replication under oxidative stress. Furthermore, as the oxidation does not affect <italic>pol</italic> activity on correctly base paired DNA, the overall reduced synthesis on mismatch containing DNA by oxidized Pol &#x003b3; is caused by combination of slow rates of error correction and mismatch burying DNA synthesis.</p></sec><sec id="SEC3-6"><title>Identification of oxidation hotspots</title><p>To reveal the chemical basis for oxidation-induced Pol &#x003b3; functional changes, we used liquid chromatography with tandem mass spectrometry (LC&#x02013;MS/MS) to identify residues oxidized by H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>. Analyses were carried out in replicas of untreated Pol &#x003b3; and treated with 500 &#x003bc;M H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> or 1 mM H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>. Pol &#x003b3; is a holoenzyme comprised of a catalytic subunit Pol &#x003b3;A and an accessory subunit Pol &#x003b3;B. The Pol &#x003b3;A used in this study contains 1204 amino acids which lacks the N-terminal 35 amino acids mitochondrial localization sequence; its exonuclease (<italic>exo</italic>) domain is located within residues 170&#x02013;440, and polymerase (<italic>pol</italic>) domain in residue 441&#x02013;475 and 784&#x02013;1239. Among five LC&#x02013;MS/MS experiments (two untreated and three oxidized samples), the overall recovered peptides are within 70&#x02013;90% of the total residues (Table <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Only residues detected in both untreated and treated samples, i.e. 926 amino acid in Pol &#x003b3;A and 331 in Pol &#x003b3;B, were used for further analyses.</p><table-wrap id="tbl2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>MS analyses coverage</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">Trial 1</th><th colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">Trial 2</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> treatment</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">untreated</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 mM</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">untreated</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5 mM</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 mM</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coverage of Pol &#x003b3;A Subunit</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Coverage of Pol &#x003b3;B Subunit</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>The degree of overall oxidation increases with elevated H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> concentrations, displaying 1.5- and 1.9-fold increase over the untreated protein for the 0.5 and 1 mM treated polymerase, respectively (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref>). Nevertheless, the amino acid locations of the most oxidized residues are highly consistent among treated proteins, regardless of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> concentration. Among three different experiments, 45% detected oxidized residues are at identical locations, 63% are within &#x000b1;1 and 90% are within &#x000b1;2 positions from each other (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>). For example, adjacent residues Ala<sup>266</sup> and Phe<sup>267</sup> were detected in different experiments, which were denoted as Ala<sup>266</sup>/Phe<sup>267</sup> (Table <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). The variation could be attributed to either partial oxidized residue assignment uncertainty in the processing software or spatially adjacent residues can all be oxidized but detected independently in different experiments. In either case, the MS method can identify oxidized amino acids with precision of &#x000b1;2 positions.</p><fig id="F5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Structural illustration of oxidized Pol &#x003b3; residues. (<bold>A</bold>) The overall fraction of oxidation (<italic>F<sub>r</sub></italic>, Equation <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="M1">1</xref>) for 500 &#x003bc;M and 1 mM H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> treated Pol &#x003b3;, relative to the untreated. (<bold>B</bold>) Consistency of oxidized residues from three different oxidation experiments (<bold>C</bold>) The average oxidation <italic>Fr</italic> of <italic>pol</italic> (red) and <italic>exo</italic> (green) active sites. (<bold>D</bold>) Oxidized residues of untreated (left) and 1 mM H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> treated (right) catalytic subunit displayed on Pol &#x003b3; holoenzyme ternary complex structure (PDB ID: 4ztz). Oxidation of each residue is color-coded by <italic>F<sub>r</sub></italic>. Oxidation clusters are indicated. (<bold>E</bold>) Oxidation of the <italic>pol</italic> site. The asterisk marks the location of <italic>pol</italic> catalytic residues D890. (<bold>F</bold>) Oxidation of the <italic>exo</italic> site. The asterisk marks the exo catalytic residue D198.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkz1018fig5"/></fig><table-wrap id="tbl3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Top 20 most oxidized amino acid clusters in Pol &#x003b3; detected by mass spectrometry</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subunit</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amino acid</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Domain</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ser296</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exo</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cys396</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exo</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ala397</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exo</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Val400, Trp401</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exo</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Thr403, His404</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exo</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asp482</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exo</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asp487</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exo</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leu528,Leu530</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spacer</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">C533</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spacer</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glu535,Glu536</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spacer</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Glu538</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spacer</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gln540,Gln541</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spacer</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ala547,Cys548</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spacer</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gln595</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spacer</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">A</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">His1110, Leu1111</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pol</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phe266,Ala267</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Asn282</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">His313,Tyr315</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Leu347,Ala348</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">B</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tyr432</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="T3TFN1"><p>Note: the residues listed on the same line are those detected within &#x000b1;2 positions from each other in separate experiments.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>To detect any oxidation clusters, or &#x02018;hotspots&#x02019;, we mapped the oxidized residues on the Pol &#x003b3;&#x02013;DNA&#x02013;dNTP ternary complex crystal structure (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). Both Pol &#x003b3;A and Pol &#x003b3;B subunits have highly oxidized amino acids. Of the top 20 most oxidized residues, 15 are located on Pol &#x003b3;A and five on Pol &#x003b3;B (Table <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). The oxidized residues on Pol &#x003b3;B are centered around Ala<sup>266</sup>/Phe<sup>267</sup> and Asn<sup>282</sup>. As Pol &#x003b3;B is a homodimer, these residues could be located on either the proximal monomer at the interface with Pol &#x003b3;A or the distal monomer that is nonfunctional to the holoenzyme (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Figure S2</xref>). The mass spec analysis alone cannot provide definitive identification. However, Oxidation of the proximal Pol &#x003b3;B monomer would affect the holoenzyme formation and potentially reduce DNA synthesis processivity, whereas oxidation of the distal monomer oxidation has no or minimum effect on Pol &#x003b3; processivity. As the holoenzyme DNA synthesis is unaffected, the oxidized residues are probably located on the distal monomer of Pol &#x003b3;B.</p><p>On the contrary, Pol &#x003b3;A oxidized residues are clustered around three areas that could significantly impact the polymerase function. Using <italic>K</italic>-means clustering method, three oxidation hotspots were revealed, which were designated as Clusters I, II and III.</p><p>Cluster I is located in the <italic>exo</italic> domain and contains 22 oxidized residues (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5D</xref>). Cluster I displayed an average Relative Oxidation Fraction (<italic>F<sub>r</sub></italic>, Equation <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="M1">1</xref>) 60-fold higher than the protein mean (&#x00192;'). Residues Cys <sup>396</sup>, Ala <sup>397</sup>, Val<sup>400</sup> and His<sup>404</sup> are among the most oxidized residues in both 0.5 mM and 1 mM H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> treated samples (Table <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Ala<sup>397</sup> and Val<sup>400</sup> were hydroxyl- modified, and C<sup>396</sup> was converted to sulfonic acid with addition of two carbonyl oxygens to the sulfur. His<sup>404</sup> lost its imidazole ring and was converted to 2-amino-5,6-dioxohexanoic acid (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Figure S3</xref>, Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>). Structurally, Cys<sup>396</sup>, Ala<sup>397</sup> and Val<sup>400</sup> are highly conserved among mitochondrial polymerases (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>); His<sup>404</sup> is conserved not only among mitochondrial DNA polymerases but also in Pol I family members. Oxidation of the histidine in T7 DNAP reduces exonuclease activity (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). Although we did not detect oxidative damage to the catalytic residues (Asp<sup>198</sup> and Glu<sup>200</sup>) for exonuclease activity, all above oxidative modifications increase negative charges in the <italic>exo</italic> active site (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5F</xref>), which would reduce <italic>exo</italic> activity by reducing its affinity to DNA substrate.</p><fig id="F6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Chemical structures of detected oxidized residues.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkz1018fig6"/></fig><p>Cluster II contains 13 residues in the AID subdomain of the Spacer domain (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5D</xref>). The AID subdomain (residues 511&#x02013;570) (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>)&#x000a0;interacts with the accessory subunit Pol &#x003b3;B in the holoenzyme primarily via the L-helix and disordered loops&#x000a0;(<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). The region displayed an average <italic>F<sub>r</sub></italic> value 80-fold higher than the &#x00192;&#x02019; (Table <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="table">3</xref>), specifically, residues on the L-helix Leu<sup>528</sup>/Leu<sup>530</sup>, Cys<sup>533</sup>, Glu <sup>535</sup>/Glu<sup>536</sup> and Ala<sup>547</sup>/Cys<sup>548</sup>. Apart from the Cysteine residues which were converted to sulfonic acid, the rest of them acquired an carbonyl or hydroxyl group. Hydroxyl-Ala<sup>547</sup> results in A547S missense mutation (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>). However, these residue side chains face away from the subunit interface and are thus less likely to alter subunit interaction.</p><p>Cluster III contains residues on the Pol &#x003b3; Thumb subdomain (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5D</xref>), including Cys<sup>471</sup>, Asp<sup>482</sup>/Trp<sup>484</sup>, Trp<sup>486</sup>/Asp<sup>487</sup>, Cys<sup>647</sup>, Ser<sup>759</sup>/Cys<sup>760</sup>. Residue modifications include that Cys<sup>533</sup> and Cys<sup>548</sup> were converted to sulfonic acid, Glu<sup>535</sup> and Glu<sup>536</sup> acquired a carbonyl group, the rest of the residues acquired an hydroxyl group. The <italic>Thumb</italic> is critical for DNA binding and transferring the primer stand between the <italic>pol</italic> and <italic>exo</italic> sites (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>), oxidation of the subdomain may alter their relative activities.</p><p>Most notably, in contrast to the highly oxidized <italic>exo</italic> site, no significant oxidation was found in the <italic>pol</italic> active site (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5D</xref>-<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">F</xref>). Within 13 &#x000c5; radium of the active site, the average oxidized amino acid (<italic>F<sub>r</sub></italic>) in <italic>exo</italic> site is 10.8-fold above than the protein mean, whereas that of the <italic>pol</italic> site is merely 1.2-fold over the protein mean (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5C</xref>). These results explain the different impact of oxidation on polymerase and exonuclease activities, providing a chemical basis for the editing-deficient phenotype of oxidized Pol &#x003b3;.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="SEC4"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>Mutations on mtDNA can disrupt cellular energy supply and cell cycle control, and are implicated in physiological process of aging, and pathology of neurodegeneration such as Alzheimer's and Parkinson diseases (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). A mitochondrion contains 10&#x02013;1000 copies of mtDNA; reduced mtDNA copy number and/or increased mutations will have detrimental effect on cellular and organelle functions. Factors contributing to mtDNA mutations are incomplete repair of DNA, oxidative stress and replication errors.</p><p>The mitochondrial matrix houses significant quantities of reactive oxygen species (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>), which are generated continuously by the oxidative phosphorylation electron transfer chain even while operating normally (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Reactive oxygen species (ROS) include superoxide anions, hydroxyl radical and hydrogen peroxide (H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>). A moderate increase in ROS can promote cell proliferation and differentiation. Nevertheless, under pathological conditions, such as cancer or degenerative diseases, ROS levels are severely elevated and disrupt redox homeostasis, leading to cell death (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). The reported H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> concentration varied greatly, from 50 to 200 &#x003bc;M (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>), up to 1&#x02013;2% of the molecular oxygen in cells (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>). We chose a wide range of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> concentrations in this study to explore differential oxidative propensity of Pol &#x003b3; <italic>pol</italic> and <italic>exo</italic> activities.</p><p>Mitochondrial DNA replicase Pol &#x003b3; is a high fidelity polymerase and contains proofreading ability to excise misincorporation in the <italic>exo</italic> site. Pol &#x003b3; replication error frequency is 2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02212;6</sup> where the <italic>exo</italic> proofreading contributes 10<sup>1</sup>&#x02013;10<sup>2</sup>-fold towards error reduction (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>), similar to other high fidelity polymerases (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>). Thus, exonuclease-deficient Pol &#x003b3; could potentially elevate mutations by two orders of magnitude.</p><p>We show in this study that oxidation of Pol &#x003b3; can increase replication errors that is positively correlated with the level of ROS. Within a relatively wide concentration range of hydrogen peroxide (50 &#x003bc;M&#x02013;1 mM), Pol &#x003b3; maintains normal polymerase activity but displays H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> concentration-dependent declined exonuclease activity. Under oxidative stress, the short-term effect is that Pol &#x003b3; could become an editing-deficient polymerase with proofreading ability reduced up to 20-fold. The long-term effect will be the overall mtDNA synthesis declines, because oxidized Pol &#x003b3; buries rather than corrects erroneously incorporated nucleotides and synthesis of burying a mismatch is much slower than extension of a correctly matched primer. Therefore, oxidation can exert dual-negative impact on Pol &#x003b3; replication: increased mutations and ultimately reduced mtDNA copy number.</p><p>The high ROS contents in mitochondria undoubtedly results oxidized mtDNA and proteins. MtDNA mutations have been observed increase with age, leading to the radicals theory in ageing where free radicals directly damage DNA thus causes mutations (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>). A weak point of the theory is that radical induced DNA damage cannot be rescued by DNA glycosylases that repair primary oxidized nucleobase, and glycosylases level does not correlate with longevity, diminishing the contribution of direction DNA oxidation. In this study, we found that oxidation reduces Pol &#x003b3; proofreading ability, which reduces replication fidelity and indirectly increases mtDNA mutations. Our results are consistent with somatic mtDNA mutations are largely random and not transversion, supporting that ROS induced mtDNA mutations are mainly results from replication errors rather than direct DNA damage. It is probable that mutations in ageing and other degenerative diseases are also the consequences of Pol &#x003b3; oxidation.</p><p>Pol &#x003b3; proofreading deficient mutations have been well-documented in human diseases and aging. Mice carrying <italic>exo</italic>-deficient Pol &#x003b3; (D257A) showed only 4-fold elevated mtDNA mutation but exhibited severe premature aging phenomenon (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). Mice carrying <italic>pol</italic>-deficient mutant Pol &#x003b3; (D1135A) displayed reduced mtDNA contents and peripheral aging characteristics with inflamed wrinkled skin and hair loss (<xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>). Our oxidation experiments subjected Pol &#x003b3; to hydrogen peroxide for only one hour, which has already produced significantly reduced <italic>exo</italic> activity. Higher concentration of ROS or longer exposure would generate greater damage to Pol &#x003b3;, rendering <italic>exo</italic>-deficient or completely inactive polymerase.</p><p>Oxidation damages both DNA and proteins, but proteins are far more sensitive to oxidation than DNA (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>). Oxidation can disrupt protein-protein interactions (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>), inhibit protein activity (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>), or up-regulate protein expression level (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>). The ROS imposes a threat particular to mitochondrial proteins, impairing metabolism and energy production. In nonalcoholic liver failure, more than 140 mitochondrial proteins are found to suffer from oxidative damage (<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>). We show here that oxidized Pol &#x003b3; increases mtDNA mutations, which, in turn, could exacerbate mitochondrial oxidative stress that may further damage Pol &#x003b3;, creating a cycle of oxidative stress (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>). To alleviate oxidative damage, Pol &#x003b3;, and perhaps many other mitochondrial proteins, should have evolved to be either more resistant to oxidation than nuclear polymerases or are turned over faster once oxidized. For example, Pol &#x003b3;A alone is more sensitive to oxidation, but becomes more resistant once complexed with the accessory subunit Pol &#x003b3;B (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>).</p><fig id="F7" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>Cooperation for protein and DNA oxidative damage.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gkz1018fig7"/></fig><p>Mass spectrometry is a reliable method for oxidative residue detection, among different experiments an oxidized amino acid can be identified with accuracy within two positions in protein sequence. The detection limit is due to difficulty in resolving adjacent oxidized amino acids. While oxidation induced protein backbone breakage can occur under extreme circumstances, side chain damages are more abundant and diverse at lower ROS. Interestingly, the oxidized amino acids we detected are not exclusively follow the reactive rate for amino acid oxidation measured individually (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>), e.g. Tyr, Phe and Met have the highest rate constants as single amino acid, but were not abundant in oxidized Pol &#x003b3;, suggesting the 3D structure or solvent accessibility play an important role in residue oxidation. Pol &#x003b3; displays a few hotspots for oxidation via a variety of side chain oxidations. The most prominent one is located in the <italic>exo</italic> active site, which exhibits relatively large solvent access surface. Oxidation enhances the negative charge in the <italic>exo</italic> site thus reduces its affinity to DNA. Contrary to <italic>exo</italic> site, the <italic>pol</italic> site is buried in a deep cavity in the polymerase, with a narrow tunnel for transporting substrate nucleotide (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). This feature, conserved among Pol I family members, may be beneficial in discouraging dissociation of the bound nucleotide, and also in preserving the rudimentary activity of the polymerase under oxidation insult. This bias towards synthesis over error-correction may be embedded in the structure of the polymerases: during high fidelity DNA replication, the primer/template DNA is frequently transferred between Pol &#x003b3; <italic>pol</italic> and <italic>exo</italic> sites that are separated by 35&#x02013;40 &#x000c5; for error correction. The shuttling between the two active sites is a slow step in DNA replication. If both <italic>exo</italic> and <italic>pol</italic> active sites were located in deep cavities, they may impose physical constraints that could limit primer strand transferring, reducing both replication rate and fidelity.</p><p>Pol &#x003b3; is an adverse reaction target for antiviral reagents designed against HIV, especially the nucleoside analog inhibitors HIV RT (NRTIs). Low toxic NRTIs are either being discriminated against its incorporation in the <italic>pol</italic> or excised from the primer stand in <italic>exo</italic> site: the most toxic NRTIs, Zalcitabine (ddC) is least likely to be excised in Pol &#x003b3; <italic>exo</italic>, whereas low toxic Emtricitabine (FTC) is excised from the primer DNA strand two orders of magnitude faster rate than ddC (<xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>), emphasizing the important of the proofreading activity in reducing NRTIs drug toxicity. The mutator phenotype of oxidized Pol &#x003b3; shows lower <italic>exo</italic> activity, potentially elevate antiviral drug toxicity. Conversely, NRTIs impose stress to mitochondria (<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>) and increase mtDNA replication errors. The observation shed lights on long-term usage of NRTIs resulted premature aging in patients.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sup1"><label>gkz1018_Supplemental_File</label><media xlink:href="gkz1018_supplemental_file.doc"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="ACK1"><title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title><p>We thank Ian Molineux for M13 phage and IJ338 cells, Geoffrey Hermann and Christie Shumate for preparing M13 ssDNA and Pol &#x003b3;A protein, Katherine Kaus for critical reading of the manuscript.</p></ack><sec id="SEC5"><title>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA</title><p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://academic.oup.com/nar/article-lookup/doi/10.1093/nar/gkz1018#supplementary-data">Supplementary Data</ext-link> are available at NAR Online.</p></sec><sec id="SEC6"><title>FUNDING</title><p>National Institutes of Health (NIH) [R01GM110591, R01AI13461, R01NS095747 and R01AI136031]; Sealy and Smith Foundation to Center for Structural Biology at University of Texas Medical Branch. Funding for open access charge: National Institutes of Health (NIH) [R01GM110591, R01AI13461, R01NS095747 and R01AI136031]; Sealy and Smith Foundation to Center for Structural Biology at University of Texas Medical Branch.</p><p>
<italic>Conflict of interest statement</italic>. None declared.</p></sec><ref-list id="REF1"><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bankier</surname><given-names>A.T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Barrell</surname><given-names>B.G.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de&#x000a0;Bruijn</surname><given-names>M.H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Coulson</surname><given-names>A.R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Drouin</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eperon</surname><given-names>I.C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nierlich</surname><given-names>D.P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roe</surname><given-names>B.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sanger</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group>
<article-title>Sequence and organization of the human mitochondrial genome</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>1981</year>; <volume>290</volume>:<fpage>457</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>465</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7219534</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>W.M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>George</surname><given-names>M.</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Rapid evolution of animal mitochondrial DNA</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source><year>1979</year>; <volume>76</volume>:<fpage>1967</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1971</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">109836</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>W.M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Prager</surname><given-names>E.M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>A.C.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Mitochondrial DNA sequences of primates: tempo and mode of evolution</article-title>. <source>J. Mol. Evol.</source><year>1982</year>; <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>225</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>239</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6284948</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonzalez-Freire</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de&#x000a0;Cabo</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bernier</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sollott</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fabbri</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Navas</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ferrucci</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Reconsidering the role of mitochondria in aging</article-title>. <source>J. Gerontol. A Biol. Sci. Med. Sci.</source><year>2015</year>; <volume>70</volume>:<fpage>1334</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1342</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25995290</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>D.C.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Mitochondrial DNA mutations in disease and aging</article-title>. <source>Environ. Mol. Mutagen.</source><year>2010</year>; <volume>51</volume>:<fpage>440</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>450</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20544884</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>D.K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>G.J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>C.H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>L.M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mauck</surname><given-names>W.M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Twu</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beal</surname><given-names>M.F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johns</surname><given-names>D.R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Somatic mitochondrial DNA mutations in cortex and substantia nigra in aging and Parkinson's disease</article-title>. <source>Neurobiol. Aging</source>. <year>2004</year>; <volume>25</volume>:<fpage>71</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>81</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14675733</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boveris</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chance</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The mitochondrial generation of hydrogen peroxide. General properties and effect of hyperbaric oxygen</article-title>. <source>Biochem. J.</source><year>1973</year>; <volume>134</volume>:<fpage>707</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>716</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4749271</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hanes</surname><given-names>J.W.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thal</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>K.A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Incorporation and replication of 8-oxo-deoxyguanosine by the human mitochondrial DNA polymerase</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2006</year>; <volume>281</volume>:<fpage>36241</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>36248</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17005553</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pursell</surname><given-names>Z.F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>J.T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mathews</surname><given-names>C.K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kunkel</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Trace amounts of 8-oxo-dGTP in mitochondrial dNTP pools reduce DNA polymerase gamma replication fidelity</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2008</year>; <volume>36</volume>:<fpage>2174</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2181</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18276636</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ameur</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>J.B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Freyer</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hagstrom</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ingman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Larsson</surname><given-names>N.G.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gyllensten</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Ultra-deep sequencing of mouse mitochondrial DNA: mutational patterns and their origins</article-title>. <source>PLos Genet.</source><year>2011</year>; <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>e1002028</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21455489</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Itsara</surname><given-names>L.S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>S.R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fox</surname><given-names>E.J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hewitt</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sanchez-Contreras</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cardozo-Pelaez</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pallanck</surname><given-names>L.J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Oxidative stress is not a major contributor to somatic mitochondrial DNA mutations</article-title>. <source>PLos Genet.</source><year>2014</year>; <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>e1003974</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24516391</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>S.R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Salk</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schmitt</surname><given-names>M.W.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Loeb</surname><given-names>L.A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Ultra-sensitive sequencing reveals an age-related increase in somatic mitochondrial mutations that are inconsistent with oxidative damage</article-title>. <source>PLos Genet.</source><year>2013</year>; <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>e1003794</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24086148</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fortini</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pascucci</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Parlanti</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>D&#x02019;Errico</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Simonelli</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dogliotti</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>8-Oxoguanine DNA damage: at the crossroad of alternative repair pathways</article-title>. <source>Mutat. Res.</source><year>2003</year>; <volume>531</volume>:<fpage>127</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>139</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14637250</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakabeppu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Regulation of intracellular localization of human MTH1, OGG1, and MYH proteins for repair of oxidative DNA damage</article-title>. <source>Prog. Nucleic Acid Res. Mol. Biol.</source><year>2001</year>; <volume>68</volume>:<fpage>75</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>94</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11554314</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boldogh</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Milligan</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>M.S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bassett</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lloyd</surname><given-names>R.S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McCullough</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>hMYH cell cycle-dependent expression, subcellular localization and association with replication foci: evidence suggesting replication-coupled repair of adenine:8-oxoguanine mispairs</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2001</year>; <volume>29</volume>:<fpage>2802</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2809</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11433026</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>de&#x000a0;Souza-Pinto</surname><given-names>N.C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eide</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hogue</surname><given-names>B.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thybo</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stevnsner</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seeberg</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klungland</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bohr</surname><given-names>V.A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Repair of 8-oxodeoxyguanosine lesions in mitochondrial dna depends on the oxoguanine dna glycosylase (OGG1) gene and 8-oxoguanine accumulates in the mitochondrial dna of OGG1-defective mice</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res.</source><year>2001</year>; <volume>61</volume>:<fpage>5378</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5381</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11454679</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Halsne</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Esbensen</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scheffler</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Suganthan</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bjoras</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eide</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Lack of the DNA glycosylases MYH and OGG1 in the cancer prone double mutant mouse does not increase mitochondrial DNA mutagenesis</article-title>. <source>DNA Repair (Amst.)</source>. <year>2012</year>; <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>278</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>285</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22209780</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Graziewicz</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Longley</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Copeland</surname><given-names>W.C.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>DNA polymerase gamma in mitochondrial DNA replication and repair</article-title>. <source>Chem. Rev.</source><year>2006</year>; <volume>106</volume>:<fpage>383</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>405</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16464011</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Graves</surname><given-names>S.W.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>K.A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Human mitochondrial DNA polymerase holoenzyme: reconstitution and characterization</article-title>. <source>Biochemistry</source>. <year>2000</year>; <volume>39</volume>:<fpage>1702</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1708</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10677218</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>S.E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Longley</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Copeland</surname><given-names>W.C.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The mitochondrial p55 accessory subunit of human DNA polymerase gamma enhances DNA binding, promotes processive DNA synthesis, and confers N-ethylmaleimide resistance</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>1999</year>; <volume>274</volume>:<fpage>38197</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>38203</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10608893</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y.S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>K.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Molineux</surname><given-names>I.J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>Y.W.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A single mutation in human mitochondrial DNA polymerase Pol gammaA affects both polymerization and proofreading activities of only the holoenzyme</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2010</year>; <volume>285</volume>:<fpage>28105</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>28116</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20513922</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y.S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Demeler</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Molineux</surname><given-names>I.J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>K.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>Y.W.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Each monomer of the dimeric accessory protein for human mitochondrial DNA polymerase has a distinct role in conferring processivity</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2010</year>; <volume>285</volume>:<fpage>1490</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1499</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19858216</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mott</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>S.W.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Denniger</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zassenhaus</surname><given-names>H.P.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Construction of transgenic mice with tissue-specific acceleration of mitochondrial DNA mutagenesis</article-title>. <source>Genomics</source>. <year>2000</year>; <volume>69</volume>:<fpage>151</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>161</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11031098</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Trifunovic</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wredenberg</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Falkenberg</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Spelbrink</surname><given-names>J.N.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rovio</surname><given-names>A.T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bruder</surname><given-names>C.E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bohlooly</surname><given-names>Y.M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gidlof</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oldfors</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wibom</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group>
<article-title>Premature ageing in mice expressing defective mitochondrial DNA polymerase</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2004</year>; <volume>429</volume>:<fpage>417</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>423</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15164064</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tabor</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>C.C.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Selective inactivation of the exonuclease activity of bacteriophage T7 DNA polymerase by in vitro mutagenesis</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>1989</year>; <volume>264</volume>:<fpage>6447</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6458</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2703498</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Graziewicz</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Day</surname><given-names>B.J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Copeland</surname><given-names>W.C.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The mitochondrial DNA polymerase as a target of oxidative damage</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2002</year>; <volume>30</volume>:<fpage>2817</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2824</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12087165</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y.S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>W.D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>Y.W.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Structural insights into human mitochondrial DNA replication and disease-related polymerase mutations</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>. <year>2009</year>; <volume>139</volume>:<fpage>312</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>324</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19837034</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>K.A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Exonuclease proofreading by human mitochondrial DNA polymerase</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2001</year>; <volume>276</volume>:<fpage>38097</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>38107</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11477094</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kunkel</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Loeb</surname><given-names>L.A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Fidelity of mammalian DNA polymerases</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>1981</year>; <volume>213</volume>:<fpage>765</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>767</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6454965</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Longley</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kunkel</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Copeland</surname><given-names>W.C.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The fidelity of human DNA polymerase gamma with and without exonucleolytic proofreading and the p55 accessory subunit</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2001</year>; <volume>276</volume>:<fpage>38555</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>38562</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11504725</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McCulloch</surname><given-names>S.D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kunkel</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The fidelity of DNA synthesis by eukaryotic replicative and translesion synthesis polymerases</article-title>. <source>Cell Res.</source><year>2008</year>; <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>148</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>161</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18166979</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Szymanski</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kuznetsov</surname><given-names>V.B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shumate</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y.S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>Y.W.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Structural basis for processivity and antiviral drug toxicity in human mitochondrial DNA replicase</article-title>. <source>EMBO J.</source><year>2015</year>; <volume>34</volume>:<fpage>1959</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1970</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26056153</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Katsonis</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lichtarge</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A formal perturbation equation between genotype and phenotype determines the Evolutionary Action of protein-coding variations on fitness</article-title>. <source>Genome Res.</source><year>2014</year>; <volume>24</volume>:<fpage>2050</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2058</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25217195</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>L.J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Naviaux</surname><given-names>R.K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brunetti-Pierri</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schmitt</surname><given-names>E.S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Truong</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Milone</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>B.H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wical</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ganesh</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group>
<article-title>Molecular and clinical genetics of mitochondrial diseases due to POLG mutations</article-title>. <source>Hum. Mutat.</source><year>2008</year>; <volume>29</volume>:<fpage>E150</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>E172</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18546365</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kowaltowski</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vercesi</surname><given-names>A.E.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Mitochondrial damage induced by conditions of oxidative stress</article-title>. <source>Free Radic. Biol. Med.</source><year>1999</year>; <volume>26</volume>:<fpage>463</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>471</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9895239</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adam-Vizi</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chinopoulos</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Bioenergetics and the formation of mitochondrial reactive oxygen species</article-title>. <source>Trends Pharmacol. Sci.</source><year>2006</year>; <volume>27</volume>:<fpage>639</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>645</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17056127</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Turrens</surname><given-names>J.F.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Superoxide production by the mitochondrial respiratory chain</article-title>. <source>Biosci. Rep.</source><year>1997</year>; <volume>17</volume>:<fpage>3</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9171915</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Malinouski</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Belousov</surname><given-names>V.V.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hatfield</surname><given-names>D.L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gladyshev</surname><given-names>V.N.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Hydrogen peroxide probes directed to different cellular compartments</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. <year>2011</year>; <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>e14564</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21283738</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ballinger</surname><given-names>S.W.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Patterson</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>C.N.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Doan</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Burow</surname><given-names>D.L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname><given-names>C.G.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yakes</surname><given-names>F.M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van&#x000a0;Houten</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ballinger</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>B.A.</given-names></name><etal>et al</etal>.</person-group>
<article-title>Hydrogen peroxide- and peroxynitrite-induced mitochondrial DNA damage and dysfunction in vascular endothelial and smooth muscle cells</article-title>. <source>Circ. Res.</source><year>2000</year>; <volume>86</volume>:<fpage>960</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>966</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10807868</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Boveris</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cadenas</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chance</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Ultraweak chemiluminescence: a sensitive assay for oxidative radical reactions</article-title>. <source>Fed. Proc.</source><year>1981</year>; <volume>40</volume>:<fpage>195</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>198</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7461143</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>K.A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Fidelity of nucleotide incorporation by human mitochondrial DNA polymerase</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source><year>2001</year>; <volume>276</volume>:<fpage>38090</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>38096</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11477093</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Loeb</surname><given-names>L.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Monnat</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name></person-group>
<article-title>DNA polymerases and human disease</article-title>. <source>Nat. Rev. Genet.</source><year>2008</year>; <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>594</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>604</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18626473</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schoeb</surname><given-names>T.R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bajpai</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Slominski</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>K.K.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Reversing wrinkled skin and hair loss in mice by restoring mitochondrial function</article-title>. <source>Cell Death Dis.</source><year>2018</year>; <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>735</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30026579</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Halliwell</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aruoma</surname><given-names>O.I.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>DNA damage by oxygen-derived species. Its mechanism and measurement in mammalian systems</article-title>. <source>FEBS Lett.</source><year>1991</year>; <volume>281</volume>:<fpage>9</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>19</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1849843</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chance</surname><given-names>M.R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Hydroxyl radical-mediated modification of proteins as probes for structural proteomics</article-title>. <source>Chem. Rev.</source><year>2007</year>; <volume>107</volume>:<fpage>3514</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3543</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17683160</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dalle-Donne</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rossi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Giustarini</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Milzani</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Colombo</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Protein carbonyl groups as biomarkers of oxidative stress</article-title>. <source>Clin. Chim. Acta</source>. <year>2003</year>; <volume>329</volume>:<fpage>23</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>38</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12589963</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tovar-Mendez</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miernyk</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Randall</surname><given-names>D.D.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Regulation of pyruvate dehydrogenase complex activity in plant cells</article-title>. <source>Eur. J. Biochem.</source><year>2003</year>; <volume>270</volume>:<fpage>1043</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1049</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12631264</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>B.J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hood</surname><given-names>B.L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aragon</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hardwick</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Conrads</surname><given-names>T.P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Veenstra</surname><given-names>T.D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>B.J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Increased oxidation and degradation of cytosolic proteins in alcohol-exposed mouse liver and hepatoma cells</article-title>. <source>Proteomics</source>. <year>2006</year>; <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>1250</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1260</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16408314</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>J.Y.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Murakami</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zorca</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>K.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schinazi</surname><given-names>R.F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Furman</surname><given-names>P.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>K.S.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Relationship between antiviral activity and host toxicity: comparison of the incorporation efficiencies of 2&#x02032;,3&#x02032;-dideoxy-5-fluoro-3&#x02032;-thiacytidine-triphosphate analogs by human immunodeficiency virus type 1 reverse transcriptase and human mitochondrial DNA polymerase</article-title>. <source>Antimicrob. Agents Chemother.</source><year>2004</year>; <volume>48</volume>:<fpage>1300</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1306</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15047533</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<article-title>Use of nucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitors and risk of myocardial infarction in HIV-infected patients</article-title>. <source>AIDS</source>. <year>2008</year>; <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>F17</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>F24</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18753925</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Opii</surname><given-names>W.O.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sultana</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abdul</surname><given-names>H.M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ansari</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nath</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Butterfield</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Oxidative stress and toxicity induced by the nucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitor (NRTI)&#x02013;2&#x02032;,3&#x02032;-dideoxycytidine (ddC): relevance to HIV-dementia</article-title>. <source>Exp. Neurol.</source><year>2007</year>; <volume>204</volume>:<fpage>29</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>38</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17069802</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Judge</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jang</surname><given-names>Y.M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hagen</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leeuwenburgh</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Age-associated increases in oxidative stress and antioxidant enzyme activities in cardiac interfibrillar mitochondria: implications for the mitochondrial theory of aging</article-title>. <source>FASEB J.</source><year>2005</year>; <volume>19</volume>:<fpage>419</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>421</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15642720</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sastre</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pallardo</surname><given-names>F.V.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Garcia&#x000a0;de&#x000a0;la&#x000a0;Asuncion</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vina</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Mitochondria, oxidative stress and aging</article-title>. <source>Free Radic. Res.</source><year>2000</year>; <volume>32</volume>:<fpage>189</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>198</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10730818</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>