<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="case-report"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Neurol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Neurol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Neurology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2377</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">31924167</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6954520</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1598</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12883-020-1598-6</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Disseminated Cryptococcosis revealed by transverse myelitis in Immunocompetent patient: a case report and review of the literature</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Qu</surname><given-names>Fangfang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Qu</surname><given-names>Zhenzhen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>Yingqian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Bo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Bailin</given-names></name><address><email>wubailins@163.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1804 3009</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.452702.6</institution-id><institution>Department of Respiratory and Critical Care Medicine, </institution><institution>Institute of Respiratory Diseases, the Second Hospital of Hebei Medical University, </institution></institution-wrap>Shijiazhuang, 050000 Hebei China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1804 3009</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.452702.6</institution-id><institution>Department of Neurologic Medicine, </institution><institution>the Second Hospital of Hebei Medical University, </institution></institution-wrap>Shijiazhuang, 050000 Hebei China </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1804 3009</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.452702.6</institution-id><institution>Department of Medical Oncology, </institution><institution>the Second Hospital of Hebei Medical University, </institution></institution-wrap>Shijiazhuang, 050000 Hebei China </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1760 8442</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.256883.2</institution-id><institution>The Public Health College, Hebei Medical University, </institution></institution-wrap>Shijiazhuang, 050000 Hebei China </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1804 3009</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.452702.6</institution-id><institution>Department of Radiology, </institution><institution>the Second Hospital of Hebei Medical University, </institution></institution-wrap>Shijiazhuang, 050000 Hebei China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>10</day><month>1</month><year>2020</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2020</year></pub-date><volume>20</volume><elocation-id>13</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>7</day><month>8</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>31</day><month>12</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s). 2020</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Transverse myelitis (TM) is due to inflammatory spinal cord injury with bilateral neurologic involvement, which is sensory, motor, or autonomic in nature. It may be associated with autoimmune disease, vaccination, intoxication and infections. The most common infection cause of TM is Coxsackie virus and Mycoplasma pneumoniae. The cryptococcosis is rare. We present the case of disseminated cryptococcosis revealed by transverse myelitis in an immunocompetent 55-year-old male patient. The literature review is also stated.</p></sec><sec><title>Case presentation</title><p id="Par2">The 55-year-old man suffered from gradual numbness, weakness in both lower limbs and finally paralyzed in the bed. The thoracic spine Computed tomography (CT) was normal, but multiple nodules in the lung were accidentally discovered. Thoracic Magnetic Resonance Imaging (MRI) showed diffused thoracic spinal cord thickening and extensively intramedullary T2 hyper intensity areas. Gadolinium contrast enhanced T1WI showed an intramedullary circle-enhanced nodule at 9th thoracic level. Diagnosis was made by histological examination of the bilateral lung biopsy. The patient was treated successfully with systemic amphotericin B liposome and fluconazole and intrathecal dexamethasone and amphotericin B liposome.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par3">This is a patient with disseminated cryptococcosis involving the lung, spinal cord and adrenal glands, which is rare in the absence of immunodeficiency.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Disseminated Cryptococcosis</kwd><kwd>Metastatic tumor</kwd><kwd>Transverse myelitis</kwd><kwd>Immunocompetent</kwd><kwd>Cryptococcosis pneumonia</kwd><kwd>Tuberculosis</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2020</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par10">Cryptococcosis has been defined as an opportunistic fungal infection because it mainly occurs in immunocompromised populations. Occasionally, it can occur inimmunocompetent hosts. But the cryptococcal infection with involvement of the lung, spine cord, and adrenal glands in a patient with no detectable immuno deficiency is rare according to the literature, and it is often easily misdiagnosed.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Case presentation</title><p id="Par11">A 55-year-old man, previously healthy, presented to our hospital on Nov 28th, 2017, with a 10-day history of gradual numbness and weakness in both lower limbs. The weakness of the lower extremities gradually developed towards the proximal end, and finally paralyzed the patient in the bed. The patient had urinary incontinence and constipation. He denied injuries to his back, history of herpes zoster or any other opportunistic infections. Physical examination was normal, except in both lower limbs, which had no power in all muscle groups, with hypotonia and hyporeflexia. There was a loss of sensation to pin prick and light touch, up to the level of the tenth thoracic dermatome.</p><p id="Par12">Laboratory data revealed the C-reactive protein (CRP) level was 166&#x02009;mg/L, tumor markers such as neuron-specific enolase (NSE) and ferroprotein (FER) were slightly abnormal. The aspergillus galactomannan was 0.90&#x003bc;g/ml. The blood sugar level and T-cell spot test for tuberculosis infection (T-SPOT.TB) were normal. Serological tests were negative for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), hepatitis B virus (HBV) and autoantibody. MRI of the brain was normal. CT of the thoracic spine was normal, but multiple nodules in the lung were accidentally discovered. Further chest CT examination showed a large number of randomly distributed nodules with varying sizes, unsmooth boundaries and a small number of burrs. (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>A1-3). One nodule in right adrenal gland was accidentally discovered at the same time. Thoracic MRI showed diffused spinal cord thickening and extensively T2WI hyper intensity areas (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>A1-A2). Gadolinium contrast enhanced T1WI showed an intramedullary circle-enhanced nodule at 9th thoracic level (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>B).
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>A1 showed longitudinal flaky hyper intense signal in the medullar with a range of approximately 8 vertebrae. A2 showed a small annular enhancement zone in the center of the lesion. B was enhanced T1WI after 2 weeks of treatment, indicating that the intramedullular annular enhancement zone was not significantly reduced. C1-C2 were images of follow up 3&#x02009;months of oral fluconazole 400&#x02009;mg/day. C1 showed a intramedullary hyper intense signal patch, with a longitudinal extent less than 1vertebrae.C2 showed a nodular enhancement area, significantly smaller than before</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12883_2020_1598_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p><p id="Par13">A careful history examination revealed that the patient developed cough, expectoration without fever 7 months ago. He didn&#x02019;t take it seriously. He presented to a local hospital with aggravated cough and expectoration 3&#x02009;months ago. The chest CT showed multiple nodules, which were considered tumor. For the first time the lung needle biopsy guided by CT was performed in local hospital. The histopathological result was bronchial mucous membrane and lung tissue granulomatous disease with no necrosis; no tumor cells and the possibility of tuberculosis could not be excluded. Then the patient was admitted to a tuberculosis hospital and was given anti-tuberculosis treatment for 1 month. But reexamination of the lung CT showed exacerbation of the diseases (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>B1-3). He was again admitted to another higher hospital. Because of the multiple nodules of lung CT, in order to further eliminate the possibility of tumor, he had a tracheoscopy and no tumor was found. Ten days ago, he presented to our hospital with weakness in lower limbs, urinary incontinence, and constipation.
<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>A1-A3 was CT images of lung oftheThoracic Hospital on October 25, 2017, showing multiple spherical lesions in both lungs. Some lesions were closely related to the bronchus (black arrows), and most of the other lesions were randomly distributed. B1-B3 showed the number of lung nodules increased before antifungal treatment. C1-C3 were re-examination after 2 weeks of treatment, showing lesions in the lung significantly reduced. D1-D3 were images follow up 3&#x02009;months of oral fluconazole 400&#x02009;mg/d, showing that the lung lesions were further reduced</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12883_2020_1598_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p><p id="Par14">The needle biopsy in the lesion of right upper lung lobe was performed again. HE staining indicated that the size varying cryptococcus was engulfed by macrophages, which were surrounded by massively infiltrated lymphocytes and a large amount of fibrous tissue that formed granulomas (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a). Periodic acid Schiff staining (PAS staining) indicated accumulated cryptococcus spores were located in the endochylema of multinucleated giant cells. The cell wall was stained red. PAS staining showed positive round microbes (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>b). Cryptococcus infection was diagnosed. The cerebrospinalfluid (CSF) revealed a chlorine level of 117.9&#x02009;mmol/L and normal white cell count, glucose level and protein level. Abnormal activation of monocytes can be seen in CSF cytology. Cryptococcus India ink stains and cryptococcus specific antigen were all negative.
<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p><bold>a</bold> was a HE stain image of lung biopsy material. Macrophage aggregation (white arrow) was seen, which indicate granulomatous lesions. Round microbes (black arrow) within macrophages were suspected fungi. <bold>b</bold> showed positive stained round microbes (black arrow) in macrophages with PAS stain, consistent with Cryptococcus</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12883_2020_1598_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p><p id="Par15">Questioning to determine exposure to cryptococcus revealed that the patient had exposure to bird droppings. The patient received anti-mycotic therapy with amphotericin B liposome 150&#x02009;mg daily and fluconazole 400&#x02009;mg daily for vein. Two weeks later, lung CT showed a shrink of nodules, also the exudation and right adrenal gland nodule reduced (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>C1-3). Thoracic MRI showed no significant change in intramedullary lesion. One month later, the sensory level of the patient declined slightly and the muscle strength of the lower limbs did not change. He was given intrathecal dexamethasone 5&#x02009;mg and amphotericin B liposome 0.01&#x02009;mg one time. One week later, a repeated lumbar puncture revealed that CSF, white cell count, chlorine level, glucose level and protein level were normal. Cryptococcus India ink stains and microbial cultures were all negative. He was transited to oral fluconazole on discharge.</p><p id="Par16">Follow-up 3 months after discharge, thoracic MRI showed that the nodular lesion shrunk and the swelling reduced significantly (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>C1-2). The lung CT showed the multiple nodules and masses gradually decreased (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>D1-3). He had no cough, neither fever, and a slight decline in the sensory level and his lower limb muscle power had slight improvement.</p></sec><sec id="Sec3"><title>Discussion and conclusions</title><p id="Par17">Cryptococcus is a nonmycelial, budding, encapsulated, opportunistic, pathogenic, and yeast-like fungus. Inhalation of either the yeast form or basidiospores from an environmental source, such as bird droppings or soil, is believed to cause infection with this opportunistic fungus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Cryptococcosis usually occurs in patients with tuberculosis, diabetes, leukemia, lymphoma, organ transplantation, acquired immune deficiency syndrome (AIDS), and histoplasmosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Occasionally, it can occur in a small subset of immunocompetent hosts, with an incidence estimated at 0.2 per million per year [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Cryptococcosis is an invasive fungal disease that invades the central nervous system, lung, skin, lymph nodes, bone marrow, etc., causing chronic inflammation and granuloma. The most frequent disease manifestation is meningoencephalitis. But cryptococcal pneumonia has not been diagnosed because of nonspecific respiratory symptoms. Cryptococcal disease can present as a cough, sputum, shortness of breath, mild fever, chest pain and other symptoms.</p><p id="Par18">The image differentiation between cryptococcosis and malignant tumor is difficult. Multiple pulmonary nodules and/or masses are often mistaken for primary or metastatic malignancy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. It is also difficult to distinguish cryptococcal infection from tuberculosis by a surgical specimen, or demonstration in culture. The pus, caseous necrosis, and granulation within cryptococcal lesions are similar to those in tuberculosis. Therefore, observation of these fungal spores, circular mycelium, is essential for a diagnosis of cryptococcal infection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Pathological PAS staining is positive in the tissue specimens of percutaneous pulmonary puncture, which should be differentiated from <italic>Histoplasma capsulatum</italic>.</p><p id="Par19">Thoracic MRI showed diffused spinal cord thickening and extensively T2WI hyper intensity areas. Gadolinium contrast enhanced T1WI showed an intramedullary circle-enhanced nodule at 9th thoracic level. In general, the high signal on T1-weighted MR images may be due to the presence of hemorrhage, melanin, fat, or granulomatous tissue [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Combined with lung histopathology, the final diagnosis was invasive cryptococcosis. Although no mycological evidence for cryptococcus was found in the patient&#x02019;s CSF, after treatment with amphotericin B liposome and fluconazole, spinal cord lesions decreased rapidly from a wide range of T2 hyperintense edematous zones, and presented nodular enhancement, which were consistent with the imaging features of granulomatous lesion.</p><p id="Par20">There are some important lessons from our case. First, Cryptococcus can rarely cause spinal cord infections apart from lung, meninges, and parenchyma. When suspecting systemic infectious disease involving the lungs, brain, meninges or spinal cord, the possibility of cryptococcus infection should be taken into account; Second, the radiological presentation of multiple nodules and masses in lungs, one nodule in right adrenal gland and the spinal cord lesions may easily be misdiagnosed as pulmonary metastases or tuberculosis. The disease is difficult to diagnose and progress gradually, leading to paraplegia. Third, when biopsy tissue pathology revealed granulomatous lesions, not only acid-fast staining to exclude tuberculosis, but also PAS staining to exclude cryptococcosis should be considered.</p><p id="Par21">CSF pleocytosis, elevated CSF IgG index, or abnormal gadolinium enhancement of the spinal cord on MRI is necessary to diagnosis of TM [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. In our case the patient has abnormal CSF and gadolinium contrast enhanced T1WI showed an intramedullary circle-enhanced nodule at 9th thoracic level, therefore, it can be diagnosed as TM. Cryptococcus rarely causes spinal cord infection, leading to transverse myomyelitis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. To our knowledge; six patients with intramedullary cryptococcus have been reported in the literature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. All patients were immunocompetent. Only the case reported by Scullery [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>] had a pulmonary cryptococcal infection 6&#x02009;months before intramedullary localization, which is consistent with our patient.</p><p id="Par22">With the deepening understanding of cryptococcosis, the diagnosis of cryptococcosis in immunocompetent patients gradually increases. When those immunocompetent patients have pulmonary lesions with meningeal or spinal cord lesions, we should think of disseminated cryptococcosis.</p></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>CNS</term><def><p id="Par4">Central nervous system</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CRP</term><def><p id="Par5">C-reactive protein</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CSF</term><def><p id="Par6">Cerebrospinal fluid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CT</term><def><p id="Par7">Computed tomography</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MRI</term><def><p id="Par8">Magnetic resonance imaging</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PAS</term><def><p id="Par9">Periodic Acid-Schiff stain</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn><fn><p>Bo&#x000a0;Song and Bailin Wu contributed equally to this work.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><p>We are grateful to Dr. Shanshan Shen (Department of Radiology, the People&#x02019;s Hospital of Hebei Province, Shijiazhuang, Hebei, China) and DrJunyu Ji (Department of Radiology, Hebei Chest Hospital, Shijiazhuang, Hebei, China) for providing important image data.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>FFQ, ZhZhQ, YQL, BS and BLW were involved in the collection of data, drafting and editing of the manuscript. All authors have read and approved the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>The study was no founded by any funding source.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>All relevant data to this case is reported in the manuscript.</p></notes><notes><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par23">This study was approved by the Ethics Committee of the Second Hospital of Hebei Medical University.</p><p id="Par24">Written informed consent for participate was obtained from the patient.</p></notes><notes><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par25">Written informed consent for publication was obtained from the patient.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par26">The authors declare that they have no conflict of interest.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Sorrell</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>Allworth</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Heath</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>McGregor</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Papanaoum</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gottlieb</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cryptococcal disease of the CNS in immunocompetent hosts: influence of cryptococcal variety on clinical manifestations and outcome</article-title><source>Clin Infect Dis</source><year>1995</year><volume>20</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>611</fpage><lpage>616</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/clinids/20.3.611</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7756484</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baddley</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Perfect</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Oster</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pankey</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Haas</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kauffman</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Zaas</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Pulmonary cryptococcosis in patients without HIV infection: factors associated with disseminated disease</article-title><source>Eur J Clin Microbiol Infect Dis</source><year>2008</year><volume>27</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>937</fpage><lpage>943</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10096-008-0529-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18449582</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The rarity of cryptococcosis in northern California: the 10-year experience of a large defined population</article-title><source>Am J Epidemiol</source><year>1983</year><volume>117</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>230</fpage><lpage>234</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/oxfordjournals.aje.a113534</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6829552</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Imaging findings of cryptococcal infection of the thoracic spine</article-title><source>Int J Infect Dis</source><year>2014</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>162</fpage><lpage>165</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijid.2014.07.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25449251</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Chhabra</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Khosla</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vertebral cryptococcosis simulating tuberculosis</article-title><source>Br J Neurosurg</source><year>2003</year><volume>17</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>556</fpage><lpage>559</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/02688690310001626868</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14756487</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Farrokh</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Fransen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Faverly</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MR findings of a primary intramedullary malignant melanoma: case report and literature review</article-title><source>AJNR Am J Neuroradiol</source><year>2001</year><volume>22</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1864</fpage><lpage>1866</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11733317</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krishnan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaplin</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name><name><surname>Pardo</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kerr</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Keswani</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Demyelinating disorders: Update on transverse myelitis</article-title><source>Curr Neurol Neurosci</source><year>2006</year><volume>6</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>236</fpage><lpage>243</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11910-006-0011-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>G&#x000fc;lta&#x0015f;li</surname><given-names>NZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ercan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Orhun</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Albayrak</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MRI findings of intramedullary spinal cryptococcoma</article-title><source>Diagn Interv Radiol (Ankara, Turkey)</source><year>2007</year><volume>13</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>64</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intramedullary cryptococcal granuloma of spinal cord: a case report</article-title><source>Zhonghua Yi Xue Za Zhi (Taipei)</source><year>1994</year><volume>53</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>58</fpage><lpage>61</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8174002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grosse</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Tintelnot</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sollner</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmitz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Encephalomyelitis due to Cryptococcus neoformans var gattii presenting as spinal tumour: case report and review of the literature</article-title><source>J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry</source><year>2001</year><volume>70</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>113</fpage><lpage>116</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/jnnp.70.1.113</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11118259</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramamurthi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>ANGULI</surname><given-names>VC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intramedullary cryptococcic granuloma of the spinal cord</article-title><source>J Neurosurg</source><year>1954</year><volume>11</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>622</fpage><lpage>624</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3171/jns.1954.11.6.0622</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13222170</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>FM</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cryptococcic granuloma of the dorsal spinal cord. A case report</article-title><source>Neurology</source><year>1961</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1066</fpage><lpage>1070</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1212/WNL.11.12.1066</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13913741</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intramedullary spinal cryptococcoma: a case report</article-title><source>J Formos Med Assoc</source><year>2001</year><volume>100</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>776</fpage><lpage>778</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11802539</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>